<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="other" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Indian J Anaesth</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Indian J Anaesth</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1243</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">ijanaesth</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJA</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Indian J Anaesth</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Indian Journal of Anaesthesia</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0019-5049</issn><issn pub-type="epub">0976-2817</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer -- Medknow Publications</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11100642</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11100642.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11100642</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11100642</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38764965</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/ija.ija_1206_23</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IJA-68-426</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Perioperative adverse cardiac events in maxillofacial surgery: A systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chohan</surname><given-names initials="M">Mehak</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0009-0004-5212-5822</contrib-id><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff"/><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="W">Winnie</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0009-0009-4898-4479</contrib-id><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chowdhury</surname><given-names initials="T">Tumul</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8946-4148</contrib-id><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">Department of Health Science, Queen's University, Kingston, ON, Canada</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>1</label>Michael G. DeGroote School of Medicine, McMaster, Hamilton, ON, Canada</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>2</label>Department of Anaesthesiology and Pain Medicine, Toronto Western Hospital, Toronto, ON, Canada</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Address for correspondence:</bold> Dr. Tumul Chowdhury, Department of Anaesthesiology and Pain Medicine, University of Toronto, 399 Bathurst St, Toronto, ON M5T 2S8, Canada. E-mail: <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="tumul.chowdhury@uhn.ca">tumul.chowdhury@uhn.ca</email></corresp><fn id="fn1"><label>*</label><p>Co-first authorship</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>5</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>4</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>68</volume><issue>5</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">462563</issue-id><fpage>426</fpage><lpage>438</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>29</day><month>2</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>3</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>05</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>18</day><month>05</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-05-20 17:25:14.290"><day>20</day><month>05</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#169; 2024 Indian Journal of Anaesthesia</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncsalicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access journal, and articles are distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 License, which allows others to remix, tweak, and build upon the work non-commercially, as long as appropriate credit is given and the new creations are licensed under the identical terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="IJA-68-426.pdf"/><abstract><sec id="st1"><title>Background and Aims:</title><p>Maxillofacial surgeries, including procedures to the face, oral cavity, jaw, and head and neck, are common in adults. However, they impose a risk of adverse cardiac events (ACEs). While ACEs are well understood for other non-cardiac surgeries, there is a paucity of data about maxillofacial surgeries. This systematic review and meta-analysis report the incidence and presentation of perioperative ACEs during maxillofacial surgery.</p></sec><sec id="st2"><title>Methods:</title><p>We included primary studies that reported on perioperative ACEs in adults. To standardise reporting, ACEs were categorised as 1. heart rate and rhythm disturbances, 2. blood pressure disturbances, 3. ischaemic heart disease and 4. heart failure and other complications. The primary outcome was ACE presentation and incidence during the perioperative period. Secondary outcomes included the surgical outcome according to the Clavien&#8211;Dindo classification and trigeminocardiac reflex involvement. STATA version 17.0 and MetaProp were used to delineate proportion as effect size with a 95% confidence interval (CI).</p></sec><sec id="st3"><title>Results:</title><p>Twelve studies (34,227 patients) were included. The incidence of perioperative ACEs was 2.58% (95% CI 1.70, 3.45, <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 96.17%, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.001). Heart rate and rhythm disturbances resulted in the greatest incidence at 3.84% among the four categories. Most commonly, these ACEs resulted in intensive care unit admission (i.e. Clavien&#8211;Dindo score of 4).</p></sec><sec id="st4"><title>Conclusion:</title><p>Despite an incidence of 2.58%, ACEs can disproportionately impact surgical outcomes. Future research should include large-scale prospective studies that may provide a better understanding of the contributory factors and long-term effects of ACEs in patients during maxillofacial surgery.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Adult</kwd><kwd>arrhythmias</kwd><kwd>blood pressure</kwd><kwd>cardiac</kwd><kwd>heart arrest</kwd><kwd>heart failure</kwd><kwd>heart rate</kwd><kwd>incidence</kwd><kwd>intraoperative complications</kwd><kwd>maxillofacial surgeries</kwd><kwd>myocardial infarction</kwd><kwd>myocardial ischaemia</kwd><kwd>perioperative care</kwd><kwd>perioperative period</kwd><kwd>reflex</kwd><kwd>trigeminocardiac</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Each year, over 100 million non-cardiac surgeries are performed worldwide, and this value is projected to increase.[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] Although these surgeries can enhance patients&#8217; quality and duration of life, the surgical experience may precipitate adverse cardiac events (ACEs), including myocardial infarctions, arrhythmias and cardiac arrest.[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] Unfortunately, ACEs following non-cardiac surgery increase hospitalisation duration and costs and are a leading cause of postoperative mortality and morbidity.[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</p><p>Oral and maxillofacial surgery includes procedures within the face, oral cavity, jaw, head, and neck.[<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref><xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] More commonly, oral maxillofacial operations are performed in adults (patients &#8805;18 years).[<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] Currently, various cardiac complications, including dysrhythmias, asystole, hypertensive crises and chest pain, have been reported in patients undergoing maxillofacial surgeries.[<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref><xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref><xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] While ACEs during other non-cardiac surgeries (i.e. vascular, thoracic, ophthalmological) are well explored, less is understood in the context of maxillofacial surgeries. There is a lack of systematically aggregated evidence on ACEs&#8217; incidence, presentation and impact during the maxillofacial perioperative period. This confers challenges to healthcare providers in better understanding their influence on surgical outcomes and management approaches. This systematic review and meta-analysis aims to elucidate the incidence and presentation of ACEs during the perioperative period of maxillofacial surgery. In addition, the review will explore the impact of these cardiac complications on surgical outcomes using the Clavien&#8211;Dindo classification system and investigate trigeminocardiac reflex (TCR) involvement.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="sec1-2"><title>METHODS</title><p>This systematic review and meta-analysis adhered to the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses (PRISMA) guidelines.[<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] The protocol was registered in the International Prospective Registry of Systematic Reviews (PROSPERO) (registration number CRD42022334058).</p><sec id="sec2-1"><title>Search strategy</title><p>The search strategy was developed in consultation with an information specialist who conducted a comprehensive systematic search to identify eligible studies. A search was conducted from MEDLINE/PubMed, Embase, Cumulative Index to Nursing and Allied Health (CINAHL), Web of Science and Cochrane Library from inception until 5 May 2023. The search strategy was limited to English. The search strategy combined appropriate controlled vocabulary and keywords: &#8216;maxillofacial surgery&#8217;, &#8216;perioperative&#8217;, &#8216;adverse cardiac events&#8217;, &#8216;reflex&#8217; and &#8216;adult&#8217;. Full details regarding the search strategy are provided in the <xref rid="APP1" ref-type="app">Supplementary Material</xref>. Reference lists were manually checked for additional publications.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title>Study selection and screening process</title><p>Two independent reviewers assessed each article in the initial stage of title and abstract screening and subsequent stages of full-text screening. Disagreements at either stage were resolved by consulting the principal investigator.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-3"><title>Inclusion and exclusion criteria</title><p>We included articles from any type of primary study, including randomised controlled trials (RCTs). Retrospective and prospective observational studies such as cohorts, cross-sectional studies and case&#8211;control studies which reported on ACEs in patients aged &#8805;18 years during the perioperative period of maxillofacial surgery were included. The perioperative period was defined in this review as the time frame from the patient's surgical admission through their intraoperative course and up to final discharge.[<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] Maxillofacial surgery includes surgeries on the face, oral cavity, head and neck, mouth and jaws. Non-English articles, animal studies, duplicates, secondary research articles, case series, case reports, conference abstracts, pregnant patients and exclusive ocular surgical patients were excluded from the study.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-4"><title>Outcomes</title><p>The primary outcomes were the incidence and presentation of ACEs during the perioperative period of oral and maxillofacial surgery. The secondary outcomes included surgical outcomes as defined by the Clavien&#8211;Dindo classification and the involvement of TCR. The following definitions were used:</p><p>ACEs &#8211; We included ACEs that were described by any of the following: 1. change in heart rate and/or blood pressure 20% or above the baseline; 2. occurrence of heart rhythm abnormalities, such as arrhythmias, atrial fibrillation, atrial flutter, atrioventricular block, etc.; 3. cardiac arrest; 4. cardiac muscle injury and/or ischaemia and 5. requirement of any therapeutic or pharmacological intervention to abort or treat the ACE. Subsequently, all ACEs that were described by the included studies were categorised into one of four broad categories to standardise reporting: 1. blood pressure disturbances, 2. heart rate and rhythm disturbances, 3. ischaemic heart disease (IHD) or 4. heart failure and complications (i.e. cardiac arrest).[<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]</p><p>Clavien&#8211;Dindo classification &#8211; All ACEs were graded according to the Clavien&#8211;Dindo surgical complications classification, with scores ranging from 1 to 5. The Clavien&#8211;Dindo system is widely used throughout surgery to grade the severity of adverse events resulting from the procedure. The grading is based on the type of therapeutic management required to correct the complication. A score of 1 refers to any deviation from the normal postoperative course without needing intervention beyond administering antiemetics, antipyretics, analgesics, diuretics, electrolytes and physiotherapy. A score of 2 refers to any other pharmacological intervention. A score of 3 refers to complications that require further surgical, endoscopic or radioscopic intervention. A score of 4 refers to multiorgan dysfunction requiring intensive care unit (ICU) admission. A score of 5 refers to patient death.[<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]</p><p>TCR was defined as a sudden onset of parasympathetic dysrhythmias, including haemodynamic instability, apnea and gastric hypermobility, that occur secondary to trigeminal nerve [cranial nerve (CN) V] stimulation.[<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] Because oral and maxillofacial procedures occur at regions innervated by the trigeminal nerve, it is suggested that these operations may induce this brainstem reflex, manifesting as sudden bradycardia and hypotension.[<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref><xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]</p></sec><sec id="sec2-5"><title>Data extraction and quality assessment</title><p>Two independent reviewers performed data extraction. The following data were extracted onto a standardised excel file: author, year of publication, country, study design, sample size, mean age, sex, comorbidities, anaesthetic agents administered, surgical procedures, follow-up period, and primary and secondary outcomes. Two independent reviewers completed the quality assessment for all studies. The principal investigator resolved any disagreement in scoring. We used the Newcastle&#8211;Ottawa Scale (NOS) for observational cohorts.[<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] NOS evaluates cohort studies according to three domains (selection, comparability and outcome) with eight question items for a maximum score of 9. Studies with a score of 7&#8211;9 were considered good quality, studies with a score of 4&#8211;6 were considered fair quality and studies with a score of 0&#8211;3 were considered poor quality. For RCTs, quality was evaluated in accordance with the Cochrane Risk of Bias 2 (RoB2) revised tool.[<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]</p></sec><sec id="sec2-6"><title>Data analysis</title><p>Data analyses were performed qualitatively and quantitatively. The demographic and outcome data description was presented using percentages and mean [standard deviation (SD)]. Data were presented in tables and figures as appropriate. Regarding the reporting of incidence, most included studies did not provide a quantitative endpoint for when the ACEs were recorded. As a result, we could not calculate the study-specific incidence rates in person-years format. Hence, we calculated each study's incidence rate as <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>/<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>, with <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> being the number of patients who developed an ACE postoperatively before discharge and <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> being the total number of patients undergoing oral and maxillofacial surgery.</p><p>The pooled incidence rate of ACEs (composite of the four categories) and the incidence rates of each ACE category were determined by a meta-analysis with inverse variance and a random effects model, given the expected heterogeneity between studies. The pooled effect sizes were cross-checked using the Freeman&#8211;Tukey double arcsine transformation. In addition, we performed a leave-one-out meta-analysis to identify studies with an exaggerated effect size.</p><p>Subgroup analyses were also performed. A subgroup analysis based on sample size (&lt;100, 100&#8211;500, &gt;500) and a meta-regression analysis was conducted to evaluate whether the study sample size influenced the effect size (i.e. incidence). Finally, a funnel plot and Egger's test value were determined to illustrate publication bias. All analyses were conducted using the STATA version 17.0 software, and MetaProp was used to delineate the incidence proportion as the effect size with a 95% confidence interval (CI).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec1-3"><title>RESULTS</title><p>Our search strategy yielded 4099 studies. After removing 351 duplicates, 3748 studies progressed to the initial title and abstract screening phase. Of these, 3652 studies were excluded based on the inclusion and exclusion criteria, and 96 full texts further underwent full-text screening. A total of 12 studies were included in the final analysis [<xref rid="ija.ija_1206_23-F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>].[<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref><xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref><xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref><xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref><xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref><xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref><xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref><xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref><xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref><xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref><xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref><xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]</p><fig position="float" id="ija.ija_1206_23-F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>PRISMA flow chart of study selection process. This figure presents the study selection process conducted in accordance with the PRISMA guidelines. After database searching, 4099 studies were retrieved. Finally, 12 studies were included in the review. PRISMA = Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic reviews and Meta-Analyses</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IJA-68-426-g001.jpg"/></fig><sec id="sec2-7"><title>Study and patient characteristics</title><p>In total, 34,227 patients were included [<xref rid="ija.ija_1206_23-T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>]. Men comprised 41.7% of the population (10 studies).[<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref><xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref><xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref><xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref><xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref><xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref><xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref><xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref><xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref><xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] The mean (SD) age was 33.5 (14.9) years.[<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref><xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref><xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref><xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref><xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] Eight studies were retrospective cohort studies, three prospective cohort studies and one RCT. Across the 11 non-randomised studies, which included both retrospective and prospective cohort studies, the mean NOS score was 5.8 (range 0&#8211;9), indicating that all studies were rated of fair quality according to the NOS criteria (with scores between 4 and 6) [<xref rid="ija.ija_1206_23-T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>].[<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref><xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref><xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref><xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref><xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref><xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref><xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref><xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref><xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref><xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref><xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] The single RCT study was deemed to have a low risk of bias according to the ROB2 scale [<xref rid="ija.ija_1206_23-T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>].[<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] Seven studies have reported on patient comorbidities, the most common being heart conditions [<xref rid="ija.ija_1206_23-T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>].[<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref><xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref><xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref><xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref><xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref><xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref><xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]</p><table-wrap position="float" id="ija.ija_1206_23-T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Study characteristics of the included studies</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">First author (year)</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Country</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study design</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total sample size</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean age (SD)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male %</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comorbidities</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Braidy (2011)[<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RC</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1167</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.8 (8.2)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.9</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetes mellitus, hypertension, neurological conditions<sup>a</sup>, psychiatric conditions<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Buitelaar (2006)[<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The Netherlands</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RC</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">469</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart conditions<sup>c</sup>, respiratory conditions<sup>d</sup>, renal conditions<sup>e</sup>, vascular disease, liver impairment, diabetes mellitus, hypertension</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Christensen (2019)[<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PC</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">642</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cramer (2016)[<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RC</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29,891</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart conditions<sup>c</sup>, respiratory conditions<sup>d</sup>, renal conditions<sup>e</sup>, haematological conditions<sup>f</sup>, diabetes mellitus, disseminated cancer, ascites, hypertension</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dean NR (2010)[<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RC</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.2 (NR)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gates (2021)[<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RC</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1081</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.0 (NR)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart conditions<sup>c</sup>, respiratory conditions<sup>d</sup>, haematological conditions<sup>f</sup>, diabetes mellitus, hypertension</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ivosevic (2017)[<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serbia</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RC</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">359</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart conditions<sup>c</sup>, renal conditions<sup>e</sup>, diabetes mellitus, hypertension, cerebrovascular conditions<sup>g</sup>, hyperlipoproteinemia</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Joshi (2017)[<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">India</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PC</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.1 (8.0)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lalabekyan (2021)[<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UK</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PC</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">187</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.2 (13.7)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mackay (2020)[<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Australia</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RCT</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.6 (12.8)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart conditions<sup>c</sup>, respiratory conditions<sup>d</sup>, cerebrovascular conditions<sup>g</sup>, diabetes mellitus, hypertension, arthritis, chronic pain syndrome</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Riley (1997)[<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RC</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">182</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.2 (11.2)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart conditions<sup>c</sup>, respiratory conditions<sup>d</sup>, hypertension</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spiegel (2005)[<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RC</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">117</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.8 (NR)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF1-1"><p>NR=Not reported, PC=Prospective cohort, RC=Retrospective cohort, RCT=Randomised controlled trial, SD=Standard deviation. <sup>a</sup>Neurological conditions: seizures. <sup>b</sup>Psychiatric conditions: attention deficit disorder, bipolar disorder, anxiety disorder. <sup>c</sup>Heart conditions include myocardial infarction, arrhythmias, coronary artery disease, congestive heart failure, ischaemic heart disease, angina pectoris. <sup>d</sup>Respiratory conditions include dyspnoea at rest or with exertion, asthma, chronic obstructive pulmonary disorder, obstructive sleep apnoea, obstructive and/or restrictive lung diseases. <sup>e</sup>Renal conditions: renal impairment with creatinine clearance &lt;50 mL/min, renal failure requiring dialysis, chronic kidney disease. <sup>f</sup>Haematological conditions: bleeding disorders, clotting disorders. <sup>g</sup>Cerebrovascular conditions: stroke</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="ija.ija_1206_23-T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Assessment of quality &#8211; Newcastle&#8211;Ottawa Scale</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Author (year)</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Cohort selection</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comparability</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Outcome ascertainment</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Total score</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Quality</th></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</th></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Representativeness of the exposed cohort</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Selection of the non-exposed cohort</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ascertainment of exposure</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Demonstration that outcome of interest was not present at the start of the study</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comparability of cases and controls based on design or analysis</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Assessment of outcome</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Was follow-up long enough for outcomes to occur?</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adequacy of follow-up of cohorts</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Braidy (2011)[<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fair</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Buitelaar (2006)[<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fair</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Christensen (2019)[<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fair</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cramer (2016)[<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fair</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dean (2010)[<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fair</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gates (2021)[<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fair</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ivosevic (2017)[<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fair</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Joshi (2017)[<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fair</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lalabekyan (2021)[<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fair</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Riley (1997)[<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fair</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spiegel (2005)[<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fair</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="ija.ija_1206_23-T3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Assessment of quality &#8211; RoB2</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Author (year)</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Domain 1: Risk of bias due to randomisation process</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Domain 2: Risk of bias due to deviations from the intended interventions</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Domain 3: Risk of bias due to missing outcome data</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Domain 4: Risk of bias due to measurement of the outcome</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Domain 5: Risk of bias due to selection of the reported result</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall risk of bias and quality</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MacKay (2020)[<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low risk of bias</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF1-2"><p>RoB2=Risk of Bias 2</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Four studies reported on the anaesthetic details of the surgery [<xref rid="ija.ija_1206_23-T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>].[<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref><xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref><xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref><xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] Sedation and general anaesthesia (GA) were the only anaesthetic techniques undertaken; both were used in two studies. Patients receiving only sedation were spontaneously ventilated, while patients undergoing GA were mechanically ventilated with either an endotracheal tube or tracheostomy, and in terms of the anaesthetic agents administered, three of the four studies described the medications given.[<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref><xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref><xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] In the studies that used sedation, patients were sedated at varying degrees of consciousness with midazolam, fentanyl, and propofol or ketamine infusions.[<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref><xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] For patients undergoing GA, they were premedicated with midazolam, induced with propofol, fentanyl and rocuronium, and maintained with sevoflurane.[<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] Three of the four studies reported on analgesia agents, and all included the use of opioids, including fentanyl and remifentanil.[<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref><xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref><xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] Local anaesthetic was reported in only one study and was used exclusively by the surgeon for infiltration at the surgical site.[<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] Regional anaesthesia was not used in any study.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="ija.ija_1206_23-T4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Anaesthetic techniques, agents and ventilation approaches</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">First author (Year)</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anaesthetic technique</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intravenous agents administered</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Volatile agents</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regional anaesthesia</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Local anaesthesia</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Analgesia</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ventilation</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Braidy (2011)[<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV sedation</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Midazolam, fentanyl, propofol and/or ketamine</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes (at the surgical site)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fentanyl</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spontaneous ventilation</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Christensen (2019)[<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV sedation</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Midazolam, fentanyl, remifentanil, propofol, ketamine</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fentanyl, remifentanil</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ivosevic (2017)[<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Midazolam, fentanyl, remifentanil, propofol, rocuronium</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes (sevoflurane)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fentanyl, remifentanil</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mechanical ventilation with ETT</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Riley (1997)[<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mechanical ventilation with ETT and tracheostomy</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF1-3"><p>ETT=Endotracheal tube, GA=General anaesthesia, IV=Intravenous, NR=Not reported</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec2-8"><title>Primary findings</title><p><xref rid="ija.ija_1206_23-T5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref> displays each study's ACE incidence rate as a proportion (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>/<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>), their specific presentations as described by the study authors, and the subsequent categorisation (heart rate and rhythm disturbances, blood pressure disturbances, IHDs, and heart failure and complications).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="ija.ija_1206_23-T5" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Presentation and incidence of ACEs</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">First author (year)</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Surgical procedures</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample size</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of patients who developed an ACE, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACE presentation (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>)</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACE classification</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Braidy (2011)[<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dental extractions<break/>Preprosthetic surgery<break/>Arch bar removal<break/>Closed reduction of mandibular fractures<break/>Pathology (biopsies, etc.)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1167</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (0.2%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension (1)<break/>Tachycardia (1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blood pressure disturbances<break/>Heart rate and rhythm disturbances</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Buitelaar (2006)[<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glossectomy<break/>Commando procedure<break/>Radical neck dissection<break/>Parotidectomy<break/>Laryngectomy<break/>Miscellaneous major tumour resections<break/>Thyroidectomy</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">469</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53 (11.3%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart failure (38)<break/>Atrial fibrillation (4)<break/>Atrial flutter (1)<break/>Atrial tachycardia (1)<break/>Ventricular fibrillation (1)<break/>Premature ventricular contractions (3)<break/>Bradycardia (2)<break/>MI (3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart rate and rhythm disturbances<break/>Ischaemic heart disease<break/>Heart failure and complications</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Christensen (2019)[<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oral and maxillofacial surgeries</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">642</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (0.5%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension (2)<break/>ST elevation (1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blood pressure disturbances<break/>Ischaemic heart disease</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cramer (2016)[<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glossectomy/floor of mouth, lip, palate/alveolar maxilla/mandible, salivary gland excision<break/>Tonsillectomy<break/>Pharyngectomy<break/>Laryngectomy<break/>Neck dissection<break/>Parotidectomy<break/>Thyroidectomy</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29,891</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">104 (0.4%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MI (NR)<break/>Cardiac arrest (NR)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ischaemic heart disease<break/>Heart failure and complications</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dean (2010)[<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Temporal bone resection</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.5%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MI (1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ischaemic heart disease</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gates (2021)[<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Palatopharyngoplasty</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1081</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (0.4%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MI (3)<break/>Cardiac arrest (1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ischaemic heart disease<break/>Heart failure and complications</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ivosevic (2017)[<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maxillofacial surgery</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">359</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87 (24.2%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bradycardia (87)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart rate and rhythm disturbances</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Joshi (2017)[<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mandibular and midface fracture repair</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (75%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bradycardia (27)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart rate and rhythm disturbances</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lalabekyan (2021)[<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Major head and neck surgery</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">187</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (1.6%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MI (3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ischaemic heart disease</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mackay (2020)[<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uvulopalatopharyngoplasty Tongue volume reduction</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.9%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MI (1)<break/>Recurrent angina (1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ischaemic heart disease</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Riley (1997)[<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mandibular osteotomy<break/>Hyoid myotomy<break/>Maxillary and mandibular advancement osteotomy</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">182</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (2.8%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arrhythmia (4)<break/>Unstable angina (1)<break/>Hypertension (160 cases)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart rate and rhythm disturbances<break/>Ischaemic heart disease<break/>Blood pressure disturbances</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spiegel (2005)[<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uvulopalatoplasty</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">117</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (3.4%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension (3)<break/>Tachycardia (1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blood pressure disturbances<break/>Heart rate and rhythm disturbances</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF1-4"><p>ACE=Adverse cardiac event, MI=Myocardial infarction, NR=Not reported. <sup>a</sup>Mackay (2020) reported two adverse cardiac events (MI and angina) that occurred within a single patient. <sup>b</sup>Riley (1997) reported five patients who developed an ACE (either arrhythmias or unstable angina) and also reported 160 cases of perioperative hypertension</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The pooled incidence rate of perioperative ACE (composite of the four categories) was 2.58% (95% CI 1.70, 3.45, <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 96.17%, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.001) [<xref rid="ija.ija_1206_23-F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>]. Following the Freeman&#8211;Tukey double arcsine transformation, the pooled incidence rate was 4.95% (95% CI 1.94, 9.12). The leave-one-out sensitivity analysis identified one study with an exaggerated effect size of 75%, and once removed, the pooled incidence rate decreased to 1.25% (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.045).[<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] The subgroup analysis based on sample size showed that studies with &gt;500 patients had a lower pooled incidence rate of 0.34% and a reduced heterogeneity of 0.00% in comparison to studies with smaller sample sizes (&lt;100 and 100&#8211;500 patients) [<xref rid="ija.ija_1206_23-F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>].</p><fig position="float" id="ija.ija_1206_23-F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Pooled incidence of perioperative adverse cardiac events in maxillofacial surgeries. The figure presents the pooled incidence of perioperative adverse cardiac events in maxillofacial surgeries, with an incidence of 2.58% (95% CI 1.70, 3.45, <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 96.17%, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.00). The analysis was performed on STATA version 17.0, and MetaProp was used to delineate proportion as effect size with a 95% CI. Considering significant heterogeneity due to study design, sampling and reporting outcomes, a random effects model was used. CI = confidence interval</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IJA-68-426-g002.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="ija.ija_1206_23-F3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Subgroup analysis of ACE incidence stratified by sample size. The figure shows studies with more than 500 patients had a lower pooled incidence rate (0.34%) and a lower heterogeneity (0.00%). Conversely, studies including lower sample sizes (&lt;100 and 100&#8211;500 patients) exhibited more heterogeneity and higher pooled incidence rates. ACE = adverse cardiac event</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IJA-68-426-g003.jpg"/></fig><p>Separate analyses for incidence rates were conducted for each ACE category [<xref rid="ija.ija_1206_23-T6" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>]. Heart rate and rhythm disturbances had the greatest incidence among the four ACE categories at 3.84% (95% CI 2.23, 5.45). This was followed by heart failure and complications, IHD and blood pressure disturbances at 0.53%, 0.21% and 0.20%, respectively.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="ija.ija_1206_23-T6" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Pooled incidence rates of each ACE category</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACE category</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Effect size (%)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% Confidence interval</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">I</italic>
<sup>2</sup>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blood pressure disturbances</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.16, 0.57</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart rate and rhythm disturbances</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.85</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.23, 5.45</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.46</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart failure and other complications</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.04, 1.10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.07</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ischaemic heart disease</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13, 0.29</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.94</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF1-5"><p>ACE=Adverse cardiac event</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Lastly, the funnel plot of the included 12 studies appeared asymmetrical, with a rightward skew [<xref rid="ija.ija_1206_23-F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>]. This indicates a likely publication bias due to the small sample sizes of the included studies. An Egger's test value for bias confirmed this assumption (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01).</p><fig position="float" id="ija.ija_1206_23-F4" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Funnel plot of the included studies (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 12). The plot includes a pseudo 95% confidence interval to assess publication bias and study heterogeneity. This funnel plot reveals an asymmetrical distribution of data points with a concentration on the right side indicative of publication bias as introduced in the review</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IJA-68-426-g004.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec2-9"><title>Secondary findings</title><p>The most common Clavien&#8211;Dindo score was 4, referring to multiorgan dysfunction requiring ICU admission, which was reported in 109 patients (37.1%). The least common Clavien&#8211;Dindo score was 3 (i.e. surgical, endoscopic or radioscopic intervention), which was reported in two patients (0.7%) only. Interventions for these patients included coronary artery stent insertion and coronary bypass surgery. Patients with a Clavien&#8211;Dindo score of 2 (11.2%) required pharmacological intervention consisting of labetalol, hydralazine, sodium nitroprusside infusion, antiarrhythmics and other antihypertensive medications. <xref rid="ija.ija_1206_23-T7" ref-type="table">Table 7</xref> presents the ACEs, their respective management and the Clavien&#8211;Dindo classification score.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="ija.ija_1206_23-T7" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 7</label><caption><p>Management of adverse cardiac events and Clavien&#8211;Dindo classification</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">First author (year)</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adverse cardiac event</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Management</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clavien&#8211;Dindo classification</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Braidy (2011)[<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blood pressure disturbances<break/>Heart rate and rhythm disturbances</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antihypertensive medications (labetalol 10 mg)<break/>Rate control medications (labetalol 30 mg)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Buitelaar (2006)[<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart rate and rhythm disturbances<break/>Ischaemic heart disease<break/>Heart failure and complications</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Death<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Christensen (2019)[<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blood pressure disturbances<break/>Ischaemic heart disease</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Resolved spontaneously</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cramer (2016)[<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ischaemic heart disease<break/>Heart failure and complications</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Required intensive care</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dean (2010)[<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ischaemic heart disease</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Required intensive care</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gates (2021)[<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ischaemic heart disease<break/>Heart failure and complications</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Required intensive care</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ivosevic (2017)[<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart rate and rhythm disturbances</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Resolved spontaneously</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Joshi (2017)[<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart rate and rhythm disturbances</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Resolves spontaneously<break/>Atropine (for two patients)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lalabekyan (2021)[<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ischaemic heart disease</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Death<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mackay (2020)[<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ischaemic heart disease</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coronary artery stent</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Riley (1997)[<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart rate and rhythm disturbances<break/>Ischaemic heart disease<break/>Blood pressure disturbances</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antiarrhythmic medications<break/>Coronary bypass surgery</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spiegel (2005)[<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blood pressure disturbances<break/>Heart rate and rhythm disturbances</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antihypertensive medications<break/>Antiarrhythmic medications</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF1-6"><p><sup>a</sup>Death occurred in six of the 53 patients (11.3%) who developed an adverse cardiac event: ventricular fibrillation (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=1), myocardial infarction (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=1), heart failure (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=4). Deaths occurred on the day of surgery, post-op day 2, 15, 20 and 21. <sup>b</sup>Death occurred in one of the three patients (33.3%) who developed a myocardial infarction on post-op day 4</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The involvement of TCR in ACEs was rare. Only two studies have noted the possible contribution of a vagal brainstem reflex during intraoperative bradycardia.[<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref><xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-4"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>In our systematic review of 34,227 patients, the incidence of perioperative ACEs for patients undergoing maxillofacial surgeries was 2.58%, and with the Freeman&#8211;Tukey arcsine transformation, it was around 4.95%. Considering the results of the leave-one-out meta-analysis and the subgroup analysis based on sample sizes, it is important to recognise that the incidence of 2.58% and 4.95% may be slightly higher than the true incidence.</p><p>Previously, studies have reported similar but slightly higher incidences within non-cardiac surgeries. Smilowitz <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.[<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] found that perioperative ACE occurred in 3.0% of all hospitalisations for non-cardiac surgery between 2004 and 2013, and Oh <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.[<xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] reported a 30-day postoperative incidence of 3.9%. However, these studies reported ACE incidence across a composite of non-cardiac surgeries and found that the majority were attributed to vascular, thoracic and transplant procedures.[<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] In comparison to maxillofacial surgeries, these procedures innately impose a higher risk. This may justify our review's lower incidence of ACEs. A study conducted by Atherton <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.[<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] which evaluated medical emergencies in dental practice, found that, on average, there was one reported cardiac complication over a 40-year career. Although this study focused on specific procedures within maxillofacial surgery, these findings indicate that ACE may be less common among this patient population, which may support our lower incidence.</p><p>The impact of ACEs on maxillofacial surgical outcomes was disproportionately high, with over 37% of patients requiring ICU management (Clavien&#8211;Dindo score of 4). A common ACE associated with ICU admission was IHD. It has been suggested that myocardial injuries are one of the most frequently reported cardiac complications in non-cardiac surgeries, with their incidence varying from 8% in 2014 to 17.9% in recent years.[<xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref><xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref><xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] The mere occurrence of IHD and other ACEs is associated with a plethora of short- and long-term consequences, such as death. After adjusting for sex, age, alcohol consumption and comorbidities, mortality incidence was higher among patients with ACEs than those without.[<xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] In our review, death was reported in seven patients (2.4%): one patient with ventricular fibrillation, two patients with myocardial infarction and four patients with heart failure. Other studies have shown a similar mortality incidence, ranging from 0.5% to 2% by day 30.[<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref><xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] Also, perioperative ACEs are the largest contributor to increased hospital stay and healthcare costs, with patients experiencing ACEs having double the average stay and up to five times the cost.[<xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>] All these show that although the incidence of perioperative ACEs in maxillofacial surgeries is fairly low, its impact on surgical outcomes can be detrimental both to the patient and the healthcare system.</p><p>When considering potential precipitating factors, anaesthetic considerations must be evaluated. Anaesthetic agents influence the development of ACEs, particularly heart rate, rhythm disturbances, and blood pressure changes. In our review, only four studies provided recounts of the anaesthetic details of the surgeries[<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref><xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref><xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref><xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] and only three studies provided specific anaesthetic agents administered.[<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref><xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref><xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] Propofol and ketamine were used for sedation as infusions and for induction as boluses.[<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref><xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref><xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] These medications are sedative&#8211;hypnotic agents with haemodynamic considerations.[<xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>] Propofol is believed to inhibit the sympathetic nervous system and is associated with bradycardia and hypotension.[<xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref><xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] Contrastingly, ketamine has less clinically relevant hypotensive and bradycardic effects.[<xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref><xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] Regardless, the study authors did not consider using either agent to contribute to ACEs. However, remifentanil was suggested to have contributed to the high incidence (24.2%) of intraoperative bradycardia in one study.[<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] In addition to its activity on opioid receptors, remifentanil increases the parasympathetic tone; thus, its usage carries the risk of severe vagal-mediated cardiovascular depression.[<xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref><xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref><xref rid="R51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] Lastly, all three studies used midazolam at either premedication or an induction dose. Midazolam has shown more excellent cardiorespiratory stability than thiopental and diazepam, favouring its suitability as both a bolus and long-term infusion.[<xref rid="R52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]</p><p>The occurrence of particular ACEs, such as the heart rate rhythm and blood pressure disturbances, may be associated with TCR. This reflex is particularly relevant for maxillofacial surgeries because these procedures are performed at the areas of innervation by the trigeminal nerve (CN V).[<xref rid="R53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] Stimulation of the sensory branches of this CN may cause heart rate abnormalities (bradycardia, asystole), changes to blood pressure (hypotension), apnoea and gastric hypermobility.[<xref rid="R53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] In our review, heart rate and rhythm disturbances, specifically bradycardia, were frequently reported. However, only two studies in our review suggested a potential relation between intraoperative bradycardia and this unique brainstem reflex.[<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref><xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] TCR-related bradycardia did not precipitate detrimental complications in both studies. Most cases were resolved spontaneously once the stimuli were halted, and only a minority of patients required intravenous medication such as atropine. These findings concur with other studies, which also surmised that most TCR-induced bradycardia events are self-limiting once the stimuli are removed.[<xref rid="R54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>] However, in some cases, a TCR response may lead to asystole, apnoea and death.[<xref rid="R55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>] Although less common, these negative outcomes should not be taken lightly. Currently, most research surrounding TCR in maxillofacial surgeries is in the form of case reports and series. However, there are still several unanswered questions regarding TCR-induced intraoperative cardiac events. Future research should address these timely and pertinent areas of concern, such as incidence, presentation and perioperative management.</p><p>Lastly, practitioners must consider preventative approaches for perioperative ACEs in maxillofacial surgeries. Firstly, patient profiles, including their comorbidities, play a predisposing role to ACEs in non-cardiac surgeries. In our review, the most commonly captured comorbidities were heart conditions [e.g. coronary artery disease (CAD), arrhythmias, congestive heart failure (CHF)]. Notably, CAD and CHF are independent risk factors for a major ACE in non-cardiac surgeries.[<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] This review also captured patients with renal insufficiency, diabetes and cerebrovascular disease, which are predictors of cardiac complications according to the Revised Cardiac Risk Index.[<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] As the demographic ages and the burden of patient comorbidities rise, the practice of conducting a thorough preoperative evaluation for elective maxillofacial surgeries should be standardised across sites, which is a critical component in minimising the risk of ACEs. In addition, considering the high incidence of IHD that this review revealed, which eventually requires ICU management, preoperative monitoring may be beneficial. Although not routinely indicated, patients at high cardiac risk, determined through a preoperative evaluation, may benefit from laboratory testing to determine baseline troponin levels.[<xref rid="R56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>] This helps to stratify the risk further and inform subsequent decisions.</p><p>Future research in maxillofacial surgeries should focus on several areas. Firstly, large-scale prospective studies examining postoperative cardiac complications should be conducted with an explicit follow-up period for assessing them; future reviews of this topic can provide an incidence rate in person-years format. In addition, future research should strive to provide details about the operation's anaesthetic approach, including information surrounding the technique(s), types and dosage of medications, duration of anaesthetic exposure, ventilation management, etc., It is well known that the anaesthetic aspects are contributory towards precipitating intraoperative complications. Ultimately, this information can be used to understand better the anaesthetic considerations, benefits, and risks of particular approaches and refine guidelines surrounding anaesthesia in maxillofacial surgeries. Lastly, future prospective studies are required to better understand ACEs&#8217; long-term effects following maxillofacial surgery.[<xref rid="R57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]</p><p>Our study had limitations. Firstly, the review's reliance on a relatively small number of studies (12 studies) may have limited the breadth of its analysis. Secondly, publication bias may be evidenced by the asymmetry of the funnel plot and Egger's test <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value &lt;0.01 [<xref rid="ija.ija_1206_23-F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>]. Thirdly, despite this review's attempt at standardisation, the varying definitions of ACEs across studies may still introduce discrepancies in reporting and categorisation. This could lead to the underreporting or overreporting of such events. Fourthly, due to the lack of reporting in follow-up periods across the included studies, we were unable to provide an incidence rate in a person-year format. Fifthly, geographic bias may be a concern since the studies were primarily conducted in Western countries and may not fully represent global populations. Lastly, the review did not adjust for all potentially confounding variables, such as using specific anaesthetic agents that may influence ACEs.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusion" id="sec1-5"><title>CONCLUSION</title><p>Our analysis revealed a 2.58% pooled incidence of perioperative ACEs and found that these ACEs can often negatively affect surgical outcomes (i.e. necessitating ICU admission). In addition, this review conducted separate analyses to evaluate the incidence rates of specific ACE categories that may interest researchers and clinicians in this field. This review maps out the current evidence on this topic and can spark future data-driven research. This hypothesis-generating study reveals areas of interest, such as contributory factors and long-term implications, for future researchers.</p><sec sec-type="funding-statement" id="sec2-11"><title>Financial support and sponsorship</title><p>Nil.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec2-12"><title>Conflicts of interest</title><p>There are no conflicts of interest.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgement</title><p>The authors thank Angelique Roy for her consultation in the development of the search strategy.</p></ack><app-group><app id="APP1"><title>SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIAL</title><p>
<bold>Search development details</bold>
</p><p>Embase Classic + Embase &lt; 1947 to 2023 05 May&gt;</p><p>
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>maxillofacial disorder/or maxillofacial implant/or maxillofacial injury/or maxillofacial surgery/ 18919</p></list-item><list-item><p>exp face surgery/ 55664</p></list-item><list-item><p>exp mandible/su or exp orthognathic surgery/or exp jaw/su 20376</p></list-item><list-item><p>exp oral surgery/ 61585</p></list-item><list-item><p>((maxillofacial or face or facial or mandible or oral or orthognathic or jaw) adj3 (disorder* or implant or
injur* or surger*)).tw, kf. 51940</p></list-item><list-item><p>1 or 2 or 3 or 4 or 5 142328</p></list-item><list-item><p>exp cardiovascular disease/ 5353614</p></list-item><list-item><p>exp heart ventricle tachycardia/or exp heart ventricle arrhythmia/or exp heart arrhythmia/ 631822</p></list-item><list-item><p>exp sinus bradycardia/or exp bradycardia/or exp experimental bradycardia/or exp reflex bradycardia/
68611</p></list-item><list-item><p>exp heart arrest/ 129597</p></list-item><list-item><p>exp heart muscle ischemia/ 102640</p></list-item><list-item><p>exp heart injury/ 56540</p></list-item><list-item><p>major adverse cardiac event/ 15144</p></list-item><list-item><p>exp hypertension/ 962290</p></list-item><list-item><p>exp tachycardia/or exp sinus tachycardia/or exp experimental tachycardia/or exp reflex tachycardia/
192789</p></list-item><list-item><p>((heart or cardiac) adj2 (attack or injury or arrest or ischemia or event)).tw, kf. 115622</p></list-item><list-item><p>(tachycardia or bradycardia or cardiac ischemia or adverse cardiac event or hypertension or arrhythmia).
tw, kf. 962875</p></list-item><list-item><p>7 or 8 or 9 or 10 or 11 or 12 or 13 or 14 or 15 or 16 or 17 5459415</p></list-item><list-item><p>exp perioperative nursing/or exp perioperative care/or exp perioperative period/ 1188583</p></list-item><list-item><p>exp postoperative complication/or exp postoperative monitoring/or exp postoperative period/
1370177</p></list-item><list-item><p>((perioperative or postoperative) adj2 (care or period or nurs* or monitoring)).tw, kf. 103260</p></list-item><list-item><p>postoperative complication.tw, kf. 19978</p></list-item><list-item><p>19 or 20 or 21 or 22 1815994</p></list-item><list-item><p>6 and 18 and 23 3557</p></list-item><list-item><p>24 not (exp juvenile/not exp adult/) 3291</p></list-item></list>
</p></app></app-group><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="R1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiser</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haynes</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Molina</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lipsitz</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Esquivel</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Uribe-Leitza</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group><article-title>Estimate of the global volume of surgery in 2012: An assessment supporting improved health outcomes</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2015</year><volume>385</volume><issue>Suppl 2</issue><fpage>S11</fpage><comment>doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736 (15) 60806-6</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(15)60806-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26313057</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Devereaux</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leslie</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guyatt</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Perioperative cardiac events in patients undergoing non-cardiac surgery: A review of the magnitude of the problem, the pathophysiology of the events and methods to estimate and communicate risk</article-title><source>CMAJ</source><year>2005</year><volume>173</volume><fpage>627</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16157727</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1503/cmaj.050011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1197163</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>VISION Study Investigators</collab>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Devereaux</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso-Coello</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berwanger</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group><article-title>Association between postoperative troponin levels and 30-day mortality among patients undergoing non-cardiac surgery</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2012</year><volume>307</volume><fpage>2295</fpage><lpage>304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22706835</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.2012.5502</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Semel</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lipsitz</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Funk</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bader</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiser</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gawande</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rates and patterns of death after surgery in the United States, 1996 and 2006</article-title><source>Surgery</source><year>2012</year><volume>151</volume><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21975292</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.surg.2011.07.021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Strickland</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quintela</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long-term major adverse cardiovascular events following myocardial injury after non-cardiac surgery: Meta-analysis</article-title><source>BJS Open</source><year>2023</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>zrad021</fpage><comment>doi: 10.1093/bjsopen/zrad021</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37104754</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/bjsopen/zrad021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10129390</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kolokythas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>What is the scope of practice of oral and maxillofacial surgeons?</article-title><source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source><year>2021</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>267.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33386085</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.joms.2020.10.021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alam</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alger-Green</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thyroid surgery by maxillofacial surgeons</article-title><source>Br J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source><year>2020</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>e191.</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Niazi</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Subramanian</surname><given-names>AKR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diana</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pughalaendhi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gurunathan</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kathiresan</surname><given-names>NGS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and pattern of adult maxillofacial injuries: An Institution-based retrospective study</article-title><source>J Pharm Bioallied Sci</source><year>2020</year><volume>12</volume><issue>Suppl 1</issue><fpage>S472</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33149508</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4103/jpbs.JPBS_142_20</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7595492</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Workman</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghantous</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chest pain as a complication of maxillofacial surgery</article-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferneini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><source>Perioperative Assessment of the Maxillofacial Surgery Patient</source><publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name><year>2018</year><fpage>557</fpage><lpage>66</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodrigo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Asystole and bradycardia during maxillofacial surgery</article-title><source>Anesth Prog</source><year>1994</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8629742</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2148710</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Precious</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Skulsky</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cardiac dysrhythmias complicating maxillofacial surgery</article-title><source>Int J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source><year>1990</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>279</fpage><lpage>82.</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2124598</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0901-5027(05)80420-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lambrecht</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Filippi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arrigoni</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cardiovascular monitoring and its consequences in oral surgery</article-title><source>Ann Maxillofac Surg</source><year>2011</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>102</fpage><lpage>6.</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23483785</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4103/2231-0746.92766</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3591025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Page</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McKenzie</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bossuyt</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boutron</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mulrow</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group><article-title>The PRISMA 2020 statement: An updated guideline for reporting systematic reviews</article-title><source>PLoS Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>e1003583</fpage><comment>doi: 10.1371/journal.pmed. 1003583</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33780438</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pmed.1003583</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8007028</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Degu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kejela</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeleke</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Perioperative mortality of emergency and elective surgical patients in a low-income country: A single institution experience</article-title><source>Perioper Med (Lond)</source><year>2023</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>49</fpage><comment>doi: 10.1186/s13741-023-00341-z</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37715264</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13741-023-00341-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10504717</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sazgary</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Puelacher</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lurati Buse</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Glarner</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lampart</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bolliger</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group><article-title>Incidence of major adverse cardiac events following non-cardiac surgery</article-title><source>Eur Heart J Acute Cardiovasc Care</source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>550</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33620378</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/ehjacc/zuaa008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8245139</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>European Society of Cardiology</collab></person-group><article-title>Risk of heart complications after major surgery is higher than previously thought</article-title><source>Eur Heart J Acute Cardiovasc Care</source><year>2020</year><comment>Available from: <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.escardio.org/The-ESC/Press-Office/Press-releases/Risk-of-heart-complications-after-major-surgery-is-higher-than-previously-thought#:~:text=Despite%20the%20advantages%2C%20surgery%20can-that%20their%20risk%20was%20unrecognised">https://www.escardio.org/The-ESC/Press-Office/Press-releases/Risk-of-heart-complications-after-major-surgery-is-higher-than-previously-thought#:~:text=Despite%20the%20advantages%2C%20surgery%20can-that%20their%20risk%20was%20unrecognised</uri>. [Last accessed on 2024 22 January]</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dindo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Demartines</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clavien</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Classification of surgical complications: A new proposal with evaluation in a cohort of 6336 patients and results of a survey</article-title><source>Ann Surg</source><year>2004</year><volume>240</volume><fpage>205</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15273542</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/01.sla.0000133083.54934.ae</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1360123</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meuwly</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chowdhury</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sandu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Golanov</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erne</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosemann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group><article-title>Definition and diagnosis of the trigeminocardiac reflex: A grounded theory approach for an update</article-title><source>Front Neurol</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>533</fpage><comment>doi: 10.3389/fneur. 2017.00533</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29085328</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fneur.2017.00533</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5649131</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lanigan</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van der Wal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trigeminocardiac reflexes: Maxillary and mandibular variants of the oculocardiac reflex</article-title><source>Can J Anaesth</source><year>1991</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>757</fpage><lpage>60.</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1914059</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/BF03008454</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bohluli</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashtiani</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khayampoor</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sadr-Eshkevari</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trigeminocardiac reflex: A MaxFax literature review</article-title><source>Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol Oral Radiol</source><year>2009</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>184</fpage><lpage>8.</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.tripleo.2009.03.050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19615657</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shea</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Connell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Newcastle-Ottawa Scale (NOS) for assessing the quality of case-control studies in meta-analyses</article-title><source>Eur J Epidemiol</source><year>2011</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>603</fpage><lpage>5</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sterne</surname><given-names>JAC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Savovi&#263;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Page</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elbers</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blencowe</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boutron</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group><article-title>RoB 2: A revised tool for assessing risk of bias in randomised trials</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2019</year><volume>366</volume><fpage>l4898</fpage><comment>doi: 10.1136/bmj.l4898</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31462531</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmj.l4898</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Braidy</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ziccardi</surname><given-names>VB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Safety of deep sedation in an urban oral and maxillofacial surgery training program</article-title><source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source><year>2011</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>2112</fpage><lpage>9.</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21783001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.joms.2011.04.017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buitelaar</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Balm</surname><given-names>AJM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Antonini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Tinteren</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huitink</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cardiovascular and respiratory complications after major head and neck surgery</article-title><source>Head Neck</source><year>2006</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>595</fpage><lpage>602.</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16475201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/hed.20374</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Svoboda</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barclay</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Springer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Voegele</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lyu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Outcomes with moderate and deep sedation in an oral and maxillofacial surgery training program</article-title><source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source><year>2019</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>2447</fpage><lpage>51.</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31449763</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.joms.2019.07.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cramer</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>UA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Samant</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Postoperative complications in elderly patients undergoing head and neck surgery: Opportunities for quality improvement</article-title><source>Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</source><year>2016</year><volume>154</volume><fpage>518</fpage><lpage>26.</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26598498</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/0194599815618204</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Desmond</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McGrew</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group><article-title>Outcomes following temporal bone resection</article-title><source>Laryngoscope</source><year>2010</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>1516</fpage><lpage>22.</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20641083</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/lary.20999</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3951338</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gates</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramadan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coutras</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adult palatopharyngoplasty: Trends in morbidity and mortality from the NSQIP database</article-title><source>Ann Otol Rhinol Laryngol</source><year>2021</year><volume>130</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>11.</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32567393</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/0003489420936711</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ivo&#353;evi&#263;</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mili&#269;i&#263;</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dimitrijevi&#263;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ivanovi&#263;</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pavlovi&#263;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stojanovi&#263;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group><article-title>Risk factors for intraoperative bradycardia during ear, nose, throat and maxillofacial surgery</article-title><source>Eur Arch Otorhinolaryngol</source><year>2018</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>579</fpage><lpage>86.</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29214434</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00405-017-4837-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>UM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Munnangi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thakur</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trigemino-cardiac reflex: A phenomenon neglected in maxillofacial surgery?</article-title><source>J Maxillofac Oral Surg</source><year>2017</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>5.</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28439158</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s12663-016-0959-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5385689</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lalabekyan</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tetlow</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moonesinghe</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burdett</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Otto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group><article-title>Cardiopulmonary exercise testing and cardiopulmonary morbidity in patients undergoing major head and neck surgery</article-title><source>Br J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source><year>2021</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>297</fpage><lpage>302.</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33589309</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bjoms.2020.08.032</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>MacKay</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carney</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Catcheside</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chai-Coetzer</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cistulli</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of multilevel upper airway surgery vs medical management on the apnea-hypopnea index and patient-reported daytime sleepiness among patients with moderate or severe obstructive sleep apnea: The SAMS randomised clinical trial</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2020</year><volume>324</volume><fpage>1168</fpage><lpage>79.</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32886102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.2020.14265</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7489419</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guilleminault</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pelayo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Troell</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea surgery: Risk management and complications</article-title><source>Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</source><year>1997</year><volume>117</volume><fpage>648</fpage><lpage>52.</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9419093</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0194-59989770047-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spiegel</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raval</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Overnight hospital stay is not always necessary after uvulopalatopharyngoplasty</article-title><source>Laryngoscope</source><year>2005</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>71.</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15630388</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/01.mlg.0000150703.36075.9c</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smilowitz</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramakrishna</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bangalore</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Perioperative major adverse cardiovascular and cerebrovascular events associated with non-cardiac surgery</article-title><source>JAMA Cardiol</source><year>2017</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28030663</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamacardio.2016.4792</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5563847</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group><article-title>Association between perioperative adverse cardiac events and mortality during one-year follow-up after non-cardiac surgery</article-title><source>J Am Heart Assoc</source><year>2022</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>e024325</fpage><comment>doi: 10.1161/JAHA.121.024325</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35411778</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1161/JAHA.121.024325</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9238468</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Atherton</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCaul</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medical emergencies in general dental practice in Great Britain Part 1: Their prevalence over a 10-year period</article-title><source>Br Dent J</source><year>1999</year><volume>186</volume><fpage>72</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10079576</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.bdj.4800023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Devereaux</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sessler</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cardiac complications in patients undergoing major non-cardiac surgery</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2015</year><volume>373</volume><fpage>2258</fpage><lpage>69</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26630144</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMra1502824</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Botto</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso-Coello</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Villar</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xavier</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Srinathan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group><article-title>Myocardial injury after non-cardiac surgery: A large, international, prospective cohort study establishing diagnostic criteria, characteristics, predictors, and 30-day outcomes</article-title><source>Anesthesiology</source><year>2014</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>564</fpage><lpage>78</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24534856</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/ALN.0000000000000113</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smilowitz</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Redel-Traub</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hausvater</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Armanious</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicholson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Puelacher</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group><article-title>Myocardial injury after non-cardiac surgery: A systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Cardiol Rev</source><year>2019</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>267</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30985328</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/CRD.0000000000000254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6776733</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kristensen</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knuuti</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saraste</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>B&#248;tker</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hert</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group><article-title>2014 ESC/ESA guidelines on non-cardiac surgery: Cardiovascular assessment and management: The Joint Task Force on non-cardiac surgery: Cardiovascular assessment and management of the European Society of Cardiology (ESC) and the European Society of Anaesthesiology (ESA)</article-title><source>Eur Heart J</source><year>2014</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>2383</fpage><lpage>431</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25086026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/eurheartj/ehu282</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sessler</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Devereaux</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Perioperative troponin screening</article-title><source>Anesth Analg</source><year>2016</year><volume>123</volume><fpage>359</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27331782</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1213/ANE.0000000000001450</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Douleh</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yarlagadda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mousavi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sethi</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Drivers of hospital length of stay in 56,000 orthopaedic trauma patients: The impact of postoperative cardiac events</article-title><source>J Clin Orthop Trauma</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28360496</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jcot.2017.02.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5359507</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kanaya</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirata</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurosawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakayama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Namiki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential effects of propofol and sevoflurane on heart rate variability</article-title><source>Anesthesiology</source><year>2003</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>34</fpage><lpage>40.</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12502976</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/00000542-200301000-00009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ebert</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Brien</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Colinco</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muzi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms whereby propofol mediates peripheral vasodilation in humans: Sympathoinhibition or direct vascular relaxation?</article-title><source>Anesthesiology</source><year>1997</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>64</fpage><lpage>72.</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9009941</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/00000542-199701000-00010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ebert</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muzi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berens</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goff</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kampine</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sympathetic responses to induction of anaesthesia in humans with propofol or etomidate</article-title><source>Anesthesiology</source><year>1992</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>725</fpage><lpage>33.</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1575340</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/00000542-199205000-00010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Atchley</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tesoro</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pulver</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benken</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hemodynamic effects of ketamine compared with propofol or dexmedetomidine as continuous ICU sedation</article-title><source>Ann Pharmacother</source><year>2022</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>764</fpage><lpage>72.</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34670425</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/10600280211051028</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of continuous ketamine infusion on hemodynamics and mortality in critically ill children</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2019</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>e0224035</fpage><comment>doi: 10.1371/journal.pone. 0224035</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31626685</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0224035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6799949</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>DeSouza</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>TerRiet</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Severe bradycardia after remifentanil</article-title><source>Anesthesiology</source><year>1997</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>1019</fpage><lpage>20.</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9357922</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/00000542-199710000-00061</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Briassoulis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spanaki</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vassilaki</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fytrolaki</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Michaeloudi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potentially life-threatening bradycardia after remifentanil infusion in a child</article-title><source>Acta Anaesthesiol Scand</source><year>2007</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>1130.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1399-6576.2007.01382.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17697311</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mirakhur</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bradycardia after administration of remifentanil</article-title><source>Br J Anaesth</source><year>2000</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>422</fpage><lpage>3.</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10793617</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/oxfordjournals.bja.a013460</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dundee</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Halliday</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brogden</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Midazolam</article-title><source>Drugs</source><year>1984</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>519</fpage><lpage>43.</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6394264</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2165/00003495-198428060-00002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chowdhury</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Brain and heart connections: The Trigeminocardiac Reflex</article-title><source>J Neuroanaesthesiol Crit Care</source><year>2017</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>7</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arasho</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sandu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spiriev</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prabhakar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schaller</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Management of the trigeminocardiac reflex: Facts and own experience</article-title><source>Neurol India</source><year>2009</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>375</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19770535</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4103/0028-3886.55577</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Loewinger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bradycardia during elevation of a zygomatic arch fracture</article-title><source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source><year>1987</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>710</fpage><lpage>1</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3475443</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0278-2391(87)90315-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Komatsu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turan</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Orhan-Sungur</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McGuire</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Radke</surname><given-names>OC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Apfel</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Remifentanil for general anaesthesia: A systematic review</article-title><source>Anaesthesia</source><year>2007</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>1266</fpage><lpage>80.</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17991265</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1365-2044.2007.05221.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hawn</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Richman</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Itani</surname><given-names>KMF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maddox</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk of major adverse cardiac events following non-cardiac surgery in patients with coronary stents</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2013</year><volume>310</volume><fpage>1462</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24101118</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.2013.278787</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>