<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">63</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmcph</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Public Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2458</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10835853</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10835853.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10835853</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10835853</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38308232</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-024-17827-0</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">17827</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The impact of changes in opioid dependency treatment upon COVID-19 transmission in Sydney, Australia: a retrospective longitudinal observational study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trevitt</surname><given-names initials="BT">Benjamin T.</given-names></name><address><email>benjamin.trevitt@health.nsw.gov.au</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names initials="V">Victoria</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deacon</surname><given-names initials="R">Rachel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mills</surname><given-names initials="L">Llewellyn</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Demirkol</surname><given-names initials="A">Apo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lintzeris</surname><given-names initials="N">Nicholas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03w28pb62</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.477714.6</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0587 919X</institution-id><institution>Drug and Alcohol Services, </institution><institution>South Eastern Sydney Local Health District, </institution></institution-wrap>Sydney, NSW Australia </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03r8z3t63</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.1005.4</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 4902 0432</institution-id><institution>School of Public Health and Community Medicine, </institution><institution>UNSW Sydney, </institution></institution-wrap>Sydney, Australia </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/0384j8v12</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.1013.3</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 834X</institution-id><institution>Speciality Addiction Medicine, Faculty Medicine and Health, </institution><institution>University of Sydney, </institution></institution-wrap>Sydney, NSW Australia </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Drug and Alcohol Clinical Research and Improvement Network, Sydney, NSW Australia </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>2</day><month>2</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>24</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">452043</issue-id><elocation-id>349</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>1</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>02</day><month>02</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>02</day><month>02</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-10-21 20:25:37.220"><day>21</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2024</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="12889_2024_Article_17827.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">In April 2020, in response to the COVID-19 public health emergency, South Eastern Sydney Local Health District (SESLHD) Drug and Alcohol services modified their delivery of opioid dependency treatment (ODT) to reduce spread of COVID-19 and maintain continuity of care by increasing use of takeaway doses (TADs), transferring clients to local community pharmacies for dosing and encouraging the use of long-acting depot buprenorphine (LADB) which enabled once a month dosing.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">This study was a retrospective longitudinal case&#8211;control study conducted from August 1st, to November 30th, 2021. Eligible clients were those admitted for treatment with SESLHD ODT Services prior to August 1st,2021 and who remained in treatment beyond November 30th, 2021. COVID-19 diagnoses were determined by a COVID-19 PCR and extracted from the electronic Medical Records (eMR) Discern Reporting Portal. Demographic, clinical and dosing related data were collected from eMR and the Australian Immunisation Register (AIR).</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">Clients attending SESLHD ODT services had significantly greater odds of acquiring COVID-19 than the NSW adult population at large (OR: 13.63, 95%CI: 9.64,18.88). Additionally, amongst SESLHD ODT clients, being of Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander origin was associated with greater odds of acquiring COVID-19 (OR&#8201;=&#8201;2.18, CI: 1.05,4.53); whilst being employed (OR&#8201;=&#8201;0.06, CI:0.01,0.46), receiving doses at pharmacy (OR&#8201;=&#8201;0.43, CI: 0.21,0.89), and being vaccinated (OR&#8201;=&#8201;0.12, CI: 0.06,0.26) were associated with lower odds. Every additional day of attendance required for dosing was associated with a 5% increase in odds of acquiring COVID-19 (OR&#8201;=&#8201;1.05, CI: 1.02,1.08).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">Clients attending SESLHD ODT services are significantly more likely to acquire COVID-19 than the NSW population at large. Promoting vaccination uptake, transferring clients to pharmacy, and reducing the frequency of dosing (by use of takeaway doses or long-acting depot buprenorphine) are all potential methods to reduce this risk.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>COVID-19</kwd><kwd>Opioid dependency treatment</kwd><kwd>Takeaway dose</kwd><kwd>Vaccination</kwd><kwd>Methadone</kwd><kwd>Sublingual buprenorphine</kwd><kwd>Long acting depot buprenorphine</kwd><kwd>Harm reduction</kwd><kwd>Vulnerable populations</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#169; BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2024</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par22">Coronavirus (COVID-19) is an infectious disease caused by severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. It was first detected in Wuhan City, China, in December 2019 during a local outbreak of respiratory illnesses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] and by March 2020 the World Health Organisation had declared it a global pandemic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. At the time of writing, Australia had already been exposed to eight different waves of COVID-19 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>], however the delta-wave outbreak (June 16, 2021 to December 15, 2021) was one of the most fatal, especially for younger populations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Over eighty thousand COVID-19 cases were recorded in New South Wales (NSW) during this timeframe (mean&#8201;=&#8201;453.4 cases/day), with a case fatality rate of 0.71% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Although extensive public health measures had already been implemented to reduce case numbers and fatalities at the time of the delta wave outbreak, (e.g. legislation enforcing mask wearing and isolation of cases, and campaigns promoting vaccination uptake) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>], the highly contagious and evolving nature of the virus meant that case fatality rates still inevitably remained high. Moreover, beyond case-fatalities, there is now a growing body of evidence that COVID-19 has long-term psychological (e.g. anxiety and depression) and physical (e.g. palpitations, sleep difficulty, hair-loss, myalgia, fatigue, anosmia and dizziness) impacts on the quality of life of many of its survivors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. It has also profoundly impacted the health of the general population, particularly health-care workers, due to increased work-related stressors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>].</p><p id="Par23">People with substance use disorders (SUDs) have higher rates of comorbidities, (such as mental health, diabetes, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, chronic kidney disease and hepatitis C) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>], than the general population. Additionally, they often face significant social disadvantages, such as homelessness, poverty, and discrimination, which can be barriers to healthcare service access [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Consequently, not only are they more vulnerable to a more severe COVID-19 illness but they are also less likely to have access to the support, information, and tools to facilitate and/or enable COVID-19 prevention, screening, and treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Emerging data, largely from North America, has illustrated that people with SUDs are significantly more likely to develop [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>], be hospitalised [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>] or die [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>] from COVID-19 than people without SUDs. Indeed, one large retrospective case control study (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;73,099,850) conducted in North America in 2020 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>] found that, of all substance users, those with opioid use disorders (both recent and long-term diagnosis) were the most at risk of COVID-19 acquisition compared to non-substance users (OR&#8201;=&#8201;10.2 (9.1&#8211;11.5) and 2.4 (2.2&#8211;2.6)) respectively) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Thus, urgent implementation of public health measures targeting this at-risk group was critical.</p><p id="Par24">South Eastern Sydney Local Health District (SESLHD) Drug and Alcohol Services have provided a range of inpatient and community-based treatment and harm reduction services for people with SUDs for over 60&#160;years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. This includes provision of opioid dependence treatment (ODT) with either oral methadone, sublingual buprenorphine (SL-BPN) or long acting depot buprenorphine (LADB) to between 520 to 600 clients at any one time, as well as counselling and social support [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Prior to COVID-19, ODT had conditions requiring daily attendance for dosing at either clinics or community pharmacies (for methadone and SL-BPN), with limited takeaway doses (TADs) available for clients assessed as &#8216;low risk&#8217; for safety [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. COVID-19 raised significant concerns for ODT services in their ability to implement effective social distancing, personal protective equipment (PPE) and isolation of cases- necessary to protect clients, staff, and their families [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Additionally, according to some recent international studies, clients with SUDs had (and still have) significantly lower vaccination rates than the rest of their communities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>].</p><p id="Par25">In April 2020, in response to the public health emergency, SESLHD dramatically modified its delivery of ODT with the aims of reducing the spread of COVID-19 and maintaining continuity of care [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>] by: increasing use of TADs; transferring clients to local community pharmacies for dosing; encouraging the use of LADB (enabling once a month dosing); increasing the use of telehealth services with clients; introducing perimeter screening of staff and clients entering clinic settings; enforcing the use of PPE for staff and mask wearing for clients in clinical settings; enforcing mandatory COVID-19 vaccination of staff; encouraging and providing COVID-19 vaccination to clients; and ensuring access to reverse transcriptase polymerase chain reaction (PCR) (and later rapid antigen [RAT]) testing for staff and clients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Other societal changes occurred in Australia outside of the treatment setting, at various periods of the COVID-19 pandemic, including provision of emergency housing for people with unstable accommodation, greater economic assistance for people with reduced employment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>], restrictions to travel in the community [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>], and free COVID-19 vaccination rollouts via medical practices and pharmacies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>].</p><p id="Par26">Many evaluations of ODT service changes in response to COVID-19 have demonstrated that neither increasing the number of TADs of methadone or SL-BPN, nor switching clients to LADB treatment was associated with negative treatment outcomes or poorer treatment adherence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Additionally, there is evidence that clients who received more TADs or who were on LADB had better continuity of care when in isolation, higher treatment retention, no significant increase in substance use, and a higher satisfaction with treatment and care in general [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>].</p><p id="Par27">However, we believe that this is the first study to evaluate whether these service changes were effective in reducing the spread of COVID-19 amongst ODT clients. This study will focus on the delta COVID-19 wave which commenced in NSW mid-2021 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>] and specifically the 4-month period August 1st, 2021 to November 30th, 2021. The reason behind the above timeframe is the relatively low total number of COVID-19 cases that had occurred across SESLHD (a population catchment of 1 million people) and the whole of NSW (population of 8.2 million) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>] prior to August 2021 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;928 and <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;8,725 respectively) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>] compared to the significantly larger number that occurred between August 1st, and November 30th, 2021 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;2,366 and <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;73,002 respectively) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. In fact, SESLHD ODT services had record of only one COVID-19 positive case occurring prior to June 2021. Additionally, during the selected timeframe, only PCR tests were considered diagnostic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>], and all positive PCR tests were automatically recorded centrally in a large database, the NSW Notifiable Conditions Information Management System (NCIMS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. However, in November 2021, due to the increasing number of positive cases, the Therapeutic Goods Administration began authorising the sale of select self-test rapid antigen test (RAT) kits [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. RAT tests were required to have a clinical sensitivity of at least 80% and a clinical specificity of at least 98% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>] and by January 2022 were considered sufficient for a positive COVID-19 diagnosis in NSW [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. This meant accurate capture of all positive cases became increasingly difficult as positive results were not automatically reported to NSW Health.</p><p id="Par28">The primary aim of this study was to determine whether treatment characteristics (dosing site, frequency required to attend clinic/pharmacy for dosing and medication type [methadone, SL-BPN, LADB]) or client characteristics (demographics, housing, employment, and vaccination status) significantly impacted on COVID-19 infection rates in ODT populations. The secondary aim was to identify whether infection rates of SESLHD ODT clients were comparable with the infection rates of NSW at large.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><p id="Par29">This study employed a retrospective longitudinal case control design of ODT clients who attended SESLHD Drug and Alcohol Services from August 1st, to November 30th, 2021. It examined the impact of location and type of treatment, frequency of attendance, and client characteristics, on COVID-19 infection rates. To be eligible for inclusion, ODT clients had to be admitted for treatment with SESLHD Drug and Alcohol Services prior to August 1st, 2021 and have remained in treatment beyond November 30th, 2021. Clinical data was sourced from the electronic medical record (eMR) system which is routinely used in NSW healthcare settings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>] and cross-checked, where necessary, with iDose (an electronic medication device which records doses of methadone, SL-BPN and LADB administered at clinics) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>].</p><sec id="Sec3"><title>Drug and alcohol services for ODT</title><p id="Par30">SESLHD Drug and Alcohol Services provides ODT to approximately 520 to 600 clients at any one time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>] within multidisciplinary teams (consisting of doctors, nurses, allied health, pharmacists and consumer workers) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. All services are free for clients, except for private dispensing fees for those dosing at community pharmacies. As of August 2021, 49% of SESLHD ODT clients were on methadone, 16% on SL-BPN and 35% on LADB. Dosing of methadone and SL-BPN could occur at either clinic or pharmacies with TADs available at pharmacies only, whilst LADB dosing was only available at clinics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Further information regarding the change in location, type of dosing, and number of TADs administered to clients in response to the COVID-19 pandemic is available in a previous research paper [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Study team and participants</title><p id="Par31">The study team consisted of clinicians, consumer-workers and researchers from SESLHD Drug and Alcohol Services who contributed to the development of the key research questions, study design, data-analysis and write-up. The participants were clients who received ODT services through SESLHD for the entire four-month period of August 1st, to November 30th, 2021. Client demographics and ODT treatment conditions were captured in SESLHD electronic medical records (eMR) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. All clients who tested positive for COVID-19 during this time frame were extracted from the Discern Reporting Portal, a feature of eMR which allows one to run various reports and extract information such as COVID-19 diagnoses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. All information recorded was de-identified. This study was retrospectively conducted by SESLHD healthcare workers with input from the Aboriginal Health Unit to ensure it was handled in a culturally appropriate manner. Research was performed in accordance with the guidelines and regulations presented in the Declaration of Helsinki. The SESLHD Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC),<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn1">1</xref> at a meeting of its Low and Negligible Risk Research Review Committee, waivered the need for informed consent and ethical approval for this study. It also determined that the study did not raise any ethical risks requiring submission to an ethical review committee in accordance with NSW Health Policy.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Evaluation period, eligibility, data sources and measures</title><p id="Par32">All clients enrolled in ODT with SESLHD Drug and Alcohol Services for the entire time-period were eligible for inclusion in the study. Data from the Australian Treatment Outcome Profile (ATOP) questionnaires [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>], eMR entries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>], patient paper-files, and iDose [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>] between August 1st, 2021 and November 30th, 2021 were captured to determine basic demographics (gender, age, housing situation, and employment status) and details of current opioid treatment (medication type, TADs, and dosing site). Data were exported from the Discern Reporting Portal in eMR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>] and the Australian Immunisation Register (AIR) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>] to determine case and vaccination status of clients respectively.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Client descriptors</title><p id="Par33">Client descriptors including demographics, substance use and social conditions were measured by ATOP&#8212;a brief questionnaire which has been validated in Australian Drug and Alcohol treatment populations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. The ATOP includes client-reported information regarding recent substance use (number of days out of the previous 28 that they used substances), ratings of physical health, psychological health and overall quality of life on scales from one (poor) to ten (excellent), about recent occupational status (proportion of the last 28&#160;days spent working/studying) and are assessed for homelessness risk and recent experience of violence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. ATOPs are routinely completed every two to three months as part of routine clinical care [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Treatment descriptors</title><p id="Par34">The <italic toggle="yes">Opioid Substitution Treatment Module</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>] details a client&#8217;s prescribed medication, (methadone, SL-BPN or LADB), dosing location, and the number of TADs received per week. This module is routinely completed by the prescribing doctor every 2-to-3&#160;months, or following any change in medication conditions.</p><p id="Par35"><italic toggle="yes">iDose</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>] details the frequency of attendance, ODT medication and dose of clients who attend SESLHD ODT clinics for dosing.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>COVID-19 and Vaccination status measurements</title><p id="Par36">A COVID-19 diagnosis was determined from a COVID PCR as it was considered the gold-standard at the time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. Positive COVID-19 diagnoses were extracted from the eMR Discern Reporting Portal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>] after being uploaded by the SESLHD Public Health Unit (PHU).</p><p id="Par37">A fully vaccinated status was defined as having received at least two doses of approved COVID-19 vaccines, as this was the NSW health criteria at the time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. A client&#8217;s vaccination status was extracted from the AIR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Data analysis</title><p id="Par38">Data was exported from eMR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>], the AIR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>] and iDOSE [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>] to Microsoft Excel where it was cleaned and collated. Data analysis was conducted using STATA v17.</p><p id="Par39">Descriptive analyses of clients&#8217; demographics (age, gender and Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn2">2</xref> status, and employment, housing, and vaccination statuses) were undertaken and compared based on ODT characteristics (e.g. medication type, dosing location and frequency of attendance required for dosing). Differences between groups were determined by comparing means and calculating odds ratios using linear and logistic regression models respectively.</p><p id="Par40">Univariate and multivariate logistic regression models were developed using demographic variables (i.e. age, gender, employment and housing status) and treatment conditions (i.e. dosing location, attendance requirements and medication type) to assess which demographic and treatment characteristics were significantly protective against COVID-19 infection. A new covariate &#8216;number of days the client was required to attend per month for dosing&#8217; was created to replace the covariate &#8216;number of takeaways per week&#8217;, to allow for inclusion of clients receiving LADB in the analysis.</p><p id="Par41">To determine which covariates to include in the final multivariate model, data was split into training and validation subsamples and the least absolute shrinkage and selection operator (lasso) was utilised to estimate model coefficients. Cross-validation, adaptive lasso and plug-in methods of tuning parameter estimation were compared based on out-of-sample mean squared error (MSE).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec11"><title>Participants</title><p id="Par42">As of August 1st, 2021 there were 522 clients enrolled in treatment at SESLHD ODT Drug and Alcohol Services. Clients discharged from the service prior to November 30th, 2021 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;78) were excluded from further analysis. Of the 444 remaining clients four had no recorded information about employment or housing status, fourteen changed pharmacological treatment or location of dosing during the above time frames, and eight had no data on vaccination status. 418 (94%) of eligible clients had complete data and were thereby included in baseline analysis (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig.&#160;1</label><caption><p>Flow chart of eligibility requirements for inclusion in the study</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO1" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12889_2024_17827_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par43">Demographics and baseline characteristics of the 418 ODT clients were compared based on prescribed opioid (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), place of dosing (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>), and number of TADs (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table&#160;1</label><caption><p>Characteristics of clients receiving ODT by prescribed opioid</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Characteristic</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Methadone (M) (</bold><bold><italic toggle="yes">n</italic></bold><bold>&#8201;=&#8201;202)</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>SL-BPN (S) (</bold><bold><italic toggle="yes">n</italic></bold><bold>&#8201;=&#8201;69)</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>LADB (L) (</bold><bold><italic toggle="yes">n</italic></bold><bold>&#8201;=&#8201;147)</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Total (</bold><bold><italic toggle="yes">n</italic></bold><bold>&#8201;=&#8201;418)</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Coefficient</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Comparison estimate (95% CI)</bold><sup>a</sup>
</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></bold><bold>-value</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1"><bold>Age</bold>, numeric, in y, M (SD)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">43.0 (10.15)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">40.3 (12.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">40.8 (11.01)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">41.8 (11.00)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1"> Beta</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">M-S: 2.7 (-0.31,5.69)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.08</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">M-L: 2.3 (-0.07,4.60) </td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.06</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">S-L: -0.4 (-3.57,2.71) </td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.79</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1"><bold>Gender</bold>, binary, (female [ref] vs male), n(%) male</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">146 (72%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">44 (64%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">89 (61%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">279 (67%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Odds Ratio</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">M-S: 1.5 (0.83,2.64) </td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>M-L: 1.7 (1.08,2.67) </bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.02</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">S-L: 1.1 (0.63,2.07) </td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.65</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1"><bold>Aboriginal client,</bold> binary, (Non-Aboriginal [ref] vs Aboriginal), n(%) Aboriginal</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">42 (21%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">12 (17%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">20 (14%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">74 (18%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Odds Ratio</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">M-S: 1.2 (0.61,2.53) </td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.54</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">M-L: 1.7 (0.93,2.98) </td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.09</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">S-L: 1.3 (0.61,2.92) </td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.47</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1"><bold>Employment status,</bold> binary, (Unemployed [ref] vs Employed), n(%) employed</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">40 (20%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">30 (43%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">41 (28%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">111 (27%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Odds Ratio</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>M-S: 0.3 (0.18,0.58)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">M-L: 0.6 (0.39,1.05) </td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.08</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>S-L: 2.0 (1.09,3.61) </bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.02</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1"><bold>Housing status</bold> binary, (Not homeless [ref] vs Homeless), n(%) Homeless</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">8 (4%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">1 (1%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">10 (7%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">19 (5%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Odds Ratio</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">M-S: 2.8 (0.34,22.83) </td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.34</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">M-L: 0.6 (0.22,1.47)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.24</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">S-L: 0.2 (0.03,1.61) </td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1"><bold>Vaccination status</bold> binary, (Not fully vaccinated [ref] vs Vaccinated), n(%) Vaccinated</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">135 (67%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">44 (64%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">107 (73%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">286 (68%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Odds Ratio</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">M-S: 1.1 (0.65,2.03) </td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.64</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">M-L: 0.8 (0.47,1.20) </td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.23</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">S-L: 0.7 (0.36,1.21) </td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.18</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>Unadjusted estimates of beta coefficients and odds ratios have been presented in this table</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table&#160;2</label><caption><p>Characteristics of clients receiving ODT by Dosing Site</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Characteristic</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pharmacy (P)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Clinic (C)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Coefficient</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Comparisons estimate (95% CI)<sup>a</sup></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Age</bold>, numeric, in y, M (SD)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.2 (11.22)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41.5 (10.80)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41.8 (10.99)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Beta</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P&#8211;C: 0.7 (-1.46,2.79)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.54</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Gender</bold>, binary, (female [ref] vs male), n(%) male</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">126 (67%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">153 (67%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">279 (67%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Odds Ratio</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P&#8211;C: 1.0 (0.68,1.54)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.91</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Aboriginal client,</bold> binary, (Non-Aboriginal [ref] vs Aboriginal), n(%) Aboriginal</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33 (18%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41 (18%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">74 (18%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Odds Ratio</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P&#8211;C: 1.0 (0.59,1.63)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.94</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Employment status,</bold> binary, (Unemployed [ref] vs Employed), n(%) employed</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64 (34%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47 (20%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">111 (27%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Odds Ratio</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>P&#8211;C: 2.0 (1.29,3.12)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.002</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Housing status</bold> binary, (Not homeless [ref] vs Homeless), n(%) Homeless</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 17 (7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21 (5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Odds Ratio</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>P&#8211;C: 0.1 (0.03,0.59)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.008</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Vaccination status</bold> binary, (Not fully vaccinated [ref] vs Vaccinated), n(%) Vaccinated</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">126 (67%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 160 (70%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">286 (68%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Odds Ratio</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P&#8211;C: 0.9 (0.59,1.35)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.58</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>Unadjusted estimates of beta coefficients and odds ratios have been presented in this table</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table&#160;3</label><caption><p>Characteristics of clients receiving ODT by weekly dosing site attendance</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Characteristic</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;&#8201;=&#8201;1 time (A) (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;235)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2&#8211;5 times (B) (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;78)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6&#8211;7 times (C) (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;105)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Coefficient</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Comparisons estimate (95% CI)<sup>a</sup></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><bold>Age</bold>, numeric, in y, M (SD)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">41.4 (11.57)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">41.3 (9.91)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">43.1 (10.37)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Beta</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C-B: 1.8 (-1.43,5.02)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.28</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>C-A: 1.8 (-0.77,4.30)</p><p>B-A: 0.0 (-2.85,2.79)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.17</p><p>0.98</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1"><bold>Gender</bold>, binary, (female [ref] vs male), n(%) male</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">141 (60%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1"> 54 (69%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">84 (80%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Odds Ratio</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C-B: 1.8 (0.90,3.50) </td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>C-A: 2.7 (1.55,4.60)</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B-A: 1.5 (0.87,2.59)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.15</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1"><bold>Aboriginal client,</bold> binary, (Non-Aboriginal [ref] vs Aboriginal), n(%) Aboriginal</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">31 (13%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">18 (23%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">25 (24%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Odds Ratio</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C-B: 1.0 (0.52,2.08)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.91</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>C-A: 2.1 (1.14,3.70)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.02</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>B-A: 2.0 (1.03,3.77)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.04</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1"><bold>Employment status,</bold> binary, (Unemployed [ref] vs Employed), n(%) employed</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">80 (34%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">26 (33%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">5 (5%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Odds Ratio</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>C-B: 0.1 (0.04,0.28)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>C-A: 0.1 (0.04,0.25)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B-A: 1.0 (0.56,1.67)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.91</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1"><bold>Housing status</bold> binary, (Not homeless [ref] vs Homeless), n(%) Homeless</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">10 (4%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">1 (1%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">8 (8%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Odds Ratio</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C-B: 6.4 (0.78,51.88)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.09</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C-A: 1.9 (0.72,4.84)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.21</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B-A: 0.3 (0.04,2.32)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.24</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1"><bold>Vaccination status</bold> binary, (Not fully vaccinated [ref] vs Vaccinated), n(%) Vaccinated</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">172 (73%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">52 (67%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">62 (59%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Odds Ratio</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C-B: 0.7 (0.39,1.33)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.29</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>C-A: 0.5 (0.33,0.86)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.01</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B-A: 0.7 (0.42,1.27)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.27</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par44">Clients on methadone, SL-BPN and LADB did not differ significantly in terms of age. The odds of clients on methadone being male were significantly greater than that of clients on LADB. The odds of clients on methadone being employed were significantly less than that of clients on LADB or SL-BPN (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p><p id="Par45">The odds of clients dosing at pharmacy being employed were significantly higher than that of clients dosing at clinics. The odds of clients dosing at pharmacy being homeless were significantly lower than clients dosing at clinics (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p><p id="Par46">The odds of clients required to attend clinic or pharmacy six for more times per week for dosing (accessing methadone or SL-BPN) being male or identifying as Aboriginal were significantly higher than that of clients required to attend one or less times per week (accessing methadone or SL BPN TADs or in LADB treatment). The odds of clients required to attend clinic or pharmacy six or seven times per week for dosing being employed or vaccinated were significantly lower than that of clients required to attend one or less times per week (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Vaccination status</title><p id="Par47">By the end of October 2021 <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;286 (68%) of SESLHD ODT clients had been double vaccinated. This was considerably lower than NSW, as a whole, which reported a double vaccination rate of 83% at that time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>].</p><p id="Par48">Double vaccinated clients were required to attend dosing sites significantly less frequently than unvaccinated clients (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). The odds of double vaccinated clients being employed were significantly higher than that of unvaccinated clients, whilst the odds of double vaccinated clients identifying as Aboriginal were significantly lower than that of unvaccinated clients.
<table-wrap id="Tab4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table&#160;4</label><caption><p>Characteristics of clients receiving ODT by vaccination status</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Characteristic</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vaccinated (V) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;286)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unvaccinated (U) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;132)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Coefficient</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Comparisons estimate (95% CI)<sup>a</sup></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Age</bold>, numeric, in y, M (SD)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.4 (11.14)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40.4 (10.56)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Beta</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">V-U: 2.0 (-0.24,4.30)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.08</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Gender</bold>, binary, (female [ref] vs male), n(%) male</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">191 (67%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88 (67%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Odds Ratio</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">V-U: 1.0 (0.65,1.56)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.98</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Aboriginal client,</bold> binary, (Non-Aboriginal [ref] vs Aboriginal), n(%) Aboriginal</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43 (15%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31 (23%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Odds Ratio</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>V-U: 0.6 (0.34,0.97)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.04</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Employment status,</bold> binary, (Unemployed [ref] vs Employed), n(%) employed</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">91 (32%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 (15%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Odds Ratio</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>V-U: 2.6 (1.53,4.47)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Housing status</bold> binary, (Not homeless [ref] vs Homeless), n(%) Homeless</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13 (5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Odds Ratio</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">V-U: 1.0 (0.37,2.69)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Dosing location</bold> binary, (Clinic [ref] vs Pharmacy), n(%) Pharmacy</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">126 (44%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">62 (47%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Odds Ratio</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">V-U: 0.9 (0.59,1.35)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.58</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Dosing Type</bold> binary, (injection [ref] vs oral/SL), n(%) oral/SL</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">179 (63%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92 (70%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Odds Ratio</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">V-U: 0.7 (0.47,1.13)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Monthly attendance for dosing, numeric, in days (M, SD)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.3 (10.60)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.3 (11.54)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Beta</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>V-U: -3.0 (-5.29,-0.77)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.009</bold></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>Unadjusted estimates of beta coefficients and odds ratios have been presented in this table</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Patient outcomes &#8211; COVID-19 univariate analysis</title><p id="Par49">Univariate analysis revealed that the odds of Aboriginal clients acquiring COVID-19 during the study timeframe were significantly higher than that of non-Aboriginal clients; whilst the odds of employed clients and clients dosing at pharmacies acquiring COVID-19 were significantly lower than that of unemployed clients and clients dosing at clinics respectively (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>). Additionally, the odds of clients required to attend clinic or pharmacy one or less or between two and five times per week acquiring COVID-19 were significantly lower than that of clients required to attend six to seven times per week. These statistically significant results still held when clients receiving LADB and clients receiving oral ODT were analysed separately. In fact, every additional day per month of required attendance for dosing was associated with a 5% increase in odds of acquiring COVID-19.
<table-wrap id="Tab5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table&#160;5</label><caption><p>Univariate modelling and frequencies by covariates with COVID-19 acquisition as outcome</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Characteristic</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">COVID-19 positive</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Age</bold>, numeric, mean (SD), in y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41.8 (10.99)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.01 (0.98,1.04)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.58</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><bold>Gender</bold>, binary, (female [ref] vs male)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Female (n, %)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14 (10.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Male (n, %)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26 (9.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.92 (0.46,1.82)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.81</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Aboriginal client,</bold> binary, (Non-Aboriginal [ref] vs Aboriginal)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.18 (1.05,4.53)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.04</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Non-Aboriginal (n, %)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28 (8.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Aboriginal (n, %)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 (16.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Employment status,</bold> binary, (Unemployed [ref] vs Employed)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.06 (0.01,0.46)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.007</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Unemployed (n, %)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39 (12.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Employed (n, %)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Housing status</bold> binary, (Not homeless [ref] vs Homeless)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.83 (0.51, 6.59)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.35</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Not homeless (n, %)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37 (9.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Homeless (n, %)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (15.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Dosing location</bold> binary, (Clinic [ref] vs Pharmacy)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.43 (0.21, 0.89)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.03</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Clinic (n, %)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29 (12.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Pharmacy (n, %)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (5.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Dosing Type</bold> binary, (Injection [ref] vs Oral)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.30 (0.64,2.63)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.47</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Injection (n, %)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 (8.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Oral (n, %)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28 (10.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Vaccination status</bold> binary, (not vaccinated [ref] vs fully vaccinated)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.12 (0.06,0.26)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Not vaccinated (n, %)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30 (22.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Fully vaccinated (n, %)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (3.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><bold>Weekly attendance rate,</bold> (6&#8201;+&#8201;[ref] vs 0&#8211;1, 2&#8211;5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;0-1 times per week (overall)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 (6.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.29 (0.14,0.60)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;0&#8211;1 times per week (inj. only)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (6.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.38 (0.18,0.81)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.01</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;0&#8211;1 times per week (oral only)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 (19.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.15 (0.04,0.52)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.003</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;2&#8211;5 times per week</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.29 (0.10,0.81)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.02</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;6&#8201;+&#8201;times per week</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference group</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference group</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Number of days attending clinic/pharmacy for dosing, mean (SD)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.8 (12.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.05 (1.02,1.08)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.001</bold></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Patient outcomes &#8211; COVID-19 multivariate analysis</title><p id="Par50">The final multivariate model used as predictor for the likelihood COVID-19 acquisition was obtained using the cross-validation based lasso method and included covariates of vaccination status, dosing location, employment status, required attendance per month (in days), whether the client identified as Aboriginal, and age (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>). Covariates sex and homelessness were also included in the model, but their coefficients were reduced to zero.
<table-wrap id="Tab6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Multivariate modelling using the cross-validation based lasso method with COVID acquisition as outcome</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Characteristic</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Employment status,</bold> binary, (Unemployed [ref] vs Employed)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.12 (0.01,1.00)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.05</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Vaccination status,</bold> binary, (Unvaccinated [ref] vs Vaccinated)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.13 (0.06,0.29)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Dosing location</bold> binary, (Clinic [ref] vs Pharmacy)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.43 (0.19,0.97)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.04</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Number of days attending clinic/pharmacy</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.03 (1.00,1.06)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.05</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Aboriginal Client,</bold> binary (non-Aboriginal [ref] vs Aboriginal)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.85 (0.81,4.20)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.15</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Age (years)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.02 (0.98, 1,06)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par51">SESLHD covers nine local governments areas, expanding from Sydney Central Business District to the Royal National Park, and manages eight public hospitals, twelve community health centres, nine oral health clinics, as well as mental health, youth health, sexual health and imaging and pathology services [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. It also offers three major public drug and alcohol clinics located in Surry Hills, Kogarah, and Sutherland [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>].</p><p id="Par52">Although preventative strategies such as reducing the frequency that clients are required to attend clinic/pharmacy for dosing by increasing TADs, transferring clients&#8217; dosing points to pharmacy and encouraging clients to switch to LADB from methadone or SL-BPN have taken place nationally and globally since the outbreak of the pandemic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>], this appears to be the first study to determine whether these strategies protected this already vulnerable population against COVID-19 infection.</p><p id="Par53">Our findings demonstrate strong evidence linking employment status, vaccination status, dosing location, and frequency of clinic or pharmacy attendance, to the likelihood of attaining COVID-19 infection amongst a cohort of clients receiving ODT between August 1st, and November 30th, 2021. Clients who were required to attend clinic once a week or less for oral ODT and clients receiving LADB were both significantly less likely to acquire COVID-19 than clients required to attend for dosing six or more times a week. However, we were unable to further stratify clients into those receiving weekly versus monthly LADB due to the low sample size of the former group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;3).</p><p id="Par54">Clients who identified as Aboriginal also had a higher risk of COVID-19 infection, (although not statistically significant in the multivariate logistic regression model after adjusting for other covariates). This inequity undoubtedly stems from the history of colonial oppression and the ongoing structural violence, racism, stigma, and intergenerational trauma faced by the Aboriginal community, the resultant mistrust in Australian health-care systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>], and the consequential lower vaccination rates, poorer treatment adherence, higher rates of missed doses and higher dosing-site attendance requirements than non-Aboriginal clients. In fact, the subgroups of clients known, from prior research, to be at an inherently greater risk of COVID-19 infection (i.e. unemployed, unvaccinated and Aboriginal people) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] were required, on average, to attend for dosing more frequently than their counterparts, based on risk assessments conducted by their prescribing doctors.</p><p id="Par55">The significantly lower COVID-19 vaccination rates amongst our cohort (68%) vs NSW vaccination rates (83%) at the end of October 2021 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>] could be partially explained by both the younger age of our cohort (vaccinations targeted the elderly first and the AstraZeneca and Pfizer vaccines had only been implemented in NSW six months prior) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>] and that almost 20% of SESLHD ODT clients identified as Aboriginal (compared to about 3.4% of the population of NSW) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. This hypothesis is supported by the fact that after stratifying by age and excluding those who identified as Aboriginal, the difference in vaccination rates between the SESLHD Drug and Alcohol ODT community and those of NSW at large [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>] reduced, particularly in the younger age group. As of October 21.<sup>st</sup>, 2021, 69% of SESLHD ODT Non-Aboriginal clients aged 16&#8211;49 were fully vaccinated compared to 70% of the NSW population aged 16&#8211;49; whilst 75% of SESLHD ODT Non-Aboriginal Clients aged 50&#8211;69 were fully vaccinated compared to 88% of the NSW population aged 50&#8211;69 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]</p><p id="Par56">Data on the proportion of Aboriginal people in NSW fully vaccinated by the end of October 2021, stratified by demographics such as age, employment status and gender, is very limited. However, it was reported that by the end of October 2021, 110,371 NSW Aboriginal people had been fully vaccinated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>], representing about 56% of the NSW Aboriginal population eligible for vaccinations at the time<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn3">3</xref> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. This was slightly less than the proportion of Aboriginal people attending SESLHD for ODT at the time who had been fully vaccinated -approximately 58%. This could perhaps be explained by the fact that Aboriginal people not on ODT may not regularly attend healthcare centres, and thus were less likely to be offered COVID-19 vaccinations on a regular basis.</p><p id="Par57">Whilst international literature had consistently voiced that COVID-19 vaccination rates were lower amongst clients with SUDs, (e.g. in countries such as Italy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>], America [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>], Canada [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>] and Spain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]), our data indicated that vaccination uptake in ODT clients was comparable to the general population after adjusting for age and whether a client identified as Aboriginal. This involved considerable effort and targeted strategies by ODT staff to increase vaccination uptake amongst clients, including providing vaccinations in ODT services, consumer worker activities and financial incentives ($20 supermarket vouchers) for clients to complete vaccination.</p><p id="Par58">Finally, approximately 10% (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;41) of SESLHD ODT clients contracted COVID-19 during the timeframe of the study which was over ten times the COVID acquisition rate of NSW adults at large across the same time span (0.8%, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;48,558) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. In addition to their requirements to regularly attend clinics/pharmacies for dosing, this also could be explained by their higher rates of unemployment (73% vs 4%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>], homelessness (5% vs 0.5%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>] and Aboriginality (18% vs 3.4%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>], as well as their lower vaccination rates (68% vs 83% as of October 21st, 2021) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>] and substance use.</p><p id="Par59">This study is relevant as it is the first to quantify the effectiveness, in terms of COVID-19 acquisition, of relaxing requirements for ODT clients to dose at pharmacy and of reducing the frequency of attendance required for supervised dosing. Had these measures not been implemented, our findings suggest that SESLHD ODT clients would likely have suffered significantly higher rates of COVID-19 acquisition with potentially serious complications. However, this study also revealed that clients whose demographics had already placed them at a higher risk of COVID-19 infection (e.g. unemployed, homeless, Aboriginal people) were less likely to have received these treatment adjustments. Much of this inequity can be explained by the structural violence, stigma and/or discrimination faced by these groups resulting in a reluctance to access and trust healthcare services and providers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>], Although much progress has been made in terms of the prevention (e.g. ongoing vaccine developments and roll-outs) and pharmacological management of COVID-19, it is generally agreed that the COVID-19 pandemic is still far from over [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. Thus, further research into how to safely and effectively reduce the frequency of clinic or pharmacy attendance required by this subgroup of clients should remain a priority.</p><p id="Par60">The results of this study are limited as these measures were established across SESLHD ODT clinics at the beginning of the first wave of COVID-19 in NSW (April 2020), prior to any recorded cases occurring amongst SESLHD ODT clients, meaning whilst we were able to conclude that clients who received these interventions were less likely to acquire COVID-19 than those who did not, we could not definitively establish that these interventions themselves caused a reduction in COVID-19 infection rates amongst clients.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par61">There is a clear association between dosing site, required attendance and vaccination status of clients, and COVID-19 acquisition, highlighting the importance of adjustments to the ODT model of care in preventing COVID-19 transmission, not only to clients, but also to healthcare workers in these settings. The fact that the more vulnerable clients already at a higher risk of COVID-19 (e.g. clients identifying as Aboriginal and unemployed clients) were required to attend more frequently for dosing and were less likely to be vaccinated calls for further research targeting these subgroups to appropriately address these modifiable risk factors.</p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>COVID-19</term><def><p id="Par5">Coronavirus-19</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ODT</term><def><p id="Par6">Opioid dependency treatment</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SESLHD</term><def><p id="Par7">South Eastern Sydney local health district</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TAD</term><def><p id="Par8">Takeaway doses</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LADB</term><def><p id="Par9">Long-acting depot buprenorphine</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>eMR</term><def><p id="Par10">Electronic medical records</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>AIR</term><def><p id="Par11">Australian immunisation register</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NSW</term><def><p id="Par12">New South Wales</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SUD</term><def><p id="Par13">Substance use disorder</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SL-BPN</term><def><p id="Par14">Sublingual buprenorphine</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PPE</term><def><p id="Par15">Personal protective equipment</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PCR</term><def><p id="Par16">Polymerase chain reaction</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RAT</term><def><p id="Par17">Rapid antigen testing</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NCIMS</term><def><p id="Par18">Notifiable conditions information management system</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ATOP</term><def><p id="Par19">Australian treatment outcomes profile</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PHU</term><def><p id="Par20">Public health unit</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MSE</term><def><p id="Par21">Mean squared error</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn id="Fn1"><label>1</label><p id="Par66">SESLHD HREC is constituted and operates in accordance with the National Health and Medical Research Council&#8217;s (NHMRC) <italic toggle="yes">National Statement on Ethical Conduction in Human Research (2007),</italic> NHRMC and Universities Australia <italic toggle="yes">Australian Code for the Responsible Conduct of Research (2007)</italic> and the <italic toggle="yes">CPMP/ICH Note for Guidance on Good Clinical Practice.</italic></p></fn><fn id="Fn2"><label>2</label><p id="Par67">Henceforth the term &#8220;Aboriginal&#8221; is used to represent &#8220;Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander&#8221;, in recognition that Aboriginal people are the original inhabitants of New South Wales.</p></fn><fn id="Fn3"><label>3</label><p id="Par68">It is estimated that in 2021 approximately 292,147 Aboriginal Australians lived in NSW of which 68% were&#8201;&gt;&#8201;15&#160;years old.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#8217;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We would like to acknowledge the Aboriginal Health Unit, in particular Ms Tiana Parashko and Mr Timothy Croft for their input on the handling and reporting of Aboriginal data. We would also like to acknowledge the input from SESLHD Drug and Alcohol senior nursing and management staff (Tracy Cowan, Helen Hamilton, Matthew Burdess, and Fiona O&#8217;Neill, health information manager (Therese Finch), consumer workers (Louisa Jansen, Sophie Maiolo, Andrew McDonnell), and clients of the service.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#8217; contributions</title><p>B.T. led the investigation, the curation and analysis of the data, and wrote the original draft manuscript with support from V.H. and N.L.. V.H. assisted in organising meetings with co-authors and representatives from the Aboriginal Health Unit. R.D. assisted in data curation. L.M. provided advice on statistical methodologies and reporting. N.L. provided initial feedback prior to circulation of the original manuscript to remaining authors. All authors contributed to the conceptualisation of the research topic, read and provided feedback to the original manuscript, and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This study received no external funding. This study was funded by Drug and Alcohol Services, SESLHD.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>The datasets used and/or analysed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par62">Research was performed in accordance with the guidelines and regulations presented in the Declaration of Helsinki. The SESLHD Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC) (SESLHD HREC is constituted and operates in accordance with the National Health and Medical Research Council&#8217;s (NHMRC) <italic toggle="yes">National Statement on Ethical Conduction in Human Research (2007),</italic> NHRMC and Universities Australia&#8217;s <italic toggle="yes">Australian Code for the Responsible Conduct of Research (2007)</italic> and the <italic toggle="yes">CPMP/ICH Note for Guidance on Good Clinical Practice.</italic>), at a meeting of its Low and Negligible Risk Research Review Committee, waived the need for informed consent due to the fact that the data collected would be non-specific and clients would not be identifiable. The SESLHD HREC also waived the need for ethical approval of this study, and deemed that this study did not raise any ethical risks requiring submission to an ethical review committee in accordance with NSW Health Policy.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par63">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par64">NL has received funding from Camurus and Indivior for unrelated research.</p><p id="Par65">All authors have affiliations with South Eastern Sydney Local Health District Drug and Alcohol Services. There are no other competing interests to declare.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Cennimo D. Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19). 2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://emedicine.medscape.com/article/2500114-overview#a1">https://emedicine.medscape.com/article/2500114-overview#a1</ext-link> Accessed 26 Feb 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cucinotta</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vanelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>WHO Declares COVID-19 a pandemic</article-title><source>Acta Biomed</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.23750/abm.v91i1.9397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32191675</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7569573</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Australian Government Department of Health and Aged Care. Communicable Diseases Intelligence: COVID-19 Australia: Epidemiology Report 77. 2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www1.health.gov.au/internet/main/publishing.nsf/Content/99424DA2A5F3A488CA2589BA0019141B/$File/covid_19_australia_epidemiology_report_77__reporting_period_ending_30_july_2023.pdf">https://www1.health.gov.au/internet/main/publishing.nsf/Content/99424DA2A5F3A488CA2589BA0019141B/$File/covid_19_australia_epidemiology_report_77__reporting_period_ending_30_july_2023.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed 31 Dec 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fahriani M, Ilmawan M, Fajar JK, Maliga HA, Frediansyah A, Masyeni S et al. Persistence of long COVID symptoms in COVID-19 survivors worldwide and its potential pathogenesis &#8211; A systematic review and meta-analysis. Narra J. 2021;&#160;10.52225/narraj.v1i2.36.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.52225/narraj.v1i2.36</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10914031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38449463</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fajar JK, Ilmawan M, Mamada S, Mutiawati E, Husnah M, Yusuf H et al. Global prevalence of persistent neuromuscular symptoms and the possible pathomechanisms in COVID-19 recovered individuals: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Narra J. 2021; doi: 10.52225/narra.v1i3.48.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.52225/narra.v1i3.48</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10914045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38450213</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hamdan A, Eastaugh J, Snygg J, Naidu J, Alhaj I. Coping strategies used by healthcare professionals during COVID-19 pandemic in Duabi: A descriptive cross-sectional study. Narra X. 2023; 10.52225/narrax.v1i1.71.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunlop</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lokuge</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Masters</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sequeira</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saul</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunlop</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Challenges in maintaining treatment services for people who use drugs during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>Harm Reduct J</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12954-020-00370-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32375887</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7201394</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>QQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaelber</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Volkow</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>COVID-19 risk and outcomes in patients with substance use disorders: analyses from electronic health records in the United States</article-title><source>Mol Psychiatry</source><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41380-020-00880-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32929211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7488216</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Volkow</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Collision of the COVID-19 and Addiction Epidemics</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/M20-1212</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32240293</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7138334</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dubey</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chatterjee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Biswas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chatterjee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dubey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>COVID-19 and addiction</article-title><source>Diabetes Metab Syndr</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.dsx.2020.06.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32540735</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7282772</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hilller-Sturmhoefel S. People With SUDs Have Increased Risk for COVID-19 and Worse Outcomes. National Institute on Drug Abuse. 2021. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://nida.nih.gov/news-events/nida-notes/2021/01/people-with-suds-have-increased-risk-for-covid-19-worse-outcomes">https://nida.nih.gov/news-events/nida-notes/2021/01/people-with-suds-have-increased-risk-for-covid-19-worse-outcomes</ext-link>. Accessed 29 Jan 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wang L, Wang Q, Davis PB, Volkow ND, Xu R. Increased risk for COVID-19 breakthrough infection in fully vaccinated patients with substance use disorders in the United States between December 2020 and August 2021. World Psychiatry. 2022;10.1002/wps.20921.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/wps.20921</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8661963</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34612005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pavarin</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>FabbrI</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Ronchi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>COVID-19 hospitalisation rates in individuals with substance or alcohol use disorders</article-title><source>Psychiatry Res</source><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psychres.2022.114521</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35338951</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8934434</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">NSW Health South East Sydney Local Health District. Drug and Alcohol Services. 2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.seslhd.health.nsw.gov.au/services-clinics/directory/drug-and-alcohol-services">https://www.seslhd.health.nsw.gov.au/services-clinics/directory/drug-and-alcohol-services</ext-link>. Accessed 26 Feb 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lintzeris</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deacon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cowan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parvaresh</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Opioid agonist treatment and patient outcomes during the COVID-19 pandemic in South East Sydney</article-title><source>Australia Drug Alcohol Rev</source><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/dar.13382</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34520592</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8652992</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lintzeris N, Hayes V, Arunogiri S. Interim guidance for the delivery of medication assisted treatment of opioid dependence in response to COVID&#8208;19: a national response. 2020. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.racp.edu.au//docs/default&#x2010;source/news&#x2010;and&#x2010;events/covid&#x2010;19/interim&#x2010;guidance&#x2010;delivery&#x2010;of&#x2010;medication&#x2010;assisted&#x2010;treatment&#x2010;of&#x2010;opiod&#x2010;dependence&#x2010;covid&#x2010;19.pdf?sfvrsn=e36eeb1a_4">https://www.racp.edu.au//docs/default&#8208;source/news&#8208;and&#8208;events/covid&#8208;19/interim&#8208;guidance&#8208;delivery&#8208;of&#8208;medication&#8208;assisted&#8208;treatment&#8208;of&#8208;opiod&#8208;dependence&#8208;covid&#8208;19.pdf?sfvrsn=e36eeb1a_4</ext-link>. Accessed 14 Dec 2022.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scheibein</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stowe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shirasaka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grandinettei</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Responding to COVID-19: emerging practices in addiction medicine in 17 countries</article-title><source>Front Psychiatry</source><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2021.634309</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33796034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8009036</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">The University of British Columbia. Lower vaccination rates among people who use drugs could lead to serious outcomes from COVID-19. 2022. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.med.ubc.ca/news/lower-vaccination-rates-among-people-who-use-drugs-could-lead-to-serious-outcomes-from-covid-19/">https://www.med.ubc.ca/news/lower-vaccination-rates-among-people-who-use-drugs-could-lead-to-serious-outcomes-from-covid-19/</ext-link>. Accessed 14 Jan 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mondera</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Direnzo</surname><given-names>GFM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cammalleri</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forestiero</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turatto</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baccolini</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>COVID-19 vaccination adherence and correlated factors in patients with substance use disorders</article-title><source>Eur J Public Health</source><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurpub/ckac131.351</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mondera</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cammalleri</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forestiero</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turatto</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Direnzo</surname><given-names>GFM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Napoli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Adherence to SARS-CoV-2 vaccination recommendations among patients with substance use disorders: A cross-sectional study in Rome</article-title><source>Italy Vacc</source><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/vaccines1109143</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10538200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37766111</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Javanbakht</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mustanski</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shoptaw</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baum</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Substance use and other factors associated with COVID-19 vaccine uptake among people at risk for or living with HIV: Findings from the C3PNO consortium</article-title><source>Prev Med Rep</source><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pmedr.2023.102300</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37455759</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10289823</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurdyak</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lebenbaum</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patrikar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rivera</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Damon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SARS-CoV-2 vaccination prevalence by mental health diagnosis: a population-based cross-sectional study in Ontario</article-title><source>Canada CMAJ Open</source><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.9778/cmajo.20220210</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37989512</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10681672</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vallecillo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dur&#225;n</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Canosa</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roquer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perell&#243;</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>COVID-19 vaccination coverage and vaccine hesitancy among people with opioid use disorder in Barcelona</article-title><source>Spain Drug Alcohol Rev</source><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/dar.1350</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35668697</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9348033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Leishman C, Aminpour F, Baker E, Beer A, Crowe A, Goodall Z, et al. Australia&#8217;s COVID-19 pandemic housing policy responses. Australian Housing and Urban Research Institute Limited Melbourne. 2022;&#160;10.18408/ahuri3227801.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Parliament of Australia. Australian Government COVID-19 disaster payments: a quick guide. 2022. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.aph.gov.au/About_Parliament/Parliamentary_Departments/Parliamentary_Library/pubs/rp/rp2122/Quick_Guides/COVID-19DisasterPayments">https://www.aph.gov.au/About_Parliament/Parliamentary_Departments/Parliamentary_Library/pubs/rp/rp2122/Quick_Guides/COVID-19DisasterPayments</ext-link>. Accessed 30 Jan 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Australian National Audit Office (ANAO). Australia&#8217;s COVID-19 Vaccine Rollout. 2022. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.anao.gov.au/work/performance-audit/australia-covid-19-vaccine-rollout">https://www.anao.gov.au/work/performance-audit/australia-covid-19-vaccine-rollout</ext-link>. Accessed 29 Jan 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lintzeris</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunlop</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haber</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lubman</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hutchinson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Patient-reported outcomes of treatment of opioid dependence with weekly and monthly subcutaneous depot vs daily sublingual buprenorphine: a randomised clinical trial</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.9041</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33970256</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8111483</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nadipelli</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Solem</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ronquest</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yeh</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Learned</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of monthly buprenorphine extended-release injections on patient-centered outcomes: A long-term study</article-title><source>J Subst Abuse Treat</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsat.2019.11.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31952623</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frost</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lintzeris</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunlop</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nunes</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long-term safety of a weekly and monthly subcutaneous buprenorphine depot (CAM2038) in the treatment of adult out-patients with opioid use disorder</article-title><source>Addiction</source><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/add.14636</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31013390</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6771955</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Amram</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amiri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Panwala</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lutz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Joudrey</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Socias</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of relaxation of methadone take-home protocols on treatment outcomes in the COVID-19 era</article-title><source>Am J Drug Alcohol Abuse</source><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00952990.2021.1979991</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34670453</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foot</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levander</surname><given-names>XA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Terashima</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McIlven</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Treatment retention, return to use, and recovery support following COVID-19 relaxation of methadone take-home dosing in two rural opioid treatment programs: A mixed methods analysis</article-title><source>J Subst Abuse Treat</source><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsat.2022.108801</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35589443</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9080674</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Australian Bureau of Statistics. COVID-19 Mortality by wave. 2022. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.abs.gov.au/articles/covid-19-mortality-wave">https://www.abs.gov.au/articles/covid-19-mortality-wave</ext-link>. Accessed 23 Jan 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Australian Bureau of Statistics. National, state and territory population. 2021. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.abs.gov.au/statistics/people/population/national-state-and-territory-population/jun-2021#states-and-territories">https://www.abs.gov.au/statistics/people/population/national-state-and-territory-population/jun-2021#states-and-territories</ext-link>. Accessed 23 Jan 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">NSW Health. COVID-19 (Coronavirus Statistics). 2021. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.health.nsw.gov.au/news/Pages/20210731_01.aspx">http://www.health.nsw.gov.au/news/Pages/20210731_01.aspx</ext-link>. Accessed 24 Jan 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">NSW Health. COVID-19 (Coronavirus Statistics). 2021. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.health.nsw.gov.au/news/Pages/20211201_00.aspx">http://www.health.nsw.gov.au/news/Pages/20211201_00.aspx</ext-link>. Accessed 27 Jan 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">NSW Health Data NSW. COVID-19 cases by notification date and age, local health district and local government area.csv. 2022. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://data.nsw.gov.au/data/dataset/covid-19-cases-by-age-range/resource/24b34cb5-8b01-4008-9d93-d14cf5518aec">https://data.nsw.gov.au/data/dataset/covid-19-cases-by-age-range/resource/24b34cb5-8b01-4008-9d93-d14cf5518aec</ext-link>. Accessed 12 Dec 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">NSW Health. COVID-19 Weekly Surveillance in NSW: Epidemiology week 01 ending 8 January 2022. 2022. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.health.nsw.gov.au/Infectious/covid-19/Documents/covid-19-surveillance-report-20220120.pdf">https://www.health.nsw.gov.au/Infectious/covid-19/Documents/covid-19-surveillance-report-20220120.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed 9 Jan 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Population Health Research Network (PHRN). National Research Infrastructure for Australia. 2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.phrn.org.au/about-us/">https://www.phrn.org.au/about-us/</ext-link>. Accessed 4 Feb 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">NSW Government. Framework for the Provision of Rapid Antigen Screening for COVID-19 in Clinical and Non-Clinical settings. 2021. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.nsw.gov.au/sites/default/files/2021-08/210817_COVID_Rapid-Anitgen-Testing_indicative-Process_A3_v10.pdf">https://www.nsw.gov.au/sites/default/files/2021-08/210817_COVID_Rapid-Anitgen-Testing_indicative-Process_A3_v10.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed 3 Feb 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bell KJL, Li Yuyang, Medcalf E, Ackermann D. COVID-19 rapid antigen tests approved for self-testing in Australia: published diagnostic test accuracy studies and manufacturer-supplied information. A systematic review. Medical Journal of Australia. 2021; 10.5694/mja2.52151.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5694/mja2.52151</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10952141</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37903650</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Australian Government Department of Health and Aged Care. COVID-19 rapid antigen self-tests (for home use). 2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.tga.gov.au/products/covid-19/covid-19-tests/covid-19-rapid-antigen-self-tests-home-use">https://www.tga.gov.au/products/covid-19/covid-19-tests/covid-19-rapid-antigen-self-tests-home-use</ext-link>. Accessed 31 Dec 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Public Health Network, Central and Eastern Sydney. COVID-19 Update &#8211; 12 January 2022. 2022. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cesphn.org.au/news/covid-19-update-12-january-2022">https://cesphn.org.au/news/covid-19-update-12-january-2022</ext-link>. Accessed 1 Feb 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">NSW Government. Electronic Medical Record (eMR). 2022. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ehealth.nsw.gov.au/solutions/clinical-care/electronic-medical-records">https://www.ehealth.nsw.gov.au/solutions/clinical-care/electronic-medical-records</ext-link>. Accessed 12 Dec 2022.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">NSW Government. Guidance on use of the iDose system by registered nurses at the NSW Health facilities. 2020. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.health.nsw.gov.au/aod/professionals/Pages/idose-nurses-guidance.aspx">https://www.health.nsw.gov.au/aod/professionals/Pages/idose-nurses-guidance.aspx</ext-link>. Accessed 19 Jan 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">NSW Ministry of Health.&#160;NSW clinical guidelines for opioid dependence. 2018. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.health.nsw.gov.au/aod/Pages/nsw-clinical-guidelines-opioid.aspx">https://www.health.nsw.gov.au/aod/Pages/nsw-clinical-guidelines-opioid.aspx</ext-link>. Accessed 17 Dec 2022.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lintzeris N, Mammen K, Holmes J,&#160;Deacon R, Mills L, Black E, et al.&#160;Australian Treatment Outcomes Profile (ATOP) Manual 1: Using the ATOP with individual clients. COQI. 2020; ISBN: 978&#8211;0&#8211;6489170&#8211;0&#8211;7.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Australian Government Department of Health and Aged Care. Australian Immunisation Register contact<italic toggle="yes">.</italic> 2021. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.health.gov.au/contacts/australian-immunisation-register-contact">https://www.health.gov.au/contacts/australian-immunisation-register-contact</ext-link>. Accessed 2 Feb 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Australian Government Department of Health and Aged Care. Covid-19 testing in Australia &#8211; information for health professionals. 2022. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.tga.gov.au/covid-19-testing-australia-information-health-professionals#:~:text=PCR%20tests%20are%20generally%20considered,laboratory%20equipment%20and%20trained%20technicians">https://www.tga.gov.au/covid-19-testing-australia-information-health-professionals#:~:text=PCR%20tests%20are%20generally%20considered,laboratory%20equipment%20and%20trained%20technicians</ext-link>. Accessed 29 Jan 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Australian Government: Operation COVID Shield. COVID-19 Vaccine Rollout. 2021. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.health.gov.au/sites/default/files/documents/2021/10/covid-19-vaccine-rollout-update-21-october-2021.pdf">https://www.health.gov.au/sites/default/files/documents/2021/10/covid-19-vaccine-rollout-update-21-october-2021.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed 3 Feb 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">NSW Government. South East Sydney Local Health District. 2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.seslhd.health.nsw.gov.au">https://www.seslhd.health.nsw.gov.au</ext-link><underline>.</underline> Accessed 31 Dec 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wright P, Angeli I. Racism in Healthcare. ANTAR. 2021, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://antar.org.au/wp-content/uploads/2021/05/Racism-in-Healthcare-Backgrounder.pdf">https://antar.org.au/wp-content/uploads/2021/05/Racism-in-Healthcare-Backgrounder.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed 31 Dec 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Australian Bureau of Statistics. Australia: Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander population summary. 2022. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.abs.gov.au/articles/australia-aboriginal-and-torres-strait-islander-population-summary">https://www.abs.gov.au/articles/australia-aboriginal-and-torres-strait-islander-population-summary</ext-link>. Accessed 23 Jan 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Australian Government Department of Health and Aged Care. Operation COVID Shield, COVID-19 Vaccine Rollout<italic toggle="yes">.</italic> 2021. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.health.gov.au/resources/publications/covid-19-vaccine-rollout-update-28-october-2021?language=en">https://www.health.gov.au/resources/publications/covid-19-vaccine-rollout-update-28-october-2021?language=en</ext-link>. Accessed 29 Jan 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Australian Institute of Health and Welfare. Profile of Indigenous Australians. 2021. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.aihw.gov.au/reports/australias-welfare/profile-of-indigenous-australians">https://www.aihw.gov.au/reports/australias-welfare/profile-of-indigenous-australians</ext-link>. Accessed 21 Jan 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Australian Bureau of Statistics. Labour Force, Australia. 2021. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.abs.gov.au/statistics/labour/employment-and-unemployment/labour-force-australia/dec-2021">https://www.abs.gov.au/statistics/labour/employment-and-unemployment/labour-force-australia/dec-2021</ext-link>. Accessed 31 Jan 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Australian Institute of Health and Welfare. Homelessness and homelessness services. 2021. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.aihw.gov.au/reports/australias-welfare/homelessness-and-homelessness-services">https://www.aihw.gov.au/reports/australias-welfare/homelessness-and-homelessness-services</ext-link>. Accessed 2 Feb 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">The Lancet. The COVID-19 pandemic in 2023: far from over. Lancet. 2023. doi:10.1016/S0140-6736(23)00050-8.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>