<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">eBioMedicine</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">EBioMedicine</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2749</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">ebiom</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>eBioMedicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2352-3964</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11731619</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11731619.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11731619</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11731619</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39719798</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ebiom.2024.105509</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2352-3964(24)00545-0</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">105509</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Reducing unnecessary preoperative testing through a comprehensive EMR based digital algorithm</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name name-style="western"><surname>Esper</surname><given-names initials="SA">Stephen A.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">g</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name name-style="western"><surname>Holder-Murray</surname><given-names initials="J">Jennifer</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">g</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meister</surname><given-names initials="K">Katie</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sylvia Lin</surname><given-names initials="HH">Hsing-Hua</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names initials="AK">Alison K.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6"><name name-style="western"><surname>Artman</surname><given-names initials="J">Jamie</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au7"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garver</surname><given-names initials="M">Michael</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">e</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au8"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lukanski</surname><given-names initials="A">Amy</given-names></name><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">f</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au9"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zuckerbraun</surname><given-names initials="BS">Brian Scott</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au10"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marroquin</surname><given-names initials="O">Oscar</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au11"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahajan</surname><given-names initials="A">Aman</given-names></name><email>mahajana@upmc.edu</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#8727;</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Anesthesiology and Perioperative Medicine, University of Pittsburgh Medical Center (UPMC)</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Department of Surgery, University of Pittsburgh Medical Center (UPMC)</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Department of Anesthesiology and Perioperative Medicine, University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Heart and Vascular Institute, University of Pittsburgh Medical Center (UPMC)</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>e</label>University of Pittsburgh Medical Center (UPMC)</aff><aff id="aff6"><label>f</label>Wolff Center, University of Pittsburgh Medical Center (UPMC)</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#8727;</label>Corresponding author. Department of Anesthesiology &amp; Perioperative Medicine, University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine, UPMC Enterprises, UPMC Perioperative and Surgical Services, Biomedical Informatics, and Pharmacology, University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine, Swanson School of Engineering, Scaife Hall, A-1305, 3550 Terrace Street, Pittsburgh, PA 15213, USA. <email>mahajana@upmc.edu</email></corresp><fn id="fn1"><label>g</label><p id="ntpara0010">Stephen A. Esper and Jennifer Holder-Murray contributed equally and should be considered co-first authors.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>111</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">477298</issue-id><elocation-id>105509</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>26</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>4</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>23</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>14</day><month>01</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-01-28 17:25:14.320"><day>28</day><month>01</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2024 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><abstract id="abs0010"><title>Summary</title><sec><title>Background</title><p>We hypothesised that the implementation of an electronic medical record (EMR) embedded perioperative clinical decision support (CDS) application, Anesthesia Testing Guidelines (ATG), would result in at least a 10% reduction of unnecessary perioperative testing in patients undergoing elective surgeries.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>The development and implementation of ATG occurred in several phases: 1) team development, 2) development of an embedded EMR application, 3) creation of ATG training and education toolkit, and 4) implementation involving promoting ATG through training and education, addressing challenges, and monitoring compliance. The proportions of patients with any overutilisation across 19 perioperative tests were compared between the baseline cohort and the ATG implementation cohort.</p></sec><sec><title>Findings</title><p>The overutilisation of perioperative tests was observed in 77.6% of the baseline cohort (n&#160;=&#160;59,799) and 68.1% in the ATG cohort (n&#160;=&#160;132,131), with a significant 12.2% reduction over two years of implementation (p&#160;&lt;&#160;0.0001). The two tests with the greatest amount of associated cost were reduced by 46% for chest X-rays and 39% for complete metabolic panels. The health system was able to reduce overall costs by 22% from baseline.</p><p>Interrupted time series analysis estimated an immediate 7.5% decrease in monthly overutilisation when ATG initially launched, and it continued to decrease by 0.24% per month.</p></sec><sec><title>Interpretation</title><p>Our findings suggest CDS ATG is a successful tactic to reduce unnecessary preoperative testing while maintaining quality of care and improving cost avoidance. This type of CDS implementation approach transforms organisational behaviour and medical practices to follow defined guidelines, thereby improving the value of care.</p></sec><sec><title>Funding</title><p>CDS ATG was supported by <funding-source id="gs1">UPMC Department of Anesthesiology and Perioperative Medicine</funding-source> and <funding-source id="gs2">UPMC Department of Finance</funding-source>.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Anesthesiology</kwd><kwd>Preoperative testing guidelines</kwd><kwd>Cost avoidance</kwd><kwd>Surgery</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="p0010">
<boxed-text id="dtbox1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Research in context</title></caption><sec id="dtbox1sec1"><title>Evidence before this study</title><p id="p0015">Preoperative testing is performed to screen for surgical risk factors and to assess the state of underlying patient comorbidities; yet unnecessary laboratory and imaging studies are frequently ordered for reasons which may include: surgeon or anesthesiologist preference; fear of medicolegal repercussions; non-evidence-based protocols; and in many instances, false assumption of clinical necessity.</p><p id="p0020">Implementation of uniform and standardized practices and guidelines across multiple clinical services and hospitals in a health system remains a challenge. The primary aim of this study was to develop electronic medical record (EMR) embedded CDS application, Anesthesia Testing Guidelines (ATG), to reduce unnecessary preoperative testing that could be efficiently implemented in a large health system.</p></sec><sec id="dtbox1sec2"><title>Added value of this study</title><p id="p0025">An evidence-based, digital platform-enabled approach embedded in the EMR is a successful tactic to reduce unnecessary preoperative testing, while maintaining quality of care and improving cost avoidance.</p></sec><sec id="dtbox1sec3"><title>Implications of all the available evidence</title><p id="p0030">We demonstrated that an easy-to-use ATG toolkit provided marked reduction in unnecessary preoperative testing. Further emphasis on provider or departmental feedback and education will likely improve unnecessary testing further. This ATG implementation approach transforms medical practices to follow defined guidelines, thereby improving the value of care.</p></sec></boxed-text>
</p><sec id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0035">Preoperative testing is performed to screen for surgical risk factors and to assess the state of underlying patient comorbidities<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref>; yet unnecessary laboratory and imaging studies are frequently ordered for reasons which may include: surgeon or anaesthetist preference; fear of medicolegal repercussions; non-evidence-based protocols; and in many instances, false assumption of clinical necessity.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> Despite overwhelming evidence describing the overutilisation of preoperative medical testing, even with clear published guidelines on appropriate testing,<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> the estimated cost of preoperative testing has risen to $18 billion annually in the United States.<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> Additionally, false-positive or borderline results (in the absence of a clinical indication), which may require further investigation, can further cause unnecessary psychological and economic burdens, postponement of surgery, and even morbidity and mortality (e.g., complications due to unnecessary biopsies performed to follow up false-positive laboratory tests).<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref></p><p id="p0040">Success of quality improvement programs in the surgical services requires methodical and comprehensive education, training, data reporting, and compliance measures across multiple disparate groups.<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> Implementation of uniform and standardised practises and guidelines across multiple clinical services and hospitals in a health system remains a challenge. Digital quality improvement and clinical decision support (CDS) methods have been utilised to improve health care delivery processes.<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref></p><p id="p0045">The primary aim of this study was to develop and test an electronic medical record (EMR) embedded CDS application, Anesthesia Testing Guidelines (ATG), to reduce unnecessary preoperative testing that could be efficiently implemented across multiple service lines and hospitals in a large health system. We describe the detailed steps undertaken to achieve the successful implementation of this digital platform in clinical practise and report the subsequent outcomes of laboratory testing reduction and cost avoidance for all patients undergoing surgery. We hypothesised that the implementation of an EMR embedded perioperative CDS ATG would result in at least a 10% reduction of unnecessary perioperative testing in all patients undergoing elective surgery at a large hospital system.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="sec2.1"><title>Study population</title><p id="p0050">This prospective cohort includes adult surgical cases (&#8805;18 years, regardless of demographic) and received elective surgery in an operating room setting across 11 health system hospitals affiliated with the University of Pittsburgh Medical Center (UPMC) in Allegheny County. Patients who had undergone elective surgery between July 1, 2019 through June 30, 2020 were used as a baseline cohort. We analysed the baseline cohort to understand the scope of over utilization in perioperative tests and to help develop the UPMC health system Anesthesia Testing Guidelines (ATG). The following six months (July&#8211;December, 2020) was the washout period when we focused on the development of the embedded ATG application and targeted education and training of health system staff and faculty. ATG initiative was launched on January 1, 2021 across the UPMC health system. Adult patients who had elective surgery from January 1, 2021 through December 31, 2022 were evaluated as the ATG implementation cohort.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="p0055">Institutional Review Board (IRB) at the University of Pittsburgh approved this study with a waiver of consent (STUDY20050148).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><title>Anesthesia Testing Guidelines (ATG)</title><p id="p0060">The UPMC health system ATG are preoperative testing recommendations based on patient age, comorbidity and scheduled surgery that are created and iteratively reviewed by a multidisciplinary team following review of the current literature and society recommendations (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#160;1</xref>). These guidelines are published on the UPMC Health System Infonet (Infonet) and are provided to preoperative clinics, surgeon offices, and preoperative testing clinics, with annual updates if necessary. ATG included 19 perioperative tests: 1) basic metabolic panels (BMP), 2) Comprehensive metabolic panels (CMP), and 3) electrolyte panels (LYTES); electrolytes including 4) sodium (Na) and 5) potassium (K); renal measures including 6) creatinine (Cr) and 7) blood urea nitrogen (BUN); liver function testing including 8) liver enzymes, 9) platelets; 10) glucose, 11) hemoglobin A1c (HbA1c); 12&#8211;13) complete blood count without/with differential (CBC, DIFF); 14) hemoglobin and hematocrit (H&amp;H); 15) prothrombin time/international normalised ratio (PT/INR); 16) partial thromboplastin time (PTT); 17) toxicology screen; and non-laboratory testing including 18) electrocardiogram (EKG) and 19) chest x-ray (CXR). Perioperative testing recorded took place at UPMC facilities.<fig id="fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig.&#160;1</label><caption><p>Anesthesia testing guidelines. Time frame: The maximum number of days prior to surgery for the lab to be ordered.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr1.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><title>Outcome assessment- overutilisation based on ATG</title><p id="p0065">The criteria for appropriate vs overutilised laboratory testing was based on the ATG. If one of the 19 tests were ordered beyond the ATG recommendations for each surgical patient, these tests were categorised as overutilisation (Yes vs No). Any overutilisation was categorised as Yes for each surgical patient if any of the 19 perioperative tests were ordered beyond ATG recommendations. The identification of overutilisation by ATG was prospectively collected in the ATG implementation cohort but retrospectively identified in the baseline cohort. All data were extracted from the EMR within Cerner (North Kansas City, MO) and Epic (Verona, WI) and adjudicated by the authors. All financial data was provided by the health system's finance department.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><title>Development and implementation of ATG</title><p id="p0070">The CPC implementation team applied the <italic toggle="yes">Plan, Do, Study, Act</italic> (PDSA)<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> implementation framework to launch the ATG initiative across the UPMC health system in January 2021 (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Material, Appendix 1</xref>). The entire process consisted of targeting a process ripe for change, modifying existing pre-surgical guidelines, ensuring buy in from executive stakeholders, analyzing cost savings opportunities, developing a SmartSet, reporting structure, educational materials, robust communication plans, launch, and continue to reassess to further ensure compliance. The development of an embedded application and subsequent implementation took place in multiple phases. The &#8216;Plan&#8217; phase consisted of 1) team development, 2) development of embedded EMR application and 3) development of ATG training and education toolkit. The &#8216;Do&#8217; phase consisted of the actual implementation through promoting ATG through training and education. The &#8216;Study&#8217; phase consisted of monitoring compliance through the use of our dashboard tools to target areas for further reeducation. The &#8216;Act&#8217; phase was addressing clinical challenges and barriers disruptive to the change with question and answer sessions as well as re-education. The process was iterative in nature as we continued to monitor compliance.</p><sec id="sec2.5.1"><title>Team development</title><p id="p0075">Leveraging support from health system and hospital executives and departmental chairpersons, the perioperative leadership team from our Center for Perioperative Care (CPC) partnered with administration, communication teams, information technology (IT), clinical analytics, and project management. The project management team included clinical IT specialists to liaise with IT for development of logic embedding the ATG in the EMR, implementation and performance improvement specialists with expertise in education to support surgical clinic staff members to understand and implement the ATG and preoperative clinic advanced practise providers (APPs) and nurses to assist in educating and realtime assistance to surgical clinic. Our clinical analytics team developed an interactive clinical dashboard and reports to monitor and audit compliance.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5.2"><title>Development of embedded digital EMR application</title><p id="p0080">An EPIC EMR Smartset&#174; (or orderset) (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#160;2</xref>) was designed to standardise the computer order entry (CPOE) process for preoperative testing. CPC team members vetted all diagnosis codes captured within the Epic EMR system and grouped them by comorbidity category, crosswalking each code, identified by its international classification of diseases (ICD) 10 code with corresponding preoperative laboratory orders. (Because this happened during transition from ICD.9 to ICD.10, we also performed the additional step of crosswalking those diagnoses as well.) The orderset was then coded based on these comorbidity groupings, utilizing diagnosis codes documented within the updated <italic toggle="yes">Problems and Diagnoses</italic> list in Epic. Upon initiation of the orderset, the corresponding recommended preoperative laboratory orders for given diagnoses, based on the guidelines, are automated for order signature. For example, if the patient has been diagnosed with anemia, ICD.10 code D64.9, the written algorithm will search for the code within the <italic toggle="yes">Problems and Diganoses&#8217; list.</italic> If the code is found in the list, the algorithm then automatically orders an H&amp;H. Because the algorithm is programmed to read the scheduled surgical date and the date of any of the priour tests that has been ordered, the algorithm will automatically prevent duplicate testing based upon laboratory results within the defined time range for any active lab orders. For example, if the same patient mentioned above had an H&amp;H drawn within 45 days of a scheduled procedure, the orderset would not recommend that test because it was resulted within the 45-day defined time range per the ATG. The ordering provider has the option to add any additional labs to the orderset or override prechecked order recommendations, if clinically appropriate when signing orders.<fig id="fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig.&#160;2</label><caption><p>EPIC SmartSet example.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr2.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec2.5.3"><title>Development of ATG training and education toolkit</title><p id="p0085">An ATG toolkit (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Material, Appendix 2</xref>) was created which included reference order pocket cards, a Best Practises to Reduce Unnecessary Testing summary, informational fliers, administrator/manager/supervisour talking points, tutorial videos, and quarterly reports (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Appendix Fig.&#160;1</xref>). The pocket cards contained the full ATG as a reference for clinical providers to have available on hand. Informational fliers and talking points were provided to administrators to help promote the ATG within the surgical clinics and to support discussions within department meetings. Tutorial videos were sent out in all internal email communications and posted as a resource on the UPMC webpage. The tutorial video provided instructions on how to order the ATG Smartset in EPIC. A &#8216;Best Practises to Reduce Unnecessary Testing&#8217; guide was developed to provide a step-by-step overview on how to effectively utilise the ATG Smartset and quarterly reports. This guide also included embedded links to the tutorial videos, frequently asked questions (FAQs), fliers, and talking points that were created to provide guidance on functionality, documentation requirements, and accessing the orderset. A paper orderset was created for offices that were new to the health system and did not have access to documents in EPIC at the time of launch.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5.4"><title>Implementation</title><sec id="sec2.5.4.1"><title>Promoting ATG through training and education</title><p id="p0090">The perioperative implementation team utilised the resources within the ATG toolkit to endorse the ATG and its orderset as part of a large-scale communication campaign. Beginning in November 2020, the CPC team began promoting the guidelines by educating departmental, surgical, executive leadership, quality and safety, medical office, and primary care physician group meetings within the health system. The project team leveraged these forums to identify and engage key stakeholders from each group to comprise more local, multidisciplinary implementation champions within the hospitals and surgical clinics. Live Town Halls were also conducted by the CPC team to spread awareness and provide a forum for questions and answers. Additionally, individual live demonstration sessions were hosted for all surgical department administrators and their corresponding clinical staff. These open forums were used to provide an overview of the ATG Smartset and provided information about the quarterly reports. The live demo sessions were offered 2 months leading up to implementation and continued within the first month of go-live. Individual sessions were conducted by request. Internal communication methods supported the ATG implementation and included weblinks posted on the health system Infonet, computer screensavers, newsletter topics, and email communications distributed to physicians, medical staff, and administrators.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5.4.2"><title>Addressing challenges</title><p id="p0095">The CPC implementation team encountered cultural and operational challenges during the initial implementation phase. Many physicians were reluctant to change their ordering practises at first. To address this, the team recruited surgical champions from executive leadership and within each surgical specialty. The role of these champions was to encourage adherence to the ATG guidelines and Smartset among their peers, administrators, and clinical staff. The physician champions were integral in decreasing overutilisation of presurgical testing within their given service line. Another challenge that the project team discovered early on was that the problems and diagnoses list was not always current. Since the Smartset&#160;algorithm was dependent on the diagnoses codes, this was a significant issue which could result in inappropriate tests being ordered. To help overcome this, the team included an overview of how to update the problem list in all training sessions and education materials. The team emphasised the importance of maintaining the problems and diagnosis list in regard to ordering the ATG and impact on data. If a surgical office did not want to order presurgical testing, they could refer their patients to the CPC clinics to ensure the ATG were followed as part of the presurgical plan. The CPC APPs worked together with referring specialists to ensure that any procedural specific or requested tests were included.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5.4.3"><title>Monitoring compliance and financial incentive</title><p id="p0100">To quantify the compliance of the ATG implementation, an electronic ATG dashboard created automated physician reports to assess ordering trends by service line, laboratory test, and hospital, including overutilisation trends by specialty and hospital, as well as orderset compliance rates. Overutilisation rates were grouped by primary surgeon or by the provider that entered the order for the laboratory studies. Automated reports were sent to each surgeon quarterly to provide insights into their ordering trends and areas for improvement (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#160;3</xref>). The top five overutilised tests with the highest associated cost savings opportunity were included in the reports. The CPC implementation team then assessed quarterly trends and targeted education efforts based on service lines and ordering departments with the highest cost-avoidance opportunity.<fig id="fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig.&#160;3</label><caption><p>Example of automated quarterly report to individual physicians.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr3.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0105">To help encourage compliance, hospital leadership and departmental chairpersons developed a shared-savings model for each specialty. The realised hospital savings on unnecessary testing were added to the budgets of the specific participating departments.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="sec2.6"><title>Statistical analysis</title><sec id="sec2.6.1"><title>Sample size and power justification</title><p id="p0110">Based on the analysis from the baseline cohort before designing the ATG program, we observed the overutilisation rate was about 78% in the baseline cohort. Expertise from the ATG development group agreed that a 10% reduction in the overutilisation rate would be clinically meaningful. Group sample sizes of 627 in the baseline cohort and 627 in the ATG cohort would achieve 90% power to detect a difference of 8% (i.e., 10% reduction from 78% at baseline) in overutilisation of perioperative tests.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.6.2"><title>Any overutilisation across 19 perioperative tests by 12 service line</title><p id="p0115">Frequency and percentages were used to summarise the numbers of patients with overutilisation in perioperative tests determined by ATG recommendations. Pearson's chi-squared test was used to examine if proportions of any overutilisation by ATG across 19 perioperative tests significantly differed between the baseline cohort and ATG implementation cohort among all the study population and then stratified by 12 surgical specialties. To correct for multiple comparisons across service lines, p-values were adjusted using Bonferroni correction for 12 independent chi-squared tests. Oral surgery/dental, podiatry, cardiac surgery (guided by societal guidelines), and solid organ transplantation (guided by disease state at frequent intervals) were excluded from the analysis. The percent reduction in overutilisation was computed by subtracting the proportions of the ATG cohort from those of the baseline cohort and then dividing this difference by the proportion observed at baseline.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.6.3"><title>Overutilisation by six top laboratory tests with high cost</title><p id="p0120">Proportions of overutilisation for each of the six most ordered and expensive individual laboratory tests (e.g., CMP, CXR, BMP, CBC, EKG, and LYTES) were also compared between baseline cohort and implementation cohort using the chi-squared test. To correct for multiple comparisons across tests, p-values were adjusted using Bonferroni correction for 6 independent chi-squared tests.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.6.4"><title>Monthly overutilisation rate over time</title><p id="p0125">The monthly overutilisation rate by ATG was calculated by dividing the total number of patients with any overutilisation by the total number of surgical patients each month. We used single interrupted time series analysis (ITSA) by segmented regression<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> to estimate the immediate level change in the monthly overutilisation rate at the beginning ATG launch and the trends of the monthly overutilisation rate before ATG (July 2019&#8211;June 2020) and after the launch of ATG (January 2021&#8211;December 2022), excluding the washout period (July&#8211;December 2020) when the development and implementation of ATG occurred.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.6.5"><title>The standard ITSA segmented regression model</title><p id="p0130"><disp-formula id="ufd1"><mml:math id="M1" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">Y</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#946;</mml:mi><mml:mn mathvariant="bold">0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#946;</mml:mi><mml:mn mathvariant="bold">1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&#215;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#946;</mml:mi><mml:mn mathvariant="bold">2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&#215;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">A</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">T</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#946;</mml:mi><mml:mn mathvariant="bold">3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&#215;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">e</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">e</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">A</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">T</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">G</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#949;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where Y<sub>t</sub> is the monthly overutilisation rate at timepoint t, time<sub>t</sub> is the time in months since the start of the study from the 1st month of the pre-ATG study period (i.e., July 2019), ATG<sub>t</sub> represents the ATG implementation as a binary variable with months before the launch of ATG designated as 0 and months after the launch of ATG designated as 1. Time since ATG is designated as 0 for the pre-ATG period and the first month of ATG implementation (January 2021), and time since ATG is designated as 1 for February 2021, 2 for March 2021, and so on. &#946;<sub>0</sub> is the intercept and represents the initial outcome Y (e.g., monthly overutilisation rate) at the 1st month of the study period, while &#946;<sub>1</sub> is the change in overutilisation rate per month before the launch of ATG. &#946;<sub>2</sub> is the level change in overutilisation rate, defined as the immediate impact of ATG implementation. &#946;<sub>3</sub> is the difference in slopes between pre- and post- ATG implementation periods. The slope after the launch of ATG is the sum of &#946;<sub>1</sub> and &#946;<sub>3</sub>. For the segmented regression of ITSA, we assessed the linearity assumption for monthly overutilisation data before and after the launch of the ATG periods. Residuals (&#949;<sub>t</sub>) for both periods followed a normal distribution, and the residual plots displayed an even scatter pattern around 0. The autocorrelation of data across time was determined by the Durbin&#8211;Watson statistics and autocorrelation functions plot. We accounted for a lag of 12 months for autocorrelation in the ITSA and adjusted the regression standard errors using the Newey&#8211;West method.<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref> ITSA estimates were used to project trends of monthly overutilisation rate with and without the ATG implementation from January 2023. The alpha level was set at 0.05 for the ITSA analysis. The ITSA analysis was not pre-planned, and it was conducted based on suggestions from reviewers during the peer-review process. SAS version 9.4 (SAS Institute Inc.) was used for the analyses.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2.7"><title>Role of funders</title><p id="p0135">There was no external funding for this study.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Results</title><p id="p0140">From the 11 hospitals over the entire study period, there were a total of 191,930 patients who underwent surgery. The baseline cohort included 59,799 cases in patients presenting for elective surgical cases, of which 46,413 (77.6%) had overutilised testing by the ATG. Following the implementation of the ATG, there were a total of 132,131 cases, of which 90,007 (68.1%) were affected by overutilisation (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#160;1</xref>). Implementation of ATG CDS resulted in a significant 12.2% decrease in overutilised testing (p&#160;&lt;&#160;0.0001). While all service lines show statistically significant reductions in testing, the greatest reduction was achieved in the surgical specialties of otolaryngology (26.5% reduction), plastic surgery (24.1% reduction), surgical oncology (17.0% reduction), and obstetrics and gynecology (18.1% reduction) (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#160;1</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table&#160;1</label><caption><p>Impact of implementation of ATG by service line.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Service Line</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Baseline Cohort (2019&#8211;2020)<hr/></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">ATG Cohort (2021&#8211;2022)<hr/></th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Difference (ATG -Baseline)</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">% Reduction Compared to Baseline Cohort</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Adjusted p-value<xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Over ATG, n (%)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Over ATG, n (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>All Service Lines</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>59,799</bold></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>46,413 (77.6%)</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>132,131</bold></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>90,007 (68.1%)</bold></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>&#8722;9.5%</bold></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>12.2%</bold></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.0001</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Orthopedic Surgery</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">19,482</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15,001 (77.0%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">43,727</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30,745 (70.3%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;6.7%</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.7%</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Urology</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5089</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4434 (87.1%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11,032</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8623 (78.2%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;8.9%</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.2%</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Neurosurgery</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3545</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3205 (90.4%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7254</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5807 (80.1%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;10.3%</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.4%</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Surgical Oncology</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4294</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3786 (88.2%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9298</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6809 (73.2%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;15.0%</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.0%</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Obstetrics Gynecology</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5936</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4751 (80.0%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13,381</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8765 (65.5%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;14.5%</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.1%</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">General Surgery</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4086</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3024 (74.0%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9387</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6120 (65.2%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;8.8%</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.9%</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Thoracic Surgery</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3546</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3467 (97.8%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6954</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6612 (95.1%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;2.7%</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.8%</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Plastic Surgery</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2578</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1924 (74.6%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5327</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3017 (56.6%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;18.0%</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.1%</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Otolaryngology</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3004</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2041 (67.9%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6614</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3299 (49.9%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;18.0%</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.5%</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vascular Surgery</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1654</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1569 (94.9%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3432</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3083 (89.8%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;5.1%</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.4%</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Colon &amp; Rectal Surgery</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">722</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">563 (78.0%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1703</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1153 (67.7%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;10.3%</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.2%</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ophthalmology</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5863</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2648 (45.2%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14,022</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5974 (42.6%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;2.6%</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.8%</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.011</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>ATG: Anesthesia testing guidelines.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl1fna"><label>a</label><p id="ntpara0015">To correct for multiple comparisons across service lines, p-values were adjusted using Bonferroni correction for 12 independent chi-squared tests.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0145">The top six most ordered and expensive individual laboratory tests include CMP, CXR, BMP, CBC, EKG, and LYTES (in order of greatest to least cost). Significant reductions in these tests were observed in the implementation cohort compared to the baseline cohort (p&#160;&lt;&#160;0.0001). The greatest reductions occurred with LYTES (47.1% reduction), CXR (46.0%), and CMP (39.0%). Both CXR and CMP were the two tests that had the greatest cost (<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table&#160;2</xref>). Based on the data provided by the UPMC Department of Finance, the health services division was able to reduce overall costs secondary to unnecessary testing by 22% from baseline (data not shown in tables). Overall average surgical case cancellation/delay remained the same.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table&#160;2</label><caption><p>Over ATG rate for the top 6 tests between baseline and ATG cohorts.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tests</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Baseline (2019&#8211;2020) n&#160;=&#160;59,799</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">ATG Cohort (2021&#8211;2022) n&#160;=&#160;132,131</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Difference (ATG&#8212;Baseline)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">%&#160;Reduction Compared to Baseline&#160;Cohort</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Adjusted p-value<xref rid="tbl2fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Complete Metabolic Panel (CMP)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16,250 (27.2%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21,991 (16.6%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;10.6%</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.0%</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chest X-ray (CXR)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15,616 (26.1%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18,680 (14.1%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;12.0%</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46.0%</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Basic Metabolic Panel (BMP)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16,782 (28.1%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26,635 (20.2%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;7.9%</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.1%</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Complete Blood Count (CBC)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37,132 (62.1%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60,511 (45.8%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;16.3%</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.2%</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Electrocardiogram (EKG)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23,442 (39.2%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41,944 (31.7%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;7.5%</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.1%</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Electrolytes (LYTES)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1032 (1.7%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1213 (0.9%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;0.8%</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47.1%</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>ATG: Anesthesia testing guidelines.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl2fna"><label>a</label><p id="ntpara0020">To correct for multiple comparisons across tests, p-values were adjusted using Bonferroni correction for 6 independent chi-squared tests.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0150">The ITSA showed that there were no major changes in ordering during the baseline period of July 2019 through June 2020 (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table&#160;3</xref>, <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#160;4</xref>). The overutilisation rate was 77.89% (95% CI: 77.40%, 78.37%) in July 2019, and it remained stable in the baseline cohort with a non-significant change of 0.04% (95% CI:&#160;&#8722;0.11%, 0.19%) per month. ATG was launched on January 1, 2021 after a six-month washout period when ATG CDS development, planning, training, and implementation occurred (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#160;4</xref>). ITSA showed the implementation of ATG was significantly associated with an immediate reduction of 7.52% (95% CI:&#160;&#8722;9.13%,&#160;&#8722;5.91%) in monthly overutilisation rate in January 2021 and then overutilisation rate decreased by 0.24% (95% CI:&#160;&#8722;0.30%,&#160;&#8722;0.18%) per month (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table&#160;3</xref>, <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#160;4</xref>). The projection data derived from ITSA estimates suggests that the overutilisation rate will drop to below 60% by October 2024. The overutilisation rate would have been 80% without the implementation of ATG CDS (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#160;4</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table&#160;3</label><caption><p>Interrupted time series analysis on the monthly overutilisation rate by ATG (%).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Parametre</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Estimate (95% CI)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">p-value</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Interpretation</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#946;<sub>0</sub></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">77.89 (77.40, 78.37)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">The intercept of the monthly overutilisation rate was 77.89%.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#946;<sub>1</sub></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.04 (&#8722;0.11, 0.19)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.60</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">The monthly overutilisation rate was stable in the baseline cohort with a non-significant change of&#160;+0.04% per month.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#946;<sub>2</sub></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;7.52 (&#8722;9.13,&#160;&#8722;5.91)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">The implementation of ATG was associated with an immediate 7.52% drop in overutilisation.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#946;<sub>3</sub></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;0.28 (&#8722;0.43,&#160;&#8722;0.13)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">The slopes before and after ATG implementation are significantly different by&#160;&#8722;0.28%.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#946;<sub>1</sub>+ &#946;<sub>3</sub></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;0.24 (&#8722;0.30,&#160;&#8722;0.18)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0009</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">After the ATG implementation, the overutilisation rate decreases by 0.24% per month.</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig.&#160;4</label><caption><p>Monthly overutilisation rate by ATG and projections with and without ATG implementation using interrupted time series analysis. ATG: Anesthesia testing guidelines; Jul: July; Dec: December; Jun: June; Jan: January.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr4.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0155">In this study, we describe the implementation of an evidence-based, digital quality improvement approach embedded in the EMR to institute health system culture and practise change for reducing unnecessary preoperative testing. The reduction of unnecessary preoperative testing resulted in cost avoidance for the health system and patients undergoing elective surgery at 11 hospitals within an academic and community healthcare system.</p><p id="p0160">There is a wealth of literature indicating that broad preoperative testing is not associated with improved outcomes, nor does it change typical treatment plans for patients during their intraoperative and postoperative course. Evidence for this goes as far back as 1985, where 2000 patients were studied over a four month period, where it was suggested that, &#8216;In the absence of specific indications, routine preoperative laboratory tests contribute little to patient care and could reasonably be eliminated.<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> In a study of over 1400 patients, less than 40% of testing ordered was consistent with guidelines and even when abnormalities were noted, there was no change in the care that the patients received.<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref> In a 2020 study of a cohort of 1527 patients undergoing urethroplasty, on whom over 8000 tests were ordered, there was no evidence that preoperative testing could predict morbidity in the postoperative arena<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> in patients who were ASA class II or lower; in other low risk procedures such as cataracts, obtaining any lab testing, regardless of ASA class, does not reduce postoperative mortality and morbidity.<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref></p><p id="p0165">There are many reasons for overtesting. An Italian study found testing was a matter more based on personal experience than on level of evidence.<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref> Anesthesiologists fear legal repercussions and surgeons generally cite fear of case delay by the anesthesiologists on the day of surgery.<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref> Furthermore, guidelines can be complex. The National Institute of Health and Care Excellence (NICE), one of the most comprehensive set of guidelines, has greater than 70 tables, in total, which account for patient variables and testing recommendations; yet these are a complex reference to facilitate widespread implementation<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref> and adherence to such complex and granular recommendations is difficult.<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref></p><p id="p0170">Grol and Grimshaw discussed that in order to achieve evidence-based practise, evidence-based implementation is no less important<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref> and the field of implementation science has seen significant progress to better understand both facilitators and barriers for implementation strategies.<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref> Further, the Cochrane Collaboration's Effective Practice and Organization of Care (EPOC) group has conducted over 130 systematic reviews of strategies including audit and feedback,<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref> printed education materials,<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref> local opinion leaders,<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref> educational outreach,<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref> computerised reminders,<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref> and tailored implementation strategies.<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33</sup></xref> Gawande identified other factors associated with successful implementation include presence of committed implementation champion, time to train staff, small amount of implementation steps, and support of institutional leadership.<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr"><sup>34</sup></xref> In order to make a successful culture change within our health system, we used a multifaceted approach, combining many of these discrete component strategies to improve adoption, sustainment, and scale-up.<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr"><sup>36</sup></xref></p><p id="p0175">Because publication of preoperative testing guidelines alone, at our health system or by national groups, without a defined and broad implementation strategy fail to yield compliance and eliminate unnecessary testing, we developed an implementation strategy emphasizing easy to use ATG, multidisciplinary and leadership support, and an automated orderset to streamline patient care. The champions (CPC Team) identified an issue dealing with quality improvement and possible fiscal ramifications. The team leveraged support from the health system, hospital executives and departmental chairpersons to obtain the resources necessary to make the change, including educators, physicians, advanced practise providers, nurses, and other administrators. After the CDS was created by the IT specialists and the champions were educated on how to use it, a set of guidelines and educational toolkit was created using both digital and paper material to aid in the use of the CDS. Tutorials and videos of a step-by-step guide were made widely available to all personnel. Screensavers were also used to notify employees of the impending initiative. Local staff at each hospital and clinic were engaged to help educate and encourage the staff at those sites. The team hosted live question and answer sessions while a service email account was developed for questions related to the implementation. We developed an interactive dashboard to monitor and audit compliance, which helped to target reeducation efforts to improve compliance over time. All of these efforts enabled our team to become part of the presentation agenda of multi-participant town-halls and executive leadership, quality and safety, medical office, primary care physician group, and surgical leadership meetings to keep focus on this initiative.</p><p id="p0180">The success of the implementation was further buoyed by the development of the orderset, the toolkit, and the shared savings. The orderset was a key component in order to facilitate and automate the recommended perioperative orders by reducing the number of steps and cognitive requirement to place them. The only two steps were: the provider first populated or verified the past medical history, which is routinely done at each appointment, and the provider then ordered the ATG orderset, where the orders were prefilled based on patient medical comorbidity. The ATG Toolkit was another key component of the implementation success as it contained education material, talking points, guidelines, and computerised reminders. Additionally, the ability to share data via a dashboard allowed for rapid feedback to assess compliance and assist in directing reeducation efforts. The UPMC Health Services Division was able to avoid 22% of the cost associated with unnecessary testing. That shared savings was then redistributed, by percentage, to each of the departments who complied with the ATG. While the shared-savings program was a contributour to success of the implementation, given that it was spread out amongst multiple surgical servicelines, it is challenging to determine the degree to which it was a contributor.</p><p id="p0185">There are many barriers to implementation that include, but are not limited to excessive cost, lack of time, lack of education and familiarity of a topic, lack of both human and digital resources, opposition from key stakeholders, lack of clarity on roles and responsibilitites, lack of coordination and teamwork, and cultural attitudes toward change.<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr"><sup>38</sup></xref> The CPC implementation team encountered several challenges regarding culture and acceptance, documentation barriers, variability in surgical workflow, and report building throughout the implementation process. Multiple physicians were resistant to change in their routine practise and were concerned that surgeries would be delayed or cancelled when testing was limited. Another barrier for implementation was EMR workflow. During the education process, it was discovered that the healthcare system had only &#8764;30% compliance rate for updating the <italic toggle="yes">Problems and Diagnosis</italic> list in Epic, which would negatively impact the logic in the ATG orderset. The CPC implementation team took a multipronged approach to address these issues, which included reeducation series, partnering with surgeons and their clinics for workflow analyses and problem solving, and marketing/utilizing the CPC clinics to streamline preoperative testing for patients referred to these clinics.</p><p id="p0190">The authors are aware that different guidelines can be chosen at different institutions, and there are not universally accepted guidelines within the United States. The Institute of Medicine has previously reported that there is variability in delivery of health care creating a primary focus for quality improvement to standardise care through cost-reduction initiatives.<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref> Our cost analysis relied on institutional financial data. Because we did not include further health system costs associated with abnormal testing, our costs are not comprehensive, and we acknowledge that they will vary widely around the country. Furthermore, it is difficult to split direct costs vs indirect cost (including the time it takes for the laboratory staff to run certain tests) and, while it may present a more nuanced and full financial analysis, we did not accomplish that in this study. Our study was also limited because we did not change patient satisfaction surveys to address the new change in perioperative testing. We aimed to describe our institutional experience and acknowledge that our data represent findings from a subset of hospitals in a large academic and community health system, and these results may not be generalizable to all other hospitals, especially for smaller or rural hospitals, even possibly smaller health systems, where resources are constrained and, in some technological instances, hospitals [rural]may not even have fully functional internet access.<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39</sup></xref> However, there are paths forward that would require resources of either cost, i.e., a consulting firm to educate and help with adoption of EMR and EMR data solutions; third party willing license a product; third party willing to do all of the work and capture all data; or time, i.e., identification of champions willing to utilise their time for this endeavor. This would be individualizable to each hospital and, most likely, far more difficult to do.</p><p id="p0195">As healthcare costs in the United States totaled over $3 trillion in 2018 and are expected to rise to beyond $6.2 trillion in 2028, healthcare expenditures will represent nearly 20% of the USA gross domestic product.<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr"><sup>40</sup></xref> Because the cost of preoperative testing has been calculated in excess of $18 billion per year<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> and more than 40 percent of patients have unnecessary tests, this is a key opportunity for improvement. Even though our initial guidelines were available for reference within the institution, they were still not adhered to by all anesthesiology or surgical teams, as 100% of the population underwent at least one nonindicated test. As such, future research might focus on the long-term impacts of reduced testing on patient outcomes, exploring whether decreases in testing maintain patient safety and surgical outcomes, which would address many concerns of our anesthesiologists and surgeons.</p><p id="p0200">In conclusion, an evidence-based, digital platform-enabled approach embedded in the EMR is a successful tactic to reduce unnecessary preoperative testing, while maintaining quality of care and improving cost avoidance. We utilised a multifaceted, tailored approach to implementation, leveraging institutional &#8216;top-down&#8217; support along with audit and feedback, printed education materials, educational outreach, computerised reminders, and key stakeholders and champions. This easy-to-use ATG toolkit provided marked reduction in unnecessary preoperative testing. Further emphasis on provider or departmental feedback and education will likely improve unnecessary testing further. This ATG implementation approach transforms medical practises to follow defined guidelines, thereby improving the value of care.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>Contributors</title><p id="p0205">All authors listed helped to write, read, revise, and ultimately approved the final manuscript. In addition: SAE, JHM, KM, AM designed and implemented the program, as well as collected analysed and verified data. H-HSL performed the statistical analysis and interpreted results, helped write and revised the manuscript. AKB designed the program. BSZ implemented the program. JLA, MG, OCM developed and coded the algorithm, collected, analysed and verified data. AL implemented the program.</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><title>Data sharing statement</title><p id="p0210">The datasets generated and/or analysed during the current study are not publicly available but are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request via email, and will be shared via secure platform, after approval by corresponding author, with a signed data access agreement.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="coi0010"><title>Declaration of interests</title><p id="p0215">The authors declare no relevant conflicts of interests for this manuscript at any time in the present or in the past 36 months, nor do the authors have any relavant competing interests, including support, grants or contracts from entities, consulting fees, royalties or licenses, payment or honoraria for lectures, presentations, speakers bureaus, manuscript writing, or educational events, payment for expert testimony, support for attending meetings and/or travel, patents planned, issued or pending, participation on data safety monitoring board or advisory boards, leadership or fiduciary role in other board, society, committee, or advocacy group, paid or unpaid, stock or stock options, receipt of equipment, materials, drugs, medical writing, gifts, or other services, or other financial or non-financial interests.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibby</surname><given-names>G.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How preoperative assessment programs can be justified financially to hospital administrators</article-title><source>Int Anesthesiol Clin</source><volume>40</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2002</year><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11897933</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/00004311-200204000-00004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Preoperative Tests (Update)</collab></person-group><part-title>Routine preoperative tests for elective surgery</part-title><year>2016</year><publisher-name>National Institute for Health and Care Excellence: Clinical Guidelines</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27077168</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dzankic</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pastor</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The prevalence and predictive value of abnormal preoperative laboratory tests in elderly surgical patients</article-title><source>Anesth Analg</source><volume>93</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2001</year><fpage>301</fpage><lpage>308</lpage><comment>2nd contents page</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11473849</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/00000539-200108000-00013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia-Miguel</surname><given-names>F.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Serrano-Aguilar</surname><given-names>P.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez-Bastida</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preoperative assessment</article-title><source>Lancet</source><volume>362</volume><issue>9397</issue><year>2003</year><fpage>1749</fpage><lpage>1757</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14643127</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0140-6736(03)14857-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>E.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheiner</surname><given-names>L.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boeckmann</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The usefulness of preoperative laboratory screening</article-title><source>JAMA</source><volume>253</volume><issue>24</issue><year>1985</year><fpage>3576</fpage><lpage>3581</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3999339</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Turnbull</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buck</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The value of preoperative screening investigations in otherwise healthy individuals</article-title><source>Arch Intern Med</source><volume>147</volume><issue>6</issue><year>1987</year><fpage>1101</fpage><lpage>1105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3592875</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Velanovich</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preoperative laboratory screening based on age, gender, and concomitant medical diseases</article-title><source>Surgery</source><volume>115</volume><issue>1</issue><year>1994</year><fpage>56</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8284762</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Guidelines and Protocols Advisory Committee (GPAC) MSC, and British Columbia Medical Association</collab></person-group><part-title>Guideline for routine pre-operative testing</part-title><source>Health VBMo</source><year>2000</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mayor</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NICE guidance clarifies when to do preoperative tests in elective surgery</article-title><source>BMJ</source><volume>326</volume><issue>7404</issue><year>2003</year><fpage>1418</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmj.326.7404.1418-i</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1151038</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12829551</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Munro</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Booth</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicholl</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Routine preoperative testing: a systematic review of the evidence</article-title><source>Health Technol Assess</source><volume>1</volume><issue>12</issue><year>1997</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9483155</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Services UDoHaH</surname></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Quality AfHRa</surname></name></person-group><source>Routine preoperative testing</source><year>2013</year><publisher-name>US Government</publisher-name><fpage>15</fpage><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.effectivehealthcare.ahrq.gov" id="intref0015">www.effectivehealthcare.ahrq.gov</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smetana</surname><given-names>G.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The conundrum of unnecessary preoperative testing</article-title><source>JAMA Intern Med</source><volume>175</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>1359</fpage><lpage>1361</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26053300</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamainternmed.2015.2106</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Backhouse</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogunlayi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quality improvement into practice</article-title><source>Br Med J</source><issue>368</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>m865</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32234777</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmj.m865</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7190269</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>R.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pincock</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baumgart</surname><given-names>D.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sadowski</surname><given-names>D.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fedorak</surname><given-names>R.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kroeker</surname><given-names>K.I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An overview of clinical decision support systems: benefits, risks, and strategies for success</article-title><source>NPJ Digit Med</source><volume>3</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>17</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32047862</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41746-020-0221-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7005290</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Quality AfHRa</surname></name></person-group><part-title>Plan-do-study-act (PDSA) directions and examples. Health literacy universal precautions toolkit</part-title><edition>2nd ed.</edition><year>2024</year><comment>Available from:</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ahrq.gov/health-literacy/improve/precautions/tool2b.html" id="intref0020">https://www.ahrq.gov/health-literacy/improve/precautions/tool2b.html</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernal</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cummins</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gasparrini</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interrupted time series regression for the evaluation of public health interventions: a tutorial</article-title><source>Int J Epidemiol</source><volume>46</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>348</fpage><lpage>355</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27283160</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/ije/dyw098</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5407170</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Newey</surname><given-names>W.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A&#160;simple, positive semi-definite, heteroskedasticity and autocorrelation consistent covariance matrix</article-title><source>Econometrica</source><volume>55</volume><issue>3</issue><year>1987</year><fpage>703</fpage><lpage>708</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>St Clair</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diver</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Adherence to evidence-based guidelines for preoperative testing in women undergoing gynecologic surgery</article-title><source>Obstet Gynecol</source><volume>116</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>694</fpage><lpage>700</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20733454</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/AOG.0b013e3181ec448d</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Avila</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahran</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Preoperative testing for urethroplasty is not associated with outcomes-A NSQIP study</article-title><source>Urology</source><volume>139</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>182</fpage><lpage>187</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32109494</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.urology.2020.02.018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Keay</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindsley</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tielsch</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schein</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Routine preoperative medical testing for cataract surgery</article-title><source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source><volume>3</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>CD007293</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22419323</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/14651858.CD007293.pub3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4261928</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ricciardi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Angelillo</surname><given-names>I.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Del Prete</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Routine preoperative investigation. Results of a multicenter survey in Italy. Collaborator Group</article-title><source>Int J Technol Assess Health Care</source><volume>14</volume><issue>3</issue><year>1998</year><fpage>526</fpage><lpage>534</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9780539</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1017/s0266462300011508</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliva</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vilarasau Farre</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin-Baranera</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>[Survey on the preoperative evaluation in Catalonian surgical centers. II. What is the attitude and opinion of the professionals involved?]</article-title><source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim</source><volume>48</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2001</year><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11234600</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Neill</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pink</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Routine preoperative tests for elective surgery: summary of updated NICE guidance</article-title><source>BMJ</source><volume>354</volume><year>2016</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">i3292</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmj.i3292</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27418436</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Preoperative routines</surname></name></person-group><article-title>The Swedish council on technology assessment in health care</article-title><source>Int J Technol Assess Health Care</source><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><year>1991</year><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2032782</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bryson</surname><given-names>G.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wyand</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bragg</surname><given-names>P.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preoperative testing is inconsistent with published guidelines and rarely changes management</article-title><source>Can J Anaesth</source><volume>53</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2006</year><fpage>236</fpage><lpage>241</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16527786</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/BF03022208</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grol</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grimshaw</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence-based implementation of evidence-based medicine</article-title><source>Jt Comm J Qual Improv</source><volume>25</volume><issue>10</issue><year>1999</year><fpage>503</fpage><lpage>513</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10522231</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s1070-3241(16)30464-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eccles</surname><given-names>M.P.M.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Welcome to implementation science</article-title><source>Implement Sci</source><volume>1</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>3</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ivers</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jamtvedt</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flottorp</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Audit and feedback: effects on professional practice and healthcare outcomes</article-title><source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source><issue>6</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>CD000259</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22696318</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/14651858.CD000259.pub3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11338587</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Farmer</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Legare</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turcot</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Printed educational materials: effects on professional practice and health care outcomes</article-title><source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source><issue>3</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>CD004398</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18646106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/14651858.CD004398.pub2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flodgren</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parmelli</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doumit</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Local opinion leaders: effects on professional practice and health care outcomes</article-title><source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source><issue>8</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>CD000125</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21833939</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/14651858.CD000125.pub4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4172331</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jamtvedt</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Educational outreach visits: effects on professional practice and health care outcomes</article-title><source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source><volume>2007</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2007</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">CD000409</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/14651858.CD000409.pub2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7032679</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17943742</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shojania</surname><given-names>K.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jennings</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mayhew</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramsay</surname><given-names>C.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eccles</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grimshaw</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effects of on-screen, point of care computer reminders on processes and outcomes of care</article-title><source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source><volume>2009</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2009</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">CD001096</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/14651858.CD001096.pub2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4171964</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19588323</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Camosso-Stefinovic</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gillies</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tailored interventions to address determinants of practice</article-title><source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source><volume>2015</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2015</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">CD005470</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/14651858.CD005470.pub3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7271646</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25923419</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gawande</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Successful implementation in surgical safety</part-title><year>2017</year><publisher-name>American Society of Anesthesiologists Annual Conference</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aarons</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ehrhart</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farahnak</surname><given-names>L.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hurlburt</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Leadership and organizational change for implementation (LOCI): a randomized mixed method pilot study of a leadership and organization development intervention for evidence-based practice implementation</article-title><source>Implement Sci</source><volume>10</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>11</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25592163</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13012-014-0192-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4310135</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Glisson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schoenwald</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hemmelgarn</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Randomized trial of MST and ARC in a two-level evidence-based treatment implementation strategy</article-title><source>J&#160;Consult Clin Psychol</source><volume>78</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>537</fpage><lpage>550</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20658810</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1037/a0019160</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3951378</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McArthur</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hewston</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giangregorio</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Straus</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Papaioannou</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Barriers and facilitators to implementing evidence-based guidelines in long-term care: a qualitative evidence synthesis</article-title><source>Implement Sci</source><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>70</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34243789</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13012-021-01140-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8267230</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Project HP</surname></name></person-group><part-title>Capacity development resource guide: implementation barriers [guidelines]</part-title><year>2014</year><publisher-name>Future Group, Health Policy Project</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc><comment>[updated November 26, 2024]. Available from:</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.healthpolicyproject.com/pubs/272_ImplementationBarriersResourceGuide.pdf" id="intref0025">https://www.healthpolicyproject.com/pubs/272_ImplementationBarriersResourceGuide.pdf</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref39"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garrett</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hart-Hester</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identifying barriers to the adoption of new technology in rural hospitals: a case report</article-title><source>Perspect Health Inf Manag</source><volume>3</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>9</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18066367</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2047308</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>CMS</collab></person-group><part-title>National health expenditure data CMS.gov</part-title><year>2020</year><comment>[updated March 24, 2020; cited 2020 March 24]. Available from:</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cms.gov/Research-Statistics-Data-and-Systems/Statistics-Trends-and-Reports/NationalHealthExpendData/NHE-Fact-Sheet" id="intref0030">https://www.cms.gov/Research-Statistics-Data-and-Systems/Statistics-Trends-and-Reports/NationalHealthExpendData/NHE-Fact-Sheet</ext-link></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="appsec1" sec-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><title>Supplementary data</title><p id="p0225">
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Supplementary Figure&#160;S1</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc1.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Supplementary Figure&#160;S2</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc2.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material>
</p></sec><ack id="ack0010"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="p0220">Megan Metcalf, UPMC Department of Finance. There was no external funding for this study.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="appsec2" fn-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><p id="p0230">Supplementary data related to this article can be found at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.ebiom.2024.105509" id="intref0010">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ebiom.2024.105509</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article></pmc-articleset>