<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMJ Open Respir Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMJ Open Respir Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2615</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmjresp</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bmjresp</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMJ Open Respiratory Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2052-4439</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMJ Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11647385</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11647385.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11647385</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11647385</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39668106</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjresp-2024-002366</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">bmjresp-2024-002366</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>2215</subject><subject>1506</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Association between birth weight and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease in the UK Biobank: a prospective cohort study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names initials="P">Pengfei</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><email>lpfei215@live.cn</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names initials="J">Jialiu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><email>hjl3304185064@163.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wan</surname><given-names initials="X">Xinglin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><email>WANxl19981010@163.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="M">Mengxia</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><email>exploding1102@126.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zheng</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><email>zhengzhu@jscdc.cn</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names initials="L">Lulu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><email>chenlulu136@163.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hang</surname><given-names initials="D">Dong</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><email>hangdong@njmu.edu.cn</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names initials="J">Jian</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><email>sujiangx@163.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tao</surname><given-names initials="R">Ran</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><email>trltjy@163.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6057-862X</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names initials="J">Jinyi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><email>zhoujinyi74@sina.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-9944-284X</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names initials="X">Xikang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/><email>xikangfan1991@jscdc.cn</email></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution>Jiangsu Provincial Center for Disease Control and Prevention</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Nanjing</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Jiangsu</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="department">Department of Epidemiology and Biostatistics</institution>, <institution>Southeast University School of Public Health</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Nanjing</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Jiangsu</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution content-type="department">Department of Epidemiology</institution>, <institution>Nanjing Medical University</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Nanjing</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn><p>Supplemental material This content has been supplied by the author(s). It has not been vetted by BMJ Publishing Group Limited (BMJ) and may not have been peer-reviewed. Any opinions or recommendations discussed are solely those of the author(s) and are not endorsed by BMJ. BMJ disclaims all liability and responsibility arising from any reliance placed on the content. Where the content includes any translated material, BMJ does not warrant the accuracy and reliability of the translations (including but not limited to local regulations, clinical guidelines, terminology, drug names and drug dosages), and is not responsible for any error and/or omissions arising from translation and adaptation or otherwise.</p></fn><fn id="fn1"><p>Additional supplemental material is published online only. To view, please visit the journal online (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjresp-2024-002366" ext-link-type="uri">https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjresp-2024-002366</ext-link>).</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="fn5"><p>None declared.</p></fn><corresp id="cor1">DrXikangFan; <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="xikangfan1991@jscdc.cn">xikangfan1991@jscdc.cn</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">452855</issue-id><elocation-id>e002366</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>08</day><month>2</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>12</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>16</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-12-17 17:25:14.283"><day>17</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; Author(s) (or their employer(s)) 2024. Re-use permitted under CC BY-NC. No commercial re-use. See rights and permissions. Published by BMJ.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed in accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is properly cited, appropriate credit is given, any changes made indicated, and the use is non-commercial. See:&#160;<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="bmjresp-11-1.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="bmjresp-11-1.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><sec><title>Background</title><p>Birth weight has been reported to be associated with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) in adulthood, but the results have not yet been determined. This study aims to analyse the potential association of birth weight with COPD risk in UK Biobank.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>We conducted a prospective analysis for participants without baseline COPD in UK Biobank. The HRs and 95% CIs were calculated by multivariable Cox regression models, and dose-response relationship was evaluated by restricted cubic splines. Besides, we also calculated the interactions for covariates and further analysed the joint effects.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>A total of 251&#8201;172 participants with birth weight data were included in this study, and 5602 COPD cases were found during follow-up. According to Cox regression models, participants with the lowest quintile of birth weight (&lt; 2.86&#8201;kg) had higher risk for COPD (HR=1.21, 95% CI 1.11 to 1.32). In addition, the dose&#8210;response analysis showed a non-linear relationship between birth weight and COPD risk, which first decreased and then increased, and the interactions for age, passive smoking and maternal smoking were also found by stratified analysis. Furthermore, we also found the joint effects between COPD risk and maternal smoking in the lowest quintile group.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>This study indicated that lower birth weight may increase the risk of COPD. The non-linear associations between birth weight and COPD risk for prospective cohort; as birth weight increased, the risk showed a trend of decreasing first and then increasing. Moreover, maternal smoking had a joint effect with low birth weight for COPD risk.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>COPD epidemiology</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Key Project of Medical Science Research of Jiangsu Provincial Health Commission</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>K2023072</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><boxed-text id="BX1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>WHAT IS ALREADY KNOWN ON THIS TOPIC</title></caption><sec><title>WHAT THIS STUDY ADDS</title><list list-type="bullet" list-content="ul"><list-item><p>Low birth weight was significantly associated with COPD risk, and interactions and joint effect were found between birth weight and maternal smoking.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec><title>HOW THIS STUDY MIGHT AFFECT RESEARCH, PRACTICE OR THE POLICY</title><list list-type="bullet" list-content="ul"><list-item><p>We should focus on the effect of early-life exposure for reducing COPD risk and ensure life quality in the early period of humans.</p></list-item></list></sec></boxed-text><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p> Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) is one of the most common chronic diseases, which has become the third most common cause for worldwide death.<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> According to the Global Burden of Disease data in 2019, 212.3&#8201;million new COPD cases and 3.3&#8201;million deaths were reported globally.<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> Meanwhile, with the intensification of global ageing, the burden of COPD may continue to increase. The occurrence of COPD is a long potential process, making it difficult to find the starting point of its onset. Therefore, searching for the potential causes of COPD is an important method to reduce its mortality rate. Smoking has been considered the most common traditional risk factor for COPD; however, other risk factors are increasingly recognised worldwide.<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3 4</sup></xref> Some studies had reported that about half of COPD cases were caused by other factors unrelated to smoking, such as household biomass fuel, occupational exposure to fume and dust, history of respiratory diseases (asthma and tuberculosis) and environmental air pollution.<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> Thus, the aetiology of COPD is still not fully elucidated.</p><p>COPD is caused by airway or alveolar abnormalities, leading to chronic respiratory symptoms such as dyspnoea, cough and sputum production. The major feature of COPD is progressive and persistent airway obstruction, resulting in impaired lung function.<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6 7</sup></xref> Lung tissue begins to gradually form as early as pregnancy, and the features in early period may have a potential impact on lung function in adulthood. Some epidemiological studies have showed an association between impaired lung development in early life and adult respiratory disease or decreased lung function.<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> Stocks <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> also focused on the unfavourable factors which adversely affect lung development in utero and within the first 5 years of life and mentioned events in early life as potential causes of lung function, such as birth weight.<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> Some evidence has suggested that birth weight is associated with abnormal lung function. For example, a meta-analysis for British women showed that the levels of lung function indicators, such as forced expiratory volume in 1&#8201;s (FEV<sub>1</sub>) and forced vital capacity (FVC), were positively correlated with birth weight, indicating that birth weight may have an impact on the normal development of the lungs.<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> Another study of Chinese adolescents found that birth weight was closely non-linear associated with lung function and asthma.<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> Another twin study had also confirmed the effect between low birth weight and impaired adult lung function.<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> Yang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> suggested that pulmonary effects due to low birth weight persisted into adulthood.<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> Therefore, low birth weight is likely to be an important risk factor for lung disease in adults.</p><p>In fact, low birth weight has been considered to be one of the underlying factors of COPD. The latest edition of the global strategy for the diagnosis, management and prevention of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease for the Global Initiative for Chronic Obstructive Lung Disease believed that low birth weight will affect the normal development of the airway and cause lung dysfunction.<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref> Brostr&#246;m <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> found that women with low birth weight increased the risk of adult COPD, and this phenomenon was also found in the elderly.<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> However, the relationship between birth weight and COPD is still not elucidated, and there is a lack of sufficient population studies to explain the relationship. Furthermore, because birth weight occurs early in life, prospective studies may be appropriate to address its association with the risk of COPD, so more evidence from large populations is needed to explain the association.</p><p>To assess a better understanding of the role of birth weight in the pathogenesis of COPD, we mined the cohort data from UK Biobank to investigate the relationship of birth weight and COPD risk, and explore the interaction or joint effects between birth weight and other factors.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>Study population</title><p>Data were obtained from UK Biobank, a large prospective cohort study, which recruited more than 500&#8201;000 participants who aged 40&#8211;69 years from 22 assessment centres in the UK.<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> At baseline, each participant was invited to take a face-to-face interview by standardised questionnaire, including demographic characteristics, living behaviours, personal health and family histories. Physical examination was completed by professionally trained staffs. All participants were registered with the UK National Health Service (NHS).</p><p>In this study, we excluded 49&#8201;724 participants with baseline airway obstruction including baseline prevalent COPD (n=3498), self-reported emphysema or chronic bronchitis (n=8349) and FVC/FEV1 &lt; lower limit of normal (calculated according to the Global Lung Function Initiative 2012 criteria) (n=41&#8201;779).<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref> Besides, we excluded 44 participants who had withdrawn from the cohort and those with missing birth weight data (n=2&#8201;01&#8201;473). Finally, 251&#8201;172 participants were included in this study (<xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental figure 1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Assessment of baseline birth weight</title><p>During the baseline survey, participants recalled their birth weight, which was reported in kilograms (kg), pounds or ounces and then unified as kilograms. The baseline body mass index (BMI) was defined as baseline weight divided by the square of baseline height (kg/m<sup>2</sup>).</p></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>Ascertainment of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD)</title><p>COPD diagnosis was defined by the electronic health records linkage to the NHS register (expiration date: 30 September 2021 for England, 28 February 2018 for Wales and 31 July 2021 for Scotland, respectively). The registration data were coded according to the 10th edition of International Classification of Diseases (ICD-10), and we applied J40&#8211;J44 to define diagnosed COPD in this study.</p></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>Covariates definition</title><p>The covariates from the UK Biobank were also collected from baseline survey. Early life factors included birth place, maternal smoking, multiple birth and breastfeeding. Moreover, we also collected demographic characteristics (sex, race, baseline age, Townsend deprivation index, occupations and education level), living behaviours (smoking status, passive smoking, alcohol consumption and physical activity), baseline asthma, family history of respiratory diseases and environmental pollution (PM<sub>2.5</sub> level). Physical activity frequency was measured as metabolic equivalent task (MET) hours per week for moderate exercise. PM<sub>2.5</sub> level was according to the average annual concentration calculated by land use regression model in 2010. Baseline asthma for participants and their family members was according to ICD-10 (J45&#8211;J46). High-risk occupations for COPD were self-reported by participants, which had positive association with COPD risk (prevalence ratio &#8805;1.30).</p></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Baseline continuous variables were described as means&#177;SDs, and categorical variables were expressed as constituent ratios (n, %). Follow-up time in cohort was calculated from the date of baseline investigation to the first diagnosis of COPD, the last date of follow-up, loss of follow-up or death date (whichever comes first). Moreover, we used standardised mean difference (SMD) to evaluate the significant differences between the included participants and those with missing birth weight. In details, SMD &gt;0.2 indicates a potentially relevant difference between the groups.</p><p>We used Cox proportional hazards regression models to estimate the HRs and 95% CIs for the association between birth weight and COPD risk. We divided birth weight into quintiles (Q1&#8211;Q5) and using Q3 as the reference group. Moreover, we built three multivariable models to analyse the results. Model 1 was adjusted for baseline age, sex and race. Model 2 was additionally adjusted by Townsend deprivation index, education level (college or university degree), BMI, physical activity (moderate MET-hours/week), smoking status (never, previous, pack-year &lt;10, 10&#8211;&lt;20 pack-year, 20&#8211;&lt;30 pack-year, pack-year &#8805;30), passive smoking (never, current (0&#8211;&lt;20&#8201;hours a week, &#8805;20&#8201;hours a week)), alcohol intake frequency, baseline asthma, high-risk occupation for COPD, PM<sub>2.5</sub> and family history of respiratory diseases. Model 3 was additionally adjusted for early life factors (birth place, maternal smoking, multiple birth and breastfeeding). Since the important effect of smoking, we further fitted these three models among current smokers and current non-smokers depend on the covariate &#8216;smoking status&#8217;, respectively. We further assessed multicollinearity with the variance inflation factor (VIF), with VIF &lt;10 indicating no significant collinearity.</p><p>Besides, we applied restricted cubic splines (RCS) to fit the dose-response relationship between birth weight and COPD risk with four knots, and we defined the median of birth weight as the reference of HR=1.00. We first established the model in all participants and then stratified into two groups with baseline current smoking or non-smokers. Moreover, the adjusted variables were also consistent with Cox regression models.</p><p>To control for confounding variables and identify subgroup effects, we performed a stratified analysis of key covariates, including age (categorised as &lt;60&#8201;and &#8805;60 years), sex, BMI (&lt;25, 25 to &lt;30 and &#8805;30&#8201;kg/m<sup>2</sup>), smoking status (never, ever and current smokers), physical activity (&lt;8&#8201;or &#8805;8 MET-hours per week), passive smoking exposure (never, ever and current), maternal smoking history (yes or no), family history of respiratory diseases (yes or no), baseline asthma (yes or no), high-risk occupations for COPD (yes or no), breastfeeding (yes or no) and multiple births (yes or no). By comparing models that include interaction terms with those that exclude them, the likelihood ratio test enables us to assess whether these interactions significantly enhance the explanatory power.</p><p>Moreover, the interactions between birth weight and other covariates were calculated by models with interaction items, and potential joint effects were analysed by setting up a reference. We also conducted sensitivity analysis by excluding the participants diagnosed as COPD during first 2 years among follow-up, with poor self-rated health, maternal smoking, non-breastfeeding and multiple birth.</p><p>All data were analysed using SAS V.9.4 (SAS Institute, USA) and R software (V.4.3.1, R Foundation for Statistical Computing). All statistical tests were two-sided, and p&lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec><sec id="s2-6"><title>Patient and public involvement</title><p>Patients and/or the public were not involved in the design, conduct, reporting, or dissemination plans of this research.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3-1"><title>Baseline characteristics of study population</title><p>In this study, we included 251&#8201;172 baseline participants, with 96&#8201;819 males (38.5%) and 1&#8201;54&#8201;353 females (61.5%). We did not observe significant differences between participants and those with missing birth weight, aside from breastfeeding (<xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental table 1</xref>). During a median follow-up of 12.3 years (IQR: 11.3&#8211;13.2 years), 5601 COPD patients were found in the whole cohort. For all participants, the median of birth weight was 3.32&#8201;kg (IQR: 2.95&#8211;3.66&#8201;kg). We further described the distribution of covariates across the population by quintiles of the population based on birth weight data. The basic characteristics of participants are shown in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>. In particular, in the lowest birth weight group (Q1), the proportion of maternal smoking was the highest (30.46%) and decreased with increasing birth weight (Q2 to Q5: 26.42% to 22.72%, respectively); moreover, all participants with lower birth weight were more likely to be females (Q1, 71.91%; Q2, 65.96%).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Basic demography characteristics of study participants for birth weight (n=2 51 172).</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1"/><td colspan="5" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">Birth weight (kg)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q1 (&lt; 2.86)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q2 (2.86-)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q3 (3.18-)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q4 (3.40-)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q5 (&#8805; 3.80)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Participants, n</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49&#8201;746</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57&#8201;504</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45&#8201;818</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47&#8201;105</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50&#8201;999</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline variables</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Women, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35&#8201;772 (71.91)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37&#8201;930 (65.96)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28&#8201;496 (62.19)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26&#8201;454 (56.16)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25&#8201;701 (50.40)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;White, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47&#8201;565 (95.62)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55&#8201;359 (96.27)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44&#8201;768 (97.71)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45&#8201;797 (97.22)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49&#8201;721 (97.49)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Age, years</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.66&#177;8.09</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.41&#177;8.14</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.77&#177;7.97</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.43&#177;8.06</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.36&#177;8.16</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Townsend deprivation index</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;1.37&#177;3.02</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;1.54&#177;2.92</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;1.60&#177;2.92</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;1.58&#177;2.91</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;1.53&#177;2.94</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;College or university degree, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14&#8201;978 (30.11)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19&#8201;858 (34.53)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16&#8201;201 (35.36)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#8201;517 (37.19)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#8201;769 (34.84)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;BMI, kg/m<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.36&#177;5.05</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.06&#177;4.78</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.19&#177;4.77</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.38&#177;4.81</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.88&#177;4.90</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Physical activity, moderate MET-hours/week</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.90&#177;18.29</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.86&#177;18.26</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.95&#177;18.31</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.83&#177;18.33</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.27&#177;18.64</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Current smoking, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3426 (6.88)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3764 (6.55)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3190 (6.97)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3224 (6.84)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3822 (7.49)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Passive smoking, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9707 (19.51)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10&#8201;693 (18.60)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8495 (18.54)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8747 (18.57)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9691 (19.01)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Alcohol intake daily or almost daily, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18&#8201;871 (37.93)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24&#8201;728 (43.00)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20&#8201;429 (44.59)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#8201;454 (45.55)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23&#8201;650 (46.37)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Asthma, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5852 (11.76)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6013 (10.46)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4706 (10.27)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4700 (9.98)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5134 (10.07)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Family history of respiratory diseases, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8414 (16.91)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8337 (14.50)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6171 (13.47)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6209 (13.18)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7188 (14.09)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;High-risk occupations of COPD, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1013 (2.03)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1009 (1.75)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">734 (1.60)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">719 (1.52)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">810 (1.59)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;PM<sub>2.5</sub>, &#956;g/m&#179;</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.94&#177;0.99</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.92&#177;1.00</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.91&#177;0.99</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.91&#177;1.00</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.92&#177;1.01</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Early life factors</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Part of multiple birth, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4904 (9.86)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1042 (1.81)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">432 (0.94)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">287 (0.61)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">190 (0.37)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Breastfeeding, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26&#8201;554 (53.38)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36&#8201;368 (63.24)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29&#8201;998 (65.47)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31&#8201;005 (65.82)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33&#8201;099 (64.90)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Maternal smoking, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15&#8201;152 (30.46)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15&#8201;192 (26.42)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11&#8201;468 (25.03)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10&#8201;842 (23.02)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11&#8201;586 (22.72)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T1_FN1" fn-type="other"><p>The data of birthweight was divided into quintiles (Q1&#8211;Q5) to describe. Q3 was defined as the reference group.</p></fn><fn id="T1_FN2" fn-type="other"><p>All continuous variables are described as means &#177; SDs, and categorical variables are calculated by quantities and percentages.</p></fn><fn fn-type="abbr"><p>BMIbody mass indexCOPDchronic obstructive pulmonary diseaseMETmetabolic equivalent task</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3-2"><title>Association between birth weight and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) risk</title><p><xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> showed the statistical associations between birth weight and COPD risk. We took the third quintile group (Q3) as the reference. In these three models, compared with reference, the first quintile (Q1) had a higher risk of COPD (model 1 (HR=1.37, 95% CI 1.26 to 1.49); model 2 (HR=1.24, 95% CI 1.14 to 1.35); model 3 (HR=1.21, 95% CI 1.11&#8211;1.32), respectively). However, the highest group (Q5) also showed a positive association with COPD risk in model 1, but not found in model 2 (HR=1.05, 95% CI 0.96 to 1.14) and model 3 (HR=1.05, 95% CI 0.96 to 1.15). Considering the significant impact of smoking on COPD, we explored the associations between baseline current smokers and non-smokers. The results showed that among current smokers, the risk of COPD associated with low birth weight was significant (Q1 vs Q3: HR=1.25, 95% CI 1.13 to 1.38), while this phenomenon was not detected among non-smokers. Meanwhile, the results of the VIF indicate that multicollinearity is not significant in our analysis (<xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Associations between birth weight and the risk of COPD for participants in UK Biobank</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="2" valign="top"/><td colspan="5" valign="top" rowspan="1">Birth weight (kg), HR (95% CIs)</td><td rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">P for non-linearity</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q1 (&lt; 2.86)</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q2 (2.86-)</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q3 (3.18-)</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q4 (3.40-)</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q5 (&#8805; 3.80)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="4" align="left" colspan="1">Total participants</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of COPD cases</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1369</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1216</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">891</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">896</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1229</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37 (1.26&#8211;1.49)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 (0.96&#8211;1.14)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ref</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99 (0.90&#8211;1.09)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14 (1.05&#8211;1.24)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.24 (1.14&#8211;1.35)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06 (0.97&#8211;1.15)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ref</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01 (0.92&#8211;1.11)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 (0.96&#8211;1.14)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.21 (1.11&#8211;1.32)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06 (0.97&#8211;1.16)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ref</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01 (0.92&#8211;1.11)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 (0.96&#8211;1.15)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="4" align="left" colspan="1">Participants with ever smoking</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of COPD cases</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1036</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">910</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">685</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">679</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">976</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.48 (1.34&#8211;1.63)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06 (0.96&#8211;1.17)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ref</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97 (0.87&#8211;1.07)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 (0.99&#8211;1.20)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28 (1.16&#8211;1.41)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04 (0.95&#8211;1.15)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ref</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99 (0.89&#8211;1.10)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04 (0.95&#8211;1.15)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25 (1.13&#8211;1.38)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 (0.95&#8211;1.16)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ref</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 (0.90&#8211;1.11)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 (0.95&#8211;1.16)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="4" align="left" colspan="1">Participants with non-smoking</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of COPD cases</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">333</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">306</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">217</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29 (1.08&#8211;1.53)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 (0.91&#8211;1.30)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ref</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06 (0.88&#8211;1.29)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14 (0.95&#8211;1.37)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14 (0.96&#8211;1.36)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07 (0.90&#8211;1.28)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ref</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04 (0.86&#8211;1.26)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 (0.87&#8211;1.26)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 (0.91&#8211;1.30)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06 (0.89&#8211;1.26)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ref</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 (0.86&#8211;1.27)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 (0.87&#8211;1.27)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T2_FN1" fn-type="other"><p>The data of birthweight was divided into quintiles (Q1&#8211;Q5) to describe. Q3 was defined as the reference group.</p></fn><fn id="T2_FN2" fn-type="other"><p>Model 1: adjusted for baseline age, sex and race.</p></fn><fn id="T2_FN3" fn-type="other"><p>Model 2: additionally adjusted for baseline Townsend deprivation index, college or university degree, body mass index, physical activity (moderate MET-hours/week), smoking status, passive smoking, alcohol intake frequency, baseline asthma, high-risk occupation for COPD, PM<sub>2.5</sub> and family history of respiratory diseases.</p></fn><fn id="T2_FN4" fn-type="other"><p>Model 3: additionally adjusted for early life factors including birth place, maternal smoking, part of multiple birth and breastfeeding.</p></fn><fn fn-type="abbr"><p>COPDchronic obstructive pulmonary disease</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3-3"><title>Non-linear relationship for birth weight and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) risk</title><p>As <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1</xref> showed, the non-linear association was significant between birth weight and COPD risk. <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1A</xref> is fitted by adjusting age, sex and race. <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B</xref> is additionally adjusted by Townsend deprivation index, education level, BMI, smoking status, passive smoking, physical activity, alcohol intake frequency, baseline asthma, high-risk occupation for COPD, PM<sub>2.5</sub> and family history of respiratory diseases, and <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1C</xref> was additionally adjusted by birth place, maternal smoking, multiple birth and breastfeeding. When using the median as a reference point, it could be seen that the relationship showed a trend of first decreasing and then increasing, and when birth weight was lower, it was also found that the relative risk of COPD was higher (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
<sub>for nonlinearity</sub>&lt;0.001).</p><fig position="float" id="F1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>The non-linear relationship between birth weight and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease risk by restricted cubic splines.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bmjresp-11-1-g001.jpg"/></fig><p>Besides, we further fitted the non-linear trends between current smokers and non-smokers at baseline. As showed in <xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental figure 2A</xref>, similar trends were also observed among baseline smokers; among non-smokers, the relationship between low birth weight and COPD risk is not significant (<xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental figure 2B</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s3-4"><title>Stratified and sensitivity analysis</title><p>In the stratified analysis (<xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental table 3</xref>), the associations between baseline birth weight and COPD risk in different subgroups were generally consistent in the same tendency, but the interactions of sex, passive smoking and maternal smoking with COPD risk were statistically significant (all <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
<sub>for interaction</sub>&lt;0.05). All results are also showed in <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">figure 2</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="F2" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Forest plot for stratified analysis and P for interaction between covariates and birth weight.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bmjresp-11-1-g002.jpg"/></fig><p>The results of sensitivity analysis were listed in <xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental table 4</xref>. The associations between birth weight and COPD risk did not change significantly when we excluded those participants who were diagnosed as COPD in the first 2 years of follow-up (n=405), with poor self-rated health (n=8816), baseline asthma (n=26&#8201;405) and multiple birth (n=8914), for all HRs &gt;1&#8201;when Q1 compared with Q3 (HR=1.21, 95% CI 1.11 to 1.32; HR=1.18, 95% CI 1.08 to 1.30; HR=1.20, 95% CI 1.09 to 1.32; HR=1.20, 95% CI 1.091.31, respectively).</p></sec><sec id="s3-5"><title>Joint analysis</title><p>We further explored the joint effect with maternal smoking, breastfeeding and birth weight for COPD risk. We combined birth weight with maternal smoking and breastfeeding respectively and used Q3 of birth weight with no maternal smoking and Q3 with no breastfeeding as reference groups for joint analysis. As showed in <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">figure 3</xref> and <xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental table 5</xref>, the people who with both maternal smoking and low birth weight had a higher risk of COPD, but we did not find the same tendency in breastfeeding.</p><fig position="float" id="F3" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>The joint effect analysis of maternal smoking, breastfeeding and birth weight for chronic obstructive pulmonary disease risk.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bmjresp-11-1-g003.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Birth weight has been considered to be related to the risk of several common chronic diseases like cardiovascular disease, hypertension and malignant cancer.<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref><xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> Likewise, the relationship between birth weight and pulmonary diseases has been already mentioned.<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref> However, its relationship with COPD incidence has been rarely reported. Here, we explored the potential association between birth weight and COPD through a long-term prospective study.</p><p>In this study, we analysed the association and observed an increased risk of COPD with low birth weight (&lt;2.86&#8201;kg). We also fitted the non-linear dose-response relationship and found interactions between birth weight and other covariates. In addition, we found a significant joint effect between maternal smoking and low birth weight. In 1991, Barker <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> conducted a survey of males in England and found low birth weight was associated with poorer adult lung function, as well as with higher COPD mortality decreased with increasing birth weight.<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref> Another meta-analysis explained some evidence on early life exposure with COPD risk in adulthood. For the pooled result by three researches, low birth weight was significantly positively associated with COPD (pooled OR=1.58, 95% CI 1.08 to 2.32).<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref> However, when the results (with populations from Lebanon, Spain and Sweden) were analysed independently, no statistically significant effects were found.<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15 25 26</sup></xref> It can be seen that the relationship between COPD and low birth weight is actually &#8216;unclear&#8217; and its relationship is uneven due to differences in populations, regions and research designs (mainly case-control or cross-sectional studies). Unlike previous studies, this study is based on a cohort study with a large sample population and long-term follow-up, with the results are relatively stable.</p><p>In addition, low birth weight often results in inadequate lung development and compromised lung architecture due to intrauterine growth restriction.<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref> Lung impairment severity and COPD risk levels vary among those with low birth weight, potentially showing threshold effects where specific birth weight ranges correspond to different health outcomes.<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> People born with a birth weight below a critical threshold may experience a pronounced risk for COPD due to the combined effects of lung development and early-life exposures, whereas those within a slightly higher range may not experience the same level of risk.<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> For example, those with low birth weight may have a higher likelihood of experiencing chronic inflammatory status, further complicating the relationship with COPD risk.<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref> Some researches indicated that individuals with low birth weight may experience higher levels of chronic inflammation postnatally, which can lead to persistent damage and remodelling of the airways, thereby increasing the incidence of COPD.<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref> Inflammatory mediators such as tumour necrosis factor (TNF-&#945;) and interleukins (IL-6) play a significant role in this process, leading to chronic airway inflammation and decreased lung function.<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref></p><p>Moreover, the pandemic of COVID-19 has further complicated this situation. Studies have showed that infection with COVID-19 can cause severe lung inflammation and damage, particularly for patients with existing COPD, who face a higher risk.<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref> COPD patients often experience more severe symptoms and complications after contracting COVID-19, leading to further deterioration of lung function. Additionally, individuals with low birth weight may be more vulnerable when infected with COVID-19 due to their impaired lung development, which can exacerbate the occurrence and progression of COPD.<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref></p><p>Another question was about the definition of low birth weight. The different results of the previous studies may also be related to differences in birth weight classification.<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref> Most previous studies defined &#8216;low birth weight&#8217; as &lt;2.50&#8201;kg, thus dividing birth weight into &#8216;normal&#8217; and &#8216;abnormal&#8217;.<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33</sup></xref> We used RCS to show the non-linear dose-response relationship.<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr"><sup>34</sup></xref> Through the function curve, we can see that when the birth weight gradually increased, the curve showed a trend of first appearance and then increased. The lowest birth weight COPD risk threshold occurred between 3 and 4&#8201;kg, so we defined the median of birth weight as the reference. Cox regression models also confirmed this phenomenon. In Cox regression, we categorised birth weight into quintiles; COPD risk was higher with lowest birth weight group (Q1) as compared with Q3.</p><p>In stratified analysis, we also show that COPD risk for low birth weight was substantially increased in the subgroup of lower age, history of passive smoking and maternal smoking. Admittedly, age is a common risk factor for lung disease, and lung function declines with age, especially in elders.<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref> Clearly, our results suggested that the risk of COPD is greater in those with low birth weight and elder. Another variable that interacted with birth weight was passive smoking.<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5 36 37</sup></xref> Not coincidentally, there has been a large amount of evidence to confirm the damage of smoking to lung function and its association with COPD. However, we did not find the effect for smoking and birth weight, for the reason of small proportion of participants who were smoking currently at baseline. Currently, low birth weight is considered to be a consequence of adverse maternal exposures during pregnancy.<xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr"><sup>38</sup></xref> Low birth weight also means poor growth and development of the foetus. McEvoy <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> mentioned maternal smoking during pregnancy as the largest preventable cause of abnormal lung development in utero.<xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39</sup></xref> The main adverse effects of maternal smoking on lung function in offspring are decreases in forced expiratory flows and decreased passive respiratory compliance.<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr"><sup>40</sup></xref> In another study for lung function trajectories and COPD risk prediction, maternal smoking was also an important part of early life predictive factors.<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr"><sup>41</sup></xref> Magnus <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> tried to estimate the association between COPD and lung function (FEV<sub>1</sub>/FVC) by using UK Biobank. Their results also suggested that abnormal lung function was positively associated with smoking during pregnancy.<xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr"><sup>42</sup></xref> Animal experiments have showed that maternal tobacco exposure during pregnancy can cause alveolar opacities in offspring, significantly reduce the activities of retinoic acid receptors &#945; and &#946;, disrupt normal lung development and cause immune damage. However, the mechanisms by which smoking during pregnancy leads to low birth weight have not been fully elucidated.<xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr"><sup>43</sup></xref> In joint analysis, our results confirmed their interactions on the risk of COPD, with a significantly higher risk associated with both exposures.</p><p>Our study has several strengths. First, the sample size of the study is large, which can basically reflect the characteristics of UK residents. Second, the subjects were followed up for a long time with accurate disease information and little recall bias. In addition, this study focused on the effect of birth weight on COPD, which was consistent with the chronological order and allowed for reasonable causal inference. However, some limitations were still existed. First, although birth weight data were collected through a standardised electronic questionnaire, the recall bias was inevitable. The participants might be influenced by different factors, such as the passage of time, sociocultural background and education level, leading to inaccurate memories of their birth weight, which could affect the reliability of the study results. Besides, the time span between birth weight and COPD diagnosis was long, so the occurrence of COPD was affected by many factors in the long term, but we could not adjust all potential influencing factors in the model, which may lead to bias from the actual effect. Third, some early life variables such as multiple births and breastfeeding were not found to be significantly associated with COPD. Additionally, although not statistically significant, we excluded participants without birth weight, making potential selection bias difficult to avoid. Furthermore, another potential limitation of our study is the risk of misclassification due to relying solely on diagnostic codes for identifying COPD. While diagnostic codes are commonly used in epidemiological studies, they may not fully capture all COPD cases, especially in the absence of more detailed clinical information. Misclassification could occur if patients with COPD are not properly coded or if those without COPD are misclassified as having the disease. Future research could benefit from considering additional criteria for case identification, such as more detailed diagnostic codes, treatment history for COPD or the occurrence of exacerbation events. These approaches could improve the accuracy of COPD case identification and reduce the risk of misclassification. Therefore, more in-depth research is needed to explain the impact of declaring early exposure on COPD.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusions</title><p>This study found a significant positive association between low birth weight and COPD risk and showed a non-linear dose-response relationship for birth weight and COPD. Low birth weight had interactions with maternal smoking, older age and passive smoking, and joint effect of low birth weight and smoking during pregnancy was demonstrated. Further analysis and research should be carried out in this direction.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>supplementary material</title><supplementary-material id="SP1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjresp-2024-002366</object-id><label>online supplemental file 1</label><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bmjresp-11-1-s001.pdf" id="d67e1061" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We are grateful to all participants in this study and the team of the UK Biobank study. This study was carried out using the UK Biobank Resource under application number 84525.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> This study was supported by grants from the Key Project of Medical Science Research of Jiangsu Provincial Health Commission (No. K2023072).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Provenance and peer review:</bold> Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Patient consent for publication:</bold> Not applicable.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Ethics approval:</bold> This study involves human participants. The ethics approval was obtained from the North West Multi-centre Research Ethics Committee (06/MRE08/65). Participants gave informed consent to participate in the study before taking part.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Data availability free text:</bold> The dataset supporting the conclusions of this study are available from UK Biobank but restrictions apply to the availability. Data were used under license of this study, which is not publicly available. However, it can be obtained with reasonable request and permission from the UK Biobank. More details can be found at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ukbiobank.ac.uk/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ukbiobank.ac.uk/</ext-link>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Patient and public involvement:</bold> Patients and/or the public were not involved in the design, conduct, reporting or dissemination plans of this research.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Safiri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carson-Chahhoud</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Noori</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Burden of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease and its attributable risk factors in 204 countries and territories, 1990-2019: results from the Global Burden of Disease Study 2019</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2022</year><volume>378</volume><elocation-id>e069679</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj-2021-069679</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35896191</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9326843</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Distributions and trends of the global burden of COPD attributable to risk factors by SDI, age, and sex from 1990 to 2019: a systematic analysis of GBD 2019 data</article-title><source>Respir Res</source><year>2022</year><volume>23</volume><elocation-id>90</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12931-022-02011-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35410227</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8996417</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Christenson</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bafadhel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2022</year><volume>399</volume><fpage>2227</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(22)00470-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35533707</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mannino</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buist</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global burden of COPD: risk factors, prevalence, and future trends</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2007</year><volume>370</volume><fpage>765</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(07)61380-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17765526</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salvi</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease in never-smokers: risk factors, pathogenesis, and implications for prevention and treatment</article-title><source>Lancet Respir Med</source><year>2022</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>497</fpage><lpage>511</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(21)00506-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35427530</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hogg</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Timens</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The pathology of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</article-title><source>Annu Rev Pathol</source><year>2009</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>435</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.pathol.4.110807.092145</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18954287</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Castro Mendes</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ducharme-Smith</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mora-Garcia</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Household Food Insecurity, Lung Function, and COPD in US Adults</article-title><source>Nutrients</source><year>2021</year><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>2098</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/nu13062098</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34205308</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8235683</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahmoud</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Granell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peralta</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Early-life and health behaviour influences on lung function in early adulthood</article-title><source>Eur Respir J</source><year>2023</year><volume>61</volume><elocation-id>2001316</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/13993003.01316-2020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36265880</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9978163</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stocks</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hislop</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sonnappa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Early lung development: lifelong effect on respiratory health and disease</article-title><source>Lancet Respir Med</source><year>2013</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>728</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(13)70118-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24429276</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lawlor</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ebrahim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davey Smith</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association of birth weight with adult lung function: findings from the British Women&#8217;s Heart and Health Study and a meta-analysis</article-title><source>Thorax</source><year>2005</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>851</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thx.2005.042408</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16055617</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1747204</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mei</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Non-linear association of birth weight with lung function and risk of asthma: A population-based study</article-title><source>Front Public Health</source><year>2022</year><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>999602</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2022.999602</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36505001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9731215</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Salem</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Willers</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amylidi-Mohr</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Low Birth Weight and Impaired Later Lung Function: Results from a Monochorionic Twin Study</article-title><source>Ann Am Thorac Soc</source><year>2022</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1856</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1513/AnnalsATS.202112-1349OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35580242</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kingsford</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Horwood</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Lung Function of Adults Born at Very Low Birth Weight</article-title><source>Pediatrics</source><year>2020</year><volume>145</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2019-2359</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31900317</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Venkatesan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GOLD COPD report: 2023 update</article-title><source>Lancet Respir Med</source><year>2023</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>18</fpage><elocation-id>S2213-2600(22)00494-5</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(22)00494-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36462509</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brostr&#246;m</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akre</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Katz-Salamon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Obstructive pulmonary disease in old age among individuals born preterm</article-title><source>Eur J Epidemiol</source><year>2013</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10654-013-9761-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23341027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Circulating liver function markers and the risk of COPD in the UK Biobank</article-title><source>Front Endocrinol (Lausanne)</source><year>2023</year><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>1121900</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fendo.2023.1121900</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37033218</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10073719</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Quanjer</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stanojevic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Multi-ethnic reference values for spirometry for the 3-95-yr age range: the global lung function 2012 equations</article-title><source>Eur Respir J</source><year>2012</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>1324</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/09031936.00080312</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22743675</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3786581</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Association between birth weight and risk of cardiovascular disease: Evidence from UK Biobank</article-title><source>Nutr Metab Cardiovasc Dis</source><year>2021</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>2637</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.numecd.2021.05.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34218988</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Birth Weight and Adult Obesity Index in Relation to the Risk of Hypertension: A Prospective Cohort Study in the UK Biobank</article-title><source>Front Cardiovasc Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>637437</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fcvm.2021.637437</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34222359</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8245673</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Birth Weight and the Risk of Cardiovascular Outcomes: A Report From the Large Population-Based UK Biobank Cohort Study</article-title><source>Front Cardiovasc Med</source><year>2022</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>827491</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fcvm.2022.827491</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35402571</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8987713</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cirillo</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krigbaum</surname><given-names>NY</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Maternal obesity, pregnancy weight gain, and birth weight and risk of colorectal cancer</article-title><source>Gut</source><year>2022</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>1332</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/gutjnl-2021-325001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34429385</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8866526</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baumann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Godtfredsen</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>The impact of birth weight on the level of lung function and lung function decline in the general adult population. The Inter99 study</article-title><source>Respir Med</source><year>2015</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>1293</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rmed.2015.08.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26320403</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Godfrey</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fall</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Relation of birth weight and childhood respiratory infection to adult lung function and death from chronic obstructive airways disease</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>1991</year><volume>303</volume><fpage>671</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.303.6804.671</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1912913</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1670943</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Impact of early life exposures on COPD in adulthood: A systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Respirology</source><year>2021</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>1131</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/resp.14144</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34541740</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Waked</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salame</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khayat</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Correlates of COPD and chronic bronchitis in nonsmokers: data from a cross-sectional study</article-title><source>Int J Chron Obstruct Pulmon Dis</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>577</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/COPD.S35044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23055708</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3459656</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cos&#237;o</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pascual-Guardia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borras-Santos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Phenotypic characterisation of early COPD: a prospective case-control study</article-title><source>ERJ Open Res</source><year>2020</year><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>00047-2020</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/23120541.00047-2020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33043045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7533304</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kooiman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Terstappen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lely</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Low Birth Weight: Intrauterine Growth Restriction or Prematurity?</article-title><source>Am J Kidney Dis</source><year>2018</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>909</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.ajkd.2018.01.045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29609978</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Canoy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pekkanen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Early growth and adult respiratory function in men and women followed from the fetal period to adulthood</article-title><source>Thorax</source><year>2007</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>396</fpage><lpage>402</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thx.2006.066241</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17105780</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2117170</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Black</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ching</surname><given-names>PST</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beaumont</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Changes in elastic fibres in the small airways and alveoli in COPD</article-title><source>Eur Respir J</source><year>2008</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>998</fpage><lpage>1004</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/09031936.00017207</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18216063</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inflammatory mechanisms in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</article-title><source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source><year>2016</year><volume>138</volume><fpage>16</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaci.2016.05.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27373322</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muneeb Hassan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ameeq</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jamal</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of covid-19 among patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease and tuberculosis</article-title><source>Ann Med</source><year>2023</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>285</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07853890.2022.2160491</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36594409</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9815254</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tahir</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ameeq</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Risk factors identification of COVID-19 patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: A retrospective study in Punjab-Pakistan</article-title><source>Immun Inflamm Dis</source><year>2023</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>e981</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/iid3.981</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37647450</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10461420</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raets</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Doninck</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Crombrugge</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Normal glucose tolerant women with low glycemia during the oral glucose tolerance test have a higher risk to deliver a low birth weight infant</article-title><source>Front Endocrinol (Lausanne)</source><year>2023</year><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>1186339</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fendo.2023.1186339</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37334297</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10272607</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Association of ambient air pollution exposure with low birth weight</article-title><source>Environ Res</source><year>2022</year><volume>215</volume><fpage>114164</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2022.114164</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36027958</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raherison</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Girodet</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology of COPD</article-title><source>Eur Respir Rev</source><year>2009</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/09059180.00003609</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20956146</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Salvi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tobacco smoking and environmental risk factors for chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</article-title><source>Clin Chest Med</source><year>2014</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ccm.2013.09.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24507834</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Salvi</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease in non-smokers</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2009</year><volume>374</volume><fpage>733</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(09)61303-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19716966</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P-D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X-R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Associations of genetic risk and smoking with incident COPD</article-title><source>Eur Respir J</source><year>2022</year><volume>59</volume><elocation-id>2101320</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/13993003.01320-2021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34172472</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McEvoy</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spindel</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pulmonary Effects of Maternal Smoking on the Fetus and Child: Effects on Lung Development, Respiratory Morbidities, and Life Long Lung Health</article-title><source>Paediatr Respir Rev</source><year>2017</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.prrv.2016.08.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27639458</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5303131</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schittny</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miserocchi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sparrow</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spontaneous peristaltic airway contractions propel lung liquid through the bronchial tree of intact and fetal lung explants</article-title><source>Am J Respir Cell Mol Biol</source><year>2000</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1165/ajrcmb.23.1.3926</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10873148</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bui</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lodge</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Childhood predictors of lung function trajectories and future COPD risk: a prospective cohort study from the first to the sixth decade of life</article-title><source>Lancet Respir Med</source><year>2018</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>535</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(18)30100-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29628376</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Magnus</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tilling</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Independent and combined associations of maternal and own smoking with adult lung function and COPD</article-title><source>Int J Epidemiol</source><year>2018</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>1855</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ije/dyy221</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30339246</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6280943</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Manoli</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vyhlidal</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Maternal smoking and the retinoid pathway in the developing lung</article-title><source>Respir Res</source><year>2012</year><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>42</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1465-9921-13-42</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22651576</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3479035</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>Data are available upon reasonable request.</p></sec></back></article></pmc-articleset>