<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2757</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">cureus</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cureus</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2168-8184</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cureus Inc.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11725060</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11725060.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11725060</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11725060</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39803120</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.75629</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Psychiatry</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Pain Management</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Analysis of Analgesics and Adjuvant Medications on Psychiatric Comorbidities in Patients With Complex Regional Pain Syndrome 1</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muacevic</surname><given-names initials="A">Alexander</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adler</surname><given-names initials="JR">John R</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names initials="A">Ashley</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Espiridion</surname><given-names initials="ED">Eduardo D</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff-1">
<label>1</label>
Psychiatry, Drexel University College of Medicine, West Reading, USA </aff><aff id="aff-2">
<label>2</label>
Psychiatry, Reading Hospital Tower Health, West Reading, USA </aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">
Ashley Deng <email>asd328@drexel.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>13</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><issue>12</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">476094</issue-id><elocation-id>e75629</elocation-id><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>13</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>12</day><month>01</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-01-13 09:25:39.737"><day>13</day><month>01</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2024, Deng et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Deng et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License CC-BY 4.0., which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000075629.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cureus.com/articles/315995-analysis-of-analgesics-and-adjuvant-medications-on-psychiatric-comorbidities-in-patients-with-complex-regional-pain-syndrome-1">This article is available from https://www.cureus.com/articles/315995-analysis-of-analgesics-and-adjuvant-medications-on-psychiatric-comorbidities-in-patients-with-complex-regional-pain-syndrome-1</self-uri><abstract><p>Complex regional pain syndrome (CRPS) is a chronic pain disorder characterized by severe, disproportionate pain relative to an inciting event. The disorder&#8217;s pathophysiology is complex, involving both central and peripheral nervous system alterations, alongside genetic, inflammatory, and psychological factors. Using data from TriNetX, this study investigated the impact of analgesic and adjuvant therapies on psychiatric outcomes in CRPS patients. The analysis included 1,029 patients treated with non-opioid versus opioid analgesics and those using antidepressants versus anticonvulsants. Results revealed no significant differences in major depressive disorder (MDD), anxiety, suicidal ideation, or&#160;post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) between opioid and non-opioid analgesic groups. However, opioid analgesic was associated with a lower risk of behavioral disorders due to psychoactive substance use disorder (0.732; 95% confidence interval [CI] 0.555-0.899). Anticonvulsants, compared to antidepressants, were linked to significantly higher odds and hazards of psychiatric comorbidities: depression (odds ratio [OR] 5.475), anxiety (OR 1.87), PTSD (OR 1.551), and suicidal ideation (OR 2.718). Hazard ratios also showed higher risks for antidepressants in depression, anxiety, and PTSD. These findings highlight the risks and benefits associated with opioid analgesics and the potential therapeutic effects of antidepressants&#160;in patients with CRPS. Treatment should consider physiological and psychiatric symptoms, as both are impactful on pain management.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>anticonvulsants</kwd><kwd>antidepressant</kwd><kwd>chronic pain</kwd><kwd>chronic regional pain syndrome</kwd><kwd>large retrospective cohort</kwd><kwd>opioid analgesics</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Complex regional pain syndrome (CRPS) is a chronic pain disorder that is characterized by disproportionate levels of spontaneous and evoked regional pain beyond what would be expected given the trauma. CRPS can be divided into CRPS 1 or CRPS 2 [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Though there is similar symptomatology, the two subtypes are divided based on causes. CRPS 1 is due to an unknown major peripheral nerve injury and accounts for 90% of cases. CRPS 2 is associated with peripheral nerve injury, which was elucidated on a nerve conduction test. An abnormal nerve conduction test is not specific to CRPS 2 but can be part of the&#160;diagnostic criteria [<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. This study will focus on CRPS 1 due to the prevalence compared to CRPS 2. Diagnosis of CRPS is based mainly on the <italic toggle="yes">Budapest Criteria</italic>, which includes <italic toggle="yes">continuing pain, which is disproportionate to any inciting event</italic>,&#160;and at least one symptom in the categories of sensory (hyperesthesia or allodynia), vasomotor (temperature asymmetry or skin color asymmetry), sudomotor/edema (edema or sweating changes), and motor/trophic (decreased range of motion, motor dysfunction, or trophic changes) [<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].&#160;A large population study of 600,000 in the Netherlands found that females aged 60-70 were most commonly affected and the upper extremity was more frequently affected than the lower [<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Additionally, in another population-based study in the United States, fracture was cited as the most common antecedent in 46% of CRPS patients [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p><p>The pathophysiology of CRPS 1 is complicated and multifactorial, affecting both the central and peripheral nervous system [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Other factors like genetic predisposition, inflammation, and psychology,&#160;including stress, anxiety, depression, and past trauma, can influence both the severity and progression of&#160;CRPS 1, resulting in diverse presentations that vary from individual to individual. After injury, the nervous system may become hypersensitive to pain (central sensitization) and peripheral nociceptors may exhibit increased responsiveness (peripheral sensitization) [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. These changes are mediated by inflammatory mediators and neuropeptides like substance P and glutamate, contributing to chronic pain, hyperalgesia, and allodynia. The pain inhibitory pathways of the brain which are opioid-mediated can be impacted in CRPS 1 patients, causing greater severity of pain. Disinhibition of the primary motor cortex and reduced gray matter volume in pain-related parts of the brain (insula and cingulate cortex) have also been noted [<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Oxidative stress markers have also been shown to elevate following limb reperfusion [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Excessive B cell activation, along with increased IL-1&#946;, substance P, and bradykinin, among other mediators, can influence inflammation and the immune response [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>].</p><p>Psychiatric comorbidities can also play a crucial role in understanding CRPS 1. It is well-documented that chronic pain and psychiatric comorbidities exist in a bidirectional state where pain exacerbates psychiatric symptoms and vice versa [<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].&#160;The bidirectional model underscores the importance of addressing both the physical and psychiatric components of CRPS 1 in treatment. Major depressive disorder, extreme pain severity, and suicidal ideation were especially prevalent in the CRPS patient population [<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) is also more frequent in patients with CRPS 1 than it is in the general population [<xref rid="REF12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Treatment of CRPS 1 is difficult as there is not one known cause. There are also limited randomized controlled trials that study treatment for CRPS 1 specifically. A meta-analysis of pharmacologic treatment options for CRPS 1 cites anticonvulsants, bisphosphonates, corticosteroids, muscle relaxants, nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), opioids, and antidepressants. However, few of these treatments were studied in CPRS patients. Most are based on other neuropathic pain trials. Even fewer are randomized controlled trials [<xref rid="REF13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].&#160;We seek to add to a limited body of literature surrounding the pharmacological treatment of CRPS 1 patients, specifically studying their impact on the psychiatric comorbidities most commonly associated with CRPS 1.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><p>Data set</p><p>This study utilized data from TriNetX, a global network of electronic health records covering over 250 million records. The de-identified data included information on lab results, diagnoses, medications, procedures, and patient demographics. Institutional Review Board (IRB) approval was not required for this study.&#160;The platform was accessible through participating institutions. Data queries were conducted using the International Classification of Diseases, Tenth Revision (ICD-10), and Veterans Affairs Drug classifications.</p><p>Study population&#160;</p><p>The research focused on the United States Collaborative Network within the TriNetX database, involving 69 healthcare organizations. We included diagnoses&#160;from the last 10 years, specifically from January 1, 2014. The initial group included patients diagnosed with CRPS 1&#160;(ICD-10 code G90.5) who were treated with either opioid analgesics (CN101) or non-opioid analgesics (CN103). To investigate the use of adjuvant medications, the study population was further refined to include patients with CRPS who were prescribed either anticonvulsants (CN400) or antidepressants (CN600).</p><p>Study design&#160;</p><p>The study consisted of two main arms: one for analgesics and another for adjuvant medications. In the analgesic arm, Cohort 1, the reference group, included CRPS 1 patients who exclusively received non-opioids, while Cohort 2 included those who only received opioid analgesics. In the adjuvant medication arm, Cohort 1 included CRPS 1 patients who exclusively received antidepressants, while Cohort 2 included those who only received anticonvulsants. To ensure exclusivity, the alternative drug class was excluded through the 'cannot have' function&#160;criteria in TriNetX. Additionally, through setting temporal relationships, patients could not have a diagnosis of major depressive disorder or anxiety-related disorders before their diagnosis and treatment of CRPS. Propensity score matching was employed to balance the cohorts regarding age, sex, ethnicity, and race. Chronic illnesses were not considered confounding variables due to their low prevalence within the study population, and medications were not included in the matching due to minimal differences between cohorts. The psychiatric outcomes evaluated included diagnoses of recurrent major depressive disorder (ICD-10 code F33.0); anxiety, dissociative, stress-related, somatoform, and other disorders (ICD-10 codes F40-F48); mental and behavioral disorders due to psychoactive substance use (ICD-10 codes F10-F19); PTSD (ICD-10 code F43.1); and suicidal ideations (ICD-10 code R45.851).</p><p>Statistical analysis</p><p>The TriNetX platform was used to analyze measures of association and survival. The 69 organizations included both academic and non-academic institutions across the United States but did not include all hospital systems. Odds ratios (ORs) were calculated using logistic regression to compare the cohorts. Survival analysis was conducted using the Cox proportional hazards model to determine hazard ratios (HRs). The survival probabilities at the end of the observation period were calculated and compared using the log-rank test, along with Cox hazard ratios (HRs) and proportionality tests. The log-rank test was used specifically to assess differences in time-to-event distributions between groups under the null hypothesis, utilizing chi-square analysis.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>After matching for demographic characteristics, the matched cohorts were predominantly female (73%), White (70%), and non-Hispanic or Latino (60%) (Table <xref rid="TAB1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Demographic characteristics for CRPS patients separated by non-opioid analgesic and opioid analgesic (n = 1,029). </title><p>Cohort 1, non-opioid analgesic; Cohort 2, opioid analgesic.</p><p>A t-test was used for continuous variables, and a chi-square test was used for categorical variables.</p><p>SD, standard deviation;&#160;CRPS,&#160;complex regional pain syndrome</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean &#177; SD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (Current age)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.1 &#177; 21.7&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,029</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.998</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (Current age)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.1 &#177; 17.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,029</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.998</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age at index</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.5 &#177; 22.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,029</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.965</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age at index</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.6 &#177; 17.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,029</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.965</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">749</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.882</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">752</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.882</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">244</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.835</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">240</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.835</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">White</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">713</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.597</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">White</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">724</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.597</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Black or African American</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.881</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Black or African American</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.881</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">American Indian or Alaska Native</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">American Indian or Alaska Native</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown race</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">136</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown race</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">136</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Native Hawaiian or Other Pacific Islander</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.140</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Native Hawaiian or Other Pacific Islander</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.140</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown ethnicity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">365</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.963</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown ethnicity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">364</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.963</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-Hispanic or Latino</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">613</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.822</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-Hispanic or Latino</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">618</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.822</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hispanic or Latino</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.679</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hispanic or Latino</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.679</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other race</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.367</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.040</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other race</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.367</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.040</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asian</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asian</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>There was no significant difference in OR in developing depression, psychoactive substance use disorder (SUD), anxiety, and PTSD when comparing the opioid to non-opioid analgesics because the 95% confidence interval (CI) includes 1. Interestingly, the OR for behavioral disorder due to psychoactive SUD indicates that opioid users are less likely to develop the outcome than non-opioid users, with an OR of 0.732 (95% CI&#160;0.555-0.899) (Table <xref rid="TAB2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Odds ratios using chi-square test of psychiatric outcomes in CRPS patients: non-opioid vs. opioid analgesics.</title><p>The reference group is Cohort 1, patients taking opioid analgesics.</p><p>CI, confidence interval; CRPS,&#160;complex regional pain syndrome; PTSD,&#160;post-traumatic stress disorder</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Condition</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Odds ratio</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Major depressive disorder</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.167</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.716-1.902</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anxiety</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.201</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.937-1.539</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Behavioral disorder due to psychoactive substance use disorder</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.732</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.555-0.899</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTSD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.628</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.811-3.270</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suicidal ideation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.814</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.833-3.949</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>There was no significant difference in the time to onset of MDD, anxiety, suicidal ideation, and PTSD. The 95% CI&#160;for the HRs&#160;included 1, and the <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-values from the log-rank tests were greater than 0.05.</p><p>In contrast, the outcomes for behavioral disorders due to psychoactive SUD were significant. The&#160;HR was 0.724 (95% CI&#160;0.542-0.968), but the log-rank test showed no significant difference in survival probabilities (&#967;&#178; = 0.855, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.355), indicating a reduced risk of behavioral disorder due to psychoactive SUD and later onset in the opioid cohort compared to the non-opioid cohort (Table <xref rid="TAB3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Hazard ratios using Cox proportional model and log-rank test of psychiatric outcomes in CRPS patients: non-opioid vs. opioid analgesics.</title><p>The reference group is Cohort 1, patients with opioid analgesic</p><p>&#967;&#178;, chi-square; CI, confidence interval; CRPS,&#160;complex regional pain syndrome; PTSD,&#160;post-traumatic stress disorder</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Condition</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hazard ratio</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#967;&#178; (Log-rank)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">df</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> (Log-rank)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Major depressive disorder</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.113</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.688-1.799</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.520</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.471</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anxiety</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.109</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.882-1.396</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.011</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.083</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Behavioral disorder due to psychoactive substance use disorder</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.724</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.542-0.968</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.855</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.355</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTSD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.552</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.777-3.099</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.263</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.608</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suicidal ideation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.142</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.931-4.926</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.230</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.632</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>After matching for demographic characteristics, the matched cohorts were predominantly female (70%), White (75%), and non-Hispanic or Latino (65%) (Table <xref rid="TAB4" ref-type="table">4</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Demographic characteristics of CRPS patients using either anticonvulsants or antidepressants (n = 2,567).</title><p>Cohort 1, antidepressant only; Cohort 2, anticonvulsant only</p><p>A t-test was used for continuous variables, and a chi-square test was used for categorical variables.</p><p>SD, standard deviation; CRPS,&#160;complex regional pain syndrome</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean &#177; SD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.0 &#177; 17.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,567</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.915</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.9 &#177; 18.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,567</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.915</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age at index</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.1 &#177; 17.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,567</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.891</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age at index</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.0 &#177; 18.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,567</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.891</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,794</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.627</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,778</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.627</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">655</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.524</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">675</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.524</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">White</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,912</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.541</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">White</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,931</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.541</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Black or African American</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">197</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.559</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.016</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Black or African American</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">186</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.559</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.016</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">American Indian or Alaska Native</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">American Indian or Alaska Native</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown race</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">317</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.798</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown race</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">311</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.798</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Native Hawaiian or Other Pacific Islander</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Native Hawaiian or Other Pacific Islander</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown ethnicity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">804</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.653</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown ethnicity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">819</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.653</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hispanic or Latino</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.659</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hispanic or Latino</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.659</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-Hispanic or Latino</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,670</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.540</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-Hispanic or Latino</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,649</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.540</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other race</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.885</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other race</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">101</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.885</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asian</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.282</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.030</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asian</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.282</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.030</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Depression was found to be more strongly linked to the anticonvulsant condition, with an OR of 5.475 (95% CI&#160;3.459-8.665). This indicates that patients receiving anticonvulsants are much more likely to develop depression compared to those receiving antidepressants. Anxiety also showed a significant increase in risk, with an OR of 1.87 (95% CI&#160;1.612-2.169). PTSD was similarly elevated, with an OR of 1.551 (95% CI&#160;1.033-2.33), suggesting a moderate association. On the other hand, SUD did not show a significant increase in odds, with an OR of 1.044 (95% CI&#160;0.896-1.216), indicating no strong link. Finally, suicidal ideation exhibited a notable increase in risk, with an OR of 2.718 (95% CI&#160;1.313-5.627), highlighting its significant association with the anticonvulsant-only condition (Table <xref rid="TAB5" ref-type="table">5</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB5" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><title>Odds ratios using chi-square of psychiatric outcomes in CRPS patients: antidepressants vs anticonvulsants.</title><p>The reference group is Cohort 1, patients using antidepressants only.</p><p>CI, confidence interval, CRPS,&#160;complex regional pain syndrome; PTSD,&#160;post-traumatic stress disorder</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Condition</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Odds ratio</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Depression</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.475</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.459-8.665</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anxiety</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.612-2.169</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Behavioral disorder due to psychoactive substance use disorder</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.044</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.896-1.216</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTSD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.551</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.033-2.33</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suicidal ideation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.718</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.313-5.627</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>The HR was notably high at 5.437 (95% CI&#160;3.447-8.576), although the log-rank test did not show statistical significance (&#967;&#178; = 2.49, df = 1, and&#160;<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.1146). Anxiety exhibited a significant increase in hazard, with an HR of 1.813 (95% CI&#160;1.583-2.077), supported by a log-rank &#967;&#178; of 9.498 (df = 1, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0021). The risk of SUD showed no significant hazard increase, with an HR of 1.045 (95% CI: 0.908, 1.204) and a nonsignificant log-rank &#967;&#178; of 0.269 (df = 1, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.6040). PTSD was associated with a moderately elevated HR of 1.553 (95% CI&#160;1.038-2.325), but the log-rank test did not yield significance (&#967;&#178; = 0.008, df = 1, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.9278). Finally, suicidal ideation showed a notable increase in risk with an HR of 2.72 (95% CI&#160;1.317-5.619), although the log-rank test did not reach statistical significance (&#967;&#178; = 0.258, df = 1, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.6114) (Table <xref rid="TAB6" ref-type="table">6</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB6" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 6</label><caption><title>Hazard ratios and log-rank test of psychiatric outcomes in CRPS patients: antidepressants vs. anticonvulsants.</title><p>The reference group is Cohort 1, patients using antidepressants only.</p><p>&#967;&#178;,&#160; chi-square; CI, confidence interval;&#160;CRPS,&#160;complex regional pain syndrome</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Condition</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hazard ratio</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#967;&#178; (Log-rank)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">df</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> (Log-rank)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Depression</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.437</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.447-8.576</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1146</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anxiety</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.813</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.583-2.077</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.498</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0021</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Behavioral disorder due to psychoactive substance use disorder</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.045</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.908-1.204</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.269</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6040</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTSD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.553</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.038-2.325</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9278</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suicidal ideation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.317-5.619</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.258</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6114</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>This study examined the association between non-opioid versus opioid analgesic and antidepressant versus anticonvulsant treatments on psychiatric outcomes in patients with CRPS 1. While the findings indicate differences in psychiatric outcomes based on the type of medication used, these results should be interpreted cautiously, emphasizing the need for further research to guide clinical decision-making in this complex patient population.</p><p>The analysis of non-opioid and opioid analgesics revealed nuanced impacts on psychiatric outcomes. While no significant differences were observed in the development of MDD, anxiety, suicidal ideation, or PTSD, patients using opioids were less likely to develop behavioral issues due to psychoactive SUD&#160;compared to those using non-opioid analgesics. This is in contrast to some studies, which have found that opioids are effective for pain management but carry a high risk of dependency and misuse, several other studies have also identified an association between prescription opioid misuse and suicidal ideation and attempts [<xref rid="REF14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>-<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. However, in alignment with our findings, a study encompassing 86,168 persons across the United States found that opioid use without misuse is associated with lower odds of suicidal ideation and plans [<xref rid="REF17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Effective opioid usage in pain control could be effective in lowering suicidal ideation as well as buffering substance use disorder tendencies.</p><p>Opioid analgesics are useful in treating chronic pain [<xref rid="REF18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. A prospective study of chronic pain patients found significant pain relief over six months of opioid analgesic treatment [<xref rid="REF19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Psychiatric associations with opioids include SUD, where patients develop a dependency that can lead to a cycle of addiction exacerbating existing psychiatric conditions [<xref rid="REF20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Long-term opioid use can also contribute to mood disorders such as depression and anxiety, complicating the psychiatric profile of patients [<xref rid="REF21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. This is especially relevant to chronic pain patients where treatment occurs over long periods and psychiatric comorbidities can exacerbate opioid use and vice versa. Understanding risk factors for misuse is essential before the prescription of opioid analgesics. These can include untreated psychiatric disorders, age, history of abuse and addiction, and living environment [<xref rid="REF22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Non-opioid analgesics like NSAIDs and acetaminophen are generally considered safer concerning addiction [<xref rid="REF23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. They may be just as effective as, or even more effective than, opioid analgesics in long-term treatment [<xref rid="REF24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].</p><p>The study also compared psychiatric outcomes in CRPS 1 patients using antidepressants versus anticonvulsants as adjuvant therapies. Antidepressants were associated with significantly higher odds and hazards of psychiatric comorbidities, including depression, anxiety, PTSD,&#160;and suicidal ideation. SUD was not significant. This could be due to other preexisting psychiatric conditions, besides MDD or anxiety, where antidepressants are often prescribed for patients with a wide range of mood disorders, whereas anticonvulsants are conventionally used as pain management or anti-seizure [<xref rid="REF25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>-<xref rid="REF27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Prospective studies are necessary to exclude all preexisting mood disorders. The marked increase in psychiatric symptoms among the antidepressant group, particularly for depression and suicidal ideation, suggests a need for careful monitoring and possibly adjunctive therapies to address these risks.&#160;</p><p>Antidepressants serve a dual role in pain management and treating psychiatric conditions, presenting a complex relationship with psychiatric health [<xref rid="REF28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. They can sometimes exacerbate psychiatric symptoms if not taken correctly or with the appropriate dosage, as the therapeutic index for each drug is narrow [<xref rid="REF29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Both antidepressants and anticonvulsants are typically not associated with addiction [<xref rid="REF30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].&#160;</p><p>The findings emphasize the complexity of managing CRPS 1, highlighting the importance of tailoring the choice of analgesic to the patient's comorbid psychiatric condition for optimal outcomes. Opioids, due to their effectiveness in pain management, may have a therapeutic effect in managing substance use disorder and suicidal ideation. However, they also pose a significant risk of developing substance use disorder, highlighting the importance of cautious use and careful consideration of alternative treatments. Non-opioid analgesics, although associated with a lower risk of SUD, were not found to protect against psychiatric symptoms, suggesting that factors such as underlying pain severity and patient psychological profiles play critical roles in treatment outcomes. For adjuvant therapies, antidepressants showed a relatively safer profile regarding psychiatric outcomes; however, there is limited evidence specifically addressing the use of antidepressants as adjuvant therapy to prevent patients with CRPS 1 from developing psychiatric disorders. Both antidepressants and anticonvulsants are used to manage various psychiatric conditions and pain management, which may be relevant to CRPS 1 patients. Treatment decisions should be individualized, considering the patient&#8217;s psychiatric history and overall clinical context.</p><p>This study has several limitations, including its reliance on retrospective data, which may overlook relevant comorbidities and potentially confound the observed relationships. Furthermore, key details such as pain severity, medication dosage, adherence and modifications, treatment duration, and direct comparisons between multiple cohorts were unavailable. These limitations constrain the generalizability and robustness of the conclusions. Nevertheless, the extensive database provided an opportunity to analyze a large cohort of patients with a rare and complex condition - offering valuable insights into the association between analgesic and adjuvant treatments and psychiatric comorbidities.</p><p>Future research should prioritize prospective studies to better understand the causal relationships between treatment types and psychiatric outcomes in CRPS 1 patients. Moreover, exploring interventional treatment options such as nerve blocks, neuromodulation, and integrated pharmacological-psychological approaches could offer more comprehensive strategies for managing this complex condition.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Overall, this study sheds light on a relatively under-studied disease with unique and complicated pathophysiology and treatment. Ultimately, careful consideration of the individuals&#8217; preexisting conditions should inform the decision between opioid and non-opioid analgesic and adjuvant analgesic therapy. A holistic approach that addresses both the physiological and psychiatric aspects of CRPS 1 is essential to minimize the risk of psychiatric outcomes that can exacerbate the pain condition.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group content-type="conflict"><title>Disclosures</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Human subjects:</bold> Consent for treatment and open access publication was obtained or waived by all participants in this study.</p><p><bold>Animal subjects:</bold> All authors have confirmed that this study did not involve animal subjects or tissue.</p><p><bold>Conflicts of interest:</bold> In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following:</p><p><bold>Payment/services info:</bold> All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Financial relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Other relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Concept and design:</bold>&#160; Eduardo D. Espiridion, Ashley Deng</p><p><bold>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</bold>&#160; Eduardo D. Espiridion, Ashley Deng</p><p><bold>Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</bold>&#160; Eduardo D. Espiridion, Ashley Deng</p><p><bold>Supervision:</bold>&#160; Eduardo D. Espiridion</p><p><bold>Drafting of the manuscript:</bold>&#160; Ashley Deng</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="REF1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Complex regional pain syndrome</article-title><source>BMJ</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruehl</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>351</volume><year>2015</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmj.h2730</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26224572</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Complex regional pain syndrome</article-title><source>Am Fam Physician</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dempsey</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><volume>104</volume><year>2021</year><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/34264598/">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/34264598/</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34264598</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><article-title>Research Diagnostic Criteria (The &#8216;Budapest Criteria&#8217;) for Complex Regional Pain Syndrome in a Randomised Placebo-Controlled Phase III Multicentre Trial: Low-Dose Intravenous Immunoglobulin Treatment for Long-Standing Complex Regional Pain Syndrome (LIPS Trial)</article-title><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Goebel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bisla</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carganillo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><publisher-name>NIHR Journals Library</publisher-name><year>2017</year><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK464482/">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK464482/</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29144634</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The incidence of complex regional pain syndrome: a population-based study</article-title><source>Pain</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>de Mos</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Bruijn</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huygen</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dieleman</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stricker</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sturkenboom</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>12</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><volume>129</volume><year>2007</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17084977</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.pain.2006.09.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Complex regional pain syndrome type I: Incidence and prevalence in Olmsted county, a population-based study</article-title><source>Pain</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sandroni</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benrud-Larson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McClelland</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>207</lpage><volume>103</volume><year>2003</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12749974</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0304-3959(03)00065-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>An update on the pathophysiology of complex regional pain syndrome</article-title><source>Anesthesiology</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruehl</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>713</fpage><lpage>725</lpage><volume>113</volume><year>2010</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20693883</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/ALN.0b013e3181e3db38</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>A new hypothesis for the pathophysiology of complex regional pain syndrome</article-title><source>Med Hypotheses</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Georgius</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santarelli</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><volume>119</volume><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30122490</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.mehy.2018.07.026</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Impaired insula functional connectivity associated with persistent pain perception in patients with complex regional pain syndrome</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>12</volume><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0180479</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5503260</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28692702</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Oxidative stress contributes to fracture/cast-induced inflammation and pain in a rat model of complex regional pain syndrome</article-title><source>J Pain</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>TZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kingery</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>1147</fpage><lpage>1156</lpage><volume>19</volume><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29715519</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jpain.2018.04.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6163064</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Comorbidity between pain and mental illness -evidence of a bidirectional relationship</article-title><source>Eur J Pain</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bondesson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larrosa Pardo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stigmar</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ringqvist</surname><given-names>&#197;</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petersson</surname><given-names>IF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>J&#246;ud</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schelin</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>1304</fpage><lpage>1311</lpage><volume>22</volume><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29577509</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/ejp.1218</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Risk factors for suicidal ideation among patients with complex regional pain syndrome</article-title><source>Psychiatry Investig</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Noh</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><fpage>32</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><volume>11</volume><year>2014</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4306/pi.2014.11.1.32</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3942549</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24605121</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Increased prevalence of posttraumatic stress disorder in CRPS</article-title><source>Eur J Pain</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Speck</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schlereth</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Birklein</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maih&#246;fner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>466</fpage><lpage>473</lpage><volume>21</volume><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27650922</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/ejp.940</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Complex regional pain syndrome</article-title><source>Am Fam Physician</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dempsey</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><volume>104</volume><year>2021</year><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/34264598/">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/34264598/</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34264598</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Co-occurring substance use and mental disorders among adults with opioid use disorder</article-title><source>Drug Alcohol Depend</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCance-Katz</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>78</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><volume>197</volume><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30784952</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2018.12.030</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Frequency of prescription opioid misuse and suicidal ideation, planning, and attempts</article-title><source>J Psychiatr Res</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashrafioun</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Conner</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pigeon</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><volume>92</volume><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28364579</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jpsychires.2017.03.011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Suicidal behaviour and associated risk factors among opioid-dependent individuals: a case-control study</article-title><source>Addiction</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Maloney</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Degenhardt</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Darke</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mattick</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>1933</fpage><lpage>1941</lpage><volume>102</volume><year>2007</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17784898</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1360-0443.2007.01971.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Opioid use and misuse and suicidal behaviors in a nationally representative sample of US adults</article-title><source>Am J Epidemiol</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Samples</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stuart</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olfson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>1245</fpage><lpage>1253</lpage><volume>188</volume><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30834448</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/aje/kwz061</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6601526</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Opioid analgesics</article-title><source>Mayo Clin Proc</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Jamison</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>957</fpage><lpage>968</lpage><volume>90</volume><year>2015</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26141334</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.mayocp.2015.04.010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Effectiveness of opioid analgesics in chronic noncancer pain</article-title><source>Pain Pract</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zanolin</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duse</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Visentin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>272</fpage><lpage>278</lpage><volume>15</volume><year>2015</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25914912</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/papr.12176</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Opioid use disorder</article-title><source>Nat Rev Dis Primers</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Strang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Volkow</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Degenhardt</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><fpage>3</fpage><volume>6</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31919349</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41572-019-0137-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Depression effects on long-term prescription opioid use, abuse, and addiction</article-title><source>Clin J Pain</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>878</fpage><lpage>884</lpage><volume>34</volume><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29505419</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/AJP.0000000000000603</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Risk factors for opioid-use disorder and overdose</article-title><source>Anesth Analg</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>1741</fpage><lpage>1748</lpage><volume>125</volume><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29049118</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1213/ANE.0000000000002496</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Chronic use of opioid analgesics in non-malignant pain: report of 38 cases</article-title><source>Pain</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Portenoy</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foley</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>186</lpage><volume>25</volume><year>1986</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2873550</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0304-3959(86)90091-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Efficacy of non-opioid analgesics to control postoperative pain: a network meta-analysis</article-title><source>BMC Anesthesiol</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Black</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhagnani</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jahr</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>272</fpage><volume>20</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33109098</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12871-020-01147-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7592505</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Prevalence of pre-existing conditions relevant for adverse events and potential drug-drug interactions associated with augmentation therapies among patients with treatment-resistant depression</article-title><source>Adv Ther</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhdanava</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karkare</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pilon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><fpage>4900</fpage><lpage>4916</lpage><volume>38</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34368919</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s12325-021-01862-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8408057</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Antidepressants for depression in physically ill people</article-title><source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source><date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><month>8</month><year>2024</year></date-in-citation><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rayner</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valsraj</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Higginson</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hotopf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>0</fpage><year>2010</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/14651858.CD007503.pub2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20238354</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Anticonvulsant drugs for management of pain: a systematic review</article-title><source>BMJ</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>McQuay</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jadad</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiffen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>1047</fpage><lpage>1052</lpage><volume>311</volume><year>1995</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7580659</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmj.311.7012.1047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2551361</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Evidence-based data on pain relief with antidepressants</article-title><source>Ann Med</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fishbain</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>305</fpage><lpage>316</lpage><volume>32</volume><year>2000</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10949061</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3109/07853890008995932</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Antidepressants, old and new: a review of their adverse effects and toxicity in overdose</article-title><source>Emerg Med Clin North Am</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarko</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>637</fpage><lpage>654</lpage><volume>18</volume><year>2000</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11130931</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0733-8627(05)70151-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Anticonvulsants for cocaine dependence</article-title><source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source><date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><month>8</month><year>2024</year></date-in-citation><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Minozzi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cinquini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amato</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davoli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farrell</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pani</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vecchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>2015</volume><year>2015</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/14651858.CD006754.pub4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8812341</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25882271</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>