<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Lancet Reg Health Am</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Lancet Reg Health Am</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">4381</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">lrhamers</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Lancet Regional Health - Americas</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2667-193X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12032934</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12032934.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12032934</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12032934</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40290132</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lana.2025.101108</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2667-193X(25)00118-8</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">101108</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Prescription opioid use and substance use disorder in US women (2006&#8211;2022): a retrospective cohort study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schoenfeld</surname><given-names initials="AJ">Andrew J.</given-names></name><email>aschoenfeld@bwh.harvard.edu</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#8727;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name name-style="western"><surname>Holly</surname><given-names initials="KE">Kaitlyn E.</given-names></name><email>keholly@bwh.harvard.edu</email><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bryan</surname><given-names initials="MR">Matthew R.</given-names></name><email>mbryan3@mgh.harvard.edu</email><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hatton</surname><given-names initials="MO">Malina O.</given-names></name><email>Malina_hatton@hms.harvard.edu</email><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wien</surname><given-names initials="M">Matthew</given-names></name><email>mwien@bwh.harvard.edu</email><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koehlmoos</surname><given-names initials="TP">Tracey P.</given-names></name><email>Tracey.koehlmoos@usuhs.edu</email><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">e</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Center for Surgery and Public Health, Department of Orthopaedic Surgery, Brigham and Women's Hospital, Harvard Medical School, 75 Francis Street, Boston, MA, 02115, USA</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Department of Orthopaedic Surgery, Brigham and Women's Hospital, Harvard Medical School, 75 Francis Street, Boston, MA, 02115, USA</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Harvard Medical School, 25 Shattuck St, Boston, MA, 02115, USA</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Department of Internal Medicine, Brigham and Women's Hospital, Harvard Medical School, 75 Francis Street, Boston, MA, 02115, USA</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>e</label>Center for Health Services Research, Uniformed Services University of the Health Sciences, 4301 Jones Bridge Road, Bethesda, MD, 20814, USA</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#8727;</label>Corresponding author. <email>aschoenfeld@bwh.harvard.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>6</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>46</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">486668</issue-id><elocation-id>101108</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>7</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>9</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>18</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>26</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-04-28 15:25:17.690"><day>28</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2025 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><abstract id="abs0010"><title>Summary</title><sec><title>Background</title><p>Research has shown that multiple deployments may have adverse effects on active-duty servicewomen and women civilian dependents of active-duty servicemembers. There is concern that the associated stress could induce sustained prescription opioid use and substance use disorder (SUD). We sought to evaluate the incidence of sustained opioid use and SUD among servicewomen and women civilian dependents during 2006&#8211;2013, a period of increased operational intensity, compared to similar individuals in 2014&#8211;2022.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>We employed Military Health System claims data to identify servicewomen and dependents who were diagnosed with SUD or demonstrated sustained prescription opioid use (i.e., six months of uninterrupted use). The incidence of sustained opioid use (primary outcome) and SUD associated (secondary outcome) with 2006&#8211;2013 was compared to 2014&#8211;2022 among servicewomen and dependents. Multivariable log binomial regression was used to adjust for confounding. Ethnicity was not available in our dataset.</p></sec><sec><title>Findings</title><p>4,876,209 individuals were included. The average age (standard deviation [SD]) of the cohorts under study were 26.6 (SD 8.2) for active duty 2006&#8211;2013, 26.0 (SD 8.0) for active duty 2014&#8211;2022, 35.3 (SD 13.1) for dependents 2006&#8211;2013 and 33.6 (SD 12.1) for dependents 2014&#8211;2022. Compared to civilian dependents in 2014&#8211;2022, servicewomen from 2006 to 2013 demonstrated an increased risk of sustained prescription opioid use (RR 1.49, 95% CI 1.46&#8211;1.53). In 2014&#8211;2022, servicewomen had a lower risk compared to dependents (RR 0.47, 95% CI 0.45&#8211;0.49), while dependents in 2006&#8211;2013 were also at higher risk (RR 1.58, 95% CI 1.56&#8211;1.60). Servicewomen in 2006&#8211;2013 were at significantly greater risk of developing SUD (RR 1.07, 95% CI 1.06&#8211;1.08). During 2014&#8211;2022, servicewomen displayed a lower risk when compared to dependents (RR 0.80, 95% CI 0.79&#8211;0.81). Dependents in 2006&#8211;2013 showed a higher risk (RR 1.24, 95% CI 1.24&#8211;1.25).</p></sec><sec><title>Interpretation</title><p>We found significant increases in the risks of sustained opioid use and SUD among servicewomen and civilian dependents during a period of increased operational intensity (2006&#8211;2013). We believe these findings reflect the deleterious effects of emotional stress, insufficient support structures, and military sexual trauma.</p></sec><sec><title>Funding</title><p><funding-source id="gs1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100005712</institution-id><institution>U.S. Department of Defense, Defense Health Agency</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> (#HU00012320021).</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Opioid use</kwd><kwd>Substance use disorder</kwd><kwd>Women's health</kwd><kwd>Epidemiology</kwd><kwd>Socioeconomic status</kwd><kwd>Combat</kwd><kwd>Military health system</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="p0010">
<boxed-text id="dtbox1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Research in context</title></caption><sec id="dtbox1sec1"><title>Evidence before this study</title><p id="p0015">We searched PubMed and Scopus for longitudinal studies reporting on the incidence of sustained prescription opioid use, or substance use disorder, among women in the US associated with combat deployment. We employed the following search terms (&#8220;addiction, opiate&#8221;) AND (&#8220;women&#8221;) AND (&#8220;combat&#8221;). The search considered all articles published up to January 22, 2025. The search identified fourteen studies, none of which specifically evaluated the association between time period, operational intensity, and combat deployment on the outcome of interest. An expanded search was performed that included ((addiction, opiate) AND (women [MeSH Terms])) AND (disorder, substance use [MeSH Terms]). This search yielded 114 results, none of which specifically focused on the intent of our investigation either. Most of the work we encountered focused on pregnant women and opioid use disorder, healthcare disparities in the receipt of treatment for opioid addiction among women or pregnant women, and drug-related infections among pregnant women. At present, the question remains as to the association between increased emotional stress associated with deployment frequency and operational intensity of combat deployments and sustained prescription opioid use and substance use disorder among both active-duty servicewomen and civilian women dependents.</p></sec><sec id="dtbox1sec2"><title>Added value of this study</title><p id="p0020">This investigation represents one of the largest and most comprehensive longitudinal assessments evaluating the association between operational intensity, combat deployments and the incidence of sustained prescription opioid use and substance use disorder in both active-duty servicewomen and women civilian dependents. We found significant increases in the risks of sustained prescription opioid use and substance use among active-duty servicewomen and women civilian dependents during the period of increased operational intensity. We believe these findings reflect the deleterious effects of emotional stress, insufficient support structures, and military sexual trauma.</p></sec><sec id="dtbox1sec3"><title>Implications of all the available evidence</title><p id="p0025">We believe that our findings are translatable to the civilian sector, given that the covered population of the military health system has previously been shown to be analogous to the US demographic aged 18&#8211;64. In particular, clinicians in the Veterans Administration system and civilian sector should be aware of a heightened risk of sustained prescription opioid use and substance use disorder for women veterans who served in Iraq and/or Afghanistan over the time period 2006&#8211;2013, as well for women spouses and children of individuals with this type of service history.</p></sec></boxed-text>
</p><sec id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0030">Over the first two decades of the 21st century, while the Iraq and Afghanistan conflicts were occurring overseas, the opioid crisis emerged as an existential challenge to the US healthcare system. The conditions of modern warfare, characterized by an increased use of explosive devices with devastating destructive potential and repeated exposure to physical and psychological stressors, have been heralded as risk factors for substance abuse and opioid dependence.<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref></p><p id="p0035">Recent research also claimed that the period of heightened operational intensity associated with troop deployments in Iraq and Afghanistan (2006&#8211;2013), culminated in elevated risks of chronic pain conditions in both active-duty servicewomen and civilian women dependents of servicemembers.<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> The development of such conditions may increase the potential for sustained prescription opioid use and substance use disorder (SUD). In the time period of 2006&#8211;2013, there was widespread use of opioid medications as the primary means of pain control within the military healthcare setting.<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> Previous studies have found that individuals sustaining injuries were almost universally given opioids and that repeat exposures over multiple healthcare encounters was very common.<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> Such prescribing behavior was not confined to surgical interventions, or restricted to individuals injured in combat.<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> These realities, combined with the psychological and emotional stressors on servicewomen and civilian dependents could have created a perfect storm increasing the potential for both sustained prescription opioid use and SUD. To the best of our knowledge, however, the associations between operational intensity and deployment stress and sustained opioid use and SUD, have not been longitudinally evaluated in a comprehensive manner.</p><p id="p0040">Prior investigations heralding the high rate of opioid exposure among combat-injured veterans were conducted in cohorts that were 99% male.<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> It is unclear that their findings apply to servicewomen. For servicewomen, the operational environment and deployment setting potentially increase both proximal and distal minority stressors, while simultaneously disrupting established social support networks.<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> The deployed environment also increases the risk of exposure to military sexual trauma in addition to the potential for combat-related injury.<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> Aside from the potential for combat-related trauma, the other associated stressors, disrupted support networks and the possibility of increased risk-taking behavior may also impact civilian dependents. These challenges may combine to further exacerbate the potential for sustained prescription opioid use and substance use disorder. For example, Cichowski et&#160;al. reported that women veterans with a history of military sexual trauma exhibited significantly greater odds of chronic opioid use for pelvic pain.<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> Similarly, Beckman et&#160;al. documented a history of military sexual assault as a risk factor for post-traumatic stress and depression severity, as well as drug abuse including non-prescribed opioids.<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref></p><p id="p0045">In this context, we used claims data from the military health system (MHS)<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> to conduct a natural experiment investigating the temporal associations between operational intensity and exposure to combat deployments on sustained prescription opioid use and SUD in servicewomen and civilian women dependents. We aimed to determine the extent to which the period of heightened operational intensity (2006&#8211;2013) was associated with an increased risk of sustained prescription opioid use and SUD among both servicewomen and dependents. We hypothesized, based on prior studies,<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> that servicewomen and women civilian dependents in the time period 2006&#8211;2013 would exhibit higher likelihoods of sustained prescription opioid use and SUD when compared to comparands in the time period 2014&#8211;2022, a timeframe associated with lower operational intensity and fewer combat deployments.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Methods</title><p id="p0050">We used claims-based data from the MHS Data Repository (fiscal years 2006&#8211;2022). The mechanisms through which this information is collected, accessed, and made available to researchers has been outlined in previously published work.<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> Clinical care within the MHS is administered through facilities maintained by the Department of Defense (direct care) or civilian hospitals (private sector care).<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> Diagnoses rendered over the course of care, and prescriptions that are issued, are captured by the central repository of the MHS irrespective of the site of service. The MHS is not responsible for care within Veterans Administration (VA) facilities and patients receiving treatment through the VA are not represented in our patient population. We adhered to published methods of MHS data retrieval, including accessing all clinical events for eligible patients within direct care or the private sector.<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></p><p id="p0055">We included adult women, ages 18&#8211;64, who were either women serving in the Army, Air Force, Navy, and Marine Corps, or civilian women dependents of active duty servicemembers. Women were identified using demographic records within the MHS identification system based on beneficiary self-report and considered as representing &#8216;biologic sex.&#8217; Each cohort was divided based on time period; 2006&#8211;2013 and 2014&#8211;2022, with the former time window representing a period of increased operational intensity and heightened number of deployments.<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> These four categories were mutually exclusive and collectively exhaustive.</p><p id="p0060">Within the timeframe of the dataset, claims for eligible servicewomen and dependents were queried for billed class II or class III opioid prescriptions (beginning with the initial prescription and ending at discharge or December 31, 2022).<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> Based on previous work, we defined sustained prescription opioid use as six-months or longer of continuous prescription opioid use, without an interruption exceeding seven days.<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> Individuals who demonstrated sustained prescription opioid use at any point during the surveillance period were categorized in the sustained opioid use group.</p><p id="p0065">Sociodemographic and additional medical information were obtained from the MDR, including age, race (obtained via self-report as standard collection with enlistment and categorized as Asian or Pacific Islander, Black, White, Other), census region (Midwest, Northeast, South, West), sponsor rank (junior enlisted [EJ], senior enlisted [ES], officer [OF]), Charlson Comorbidity Index (categorized as 0 or one or more co-morbid conditions), and the presence of one or more of the following mental health diagnoses: depression, anxiety, post-traumatic stress.<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> Based on previous research, sponsor rank was used as a proxy for socioeconomic status, with junior enlisted sponsor rank considered to be representative of lower socioeconomic strata.<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> Hispanic ethnicity was not available in our dataset. In secondary analysis, individuals diagnosed with substance use disorder (SUD) were identified using relevant International Classification of Diseases, Ninth (ICD-9) and Tenth Revision (ICD-10) codes.</p><p id="p0070">Sustained prescription opioid use represented the primary outcome, while the primary exposure consisted of the combination of active-duty status (servicewomen or civilian dependent) and time of service (2006&#8211;2013 or 2014&#8211;2022). All comparisons were made to dependents in 2014&#8211;2022 as the referent. All other abstracted variables were considered confounders based on causal models informed by prior literature and clinical observations regarding the factors associated with the risks of developing sustained prescription opioid use and SUD.<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> Due to the nature by which such data is collected and presented in the MHS, we included all covariates in our regression models for the purposes of adjustment. Missing data was minimal in all categories except for patient race where it was missing for 64% of cases and over 85% of dependents. We addressed this using multiple imputation under the missing at random assumption.</p><p id="p0075">We report continuous data using means and standard deviations, and categorical data using frequencies and percentages. We employed multivariable log-binomial regression to adjust for confounding. All results were expressed using risk ratios (RR) with 95% confidence intervals (95% CI). We considered two-sided P-values &lt;0.05, and RR with 95% CI exclusive of 1.0 statistically significant. All analyses were performed using SAS version 9.4 (SAS Institute). Data were analyzed from April 2024 to April&#160;2025.</p><p id="p0080">This work was found exempt by the Institutional Review Board of the Uniformed Services University of the Health Sciences and Partners Institutional Review Board. The conduct and reporting of the research are aligned with the STROBE guidelines.</p><sec id="sec3.1"><title>Role of the funding source</title><p id="p0085">This study was funded through a grant from the U.S. Department of Defense, Defense Health Agency (award # HU00012320021). The funder had no role in the development, conduct, or determinations of the study, preparation of the manuscript, or decision to publish.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Results</title><p id="p0090">We included 4,876,209 individuals in this analysis [servicewomen: 670,850 (13.8%) in 2006&#8211;2013; 613,300 (12.6%) in 2014&#8211;2022 (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#160;1</xref>). Dependents: 2,208,365 (45.3%) in 2006&#8211;2013; 1,383,694 (28.4%) in 2014&#8211;2022]. Data collection was complete for all variables except sponsor rank (2610 missing), race (3,123,489 missing) and census region (421,334 missing). Individuals with missing race were retained in the model and assigned to an unknown category for analysis. The average age (standard deviation [SD]) of the cohorts under study were 26.6 (SD 8.2) for active duty 2006&#8211;2013, 26.0 (SD 8.0) for active duty 2014&#8211;2022, 35.3 (SD 13.1) for dependents 2006&#8211;2013 and 33.6 (SD 12.1) for dependents 2014&#8211;2022. In total, the cohort was comprised of 1,065,541 (21.9%) White women, 442,613 (9.1%) Black women, 132,889 (2.7%) Asian women and 3,123,489 (64.1%) women with an unknown race. Close to 99% (4,807,622) of the population did not have a recorded medical co-morbidity. Approximately 19% (913, 546) of the population had one, or more, mental health diagnoses. Close to 3% (132,509) of the population had a diagnosis of post-traumatic stress, 18% (701,162) carried a diagnosis of anxiety and 12% (477,477) were diagnosed with depression.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table&#160;1</label><caption><p>Clinical and demographic characteristics of the study cohort.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Active duty 2006&#8211;2013</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Active duty 2014&#8211;2022</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dependent 2006&#8211;2013</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dependent 2014&#8211;2022</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Frequency (%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">670,850 (13.76)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">613,300 (12.58)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,208,365 (45.29)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,383,694 (28.38)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,876,209 (100)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Mean (SD)</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Mean (SD)</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Mean (SD)</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Mean (SD)</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age (Years)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.57 (8.21)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.02 (7.97)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.29 (13.11)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.56 (12.14)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Frequency (%)</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Frequency (%)</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Frequency (%)</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Frequency (%)</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Frequency (%)</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rank</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Enlisted junior</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">381,299 (56.85)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">361,595 (59.15)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">415,131 (18.80)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">303,528 (21.94)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,461,553 (29.99)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Enlisted senior</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">195,677 (29.17)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">161,567 (26.43)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,357,369 (61.47)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">747,950 (54.06)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2462,563 (50.53)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Officer</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">93,767 (13.98)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">88,147 (14.42)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">435,574 (19.73)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">331,995 (24.00)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">949,483 (19.48)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Race</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;White</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">394,559 (58.81)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">364,378 (59.41)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">195,336 (8.85)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">111,268 (8.04)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,065,541 (21.85)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Asian</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">45,331 (6.76)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">38,533 (6.28)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">31,756 (1.44)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17,269 (1.25)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">132,889 (2.73)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Black</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">174,404 (26.00)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">158,402 (25.83)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">72,576 (3.29)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">37,231 (2.69)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">442,613 (9.08)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Unknown</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12,611 (1.88)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13,815 (2.25)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,890,127 (85.59)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,206,936 (87.23)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,123,489 (64.06)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Other</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">43,945 (6.55)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">38,172 (6.22)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18,570 (0.84)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10,990 (0.79)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">111,677 (2.29)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Census region</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Midwest</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">69,236 (10.65)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">46,941 (9.89)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">162,993 (7.66)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">86,166 (7.17)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">365,336 (8.20)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Northeast</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32,239 (4.96)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">22,767 (4.80)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">77,561 (3.65)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">52,077 (4.33)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">184,644 (4.14)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;South</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">343,820 (52.87)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">243,250 (51.25)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,138,260 (53.50)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">639,710 (53.19)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,365,040 (53.09)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;West</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">204,956 (31.52)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">161,663 (34.06)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">748,600 (35.19)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">424,636 (35.31)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,539,855 (34.57)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Charlson comorbidity index</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">665,974 (99.27)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">610,845 (99.60)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,166,420 (98.10)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,364,383 (98.60)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,807,622 (98.59)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#8805;1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4876 (0.73)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2455 (0.40)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">41,945 (1.90)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">19,311 (1.40)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">68,587 (1.41)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mental health diagnosis</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">53,620 (7.99)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">83,041 (13.54)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">412,164 (18.66)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">364,721 (26.36)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">913,546 (18.73)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">617,230 (92.01)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">530,259 (86.46)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,796,201 (81.34)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,018,973 (73.64)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,962,663 (81.27)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sustained prescription opioid use</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8464 (1.26)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2752 (0.45)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">77,664 (3.52)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">31,257 (2.26)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">120,137 (2.46)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">662,386 (98.74)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">610,548 (99.55)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,130,701 (96.48)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,352,437 (97.74)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,756,072 (97.54)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Substance use disorder</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">41,559 (6.19)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32,346 (5.27)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">221,574 (10.03)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">122,600 (8.86)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">418,079 (8.17)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">629,291 (93.81)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">580,954 (94.73)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,986,791 (89.97)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,261,094 (91.14)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,458,130 (91.43)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0095">Sustained prescription opioid use was identified in 120,137 individuals (2.5%). Following adjusted analysis, when compared to dependents in 2014&#8211;2022, servicewomen from 2006 to 2013 demonstrated an increased risk of sustained prescription opioid use (RR 1.49, 95% CI 1.46&#8211;1.53). In 2014&#8211;2022, servicewomen had a lower risk of sustained opioid use compared to dependents (RR 0.47, 95% CI 0.45&#8211;0.49). Dependents in 2006&#8211;2013 were also found to have higher risk of sustained opioid use (RR 1.58, 95% CI 1.56&#8211;1.60; <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table&#160;2</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table&#160;2</label><caption><p>Results of the adjusted multivariable logistic regression analysis evaluating the association between sustained prescription opioid use and active-duty servicewomen and civilian women dependents in 2006&#8211;2013 versus 2014&#8211;2022.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Variable</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Risk ratio (95% CI)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">P-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Time period</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="char" rowspan="5" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Active-duty servicewomen 2006&#8211;2013</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.49 (1.46&#8211;1.53)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Active-duty servicewomen 2014&#8211;2022</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.47 (0.45&#8211;0.49)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Dependent 2006&#8211;2013</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.58 (1.56&#8211;1.60)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Dependent 2014&#8211;2022</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">referent</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Age (per 10-year interval increase in Years)</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.66 (1.65&#8211;1.67)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Rank</bold></td><td align="char" rowspan="4" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Enlisted junior</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.28 (1.25&#8211;1.32)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Enlisted senior</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.76 (1.73&#8211;1.79)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Officer</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">referent</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Race</bold></td><td align="char" rowspan="5" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Asian</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.63 (0.61&#8211;0.65)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Black</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.78 (0.76&#8211;0.79)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Other</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.82 (0.80&#8211;0.85)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;White</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">referent</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Census region</bold></td><td align="char" rowspan="5" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Midwest</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.92 (0.90&#8211;0.94)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Northeast</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.73 (0.70&#8211;0.75)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;South</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.16 (1.14&#8211;1.17)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;West</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">referent</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Charlson comorbidity index (One or More conditions)</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.10 (1.10&#8211;1.11)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Mental health diagnosis</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.01 (5.02&#8211;5.13)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>In this analysis, time period is the predictor of interest. All other variables were considered as confounders and their results are presented for transparency.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0100">SUD was diagnosed in 418,079 (8.2%) of the study cohort. Servicewomen in the period 2006&#8211;2013 were at significantly greater risk of developing SUD (RR 1.07, 95% CI 1.06&#8211;1.08). During 2014&#8211;2022, servicewomen displayed a lower risk of SUD when compared to dependents (RR 0.80, 95% CI 0.79&#8211;0.81; <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table&#160;3</xref>). In contrast, dependents in 2006&#8211;2013 were at a higher risk of developing SUD (RR 1.24, 95% CI 1.24&#8211;1.25).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table&#160;3</label><caption><p>Adjusted multivariable logistic regression analysis of the association between substance use disorder and active-duty servicewomen and civilian women dependents in 2006&#8211;2013 versus 2014&#8211;2022.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Variable</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Risk ratio (95% CI)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">P-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Time period</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="char" rowspan="5" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Active-duty servicewomen 2006&#8211;2013</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.07 (1.06&#8211;1.08)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Active-duty servicewomen 2014&#8211;2022</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.80 (0.79&#8211;0.81)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Dependent 2006&#8211;2013</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.24 (1.24&#8211;1.25)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Dependent 2014&#8211;2022</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">referent</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Age (per 10-year interval increase in Years)</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.08 (1.07&#8211;1.08)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Rank</bold></td><td align="char" rowspan="4" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Enlisted junior</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.91 (1.89&#8211;1.93)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Enlisted senior</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.04 (2.02&#8211;2.06)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Officer</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">referent</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Race</bold></td><td align="char" rowspan="5" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Asian</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.89 (0.87&#8211;0.90)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Black</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.89 (0.88&#8211;0.90)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Other</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.93 (0.92&#8211;0.95)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;White</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">referent</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Census region</bold></td><td align="char" rowspan="5" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Midwest</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.08 (1.07&#8211;1.10)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Northeast</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.06 (1.05&#8211;1.08)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;South</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.15 (1.14&#8211;1.15)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;West</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">referent</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Charlson comorbidity index (One or More conditions)</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.08 (1.07&#8211;1.09)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Mental health diagnosis</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.19 (4.17&#8211;4.21)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>In this analysis, time period is the predictor of interest. All other variables were considered as confounders and their results are presented for transparency.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0105">Our study represents the first of its kind to longitudinally examine the development of sustained prescription opioid use and SUD among a large cohort of US women. We believe our findings highlight the deleterious impact of operational intensity and combat deployments on sustained prescription opioid use and SUD in both servicewomen and women civilian dependents. Starting insidiously in the early 2000s, the opioid crisis began to be recognized within the US health system over the time period of our study through a marked increase in the incidence of sustained prescription opioid use, substance use disorder, drug-related infections, transition to illegal opioids, and concomitant elevations in incarceration, opioid addiction treatment, and opioid-related deaths.<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref> At the same time, the wars in Iraq and Afghanistan were contributing to heightened deployment schedules and repeated exposures to the combat environment that exerted psychological and physical stress on both servicemembers and their civilian dependents.<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></p><p id="p0110">Previous research reported that both active-duty servicewomen and women civilian dependents associated with service in 2006&#8211;2013 were more likely to develop chronic pain conditions than comparands associated with later periods of service.<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> This was attributed to several important factors including the rigors of exposure to the combat environment, repeated deployments, emotional distress impacting both servicemembers and their dependents, and exposure to military sexual trauma. These same issues are also known to influence the proclivity of sustained prescription opioid use and SUD that were encountered in the present investigation. While both of these conditions are multifactorial, we believe that the various psychological and physical stressors associated with increased operational intensity and repeated deployments leave civilians and servicemembers alike susceptible to sustained opioid use and SUD.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref></p><p id="p0115">Agniel et&#160;al. previously characterized opioid exposure as a household risk.<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> In their cohort study, the hazard for opioid misuse among family members of a chronic opioid user were increased by more than a factor of 2.5. In that investigation, the index patient in households with opioid prescriptions and opioid prescription refills were both more likely to be female (51.4% and 52.6%, respectively).<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> Similarly, in a large cohort of Medicare beneficiaries undergoing total knee replacement, women were over-represented among intermittent and continuous opioid users, when compared to those who were opioid non-users at the time of surgery.<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> In this study, women represented over 76% of the population who were continuous opioid users. Prior research on combat-related injuries maintained there was no significant differences between males and females with respect to sustained prescription opioid use.<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> Initial treatment following the traumatic event could play a vital role in creating a predilection for sustained use. For example, research has shown that both too little and too much opioid use can increase the risk of long-term dependence and pain disorders, highlighting the need for pain management approaches that carefully balance pain relief against the potential for sustained opioid use.<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref></p><p id="p0120">Prominent drivers of chronic opioid use and misuse in women include sexual trauma, familial and social problems.<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref> The potential for such issues to be present is particularly elevated in the high-stress environment of heightened operational intensity and combat-related deployments. Moreover, people exposed to trauma may be more likely to use opioids long-term and transition to a substance use disorder, possibly as a way to manage both physical and psychological pain.<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> Rabenhorst et&#160;al. previously reported that rates of moderate to severe spousal abuse and alcohol related spousal abuse were elevated in Air Force personnel following deployment.<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref> Furthermore, an injured spouse exposed to opioids for combat-related trauma and who then progresses to chronic opioid use themselves would additionally increase the risk among civilian dependents, as was attested in the study of Agniel et&#160;al.<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> Finally, Davis et&#160;al. indicated that women exhibited greater functional opioid-related impairment as compared to men and progressed to a diagnosable disorder faster,<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref> a reality that may be reflected in the higher risk ratios of SUD and susustained opioid use that were observed among the civilian women dependents in our analysis.</p><p id="p0125">There are several factors that provide face validity for our results and support their translational capacity. The other factors associated with sustained opioid use and SUD in this study have also been recognized in other research settings, including age, socioeconomic status, medical comorbidities, and mental health conditions.<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref> The risk ratios of the time-periods associated with sustained opioid use and SUD all indicate clinically important alterations. The observed reductions in sustained prescription opioid use and SUD in the cohorts associated with military service in 2014&#8211;2022 are also aligned with previous literature suggesting meaningful reductions in sustained opioid dependence that resulted from the implementation of Federal regulations and pain management guidelines beginning in 2017.<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Furthermore, increased awareness and a shift away from opioid-based pain regimens to multimodal analgesia contributed to the reduced proclivity for sustained opioid use and SUD in the 2014&#8211;2022 window.<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref> While the end of the 2014&#8211;2022 window included the time period of the COVID-19 pandemic, the impact of the pandemic on sustained opioid use was not uniform and highly dependent on the clinical context. Currie et&#160;al. reported that the ordering of opioid medications was only impacted in the early phases of the pandemic and then rebounded to pre-pandemic levels.<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref> Crawford et&#160;al. documented increased rates of sustained opioid use in all phases of the pandemic, when compared to the time period immediately preceding the onset of COVID-19.<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref> We are unaware of studies that show a persistent signal of reduction in sustained prescription opioid use that is attributable to the impact of COVID-19 on healthcare delivery and prescribing practices. Due to the previously demonstrated representative nature of the population served by the MHS under age 65,<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> we believe that our findings could be generalizable to a broader demographic.</p><p id="p0130">As a result, the findings of this investigation are important to the US healthcare system, policy makers and the Department of Defense. Foremost, at a macroscopic level, our study is the first we are aware of to objectively demonstrate the deleterious impact of heightened deployment schedules, operational intensity, combat exposure and associated familial stressors on sustained prescription opioid use and SUD in uniformed servicemembers and civilian dependents who are women. This is of paramount importance as US women are now serving in direct combat roles in the military and the combat intensity and lethality of warfare in the future is only anticipated to increase.<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref> The translational nature of this population means that we believe these realities are also likely to be present to a certain extent in civilian women who are exposed to similar familial, occupational, or environmental stressors even in the absence of direct military affiliation. Such situations could include law enforcement, presence at mass casualty events, and front-line medical and behavioral health providers, especially those serving over the course of the COVID-19 pandemic.<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref> At a minimum, clinicians in the Veterans Administration system and civilian sector should be aware of the apparent heightened risk of sustained prescription opioid use and SUD for women veterans who served in Iraq and/or Afghanistan over the time period 2006&#8211;2013, as well as an elevated risk of SUD and sustained opioid use among women spouses and children of individuals with similar service history. We wish to emphasize, however, that our findings should not be interpreted to mean that people who experience combat or trauma should be denied opioids when clinically appropriate. Instead, our results simply emphasize the need for thoughtful pain management strategies capable of addressing physical and psychological health needs while also reducing the prospect of long-term opioid use.</p><p id="p0135">Limitations to this study include a reliance on claims-based data and coding, without clinical granularity. We are, therefore, unable to understand the exact circumstances or diagnostic criteria that were used when rendering a diagnosis of SUD. The nature of the data imparted by the MHS also means that we are largely restricted to administrative level patient information and there is prospect for residual confounding including a lack of information around prescription intensity. Although prescription opioid information is widely used in studies such as ours as a proxy for use, we recognize that the use of these medications do not always align with the receipt of prescriptions including prospects for misuse, abuse and illegal consumption. The data is also subject to secular trends in the acceptance of, and social support for, seeking help with behavioral health conditions and logistic realities around documentation of substance use disorder. In line with this, over the time period of our investigation, the Department of Defense improved access to care for SUD for servicemembers and dependents. The actual prevalence of behavioral health disorders and substance use disorder may be underrepresented within our population as a result. While our cohort did exhibit restricted clinical variation with respect to comorbid medical conditions, we believe this is reflective of the general population in the age range 26&#8211;34 and therefore is not a threat to our contentions regarding translational capacity. Nonetheless, the findings may not be entirely applicable to older populations or those with more extensive medical or behavioral health issues at baseline. Due to issues around restricted reporting on race, particularly among dependents, we used multiple imputation to facilitate our analyses. Furthermore, ethnicity was not available in our dataset, and thus we cannot comment on the impact of cultural differences and concomitant structural drivers on sustained opioid use and SUD. As historically, and even in the time period under investigation, men represented a very small minority of civilian dependents,<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> we used civilian dependent women in the time period 2014&#8211;2022 as the control group in this investigation. While the timeframe 2006&#8211;2013 is broadly accepted as a period of increased operational intensity, we acknowledge this is a proxy and we do not have specific information about the operational environment or deployment locations. Moreover, we are unable to characterize the indications for opioid prescriptions or account for misuse or illicit use.</p><p id="p0140">In conclusion, we found that sustained prescription opioid use was significantly increased among servicewomen and women dependents during a period of heightened operational intensity (2006&#8211;2013), and servicewoman and women civilian dependents from this period also carried an increased likelihood of developing SUD. We believe that our findings are translatable to the civilian sector, given that the covered population of the&#160;MHS has previously been shown to be analogous to the US demographic aged 18&#8211;64. In particular, clinicians in the Veterans Administration system and civilian sector should be aware of a heightened risk of sustained prescription opioid use for women veterans who served in Iraq and/or Afghanistan over the time period 2006&#8211;2013, as well as an elevated risk of SUD and sustained opioid use among women spouses and children of individuals with such service history.</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><title>Contributors</title><p id="p0145">AJS, KEH, MRB, MOH, MW, and TPK had full access to all the data in the study and take responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis.</p><p id="p0150">Study Concept and Design: AJS, TPK.</p><p id="p0155">Acquisition of Data: AJS, MW, TPK.</p><p id="p0160">Analysis and Interpretation of Data: AJS, MW, KEH, MRB, MOH, TPK.</p><p id="p0165">Drafting of the Manuscript: AJS, KEH, MRB, MW, MOH, TPK.</p><p id="p0170">Critical Revision of the Manuscript for Important Intellectual Content: AJS, TPK.</p><p id="p0175">Statistical Analysis: AJS, MW.</p><p id="p0180">Obtained Funding: AJS, TPK.</p><p id="p0185">Administrative, technical, or material support: AJS, KEH, MRB, MW, MOH.</p><p id="p0190">Study Supervision: AJS, TPK.</p><p id="p0195">Decision to submit the manuscript: AJS, KEH, MRB, MOH, MW, and TPK.</p></sec><sec id="sec7"><title>Data sharing statement</title><p id="p0200">The data that support the findings of this study are available from the Defense Health Agency, but restrictions may apply to the availability of these data, which were used under a data sharing agreement for the current study, and so are not publicly available. Data are however available from the authors upon reasonable request and with permission of the Defense Health Agency.</p></sec><sec id="sec8"><title>Disclaimer</title><p id="p0205">The contents of this publication are the sole responsibility of the authors and do not necessarily reflect the views, assertions, opinions, or policies of the Uniformed Services University of the Health Sciences (USUHS) or the Departments of the Army, Navy, or Air Force. Mention of trade names, commercial products, or organizations does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="coi0010"><title>Declaration of interests</title><p id="p0210">Andrew Schoenfeld declared receiving grants or contracts from NIH-NIAMS, OREF, royalties or licenses from Wolters Kluwer and Springer Nature, consulting fees from Vertex, and had leadership or fiduciary role as Editor in Chief of Spine, Board of Directors at NASS, and Editorial Board at JBJS.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Belmont</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Owens</surname><given-names>B.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schoenfeld</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Musculoskeletal injuries in Iraq and Afghanistan: epidemiology and outcomes following a decade of war</article-title><source>J&#160;Am Acad Orthop Surg</source><volume>24</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>341</fpage><lpage>348</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5435/JAAOS-D-15-00123</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27115793</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pemberton</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hourani</surname><given-names>L.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mattiko</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Babeu</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Substance use and mental health trends among U.S. military active duty personnel: key findings from the 2008 DoD health behavior survey</article-title><source>Mil Med</source><volume>175</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>390</fpage><lpage>399</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7205/MILMED-D-09-00132</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20572470</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schoenfeld</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cirillo</surname><given-names>M.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Development of chronic pain conditions among women in the military health system</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><volume>7</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2024</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e2420393</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.20393</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11227075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38967922</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalton</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manful</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jarman</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long-term prescription opioid use among US military service members injured in combat</article-title><source>J&#160;Trauma Acute Care Surg</source><volume>91</volume><issue>2S Suppl 2</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>S213</fpage><lpage>S220</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34324474</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/TA.0000000000003133</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schoenfeld</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaudhary</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scully</surname><given-names>R.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koehlmoos</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haider</surname><given-names>A.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sustained prescription opioid use among previously opioid-naive patients insured through TRICARE (2006-2014)</article-title><source>JAMA Surg</source><volume>152</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>1175</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamasurg.2017.2628</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28813584</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5831440</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beckman</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shipherd</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lehavot</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Military sexual assault in transgender veterans: results from a nationwide survey</article-title><source>J&#160;Trauma Stress</source><volume>31</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>190</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29603392</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/jts.22280</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6709681</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cichowski</surname><given-names>S.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>R.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Komesu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A&#160;10-yr analysis of chronic pelvic pain and chronic opioid therapy in the women veteran population</article-title><source>Mil Med</source><volume>183</volume><issue>11&#8211;12</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>e635</fpage><lpage>e640</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29788455</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/milmed/usy114</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref8"><part-title>Committee on the well-being of military families, board on children, youth, and families, division of behavioral and social Sciences and education, national academies of Sciences, engineering, and medicine</part-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kizer</surname><given-names>K.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Menestrel</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Strengthening the military family readiness system for a changing American society [internet]</source><year>2019</year><publisher-name>National Academies Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Washington, D.C.</publisher-loc><comment>Available from:</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.nap.edu/catalog/25380/" id="intref0010">https://www.nap.edu/catalog/25380/</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31600043</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaudhary</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhulani</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Jager</surname><given-names>E.C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Development and validation of a bedside risk assessment for sustained prescription opioid use after surgery</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><volume>2</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2019</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e196673</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2019.6673</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6624809</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31290987</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scully</surname><given-names>R.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schoenfeld</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Defining optimal length of opioid pain medication prescription after common surgical procedures</article-title><source>JAMA Surg</source><volume>153</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>37</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamasurg.2017.3132</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28973092</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5833616</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schoenfeld</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaji</surname><given-names>A.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haider</surname><given-names>A.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Practical guide to surgical data sets: military health system tricare encounter data</article-title><source>JAMA Surg</source><volume>153</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>679</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamasurg.2018.0480</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29617526</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oleisky</surname><given-names>E.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pennings</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hills</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparing different chronic preoperative opioid use definitions on outcomes after spine surgery</article-title><source>Spine J</source><volume>19</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>984</fpage><lpage>994</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30611889</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.spinee.2018.12.014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nurutdinova</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chrusciel</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeringue</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mental health disorders and the risk of AIDS-defining illness and death in HIV-infected veterans</article-title><source>AIDS</source><volume>26</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>229</fpage><lpage>234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/QAD.0b013e32834e1404</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22089375</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuehn</surname><given-names>B.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Massive costs of the US opioid epidemic in lives and dollars</article-title><source>JAMA</source><volume>325</volume><issue>20</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>2040</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2021.7464</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34032821</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Agniel</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brat</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marwaha</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association of postsurgical opioid refills for patients with risk of opioid misuse and chronic opioid use among family members</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><volume>5</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2022</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e2221316</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.21316</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9287751</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35838671</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y.C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association of preoperative opioid use with mortality and short-term safety outcomes after total knee replacement</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><volume>2</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2019</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e198061</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2019.8061</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6669774</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31365106</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karamchandani</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klick</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Linskey Dougherty</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonavia</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>Z.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pain management in trauma patients affected by the opioid epidemic: a narrative review</article-title><source>J&#160;Trauma Acute Care Surg</source><volume>87</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>430</fpage><lpage>439</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30939572</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/TA.0000000000002292</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eddie</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prindle</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sex differences in factors predicting post-treatment opioid use</article-title><source>Addiction</source><volume>116</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>2116</fpage><lpage>2126</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33405314</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/add.15396</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8254742</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Santo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gisev</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Degenhardt</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exposure to childhood trauma increases risk of opioid use disorder among people prescribed opioids for chronic non-cancer pain</article-title><source>Drug Alcohol Depend</source><volume>230</volume><year>2022</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">109199</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2021.109199</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34875576</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rabenhorst</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomsen</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Spouse abuse among United States Air Force personnel who deployed in support of operation Iraqi freedom/operation enduring freedom</article-title><source>J&#160;Fam Psychol</source><volume>27</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>754</fpage><lpage>761</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24015706</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1037/a0034283</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schoenfeld</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Munigala</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Reductions in sustained prescription opioid use within the US between 2017 and 2021</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2024</year><fpage>1432</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-52032-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38228721</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10791599</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schoenfeld</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Banaag</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long-term prescription opioid use following surgery in the US (2017-2022): a population-based study</article-title><source>Lancet Reg Health Am</source><volume>40</volume><year>2024</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100948</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.lana.2024.100948</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11703578</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39763498</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bohnert</surname><given-names>A.S.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kerns</surname><given-names>R.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clay</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ganoczy</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ilgen</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of the opioid safety initiative on opioid-related prescribing in veterans</article-title><source>Pain</source><volume>158</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>833</fpage><lpage>839</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/j.pain.0000000000000837</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28240996</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Campello</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ziemke</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hiebert</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Implementation of a multidisciplinary program for active duty personnel seeking care for low back pain in a U.S. Navy medical center: a feasibility study</article-title><source>Mil Med</source><volume>177</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>1075</fpage><lpage>1080</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7205/MILMED-D-12-00118</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23025138</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ladha</surname><given-names>K.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patorno</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huybrechts</surname><given-names>K.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rathmell</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bateman</surname><given-names>B.T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Variations in the use of perioperative multimodal analgesic therapy</article-title><source>Anesthesiology</source><volume>124</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>837</fpage><lpage>845</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/ALN.0000000000001034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26835644</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4792695</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Currie</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schnell</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwandt</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prescribing of opioid analgesics and buprenorphine for opioid use disorder during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><volume>4</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2021</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e216147</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.6147</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8050741</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33856474</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Striano</surname><given-names>B.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koehlmoos</surname><given-names>T.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schoenfeld</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Validation of the stopping opioids after surgery (SOS) score for the sustained use of prescription opioids following orthopaedic surgery</article-title><source>J&#160;Bone Joint Surg Am</source><volume>105</volume><issue>18</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>1403</fpage><lpage>1409</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37410854</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2106/JBJS.23.00061</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lawry</surname><given-names>L.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mani</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamm</surname><given-names>T.E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Qualitative assessment of combat-related injury patterns and injury prevention in Ukraine since the Russian invasion</article-title><source>BMJ Mil Health</source><year>2025</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/military-2024-002863</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39904535</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mani</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pomer</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pritchett</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Filling the gaps in the COVID-19 pandemic response: medical personnel in the US military health system</article-title><source>BMC Health Serv Res</source><volume>24</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2024</year><fpage>1140</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39334343</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12913-024-11616-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11430540</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ack id="ack0010"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="p0215">Funding: This study was funded through a grant from the <funding-source id="gs2"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100005712</institution-id><institution>U.S. Department of Defense, Defense Health Agency</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> (award # HU00012320021). The funder had no role in the development, conduct or determinations of the study, preparation of the manuscript or decision to publish.</p></ack></back></article></pmc-articleset>