<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2786</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">medicine</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MD</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0025-7974</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1536-5964</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer Health</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11309654</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11309654.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11309654</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11309654</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36827043</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000032998</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" article-version-type="Version of Record">3</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>7100</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Research Article</subject><subject>Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Efficacy of laparoscopic inguinal hernia in day surgery mode and inpatient surgery mode in China: A meta-analysis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true" content-type="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2852-3965">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2852-3965</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yang</given-names></name><degrees>MM</degrees><email>zqloove1@163.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="c1" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names initials="M">Miao</given-names></name><degrees>BS</degrees><email>382289552@qq.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zhi</given-names></name><degrees>MM</degrees><email>270524694@qq.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names initials="JY">Jian Yu</given-names></name><degrees>MM</degrees><email>182427684@qq.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names initials="XJ">Xiao Jiang</given-names></name><degrees>MM</degrees><email>446982733@qq.com</email><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="M">Mao</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD</degrees><email>270524694@qq.com</email><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname><given-names initials="AP">Ai Ping</given-names></name><degrees>MM</degrees><email>369563889@qq.com</email><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names initials="L">Long</given-names></name><degrees>MM</degrees><email>394578415@qq.com</email><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="JS">Jian Shui</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label> Department of Hepatobiliary Surgery, Affiliated Hospital of North Sichuan Medical College, Nanchong, China</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label> Institute of Hepatobiliary, Pancreatic and Intestinal Disease, North Sichuan Medical College, Nanchong, China</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label> Affiliated Hospital of North Sichuan Medical College, Nanchong, China</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label> Department of Gastrointestinal Surgery, Nanchong Central Hospital, Nanchong, China.</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1">* Correspondence: Jian Shui Li, Department of Hepatobiliary Surgery, Affiliated Hospital of North Sichuan Medical College, No. 1 Maoyuan South Road, Nanchong City, Sichuan Province 637000, China (e-mail: <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ljs2005doctor@126.com">ljs2005doctor@126.com</email>).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>22</day><month>2</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>2</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>102</volume><issue>8</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">435162</issue-id><elocation-id>e32998</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>07</day><month>10</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>25</day><month>1</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>1</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>22</day><month>02</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>08</day><month>08</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-08-28 17:25:27.790"><day>28</day><month>08</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2023 the Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-Non Commercial License 4.0 (CCBY-NC)</ext-link>, where it is permissible to download, share, remix, transform, and buildup the work provided it is properly cited. The work cannot be used commercially without permission from the journal.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="medi-102-e32998.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="medi-102-e32998.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background:</title><p>In China, laparoscopic inguinal hernia repair (LIHR) under the day surgery mode (DSM) has developed rapidly as an important surgical method for inguinal hernia repair, and it has unique advantages in many aspects. Compared with inpatient surgery mode (ISM), there are some differences in intraoperative and postoperative related indicators, hospitalization costs, and patient satisfaction. Many studies have shown that LIHR in DSM can significantly shorten hospital stay, effectively reduce hospitalization costs, and improve patient satisfaction. Accordingly, this study aimed to compare the differences in intraoperative and postoperative related indicators, hospitalization costs, and patient satisfaction of LIHR between DSM and ISM in China.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods:</title><p>The PubMed/Medline, EMBASE, Cochrane Library, China National Knowledge Infrastructure, and Wan Fang databases were searched for randomized controlled trials, cohort studies from the establishment of the database to July 1, 2022. Odds ratio (OR), mean difference, standardized mean difference (SMD), and 95% confidence interval were selected as the effect scale indices for the evaluation of the difference in hospitalization costs, hospital stay, operation time, recovery time, complications, and patient satisfaction. All of these were compared using RevMan 5.3 Software (The Cochrane Collaboration, Copenhagen, Denmark).</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>Nine studies involving 1176 patients, 590 in the DSM group and 586 in the ISM group, were included. The hospital stay (d) (SMD&#8197;=&#8197;&#8722;7.27, 95% confidence interval, CI: &#8722;8.68 to &#8722;5.87, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;<italic toggle="yes">&lt;</italic>&#8197;.001), hospitalization costs (SMD&#8197;=&#8197;&#8722;7.89, 95% CI: &#8722;10.25 to &#8722;5.53, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;<italic toggle="yes">&lt;</italic>&#8197;.001) in DSM group were significantly lower than the ISM group. Additionally, the patient dissatisfaction (OR&#8197;=&#8197;0.05, 95% CI: 0.01&#8211;0.17, <italic toggle="yes">P&#8197;&lt;&#8197;</italic>.001) in DSM group was significantly lower than the ISM group. Nevertheless, no significant differences were found in the operation time (minute) (mean difference&#8197;=&#8197;&#8722;0.32, 95% CI: &#8722;1.78 to 1.14, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;=&#8197;.67), recovery time (h) (SMD&#8197;=&#8197;&#8722;3.27, 95% CI: &#8722;6.95 to 0.41, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;<italic toggle="yes">=</italic>&#8197;.08), and postoperative complications (OR&#8197;=&#8197;0.80, 95% CI: 0.47&#8211;1.36, <italic toggle="yes">P&#8197;=&#8197;</italic>.41) between the 2 groups.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion:</title><p>In China, compared with ISM, LIHR under DSM can significantly shorten hospital stay, greatly reduce hospitalization costs, and significantly improve patient satisfaction. There were no significant differences in operation time, recovery time and postoperative complications.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>China</kwd><kwd>day surgery mode</kwd><kwd>efficacy</kwd><kwd>inpatient surgery mode</kwd><kwd>laparoscopic inguinal hernia repair</kwd><kwd>meta-analysis</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name><meta-value>TRUE</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>1. Introduction</title><p>Inguinal hernia is a common disease worldwide, lifetime occurrence of groin hernia-viscera or adipose tissue protrusions through the inguinal or femoral canal-is 27% to 43% in men and 3% to 6% in women,<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</sup> the only cure is surgery.<sup>[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</sup> Worldwide, more than 20 million patients undergo groin hernia repair annually.<sup>[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</sup> In China, approximately 2 million hernia patients require surgery each year.<sup>[<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]</sup> The Lancet reported in 2017 and 2018 an evaluation of the Medical Accessibility and Treatment Quality Index for inguinal hernia in adults in China (scores of 99 and 100, respectively),<sup>[<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</sup> surpassing many developed countries.</p><p>The concept of day surgery (Ambulatory Surgery/Day Surgery) was first proposed by Dr Nicoll in England. With the establishment of The International Association of Ambulatory Surgery (IAAS), ambulatory surgery has developed into a more mature form of surgical management model. The International Association for Ambulatory Surgery (IAAS) recommends that ambulatory surgery be defined as a patient who completes the surgery or procedure within 1 working day and is discharged from the hospital, excluding surgery or procedures performed in clinics or outpatient clinics. The definition of day surgery in China is basically the same, but a supplementary explanation is made on this basis: for patients with delayed hospitalization for day surgery, the maximum length of hospitalization shall not exceed 48 hours.<sup>[<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</sup> Day surgery has the advantages of shortening the average length of hospital stay, reducing hospitalization costs, and accelerating patient recovery, and can effectively improve the utilization of medical resources.<sup>[<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</sup>In the United States, there were more than 4000 independent day surgery centers in 2004, and now covering almost all surgical departments.<sup>[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]</sup> In China, the development of day surgery is significantly later than that in Western countries. After more than 10 years of development, it has shown its advantages in shortening the average hospital stay, reducing medical expenses, accelerating patient recovery, and improving the utilization rate of medical resources.</p><p>Since the first report of day surgery for inguinal hernias in 1955,<sup>[<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]</sup> the open approach inguinal hernia repair under day surgery mode (DSM) has proven to be safe, feasible and cost-effective, and many countries have made open approach inguinal hernia repair routine;<sup>[<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]</sup> In China, DSM is becoming more and more popular. According to statistics, the number of day surgery for inguinal hernia performed every year has taken the second place in all day surgery diseases.<sup>[<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</sup></p><p>Studies have shown that simple inguinal hernias can be performed in a DSM, whether open surgery or laparoscopic surgery.<sup>[<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</sup> The advantages of laparoscopic inguinal hernia repair (LIHR) over open hernia repair seem to be more suitable for the DSM. Since 1993, transabdominal preperitoneal hernia repair (TAPP) and total extraperitoneal hernia repair (TEP) have been regarded as the gold standard procedures for LIHR, and the number has increased rapidly year by year. In the past 10 years, LIHR surgery has developed rapidly in China, and the amount of surgery has accounted for 10% to 40% of tension-free inguinal hernia repair,<sup>[<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]</sup>it has the advantages of less postoperative pain, faster postoperative recovery, and shorter hospital stay.<sup>[<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]</sup></p><p>Although LIHR has the above advantages, due to China&#8217;s vast territory and large regional differences, the development level of day surgery technology and management is unbalanced, and patient concepts, medical policies, and process management also affect the development of day surgery. In China, the advantages of LIHR under the DSM still lack strong support from large-scale, multi center research conclusions. Therefore, this study searched and included relevant studies to systematically evaluate the intraoperative and postoperative efficacy of LIHR under DSM and inpatient surgery mode (ISM) in China, in order to seek relatively objective and accurate conclusions. We hope to provide a favorable evidence-based medical basis for clinical treatment.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>2. Materials and methods</title><sec><title>2.1. Search strategy</title><p>The PubMed/Medline, EMBASE, Cochrane Library, China National Knowledge Infrastructure, and Wanfang databases were searched for Chinese studies published from their inception to July 1, 2022, comparing DSM versus ISM for LIHR. The search was performed for studies that included in their Title or Abstract the following search terms: day surgery, inpatient surgery, inguinal hernia, total extraperitoneal hernia repair, TEP, transabdominal preperitoneal, TAPP, only in English and Chinese.</p><p>This study was approved by the Ethics Committee of the Affiliated Hospital of the North Sichuan Medical College.</p></sec><sec><title>2.2. Inclusion and exclusion criteria</title><p>The following inclusion criteria were applied: First, the original study must have compared LIHR patients in China who underwent DSM or ISM. Second, the original study types included randomized controlled trials, and cohort studies. Third, at least one of the following indicators should be considered: operation time, recovery time, postoperative complications, hospital stay, hospitalization costs, and patient satisfaction. The exclusion criteria were as follows: retrospective studies, review articles, case reports, abstracts, editorials, letters to the editor, studies with insufficient data on outcome measures, and incomplete documents or documents with incomplete data.</p></sec><sec><title>2.3. Data extraction</title><p>Original data, including the first author, year of publication, type of procedure, sample size, age, sex, and outcome, were independently extracted from the articles by 2 authors and keyed them in a standardized form. Conflicts in data abstraction were resolved by referring to the original article.</p></sec><sec><title>2.4. Quality assessment</title><p>The quality of the literature was independently assessed by the authors, in accordance with the Cochrane Collaboration Handbook. The assessment tools included the following criteria: random sequence generation, allocation concealment, blinding of participants and personnel, blinding of the assessment results, incomplete data of the results, selective reporting, and other sources of bias. A controversial article was selected after discussion with a third researcher.</p></sec><sec><title>2.5. Statistical analysis</title><p>Review Manager version 5.3 (The Cochrane Collaboration, Copenhagen, Denmark) was used to perform a meta-analysis. Odds ratio (OR), mean difference, standardized mean difference (SMD), and 95% confidence interval were selected as the effect scale indicators. The heterogeneity of each study was evaluated using the Cochrane <italic toggle="yes">Q</italic> test and <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> test; if case <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup>&#8197;&#8805;&#8197;50%, heterogeneity appeared between studies. A random-effects model was used in cases of significant heterogeneity. Otherwise, a fixed-effects model was used. This study conducted a sensitivity analysis by excluding studies 1 by 1, and the stability of the results of <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> and the changes in the combined effect size after excluding studies were analyzed.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>3. Results</title><sec><title>3.1. Basic information of the included studies</title><p>A total of 802 original studies were obtained by searching the databases. A total of 390 duplicate, irrelevant, and unqualified studies were excluded after reading the texts and abstracts, and the remaining 37 studies satisfied the research topic. Furthermore, 28 studies were excluded because of improper grouping or different outcomes. A detailed flowchart of the selection process is presented in Figure <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Screening process of the paper.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="medi-102-e32998-g001.jpg"/></fig><p>Finally, 9 studies<sup>[<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]</sup> were identified, including 5,<sup>[<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]</sup> and 4 cohort studies.<sup>[<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]</sup> A total of 1176 patients were included, including 590 in DSM group and 586 in ISM group. The baseline data are shown in Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Basic information of included studies.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Author, year</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study design</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample size (DSM/ISM)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (year) (DSM/ISM)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender (m) (DSM/ISM)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outcome</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wang, et al 2022</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort study</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31/31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.8&#8197;&#177;&#8197;11.6/42.4&#8197;&#177;&#8197;10.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24/23</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#9312;&#9313;&#9314;&#9315;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Li, et al 2021</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RCT</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60/60</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.58&#8197;&#177;&#8197;1.78/40.28&#8197;&#177;&#8197;1.23</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53/52</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#9312;&#9313;&#9314;&#9315;&#9316;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Li, et al 2020</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RCT</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40/40</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.27&#8197;&#177;&#8197;8.35/49.09&#8197;&#177;&#8197;7.65</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34/32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#9312;&#9313;&#9314;&#9315;&#9316;&#9317;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rena, et al 2020</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort study</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30/30</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#9312;&#9314;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gao, et al 2019</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort study</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86/82</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#9312;&#9313;&#9315;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wang, et al 2018</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort study</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38/38</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.87&#8197;&#177;&#8197;9.75/50.26&#8197;&#177;&#8197;10.18</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31/33</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#9312;&#9313;&#9314;&#9315;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wang, et al 2017</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RCT</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77/77</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.9&#8197;&#177;&#8197;13.7/56.1&#8197;&#177;&#8197;9.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#9312;&#9313;&#9314;&#9317;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gu, et al 2017</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RCT</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">200/200</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.2&#8197;&#177;&#8197;15.2/58.3&#8197;&#177;&#8197;15.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">145/155</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#9312;&#9313;&#9315;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chen, et al 2015</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RCT</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28/28</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.55&#8197;&#177;&#8197;15.95/41.39&#8197;&#177;&#8197;16.44</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#9312;&#9313;&#9314;&#9317;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>Outcome: &#9312; = hospital stay, &#9313; = postoperative complications, &#9314; = hospitalization costs, &#9315; = operation time, &#9316; = recovery time, &#9317; = patient satisfaction.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>DSM = day surgery mode, ISM = inpatient surgery mode, RCT = randomized controlled trial.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>3.2. Length of hospital stay</title><p>Nine studies<sup>[<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]</sup> provided data regarding the length of hospital stay (d) with a total of 1176 cases, covering 590 cases in the DSM group and 586 in the ISM group. Heterogeneity analysis showed obvious heterogeneity among the results of each study (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;&lt;&#8197;.001, <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup>&#8197;=&#8197;100%), and the random-effects model was adopted. The length of hospital stay of the DSM group was shorten to that of the ISM group (SMD&#8197;=&#8197;&#8722;7.27, 95% confidence interval, CI: &#8722;8.68 to 5.87, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;&lt;&#8197;.001) (Fig. <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Sensitivity analysis was performed after removing the articles individually, and neither heterogeneity nor forest plot changed significantly, indicating that the meta-analysis results were stable and reliable.</p><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Forest plot of comparison on hospital stay: DSM vs ISM. DSM&#8197;=&#8197;day surgery mode, ISM&#8197;=&#8197;inpatient surgery mode.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="medi-102-e32998-g002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>3.3. Hospitalization costs</title><p>Seven studies<sup>[<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]</sup> provided data regarding the hospitalization costs (CNY) with a total of 608 cases, covering 304 cases in the DSM group and 304 in the ISM group. Heterogeneity analysis showed heterogeneity among the results of each study (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;&lt;&#8197;.001, <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup>&#8197;=&#8197;99%), and the random-effects model was adopted. The hospitalization costs of the DSM group were significantly lower than that of the ISM group (SMD&#8197;=&#8197;&#8722;7.89, 95% CI: &#8722;10.25 to 5.53, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;&lt;&#8197;.001) (Fig. <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Sensitivity analysis indicating that the meta-analysis results were stable and reliable.</p><fig position="float" id="F3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Forest plot of comparison on hospitalization costs: DSM vs ISM. DSM&#8197;=&#8197;day surgery mode, ISM&#8197;=&#8197;inpatient surgery mode.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="medi-102-e32998-g003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>3.4. Operation time</title><p>Six studies<sup>[<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]</sup> provided data regarding the operation time (minute) with a total of 906 cases, covering 455 cases in the DSM group and 451 in the ISM group. Heterogeneity analysis showed no obvious heterogeneity among the results of each study (<italic toggle="yes">P&#8197;=&#8197;</italic>.91, <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup>&#8197;=&#8197;0%), and the fixed-effects model was adopted. The operation time of the DSM group was similar to that of the ISM group (mean difference&#8197;=&#8197;&#8722;0.32, 95% CI: &#8722;1.78 to 1.14, <italic toggle="yes">P&#8197;=&#8197;</italic>.67) (Fig. <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Sensitivity analysis indicating that the meta-analysis results were stable and reliable.</p><fig position="float" id="F4" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Forest plot of comparison on operation time: DSM vs ISM. DSM&#8197;=&#8197;day surgery mode, ISM&#8197;=&#8197;inpatient surgery mode.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="medi-102-e32998-g004.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>3.5. Postoperative complications</title><p>Eight studies<sup>[<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]</sup> provided data regarding the postoperative complications with a total of 1116 cases, covering 560 cases in the DSM group and 556 in the ISM group. Heterogeneity analysis showed no obvious heterogeneity among the results of each study (<italic toggle="yes">P&#8197;=&#8197;</italic>.92, <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup>&#8197;=&#8197;0%), and the fixed-effects model was adopted. The complications of the DSM group were similar to that of the ISM group (OR&#8197;=&#8197;0.80, 95% CI: 0.47&#8211;1.36, <italic toggle="yes">P&#8197;=&#8197;</italic>.41) (Fig. <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Sensitivity analysis indicating that the meta-analysis results were stable and reliable.</p><fig position="float" id="F5" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Forest plot of comparison on complications: DSM vs ISM. DSM&#8197;=&#8197;day surgery mode, ISM&#8197;=&#8197;inpatient surgery mode.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="medi-102-e32998-g005.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>3.6. Recovery time</title><p>Three studies<sup>[<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]</sup> provided data regarding the recovery time (hours) with a total of 276 cases, covering 138 cases in the DSM group and 138 in the ISM group. Heterogeneity analysis showed obvious heterogeneity among the results of each study (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;&lt;&#8197;.001, <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup>&#8197;=&#8197;94%), and the random-effects model was adopted. The recovery time of the DSM group were similar to that of the ISM group (SMD&#8197;=&#8197;&#8722;3.27, 95% CI: &#8722;6.95 to 0.41, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;=&#8197;.08) (Fig. <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). Sensitivity analysis indicating that the meta-analysis results were stable and reliable.</p><fig position="float" id="F6" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Forest plot of comparison on recovery time: DSM vs ISM. DSM&#8197;=&#8197;day surgery mode, ISM&#8197;=&#8197;inpatient surgery mode.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="medi-102-e32998-g006.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="subjects"><title>3.7. Patient satisfaction</title><p>Three studies<sup>[<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]</sup> provided data regarding the patient satisfaction with a total of 290 cases, covering 145 cases in the DSM group and 145 in the ISM group. Heterogeneity analysis showed no obvious heterogeneity among the results of each study (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;=&#8197;.42, <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup>&#8197;=&#8197;0%), and the fixed-effects model was adopted. The patient dissatisfaction of the DSM group was lower than that of the ISM group (1.38% vs 26.89%) (OR&#8197;=&#8197;0.05, 95% CI: 0.01&#8211;0.17, <italic toggle="yes">P&#8197;&lt;&#8197;</italic>.001) (Fig. <xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). Sensitivity analysis indicating that the meta-analysis results were stable and reliable.</p><fig position="float" id="F7" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Forest plot of comparison on patient dissatisfaction: DSM vs ISM. DSM&#8197;=&#8197;day surgery mode, ISM&#8197;=&#8197;inpatient surgery mode.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="medi-102-e32998-g007.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>3.8. Risk of bias in included studies</title><p>No obvious publication bias can be observed from the bias analysis chart. All the included literatures were analyzed. The risk of bias of the included studies is shown in Figure <xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="F8" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>Consensus risk of-bias assessment of the included studies. Green&#8197;=&#8197;low risk, yellow&#8197;=&#8197;unclear; red&#8197;=&#8197;high risk.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="medi-102-e32998-g008.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>4. Discussion</title><p>This study compared the differences in LIHR (TAPP, TEP) surgery-related indicators, hospital stay, treatment costs, and patient satisfaction between DSM and ISM in China. A total of 1176 patients were included in the study, of which 590 were in DSM group and 586 were ISM group. The results showed that there were significant differences between the 2 groups in hospital stay, hospitalization costs, and patient satisfaction. However, no significant difference was found in operation time, recovery time, and postoperative complications.</p><p>Inguinal hernia repair in DSM is increasingly becoming an important part of day surgery because of its standardized surgical methods, rapid recovery, and intuitive effects, and its application scope and extent are expanding. In the past, the open approach under local anesthesia was mostly used for day surgery inguinal hernia repair. However, for some special patients, such as obesity, bilateral inguinal hernia, and patients with open postoperative recurrence, LIHR under general anesthesia has the greater advantage.<sup>[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]</sup> It has the characteristics of &#8220;posterior approach,&#8221; &#8220;observability&#8221; and &#8220;operation under direct vision&#8221; which are not available in open surgery. Studies have shown that LIHR in DSM can further reduce postoperative pain and chronic postoperative pain, shorten the recovery time, and reduce the omission of occult hernias.<sup>[<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]</sup></p><p>As mentioned above, due to China&#8217;s vast territory and large regional differences, the development level of day surgery technology and management is unbalanced, and patient concepts, medical policies, and process management also affect the development of day surgery. Therefore, in China, the advantages of LIHR in DSM still lack strong support from large-scale, multi center research conclusions. In addition, most previous studies in China have shortcomings such as small sample size, inconsistent conclusions, and low reliability, and are not convincing. In view of the above reasons, in order to improve the credibility of the conclusions and obtain more objective conclusions, we formulated and improved the inclusion criteria, focusing on the inclusion of randomized controlled studies and cohort studies were included, and the number of included studies was greater, the data were updated, the quality was higher, and the grouping was more scientific. This study strictly screened the literature according to the inclusion and exclusion indicators, and finally included 9 literatures, and processed the relevant data through the Meta analysis software. The results showed that the LIHR operation in the DSM has obvious advantages in China. Compared with the ISM, the LIHR in the DSM can significantly shorten the hospital stay, greatly reduce the hospitalization costs, and improve patient satisfaction, without increasing the operation time, recovery time, and postoperative complications.</p><p>The main goal of the DSM is to shorten the treatment cycle of patients. By optimizing the perioperative process, the treatment cycle can be greatly shortened. Most studies in China and abroad show that day surgery performed in multiple disciplines including gynecology, ophthalmology, and hepatobiliary surgery can significantly shorten the length of hospital stay. Although some studies in China have shown that LIHR under the DSM can save operation time, there is still a lack of systematic review of related studies. Therefore, this study collects relevant high-quality literatures in China and conducts a systematic review to make up for the lack of research in this field. The results of this study showed that: in China, LIHR under the DSM can significantly shorten the hospital stay of patients, which achieved the original intention of establishing the DSM.</p><p>The most immediate benefit of shortening the length of hospital stay is the reduction in hospital costs. The literature included in this study all suggest that the treatment cost of LIHR in the DSM is lower than that in the ISM, and the results of the meta-analysis support this conclusion. Although compared with foreign countries, there are large regional differences in China, and there are also corresponding differences in surgical techniques, management levels, patient concepts, medical policies, and process management; however, the advantages of LIHR under the DSM are still effective, it can effectively reduce the cost of treatment.</p><p>On the basis of significantly shortening the length of hospital stay and reducing the cost of treatment, LIHR in the DSM does not sacrifice other indicators. From the results of the meta-analysis, there were no significant differences in the operation time, recovery time, and postoperative complications between the DSM and the ISM. At the same time, we also counted the readmission rate of the included studies, among which 6 studies<sup>[<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]</sup> had no readmission cases during the follow-up period, and 3 studies<sup>[<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]</sup> did not mention the readmission rate, indicating that there was no significant difference in readmission rate between DSM and ISM. In contrast to the above results, the analysis of patient satisfaction showed that LIHR in the DSM can significantly improve patient satisfaction. In the development of modern medicine, patient satisfaction is one of the most important goals other than the pursuit of the best curative effect and the least complications, and the LIHR in the DSM has successfully achieved this goal and played a role in its obvious advantages.</p><p>However, our study also has certain limitations: Firstly, the number of included articles is small; Secondly, the types and severity of inguinal hernias are inconsistent, and between different studies There are some differences in the surgical skills of surgeons and the management of patients, which may lead to implementation bias and some degree of heterogeneity; Thirdly, because the basic data of the included studies could not fully meet the needs, we failed to conduct a subgroup analysis of patients including different ages, different hernia types and so on, which needs to be further improved in subsequent studies.</p></sec><sec><title>5. Conclusion</title><p>Meta-analysis results show that LIHR in the DSM, as an emerging surgical mode, it has achieved quite good curative effect in China. It has indeed shortened the hospital stay, reduced the treatment cost, and improved the satisfaction of the patients, and it is not affected in terms of operation time, recovery time, and postoperative complications. In conclusion, this surgical model is safe and feasible, and patients can benefit significantly, and it is worthy of further popularization in China. At the same time, it also reminds us: should we accelerate the promotion of this surgical model in more developing countries?. This is an issue that deserves to be put on the agenda early. Of course, well-designed, large-scale and multi center studies are needed to further confirm the results of this study.</p></sec><sec><title>Author contributions</title><p><bold>Conceptualization:</bold> Yang Zhong, Jian Shui Li.</p><p><bold>Data curation:</bold> Yang Zhong, Miao He, Zhi Liu, Jian Yu Chen.</p><p><bold>Formal analysis:</bold> Yang Zhong, Miao He, Zhi Liu, Mao Liu, Ai Ping Wen.</p><p><bold>Funding acquisition:</bold> Yang Zhong.</p><p><bold>Investigation:</bold> Yang Zhong, Miao He.</p><p><bold>Methodology:</bold> Yang Zhong, Miao He, Zhi Liu.</p><p><bold>Project administration:</bold> Yang Zhong, Miao He, Jian Yu Chen.</p><p><bold>Resources:</bold> Yang Zhong, Jian Yu Chen, Xiao Jiang Lv, Mao Liu.</p><p><bold>Software:</bold> Yang Zhong, Jian Yu Chen, Xiao Jiang Lv, Mao Liu, Ai Ping Wen, Long Qin.</p><p><bold>Supervision:</bold> Yang Zhong, Jian Yu Chen, Mao Liu, Long Qin, Jian Shui Li.</p><p><bold>Validation:</bold> Yang Zhong, Xiao Jiang Lv, Ai Ping Wen, Long Qin, Jian Shui Li.</p><p><bold>Visualization:</bold> Yang Zhong, Xiao Jiang Lv, Long Qin, Jian Shui Li.</p><p><bold>Writing &#8211; original draft:</bold> Yang Zhong, Miao He, Zhi Liu.</p><p><bold>Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing:</bold> Yang Zhong, Jian Shui Li.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="abbr"><p>
<def-list><title>Abbreviations:</title><def-item><term>CI</term><def><p>confidence interval</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DSM</term><def><p>day surgery mode</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ISM</term><def><p>inpatient surgery mode</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LIHR</term><def><p>laparoscopic inguinal hernia repair</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OR</term><def><p>odds ratio</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SMD</term><def><p>standardized mean difference</p></def></def-item></def-list>
</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p>The datasets generated during and/or analyzed during the current study are publicly available.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p>This study is funding by Bureau of science &amp; Technology Nanchong City(20SXQT0272) and Research Project of Affiliated Hospital of North Sichuan Medical College(2022ZD001).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>How to cite this article: Zhong Y, He M, Liu Z, Chen JY, Lv XJ, Liu M, Wen AP, Qin L, Li JS. Efficacy of laparoscopic inguinal hernia in day surgery mode and inpatient surgery mode in China: A meta-analysis. Medicine 2023;102:8(e32998).</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>[1]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kingsnorth</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Hernias: inguinal and incisional.</article-title><source>Lancet</source>. <year>1561</year>;<volume>362</volume>:<lpage>1571</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(03)14746-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14615114</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>[2]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fitzgibbons</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramanan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Long-term results of a randomized controlled trial of a nonoperative strategy (watchful waiting) for men with minimally symptomatic inguinal hernias.</article-title><source>Ann Surg</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>258</volume>:<fpage>508</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>15</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24022443</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/SLA.0b013e3182a19725</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>[3]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Hernia Surge Group</collab>. <article-title>International guidelines for groin hernia management.</article-title><source>Hernia</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>165</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10029-017-1668-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5809582</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29330835</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>[4]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>JX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Future development of hernia and abdominal wall surgery in China.</article-title><source>Shanghai Med J</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>211</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>[5]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>GBD 2016 Healthcare Access and Quality Collaborators</collab>. <article-title>Measuring performance on the healthcare access and quality index for 195 countries and territories and selected subnational locations: a systematic analysis from the global burden of disease study 2016.</article-title><source>Lancet</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>391</volume>:<fpage>2236</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>71</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29893224</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(18)30994-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5986687</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>[6]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>GBD 2015 Healthcare Access and Quality Collaborators</collab>. <article-title>Healthcare access and quality index based on mortality from causes amenable to personal health care in 195 countries and territories, 1990-2015: a novel analysis from the global burden of disease study 2015.</article-title><source>Lancet</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>390</volume>:<fpage>231</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>66</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28528753</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(17)30818-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5528124</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>[7]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Development and prospect of day surgery in China.</article-title><source>Chin HospitaI Manag</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>16</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>[8]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Exploration of day surgery practice in urology department of Shanghai Renji Hospital.</article-title><source>Chin J Hospital Adm</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>349</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>51</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>[9]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cadariu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Enache</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Avram</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Day surgery in Romania.</article-title><source>Ann Ital Chir</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>88</volume>:<fpage>567</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>71</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29339592</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>[10]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Margaret</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Golosinskiy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Ambulatory surgery in the United States, 2006.</article-title><source>Natl Health Stat Rep</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>28</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19294964</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>[11]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Farquharson</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Early ambulation; with special reference to herniorrhaphy as an outpatient procedure.</article-title><source>Lancet</source>. <year>1955</year>;<volume>269</volume>:<fpage>517</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13252904</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0140-6736(55)93272-4</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>[12]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Drissi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jurczak</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cossa</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Outpatient groin hernia repair: assessment of 9330 patients from the French &#8220;Club Hernie&#8221; database.</article-title><source>Hernia</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>427</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>35</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29080110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10029-017-1689-5</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>[13]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Expert consensus on the standard process of ambulatory surgery for inguinal hernia (2020 edition).</article-title><source>Chin J Dig Surg</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>714</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>[14]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Majholm</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Engbaek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartholdy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Is day surgery safe? a Danish multicentre study of morbidity after 57,709 day surgery procedures.</article-title><source>Acta Anaesth Scand</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>323</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>31</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22335277</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1399-6576.2011.02631.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>[15]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McCormack</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>NW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Go</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Laparoscopic techniques versus open techniques for inguinal hernia repair.</article-title><source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>2003</volume>:<fpage>CD001785</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12535413</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/14651858.CD001785</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8407507</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>[16]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>JX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The development of hernia and abdominal wall surgery in China and the challenge of innovation in the new century.</article-title><source>Chin J Pract Surg</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>89</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>92</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>[17]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Closure of a direct inguinal hernia defect in laparoscopic repair with barbed suture: a simple method to prevent seroma formation?</article-title><source>Surg Endosc</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>1082</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28779243</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00464-017-5760-1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>[18]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scheuermann</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niebisch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lyros</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Transabdominal Preperitoneal (TAPP) versus lichtenstein operation for primary inguinal hernia repair - a systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials.</article-title><source>BMC Surg</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>55</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28490321</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12893-017-0253-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5424320</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>[19]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Application of adult laparoscopic daytime tension-free repair of inguinal hernia in county-level hospitals.</article-title><source>Chin Commun Doctors</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>45</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>[20]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>QW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical benefits analysis of day surgery for laparoscopic inguinal herniorrhaphy.</article-title><source>Chin J Hernia Abdominal Wall Surg</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>19</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>[21]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rena</surname><given-names>ALP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meiheriali</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect analysis of day ward nursing mode for patients undergoing laparoscopic inguinal hernia repair.</article-title><source>China Health Vision</source>. <year>2020</year>:<fpage>144</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>[22]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>ZQ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Feasibility study on the daytime operation mode of laparoscopic transabdominal peritoneal hernia repair.</article-title><source>Med Innov China</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>[23]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical application effect and implementation value of adult laparoscopic inguinal hernia repair in day surgery mode.</article-title><source>Health for Everyone</source>. <year>2019</year>:<fpage>79</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>[24]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>XZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Observation on the effect of laparoscopic hernia repair in the treatment of hernia under day surgery mode.</article-title><source>Inner Mongolia Med J</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>50</volume>:<fpage>1048</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>[25]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>XM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical application of adult laparoscopic inguinal hernia repair in day surgery mode.</article-title><source>China Pract Med</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>61</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>[26]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>CX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical effect of day surgery ward nursing mode for patients with laparoscopic inguinal hernia repair.</article-title><source>Electron J Clin Med Lit</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>19510</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>[27]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>XP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of day care nursing model of patients with laparoscopic inguinal hernia repair.</article-title><source>Mil Nurs</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>63</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>[28]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The gold standard for inguinal hernia repair - Lichtenstein procedure, TAPP or TEP?</article-title><source>Chin J Pract Surg</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>1236</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>[29]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuen</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Day-case endoscopic totally extraperitoneal inguinal hernioplasty versus open Lichtenstein hernioplasty for unilateral primary inguinal hernia in males: a randomized trial.</article-title><source>Surg Endosc</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>76</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>81</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16247575</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00464-005-0203-9</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>[30]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Altieri</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Long-term incidence of contralateral primary hernia repair following unilateral inguinal hernia repair in a cohort of 32,834 patients.</article-title><source>Surg Endosc</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>817</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>22</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27369285</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00464-016-5037-0</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>