<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Orthop Surg Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Orthop Surg Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">438</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jorthsurg</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Orthopaedic Surgery and Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1749-799X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11871755</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11871755.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11871755</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11871755</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40022183</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13018-025-05538-0</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">5538</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Assessing the reproducibility of American College of Surgeons National Surgical Quality Improvement Program (ACS-NSQIP) arthroplasty studies</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogunsola</surname><given-names initials="AS">Ayobami S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marinier</surname><given-names initials="MC">Michael C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hlas</surname><given-names initials="AC">Arman C.</given-names></name><address><email>arman-hlas@uiowa.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elkins</surname><given-names initials="JM">Jacob M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/036jqmy94</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.214572.7</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 8294</institution-id><institution>Department of Orthopedics and Rehabilitation, </institution><institution>University of Iowa, </institution></institution-wrap>200 Hawkins Drive, Iowa City, IA 52242 USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>1</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>20</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">478198</issue-id><elocation-id>216</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>7</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>03</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>01</day><month>03</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-03-05 13:25:13.500"><day>05</day><month>03</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#8217;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#8217;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="13018_2025_Article_5538.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Utilization of large-volume clinical registries for observational research has gained popularity in orthopaedic literature. However, concerns exist regarding inadequate reporting of methodology in this type of research. Despite these concerns, the reproducibility of such studies has not been adequately assessed in existing literature. This study aims to assess the reproducibility of American College of Surgeons National Surgical Quality Improvement Program (ACS-NSQIP) arthroplasty studies on smoking as a risk factor for poor surgical outcomes by employing identical datasets and statistical methods.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">A systematic PubMed search between 2013 and 2023 identified ACS-NSQIP studies involving hip or knee arthroplasty and smoking as a potential risk factor for poor surgical outcomes. Each study&#8217;s methods were reproduced by a trained statistician based on the reported methodology. In cases where certain steps were not explicitly stated, the statistician made informed decisions to reproduce those steps. Adjusted odds ratios (aORs) and <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-values (&#945;&#8201;=&#8201;0.05) were compared between the original and reanalyzed datasets.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">The initial search yielded 43 studies, with 11 meeting inclusion criteria resulting in the reanalysis of 268 aORs. Upon reanalysis, 12.69% of the original studies&#8217; aORs changed in interpretation, while 13.43% experienced a change in statistical significance. The average magnitude change of each aOR across all studies was 17.22%, and the sample size (N) in reanalysis varied by up to 47.84%. Among the 11 commonly cited studies, approximately one in eight objective conclusions changed in interpretation or statistical significance.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">Inconsistent reproducibility exists across many arthroplasty studies that utilize the ACS-NSQIP database. These findings highlight the importance of rigorous reporting of study methodology, data collection, and statistical analyses when utilizing large-volume databases in orthopaedic research. This burden of responsibility should be shared among authors, peer reviewers, and orthopaedic journals to confirm the accuracy and validity of published database research.</p></sec><sec><title>Level of evidence</title><p id="Par5">This study systematically reviewed and analyzed, in attempt to reproduce, published arthroplasty studies utilizing ACS-NSQIP database to assess smoking as a potential risk factor for poor surgical outcomes. All analyzed studies included Level III Evidence, therefore this current study compares reproduced Level III Evidence to the original Level III Evidence.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s13018-025-05538-0.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Reproducibility</kwd><kwd>Arthroplasty</kwd><kwd>ACS-NSQIP</kwd><kwd>Smoking</kwd><kwd>Risk factors</kwd><kwd>Surgical outcomes</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#169; BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par6">In the past decade, utilization of large-volume clinical registries for observational research has increased markedly in orthopaedic literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. These national databases offer a vast and accessible study population with numerous variables available for investigation over a designated time period [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Although randomized control trials remain the gold standard in orthopaedic research, such trials can be expensive, time-consuming, and limited in sample size to enable generalizability to broader populations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Some research topics may also be ill-suited for these designs owing to ethical concerns or lack of feasibility in answering specific questions in today&#8217;s era [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Consequently, well-conducted observational studies have emerged as a viable alternative to answer research questions that are too difficult or costly to address through other study designs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Large-volume clinical registries provide robust data to conduct these studies in a low-cost and efficient manner.</p><p id="Par7">The American College of Surgeons National Surgical Quality Improvement Program (ACS-NSQIP) database remains one of the most commonly utilized clinical registries in surgical research (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). This database contains preoperative, intraoperative, and 30-day postoperative data prospectively collected by clinical reviewers through a standardized process with frequent data auditing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]; as a result, the strength of NSQIP lies in the accuracy of collected data and its utility as a resource both developed and validated by surgeons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. In orthopaedics, many authors have utilized ACS-NSQIP in arthroplasty research to identify risk factors for poor surgical outcomes including postoperative complications, increased length of hospital stay, and hospital readmission. The effects of smoking as a potential risk factor have been frequently explored in much of this research [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. These studies largely report Level III evidence due to their observational design [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>].</p><p id="Par8">
<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>ACS-NSQIP database publication count, 1998&#8211;2022</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e250" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="13018_2025_5538_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par9">Although observational database research represents a growing subset of orthopaedic literature, several limitations exist with this study design. Observational studies can only establish association between predictor and outcome variables, and cannot be used to determine causality [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Lack of control over predictor variables introduces the potential for bias or confounding in these studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Extensive data mining to unveil statistically significant associations can also lead to poor recollection and reporting of study methodology. Recent studies have demonstrated that the majority of database research fails to adhere to current methodologic reporting standards [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>], which can lead to further decreases in study validity. One way to confirm the reliability of such research is by assessing study reproducibility [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. While observational database research offers the opportunity to address questions that are difficult to answer through other study designs, the reproducibility of such studies has not been adequately assessed in existing literature.</p><p id="Par10">This study aimed to determine the reproducibility of ACS-NSQIP hip or knee arthroplasty studies assessing smoking as a risk factor for poor surgical outcomes by employing identical datasets and statistical methods as described in selected publications.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Search strategy and study selection</title><p id="Par11">A PubMed search was completed for relevant studies published between 2013 and 2023. Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> includes our complete search term used to conduct this analysis. Following this comprehensive search, two independent reviewers (ASO and MCM) screened all titles and abstracts. Articles including content related to our initial search strategy were selected for independent full-text review by the same two reviewers. Inclusion and exclusion criteria for final study selection are outlined in Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. A third reviewer (JME) resolved any disagreements regarding study inclusion. Author and reference tracking were conducted using selected studies to identify any relevant articles that were missing in our original search. Figure&#160;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> outlines a complete flow diagram for study selection and inclusion.</p><p id="Par12">
<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The PubMed search criteria and inclusion/exclusion criteria for the selected studies</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Search Term</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Total Joint Arthroplasty&#160;</italic>
<bold>OR&#160;</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">Total Hip Arthroplasty&#160;</italic>
<bold>OR&#160;</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">Total Knee Arthroplasty</italic>
</p><p>
<bold>AND</bold>
</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Smoking</italic>
</p><p>
<bold>AND</bold>
</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">American College of Surgeons National Surgical Quality Improvement Program&#160;</italic>
<bold>OR</bold>
</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">National Surgical Quality Improvement Program&#160;</italic>
<bold>OR&#160;</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">NSQIP</italic>
</p><p>
<bold>AND</bold>
</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Outcomes&#160;</italic>
<bold>OR&#160;</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">Complications</italic>
</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Inclusion Criteria</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Exclusion Criteria</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8226; Discusses primary and/or revision total hip and/or knee arthroplasty</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8226; Discusses shoulder, ankle, metacarpal, or other non-hip or knee joint arthroplasty</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8226; Includes theme of smoking as a specific predictor for selected outcomes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8226; Discusses machine learning or use of technology</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8226; Utilizes ACS-NSQIP database</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8226; Includes non-observational study designs</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8226; Includes clearly defined variables and outcomes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8226; Includes risk calculator</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8226; Published between 2013 and 2023</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8226; Includes trend studies</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8226; Has been cited in other publications</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8226; Includes only a single outcome</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par13">
<fig id="Fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Flow diagram for study selection and inclusion in ACS-NSQIP reproducibility study</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e426" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="13018_2025_5538_Fig2_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Data acquisition and analysis</title><p id="Par14">The exact data from selected studies were obtained from our institution&#8217;s NSQIP office. Once obtained, data were analyzed by our statistician (ASO) utilizing identical statistical approaches employed by the original authors as defined in their methodology section. In cases where a required step was not explicitly stated in the original publication, the statistician made informed decisions to reproduce those steps (see Supplemental Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). Reproducibility was assessed by comparing the adjusted odds ratios (aORs) and their associated <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-values (with &#945;&#8201;=&#8201;0.05) between the original paper results and the reanalyzed results. All data analyses were performed using SAS version 9.4 (TS1M1) (SAS Institute, Cary, North Carolina) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Results</title><p id="Par15">Our initial literature search yielded 43 studies. Upon title and abstract screening, 36 studies were selected for full-text review. After full-text review, 10 studies met the inclusion criteria and 1 additional study was added via author/reference tracking for a net total of 11 included studies, all of which were observational studies (i.e. Level III evidence) (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Six studies evaluated smoking as a potential risk factor for postoperative complications after total joint arthroplasty. The remaining five studies assessed smoking and other potential risk factors associated with perioperative complications, increased length of hospital stay, and/or readmission rates after total joint arthroplasty (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p><p id="Par16">
<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Reproducibility of database studies in arthroplasty: a comparative analysis of original and reanalyzed data from ACS-NSQIP database</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Study Number</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Authors</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Journal of Publication</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Original Manuscript Findings</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reanalyzed Data Findings</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Duchman et al., 2015</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Journal of Bone and Joint Surgery</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Current smokers have an increased risk of wound complications and both current and former smokers have an increased risk of total complications following total hip or total knee arthroplasty. Increasing pack-year history of smoking resulted in increasing total complication risk.</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Current smokers have an increased risk of wound complications but did not have an increased risk of total complications following total hip or total knee arthroplasty. Former smokers have a reduced risk of total complications. There is no significant association between increasing pack-year history of smoking and total complications.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Liodakis et al., 2015</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">The Journal of Arthroplasty</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patients who underwent revision hip arthroplasty (RHA) had more perioperative complications, longer operative time, more blood transfusions, and longer hospital stay compared to those who underwent revision knee arthroplasty (RKA). The strongest modifiable risk factor for major complications and prolonged hospital stay after RHA and RKA was low preoperative hematocrit.</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">The reanalyzed data findings and conclusions were comparable to the original manuscript.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Keswani et al., 2015</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">The Journal of Arthroplasty</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Multivariate analysis revealed risk factors for readmission after revision hip and knee arthroplasty including male sex, pulmonary disease, severe adverse event before discharge, stroke, cardiac disease, and American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) class 3 or 4. Independent predictors of extended length of stay included infection or fracture etiology relative to mechanical loosening etiology, dependent functional status, BMI&#8201;&#8805;&#8201;40&#160;kg/m<sup>2</sup>, history of smoking, diabetes, cardiac disease, stroke, bleeding disorders, wound class 3 or 4, and ASA class 3 or 4.</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pulmonary disease is not a significant predictor for readmission after revision hip and knee arthroplasty. Fracture etiology relative to mechanical loosening etiology, history of smoking, and bleeding disorders were not significant predictors for extended length of stay in the revision knee arthroplasty group. Results were otherwise similar to the original manuscript.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Courtney et al., 2016</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">The Journal of Arthroplasty</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patients age&#8201;&#8805;&#8201;70 years, those with a cardiac history, smoking history, malnutrition, or diabetes have greater risk for readmission and complications after total joint arthroplasty (TJA). Outpatient TJA alone did not increase risk of readmission or reoperation, and it was a negative independent risk factor for postoperative complications.</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cardiac history is not a significant risk factor associated with readmission and complications after TJA. Results were otherwise similar to the original manuscript.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sher et al., 2016</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">The Journal of Arthroplasty</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patients discharged within 24&#160;h after total joint arthroplasty (TJA) were more likely to be younger, male sex, American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) class 1 or 2, and less likely to be taking steroids or have comorbidities. Multivariate analysis revealed independent predictors for adverse events or readmission including age&#8201;&#8805;&#8201;80 years, smoking, bleeding disorders, ASA class 3 or 4, and experiencing severe adverse events (SAE) prior to discharge.</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Smoking, ASA class 3 or 4, and experiencing SAE prior to discharge were not significant predictors for adverse events or readmission after TJA. Results were otherwise similar to the original manuscript.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bedard et al., 2018</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">The Journal of Arthroplasty</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Multivariate analysis showed that current smokers have an increased risk of deep infection and reoperation after revision total hip arthroplasty (THA). Smoking status additionally had no effect on wound complications after revision THA.</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Current smokers did not have an increased risk of deep infection or reoperation after revision THA. Results were otherwise similar to the original manuscript.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bedard et al., 2018</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">The Journal of Arthroplasty</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Multivariate analysis showed that current smokers have an increased risk of any wound complication and deep infection after revision total knee arthroplasty (TKA). Smoking status additionally had no effect on reoperation after revision TKA.</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Current smokers have an increased risk of any wound complication; however, current smokers did not have an increased risk of deep infection after revision TKA. Results were otherwise similar to the original manuscript.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sahota et al., 2018</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">The Journal of Arthroplasty</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Smokers in the combined total hip and knee arthroplasty cohort had higher rates of readmission and deep surgical site infection compared to non-smokers. Smokers in the combined cohort were also more likely to have a surgical complication compared to non-smokers.</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">The reanalyzed data findings and conclusions were similar to the original manuscript.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Johnson et al., 2019</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">The Journal of Arthroplasty</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Increasing age, obesity, smoking, diabetes, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), hypertension, bleeding disorders, corticosteroid use, and dependent functional status conferred an increased risk of discharge after 24&#160;h following total knee arthroplasty (TKA). Male gender, spinal anesthesia, and monitored anesthesia care were protective against length of stay greater than 24&#160;h.</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">The reanalyzed data findings and conclusions were similar to the original manuscript.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Agrawal et al., 2021</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">The Journal of Arthroplasty</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Multivariate analysis revealed smokers have an increase in pulmonary and infectious complications and longer hospital stays compared to non-smokers.</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Smokers do not have an increase in pulmonary complications compared to non-smokers. Results were otherwise similar to the original manuscript.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Heckmann et al., 2021</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Orthopedics</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Risk of total complications or thrombotic events is not accentuated in smokers who underwent total joint arthroplasty. Regardless of pack-year exposure, smokers have increased risk of readmission and wound complications.</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">The reanalyzed data findings and conclusions were similar to the original manuscript.</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par17">Among the 11 reanalyzed studies, a total of 268 aORs were examined. Of these 268 original aORs, 34 aORs (12.69%) changed in interpretation from harmful to protective or vice versa upon reanalysis and 36 aORs (13.43%) experienced a change in statistical significance (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Furthermore, the average magnitude change for each individual aOR was 17.22% (range&#8201;=&#8201;2.10 &#8722;&#8201;47%; median&#8201;=&#8201;13.67%) across included studies, and the total sample size (N) of included studies varied by an average of 2.83% (range&#8201;=&#8201;0 &#8722;&#8201;47.84%; median&#8201;=&#8201;5.75%). Seven studies had conclusions that changed in this reanalysis, with approximately one in eight objective conclusions varying in interpretation or statistical significance. Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> outlines the original conclusions of selected studies and how these findings changed upon reanalysis.</p><p id="Par18">
<table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Summary of reproduced adjusted odds ratios (aORs). Specifically, reproduced aORs that changed in interpretation from the original study, changes in statistical significance in reproduced aORs, and changes in sample size between original and reproduced data are included</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Study Number</th><th align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">aORs</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Statistical Significance*</th><th align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Comparison of Sample Size (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>)</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total aORs in Study</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reproduced aORs that changed in interpretation</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total aOR Change (%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Average Magnitude Change of aOR (%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reproduced aORs that changed in significance</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Significance Change (%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Original Total (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reproduced Total (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Difference in Sample Size</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Difference in Sample Size (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.67</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.40</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">78,191</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">83,736</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5545</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">7.09</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.14</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.29</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5068</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5198</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">130</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">2.57</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.57</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.34</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.93</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10,112</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9788</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">324</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">3.20</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.50</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.50</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">169,406</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">169,406</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.43</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.49</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.86</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">120,742</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">167,402</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46,660</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">38.64</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.30</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66.67</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8237</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8790</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">553</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">6.71</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.67</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8776</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7945</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">831</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">9.47</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47.00</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66.67</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2502</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2476</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">1.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.79</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">210,075</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">210,064</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.57</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.99</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">71.43</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67,897</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35,413</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32,484</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">47.84</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.00</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.35</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.00</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2088</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2208</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">120</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">5.75</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Total</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>268</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>34</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>12.69%</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>17.22%</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>36</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>13.43%</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>683,094</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>702,426</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>19,332</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<bold>2.83%</bold>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*Determined by <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par19">Observational research utilizing large clinical registries represents a growing area of orthopaedic literature. However, concerns exist regarding inadequate reporting of study methodology in many of these orthopaedic studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Despite these concerns, the reproducibility of such studies has not been adequately assessed in existing literature. This study aimed to determine the reproducibility of ACS-NSQIP studies on smoking as a risk factor for poor surgical outcomes after total joint arthroplasty. Our results demonstrated inconsistent reproducibility in many of these studies, with significant variability observed in included sample size, calculation of aORs, and study conclusions despite employing identical datasets and statistical methods. These findings highlight the importance of rigorous reporting of study methodology, data collection, and statistical analyses when utilizing large-volume databases in orthopaedic research.</p><p id="Par20">Recent studies have highlighted that most observational database research has inadequate reporting of study methodology. Khera et al. analyzed 120 studies published between 2015 and 2016 using the National Inpatient Sample (NIS) database in both medical and surgical fields and discovered that most did not adhere to recommended practices for methodologic reporting [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. In orthopaedics specifically, Teng et al. evaluated 136 studies published between 2016 and 2017 using the NIS and found again that the majority did not adhere to recommended practices for reporting methodology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Insufficient detailing of these methods may cast doubt on the integrity and conclusions of the study, particularly when attempts to reproduce findings based on the reported methodology yield divergent results.</p><p id="Par21">Several features inherent to this type of research may predispose to these shortcomings. The complexity and vastness of data collected from these sources makes it challenging to provide both succinct and comprehensive descriptions of methodologic practices [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. The extensive process of data extraction, handling, and cleaning prior to statistical analysis can also hinder researchers&#8217; ability to recall and articulate intricate details of their methods accurately [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. These intricacies of data handling, such as how missing values were addressed within the study, can lead to substantial differences in sample size or findings during methodologic appraisal or study reproduction if not reported correctly. Stringent word count limitations often imposed by journals compound these challenges, compelling authors to abbreviate or omit detailed descriptions of methodology in order to prioritize the results and discussion sections. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. This practice errantly assumes that readers will grasp and trust study methodology implicitly by virtue of the manuscript undergoing peer review; however, peer review alone does not guarantee study reliability and validity, and readers should be given the opportunity to assess this independently. The absence of standardized reporting guidelines for methodology in many orthopaedic journals also contributes to these inconsistencies, resulting in further variation in reporting of study methods in observational database research [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>].</p><p id="Par22">Given the utility of these study designs, focused efforts on addressing transparency, clarity, and adherence to rigorous reporting standards are needed to enhance the reliability of orthopaedic database research. From an author perspective, researchers must ensure to employ high standards for reporting by providing rigorous detail of methodologic practices that enables accurate assessment of study validity and reproducibility. This must be done with specific attention towards outlining: (1) the database utilized and its potential applications, strengths, and limitations in the study, (2) protocols for data extraction and handling of any missing values or duplicate records in the initial dataset, (3) data handling and cleaning practices to achieve the final dataset, and (4) any subsequent analyses performed with the resulting data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. In instances where limited word count hinders the ability to document this information, authors should take advantage of the use of tables, figures, supplemental materials, and/or appendices to provide sufficiently detailed descriptions of methodology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Utilization of trained statisticians or health sciences writing experts at institutional libraries may also provide aid in writing this section with an appropriate level of detail [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. From a reviewer and editor perspective, thorough methodologic appraisal is critical to ensure studies have sufficient reporting prior to their publication. Utilization of standardized methodologic reporting guidelines, such as the Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (STROBE) checklist, by orthopaedic journals may improve adherence rates while also making the job of reviewers and editors easier [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. From a broader journal perspective, expanding or eliminating word count limitations in journals may provide additional space to allow adequate reporting of study methods. Furthermore, demanding raw data from the final dataset in addition to reproducible, step-by-step instructions for how this final dataset was achieved may provide further transparency and methodologic integrity in observational database research; however, this must be balanced with a concern for patient confidentiality and privacy in the provided datasets [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>].</p><sec id="Sec7"><title>Limitations</title><p id="Par23">This study is not without limitations. First, this study limited our initial search to PubMed exclusively, potentially excluding articles of interest that are not indexed in PubMed. Author and reference tracking was incorporated into our comprehensive search strategy to mitigate this unintended consequence and reduce the likelihood of article exclusion. Second, our study focused solely on manuscripts utilizing the ACS-NSQIP database. Numerous clinical registries exist and have been used in orthopaedic literature, and inconsistent reproducibility may have arisen from inherent features of NSQIP database. However, limiting the scope of our analysis to studies using this database helped facilitate detailed reproduction of study methodology while also reducing confounding due to variability between different clinical registries. Third, some degree of variability in study reproduction may be due to intrinsic features of the NSQIP database, such as differences in hospital participation, data updates, or data retrieval processes over time. Lastly, our study only included manuscripts in arthroplasty focusing on smoking as a risk factor for poor surgical outcomes. While this represents only a subset of orthopaedic literature and may reduce generalizability to the broader field, this remains one of the most common applications of these registries in orthopaedic surgery research. Narrowing our focus in this manner also enabled thorough reanalysis of manuscript findings within this specific area of research. Further studies should be conducted to assess the reproducibility of observational database research across other orthopaedic subspecialties.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par24">Utilization of large-volume clinical registries for observational research has gained popularity in orthopaedic literature. However, the validity and reproducibility of such studies is often overlooked. This study aimed to determine the reproducibility of ACS-NSQIP studies evaluating smoking as a risk factor for poor surgical outcomes after total joint arthroplasty. Our results indicate that reproducibility of many of these studies is inconsistent, with significant variability observed in included sample size, calculation of aORs, and study conclusions despite employing identical datasets and statistical methods. These findings highlight the importance of rigorous reporting of study methodology, data collection, and statistical analyses when utilizing large-volume databases in orthopaedic research. This burden of responsibility should be shared among authors, peer reviewers, and orthopaedic journals to confirm the accuracy and validity of published database research.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="13018_2025_5538_MOESM1_ESM.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#8217;s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>JME conceptualized and reviewed this study. ASO performed study screening, data analysis, and manuscript writing. MCM performed study screening and manuscript writing. ACH performed manuscript writing. All authors contributed to study design, and each have read and approved the final submitted manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>No funding was utilized in the completion of this study.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The data supporting the conclusions of this article are available in the American College of Surgeons National Surgical Quality Improvement Program (ACS-NSQIP) repository, [<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.facs.org/quality-programs/data-and-registries/acs-nsqip/">https://www.facs.org/quality-programs/data-and-registries/acs-nsqip/</ext-link>].</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par32">JME serves as an Editor in the Journal of Arthroplasty and has received research support from DePuy Synthes and IronMind Enterprises. The other authors of this study have nothing to declare.</p></notes></notes><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>ACS-NSQIP</term><def><p id="Par35">American College of Surgeons National Surgical Quality Improvement Program</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>aOR</term><def><p id="Par36">Adjusted odds ratio</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NIS</term><def><p id="Par37">National Inpatient Sample</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>STROBE</term><def><p id="Par38">Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karlson</surname><given-names>NW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nezwek</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Menendez</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tybor</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salzler</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increased utilization of American Administrative Databases and large-scale clinical registries in Orthopaedic Research, 1996 to 2016</article-title><source>J Am Acad Orthop Surg Glob Res Rev</source><year>2018</year><volume>2</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>e076</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5435/JAAOSGlobal-D-18-00076</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30656264</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6324904</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Karlson NW, Nezwek TA, Menendez ME, Tybor D, Salzler MJ. Increased utilization of American Administrative Databases and large-scale clinical registries in Orthopaedic Research, 1996 to 2016. J Am Acad Orthop Surg Glob Res Rev. 2018;2(11):e076. 10.5435/JAAOSGlobal-D-18-00076.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30656264</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5435/JAAOSGlobal-D-18-00076</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6324904</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bohl</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grauer</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nationwide databases in orthopaedic surgery research</article-title><source>J Am Acad Orthop Surg</source><year>2016</year><volume>24</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>673</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5435/JAAOS-D-15-00217</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27579813</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Bohl DD, Singh K, Grauer JN. Nationwide databases in orthopaedic surgery research. J Am Acad Orthop Surg. 2016;24(10):673&#8211;82. 10.5435/JAAOS-D-15-00217.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27579813</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5435/JAAOS-D-15-00217</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pugely</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harwood</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ong</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bozic</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Callaghan</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Database and Registry Research in Orthopaedic surgery: part 2: clinical Registry Data</article-title><source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source><year>2015</year><volume>97</volume><issue>21</issue><fpage>1799</fpage><lpage>808</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2106/JBJS.O.00134</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26537168</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Pugely AJ, Martin CT, Harwood J, Ong KL, Bozic KJ, Callaghan JJ. Database and Registry Research in Orthopaedic surgery: part 2: clinical Registry Data. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2015;97(21):1799&#8211;808. 10.2106/JBJS.O.00134.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26537168</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2106/JBJS.O.00134</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nunley</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Minhas</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Administrative databases in Orthopaedic Research: pearls and pitfalls of Big Data</article-title><source>J Am Acad Orthop Surg</source><year>2016</year><volume>24</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>172</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5435/JAAOS-D-13-00009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26836377</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Patel AA, Singh K, Nunley RM, Minhas SV. Administrative databases in Orthopaedic Research: pearls and pitfalls of Big Data. J Am Acad Orthop Surg. 2016;24(3):172&#8211;9. 10.5435/JAAOS-D-13-00009.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26836377</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5435/JAAOS-D-13-00009</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fuchshuber</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Greif</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tidwell</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The power of the National Surgical Quality Improvement Program&#8212;achieving a zero pneumonia rate in general surgery patients</article-title><source>Perm J</source><year>2012</year><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7812/TPP/11-127</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22529758</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3327110</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Fuchshuber PR, Greif W, Tidwell CR, et al. The power of the National Surgical Quality Improvement Program&#8212;achieving a zero pneumonia rate in general surgery patients. Perm J. 2012;16(1):39&#8211;45. 10.7812/TPP/11-127.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22529758</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7812/tpp/11-127</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3327110</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Molina</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thakore</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blumer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Obremskey</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sethi</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of the National Surgical Quality Improvement Program in orthopaedic surgery</article-title><source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source><year>2015</year><volume>473</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1574</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11999-014-3597-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24706043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4385340</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Molina CS, Thakore RV, Blumer A, Obremskey WT, Sethi MK. Use of the National Surgical Quality Improvement Program in orthopaedic surgery. Clin Orthop Relat Res. 2015;473(5):1574&#8211;81. 10.1007/s11999-014-3597-7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24706043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11999-014-3597-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4385340</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liodakis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bergeron</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zukor</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Perioperative complications and length of stay after revision total hip and knee arthroplasties: an analysis of the NSQIP database</article-title><source>J Arthroplasty</source><year>2015</year><volume>30</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1868</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arth.2015.05.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26026655</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Liodakis E, Bergeron SG, Zukor DJ, et al. Perioperative complications and length of stay after revision total hip and knee arthroplasties: an analysis of the NSQIP database. J Arthroplasty. 2015;30(11):1868&#8211;71. 10.1016/j.arth.2015.05.029.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26026655</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.arth.2015.05.029</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Keswani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lovy</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Risk factors predict increased length of stay and readmission rates in revision joint arthroplasty</article-title><source>J Arthroplasty</source><year>2016</year><volume>31</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>603</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arth.2015.09.050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26601636</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Keswani A, Lovy AJ, Robinson J, et al. Risk factors predict increased length of stay and readmission rates in revision joint arthroplasty. J Arthroplasty. 2016;31(3):603&#8211;8. 10.1016/j.arth.2015.09.050.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26601636</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.arth.2015.09.050</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Courtney</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boniello</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Complications following outpatient total joint arthroplasty: an analysis of a national database</article-title><source>J Arthroplasty</source><year>2017</year><volume>32</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1426</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arth.2016.11.055</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28034481</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Courtney PM, Boniello AJ, Berger RA. Complications following outpatient total joint arthroplasty: an analysis of a national database. J Arthroplasty. 2017;32(5):1426&#8211;30. 10.1016/j.arth.2016.11.055.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28034481</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.arth.2016.11.055</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sher</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keswani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Predictors of same-day discharge in primary total joint arthroplasty patients and risk factors for post-discharge complications</article-title><source>J Arthroplasty</source><year>2017</year><volume>32</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>S150</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arth.2016.12.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28089186</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Sher A, Keswani A, Yao D, et al. Predictors of same-day discharge in primary total joint arthroplasty patients and risk factors for post-discharge complications. J Arthroplasty. 2017;32(9):S150. S156.e1.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28089186</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.arth.2016.12.017</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castle</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartwell</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>D&#8217;Heurle</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manning</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk factors for greater than 24-hour length of stay after primary total knee arthroplasty</article-title><source>J Arthroplasty</source><year>2020</year><volume>35</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>633</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arth.2019.10.037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31757697</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Johnson DJ, Castle JP, Hartwell MJ, D&#8217;Heurle AM, Manning DW. Risk factors for greater than 24-hour length of stay after primary total knee arthroplasty. J Arthroplasty. 2020;35(3):633&#8211;7. 10.1016/j.arth.2019.10.037.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31757697</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.arth.2019.10.037</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duchman</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pugely</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The effect of smoking on short-term complications following total hip and knee arthroplasty</article-title><source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source><year>2015</year><volume>97</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>1049</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2106/JBJS.N.01016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26135071</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Duchman KR, Gao Y, Pugely AJ, et al. The effect of smoking on short-term complications following total hip and knee arthroplasty. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2015;97(13):1049&#8211;58. 10.2106/JBJS.N.01016.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26135071</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2106/JBJS.N.01016</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bedard</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dowdle</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Owens</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>What is the impact of smoking on revision total hip arthroplasty?</article-title><source>J Arthroplasty</source><year>2018</year><volume>33</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>S182</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arth.2017.12.041</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29463436</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Bedard NA, Dowdle SB, Owens JM, et al. What is the impact of smoking on revision total hip arthroplasty? J Arthroplasty. 2018;33(7):S182&#8211;5. 10.1016/j.arth.2017.12.041.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29463436</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.arth.2017.12.041</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bedard</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dowdle</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>What is the impact of smoking on revision total knee arthroplasty?</article-title><source>J Arthroplasty</source><year>2018</year><volume>33</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>S172</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arth.2018.03.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29680584</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Bedard NA, Dowdle SB, Wilkinson BG, et al. What is the impact of smoking on revision total knee arthroplasty? J Arthroplasty. 2018;33(7):S172&#8211;6. 10.1016/j.arth.2018.03.024.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29680584</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.arth.2018.03.024</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sahota</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lovecchio</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harold</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beal</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manning</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of smoking on thirty-day postoperative complications after total joint arthroplasty: a propensity score-matched analysis</article-title><source>J Arthroplasty</source><year>2018</year><volume>33</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>30</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arth.2017.07.037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28870742</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Sahota S, Lovecchio F, Harold RE, Beal MD, Manning DW. The effect of smoking on thirty-day postoperative complications after total joint arthroplasty: a propensity score-matched analysis. J Arthroplasty. 2018;33(1):30&#8211;5. 10.1016/j.arth.2017.07.037.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28870742</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.arth.2017.07.037</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ingrande</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Said</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gabriel</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The association of preoperative smoking with postoperative outcomes in patients undergoing total hip arthroplasty</article-title><source>J Arthroplasty</source><year>2021</year><volume>36</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>1029</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arth.2020.09.049</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33616063</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Agrawal S, Ingrande J, Said ET, Gabriel RA. The association of preoperative smoking with postoperative outcomes in patients undergoing total hip arthroplasty. J Arthroplasty. 2021;36(3):1029&#8211;34. 10.1016/j.arth.2020.09.049.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33616063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.arth.2020.09.049</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heckmann</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Katebian</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lieberman</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Smoking as a risk factor for complications following total joint arthroplasty</article-title><source>Orthopedics</source><year>2021</year><volume>44</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>e639</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3928/01477447-20210817-03</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34590942</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Heckmann ND, Katebian B, Chung BC, Lieberman JR. Smoking as a risk factor for complications following total joint arthroplasty. Orthopedics. 2021;44(5):e639&#8211;44. 10.3928/01477447-20210817-03.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34590942</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3928/01477447-20210817-03</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marx</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Swiontkowski</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Updating the assignment of levels of evidence</article-title><source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source><year>2015</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>2</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2106/JBJS.N.01112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25568387</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Marx RG, Wilson SM, Swiontkowski MF. Updating the assignment of levels of evidence. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2015;97:1&#8211;2. 10.2106/JBJS.N.01112.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25568387</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2106/JBJS.N.01112</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Browne</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Springer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spindler</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Optimizing Use of large databases in Joint Arthroplasty and Orthopaedics</article-title><source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source><year>2022</year><volume>104</volume><issue>Suppl 3</issue><fpage>28</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2106/JBJS.22.00562</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36260041</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Browne JA, Springer B, Spindler KP. Optimizing Use of large databases in Joint Arthroplasty and Orthopaedics. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2022;104(Suppl 3):28&#8211;32. 10.2106/JBJS.22.00562.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36260041</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2106/JBJS.22.00562</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hess AS, Abd-Elsayed A. Observatioanl studies: uses and limitations. In: Abd-Elsayed A, editor. Pain. Springer; 2019. pp. 123&#8211;5.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khera</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Angraal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Couch</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Welsh</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nallamothu</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Girotra</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krumholz</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adherence to Methodological standards in Research using the National Inpatient Sample</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2017</year><volume>318</volume><issue>20</issue><fpage>2011</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2017.17653</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29183077</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5742631</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Khera R, Angraal S, Couch T, Welsh JW, Nallamothu BK, Girotra S, Chan PS, Krumholz HM. Adherence to Methodological standards in Research using the National Inpatient Sample. JAMA. 2017;318(20):2011&#8211;8. 10.1001/jama.2017.17653.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29183077</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.2017.17653</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5742631</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Teng</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Menendez</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Okike</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cassidy</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salzler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Most orthopaedic studies using the National Inpatient sample fail to adhere to recommended Research practices: a systematic review</article-title><source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source><year>2020</year><volume>478</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>2743</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/CORR.0000000000001355</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32541580</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7899397</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Teng TL, Menendez ME, Okike K, Cassidy C, Salzler M. Most orthopaedic studies using the National Inpatient sample fail to adhere to recommended Research practices: a systematic review. Clin Orthop Relat Res. 2020;478(12):2743&#8211;8. 10.1097/CORR.0000000000001355.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32541580</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/CORR.0000000000001355</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7899397</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Diaba-Nuhoho</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amponsah-Offeh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reproducibility and research integrity: the role of scientists and institutions</article-title><source>BMC Res Notes</source><year>2021</year><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>451</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13104-021-05875-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34906213</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8672590</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Diaba-Nuhoho P, Amponsah-Offeh M. Reproducibility and research integrity: the role of scientists and institutions. BMC Res Notes. 2021;14(1):451. 10.1186/s13104-021-05875-3.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34906213</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13104-021-05875-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8672590</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Verpillat</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rassen</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patrick</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garry</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartels</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transparency and reproducibility of Observational Cohort studies using large Healthcare databases</article-title><source>Clin Pharmacol Ther</source><year>2016</year><volume>99</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>325</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cpt.329</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26690726</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7833029</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Wang SV, Verpillat P, Rassen JA, Patrick A, Garry EM, Bartels DB. Transparency and reproducibility of Observational Cohort studies using large Healthcare databases. Clin Pharmacol Ther. 2016;99(3):325&#8211;32. 10.1002/cpt.329.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26690726</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/cpt.329</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7833029</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>SAS&#174;</surname></name></person-group><source>Version 9.4 (TS1M1)</source><year>2013</year><publisher-loc>Cary, NC, USA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>SAS Institute Inc</publisher-name></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="book">SAS<sup>&#174;</sup>. Version 9.4 (TS1M1). Cary, NC, USA: SAS Institute Inc.; 2013.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The rise of big clinical databases</article-title><source>Br J Surg</source><year>2015</year><volume>102</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>e93</fpage><lpage>101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bjs.9723</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25627139</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Cook JA, Collins GS. The rise of big clinical databases. Br J Surg. 2015;102(2):e93&#8211;101. 10.1002/bjs.9723.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25627139</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/bjs.9723</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van den Broeck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eeckels</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herbst</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Data cleaning: detecting, diagnosing, and editing data abnormalities</article-title><source>PLoS Med</source><year>2005</year><volume>2</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>e267</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.0020267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16138788</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1198040</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Van den Broeck J, Cunningham SA, Eeckels R, Herbst K. Data cleaning: detecting, diagnosing, and editing data abnormalities. PLoS Med. 2005;2(10):e267. 10.1371/journal.pmed.0020267.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16138788</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pmed.0020267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1198040</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alluri</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leland</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heckmann</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Surgical research using national databases</article-title><source>Ann Transl Med</source><year>2016</year><volume>4</volume><issue>20</issue><fpage>393</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/atm.2016.10.49</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27867945</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5107400</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Alluri RK, Leland H, Heckmann N. Surgical research using national databases. Ann Transl Med. 2016;4(20):393. 10.21037/atm.2016.10.49.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27867945</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.21037/atm.2016.10.49</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5107400</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adams-Huet</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bridging clinical investigators and statisticians: writing the statistical methodology for a research proposal</article-title><source>J Investig Med</source><year>2009</year><volume>57</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>818</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2310/JIM.0b013e3181c2996c</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19875966</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4415704</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Adams-Huet B, Ahn C. Bridging clinical investigators and statisticians: writing the statistical methodology for a research proposal. J Investig Med. 2009;57(8):818&#8211;24. 10.2310/JIM.0b013e3181c2996c.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19875966</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.231/JIM.0b013e3181c2996c</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4415704</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheffler</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhandari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Observational studies in orthopaedic surgery: the STROBE statement as a tool for transparent reporting</article-title><source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source><year>2013</year><volume>95</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>e14</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2106/JBJS.L.00484</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23389794</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Sheffler LC, Yoo B, Bhandari M, Ferguson T. Observational studies in orthopaedic surgery: the STROBE statement as a tool for transparent reporting. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2013;95(3):e14. 10.2106/JBJS.L.00484.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2106/JBJS.L.00484</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23389794</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>