<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="review-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Oncol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Oncol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1755</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">frontonco</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Oncol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Oncology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2234-943X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10196487</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10196487.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10196487</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10196487</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37213277</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fonc.2023.1132306</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Oncology</subject><subj-group><subject>Review</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Risk factors for early-onset colorectal cancer: systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hua</surname><given-names initials="H">Hongmei</given-names></name><xref rid="fn003" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names initials="Q">Qiuping</given-names></name><xref rid="fn001" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn003" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2151746"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names initials="P">Pan</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names initials="X">Xing</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<institution>Department of Nursing, The Second Affiliated Hospital of Zhejiang University School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Hangzhou, Zhejiang</addr-line>, <country>China</country>
</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Farnam Mohebi, University of California, Berkeley, United States</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Lian-Ping He, Taizhou University, China; Athanasia Pavlopoulou, Dokuz Eyl&#252;l University, T&#252;rkiye</p></fn><corresp id="fn001">*Correspondence: Qiuping Jiang, <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mailto:bottle@zju.edu.cn">bottle@zju.edu.cn</email></corresp><fn fn-type="equal" id="fn003"><p>&#8224;These authors have contributed equally to this work and share first authorship</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>05</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">427504</issue-id><elocation-id>1132306</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>12</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>4</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>20</day><month>05</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-07-07 15:25:37.070"><day>07</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2023 Hua, Jiang, Sun and Xu</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Hua, Jiang, Sun and Xu</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fonc-13-1132306.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>The incidence of early-onset colorectal cancer (EOCRC), which means colorectal cancer diagnosed in patients under 50 years, has been increasing around the world. However, the etiology remains unclear. This study aims to identify risk factors for EOCRC.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>This systematic review was conducted in PubMed, Embase, Scopus, and Cochrane Library databases from inception to November 25, 2022. We examined risk factors for EOCRC, including demographic factors, chronic conditions, and lifestyle behaviors or environmental factors. Random-effects/fixed-effects meta-analysis was adopted to combine effect estimates from published data. Study quality was evaluated with the Newcastle-Ottawa Scale (NOS). Statistical analysis was performed Revman5.3. Studies not suitable for the meta-analysis were analyzed by a systematic review.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>A total of 36 studies were identified for this review, and 30 studies were included in the meta-analysis. Significant risk factors for EOCRC included male (OR=1.20; 95% CI, 1.08-1.33), Caucasian (OR=1.44; 95% CI, 1.15-1.80), a family history of CRC (OR=5.90; 95% CI, 3.67-9.48), inflammatory bowel disease (OR=4.43; 95% CI, 4.05-4.84), obesity (OR=1.52; 95%CI, 1.20-1.91), overweight (OR=1.18; 95% CI, 1.12-1.25), triglycerides (OR=1.12; 95% CI, 1, 08-1.18), hypertension (OR=1.16; 95% CI, 1.12-1.21), metabolic syndrome (OR=1.29; 95% CI, 1.15-1.45), smoking (OR=1.44; 95% CI, 1.10-1.88), alcohol consumption (OR=1.41; 95% CI, 1.22-1.62), a sedentary lifestyle (OR=1.24; 95% CI, 1.05-1.46), red meat (OR=1.10; 95% CI, 1.04-1.16), processed meat (OR=1.53; 95% CI, 1.13-2.06), Western dietary patterns (OR=1.43; 95% CI, 1.18-1.73) and sugar-sweetened beverages (OR=1.55; 95% CI, 1.23-1.95). However, no statistical differences were found for hyperlipidemia and hyperglycemia. Vitamin D may be a protective factor (OR=0.72; 95% CI, 0.56-0.92). There was considerable heterogeneity among studies (I<sup>2</sup>&gt;60%).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>The study provides an overview of the etiology and risk factors of EOCRC. Current evidence can provide baseline data for risk prediction models specific to EOCRC and risk-tailored screening strategies.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>colorectal cancer</kwd><kwd>early-onset</kwd><kwd>risk factors</kwd><kwd>demographics</kwd><kwd>chronic conditions</kwd><kwd>lifestyle factors</kwd><kwd>environmental factors</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>Zhejiang Medical Health Science and Technology Project (2023KY766).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="2"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="59"/><page-count count="14"/><word-count count="5658"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>section-in-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Gastrointestinal Cancers: Colorectal Cancer</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Colorectal cancer (CRC) is the third most common cancer worldwide and the second most common cause of cancer-related death (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). In recent decades, the number of cases of early-onset colorectal cancer (EOCRC), defined as CRC diagnosed before age 50 (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>), has increased dramatically in the United States (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>), Japan, Australia (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>), Canada (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>), China, the United Kingdom, and other countries (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). According to the current data, it is estimated that in the next ten years, the incidence rates of rectal cancer and colon cancer in adults aged 20-34 will increase by 90% and 124% respectively, while the incidence rate in adults aged 35-49 will increase by 27% and 46% respectively (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Moreover, most young CRC patients have a later stage of disease at diagnosis, a higher risk of metastasis, and a poorer prognosis than elderly CRC patients, which highlights the need for the public and medical personnel to enhance their understanding of the disease (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>).</p><p>Multiple risk factors have been identified, such as a family history of CRC, inflammatory bowel disease (IBD), sedentary behaviors, smoking, elevated body mass index (BMI), diabetes, and poor diet (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). However, the conclusions of different studies remain controversial, such as obesity, data from a prospective cohort study (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>) and an observational study (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>) showed that obesity during adolescence was associated with an increased incidence and mortality of EOCRC. A cross-sectional study (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>) of local Songjiang District community residents in the city of Shanghai, east of China also found that obesity was an independent risk factor for early colorectal neoplasm. In contrast, Low et&#160;al. (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>) found that obesity or overweight was a protective factor for EOCRC. The risk factors for EOCRC remain unclear. Identifying risk factors for EOCRC can inform primary prevention programs and targeted screening approaches for high-risk individuals.</p><p>To the best of our knowledge, O&#8217;Sullivan et&#160;al. (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>) conducted a meta-analysis of risk factors for EOCRC and showed that smoking was not significantly associated with EOCRC. However, we found that some potentially important studies were not included in this study, such as a study (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>) involving 8,873,080 people, which compared patients with EOCRC with healthy individuals under 50 and illustrated that smoking was significantly associated with the incidence rate of EOCRC (adjusted OR=2.675; P&lt;0.001), which may affect the results. In addition, there were few studies included in the above meta-analysis, and the results may be biased. Carroll et&#160;al. (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>) and Li et&#160;al. (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>) only evaluated a single factor in their systematic reviews, and could not determine all the risk factors related to EOCRC. With the in-depth study of EOCRC in recent years, it is very important to identify the risk factors that may increase EOCRC through a comprehensive literature search.</p><p>To improve knowledge based on existing evidence and to address the limitations of previous reviews, we conducted a systematic review and meta-analysis to investigate risk factors for EOCRC. Our goal was to synthesize previous studies, which we hypothesized would be highly heterogeneous, under a uniform framework that can provide insights into development of new, evidence-based identification of risk factors associated with EOCRC, exploration of more effective prevention methods, and improved screening of high-risk populations.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Methods</title><p>The protocol was registered with PROSPERO (CRD42022371340). We conducted this systematic review and meta-analysis according to the guidelines of Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses (PRISMA) (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>) and Meta-analysis of Observational Studies in Epidemiology recommendations (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>).</p><sec id="s2_1"><title>Search strategy</title><p>A literature search without any country restriction was performed to identify studies that described risk factors for EOCRC. Two researchers (QP J and HM H) independently searched PubMed (1950-present), Embase (1947-present), Scopus (1970-present), and the Cochrane Library (1995-present) from inception to November 25, 2022. The following keywords or terms were used to search: early-onset colorectal cancer, EOCRC, young colorectal cancer, risk factors, and risk. The complete search strategy is provided in the <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">
<bold>Supplementary Material</bold>
</xref>. In addition, study references and study lists cited in articles related to the topic were browsed and manually searched to determine if any study had performed subgroup analyses in subjects younger than 50 years, further supplementing eligible studies for our study.</p></sec><sec id="s2_2"><title>Study inclusion and exclusion</title><p>The inclusion criteria were as follows: (1) study design: case-control or cohort studies, (2) studies of which full-text could be obtained, (3) studies reporting the risk factors related to EOCRC, (4) studies comparing patients with EOCRC and healthy individuals younger than 50 years, and (5) studies on patients with CRC diagnosed for the first time. The exclusion criteria were as follows: (1) studies comparing characteristics between EOCRC cases and late-onset cases, (2) studies on patients with advanced polyps, (3) studies not reporting effect estimates or from which effect estimates could not be obtained, or (4) studies not published in English.</p></sec><sec id="s2_3"><title>Study selection</title><p>According to the inclusion and exclusion criteria, literature screening and data extraction were completed independently by two researchers (QP J and X X) and then cross-checked. Any conflict was resolved by HM H.</p></sec><sec id="s2_4"><title>Risk of bias and quality assessment</title><p>Study quality was evaluated by two researchers (QP J and P S) using the Newcastle-Ottawa Scale (NOS) (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). The NOS is a quality scale that evaluates studies based on 3 broad categories: selection (maximum of four stars); comparability (maximum of two stars); and exposure/outcome (maximum of three stars). This scale has a total score of 9 stars, and a study with a score &#8805;6 stars is considered to have &#8220;good&#8221; quality. Differences of opinion during the evaluation were resolved through mutual discussion or consultation with a third researcher (HM H).</p></sec><sec id="s2_5"><title>Data extraction</title><p>We extracted data on characteristics of the included studies, including author, year of publication, country, study type, age at diagnosis of EOCRC, sample size, geographic location, participant sex, and population selection. We extracted information about the types of risk factors (demographic characteristics, lifestyle or environmental factors, clinical factors, comorbidities, reproductive factors, genetic factors), and measurement of risk factors (cutoff value for clinical factors, diagnosis of comorbidities), and extracted the referent category, effect estimates, 95% confidence intervals (CIs) for exposure categories of each risk factor. Risk factors could be obtained through patient self-reported or physician measurements.</p></sec><sec id="s2_6"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>For the purposes of this study, the relative ratios and hazard ratios were treated as estimates of odds ratios (ORs). We performed log transformation on the extracted ORs and indirectly estimated their standard errors. As a risk factor was reported in at least 2 studies, we included these studies in meta-analyses. RevMan5.3 was used for statistical analysis. Cochrane Q-test and I<sup>2</sup> test were used to evaluate heterogeneity. Fixed-effects models or random-effects models were selected according to the heterogeneity of test results. Sensitivity analysis was used to identify the source of heterogeneity. If more than 10 studies were included in the meta-analysis, funnel plots were used to assess the risk of publication bias for each risk factor. Studies not suitable for the meta-analysis were analyzed through a systematic review.</p><p>We used the BMI classification of the World Health Organization. Due to the different classifications of BMI in the included studies, we performed the meta-analysis using two methods: (1) making comparison between obese (BMI&gt;30 kg/m<sup>2</sup>) and normal-weight subjects, and (2) making comparison between overweight (30&#8805;BMI&#8805;24.9 kg/m<sup>2</sup>) and normal-weight subjects. We also evaluated the effect of abdominal obesity on EOCRC. Glover et&#160;al. (15) did not define obesity and Kwak et&#160;al. (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>) only compared individuals with BMI&#8805;25 kg/m<sup>2</sup> with the general population, so we did not include it in the analysis. For smoking, we pooled estimates of the effects of smokers (former and current) and never-smokers. For alcohol consumption, we pooled estimates of the effects of drinkers (past and current) and never-drinkers. We included dyslipidemia in the analysis, and a separate meta-analysis was conducted on triglyceride. In terms of diet, due to the limited number of studies, we only included red meat, processed meat, Western dietary patterns, sugar-sweetened beverages, and vitamin D for the meta-analysis. All <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> values were two-sided, and the significance level was set at 0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><p>Initial searches identified 4137 studies, and 16 additional studies were identified from references. Subsequently, 2038 studies were obtained after removing duplicate literature, and 1060 were excluded after screening titles and abstracts. After full-text review, a total of 36 studies examining at least one risk factor for EOCRC were retained, and 30 of these studies were included in the meta-analysis (<xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figure&#160;1</bold>
</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="f1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure&#160;1</label><caption><p>PRISMA flow diagram.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fonc-13-1132306-g001.jpg"/></fig><p>Among the 36 studies (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>), 19 were cohort studies and 17 were case-control studies, with 66312 participants. The year of publication ranged from 1989 to 2022, and studies in the last three years accounted for 56.76% (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">
<bold>Table&#160;1</bold>
</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table&#160;1</label><caption><p>Characteristics of all studies investigating risk factors for the development of early-onset (&lt;50 years of age) colorectal cancer.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">First Author<break/>(year)</th><th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study Type</th><th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age at Diagnosis of EOCRC</th><th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample Size<break/>(cases)</th><th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Location</th><th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</th><th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outcome</th><th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Risk Factors Identified</th><th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population Selection</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Puzzono 2022 (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">case-control (2018&#8211;2021)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18-49</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Italy</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRC</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">family history, processed meat, dairy products, smoking</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">third-level academic hospital in Milan</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nguyen 2022 (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">case-control (2006-2016)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;50</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2557</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sweden</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRC</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">antibiotics</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The Swedish National Board of Health and Welfare and Epidemiology Strengthened by histoPathology Reports in Sweden(ESPRESSO)</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">McDowell 2022 (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">case-control(1999-2011)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;50</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">445</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scotland</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRC, colon cancer, rectal cancer</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">antibiotics</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">population-based, Primary Care Clinical Information Unit Research (PCCIUR) database</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Li 2022 (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">case-control(2003-2020)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;50</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">339</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Germany</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRC, colon cancer, rectal cancer</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">obesity</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">population-based,Chancen der Verh&#252;tung durch Screening(DACHS)</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jin 2022 (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cohort<break/>(2009-2010)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;50</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8320</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">South Korean</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRC</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MetS, obesity</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">population-based,National Health Insurance Service (NHIS)</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pang 2022 (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cohort<break/>(2014-2019)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;50</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">621</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Colorectal Adenomas</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">age, female, BMI, undergone a diagnostic colonoscopy</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital-based</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Danial 2022 (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">case-control(1999-2019)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20-50</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13800</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The United States</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRC</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">family history, primary malignant neoplasm of breast, IBD, alcohol consumption, smoking, obesity, diabetes, hyperlipidemia, Caucasians</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">population-based, commercial database (Explorys)</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Archambault 2021 (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">case-control<break/>(1990s-<break/>2010s)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;50</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3767</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRC, colon cancer, rectal cancer</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Family history, red meat, processed meat, smoking, alcohol consumption, Sedentary, diabetes</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">population-based,the Colon Cancer Family Registry, the Colorectal Transdisciplinary study, and the Genetics and Epidemiology of Colorectal Cancer Consortium</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kim 2021 (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cohort<break/>(1991-2015)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25-42</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">111</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The United States</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRC</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">vitamin D</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nurses&#8217; Health Study II</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zheng 2021 (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cohort<break/>(1991-2011)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25-42</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1153</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The United States</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">adenoma, distal colon and rectum</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Western diet</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nurses&#8217; Health Study II</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yue 2021 (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cohort<break/>(1991-2015)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26-45</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">332</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The United States</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRC</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">empirical dietary index for hyperinsulinemia (EDIH), empirical lifestyle index for hyperinsulinemia (ELIH), Hyperinsulinemia dietary, lifestyle patterns</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nurses&#8217; Health Study II</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Schumacher 2021 (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">case-control(2008-2018)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15-49</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1032</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kaiser Permanente Southern California (KPSC)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">colorectal adenocarcinoma</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">obesity</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">population-based, Kaiser Permanente Southern California (KPSC)</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nguyen 2021 (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cohort<break/>(1991-2015)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25-42</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2911</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The United States</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">adenoma</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sulfur microbial diet</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nurses&#8217; Health Study II</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Joh 2021 (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cohort<break/>(1999-2015)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25-42</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4364</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The United States</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">adenomas</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High sugar,<break/>sugar-sweetened beverage</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nurses&#8217; Health Study II</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chen 2021 (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">case-control (2006-2015)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18-49</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4673</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The United States</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRC, colon cancer (proximal and distal), rectal cancer</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MetS</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MarketScan databases</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hur 2021 (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cohort<break/>(1991-2015)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25-42</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">109</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The United States</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRC</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sugar-sweetened beverage</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nurses&#8217; Health Study II</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chang 2021 (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">case-control (2018-2019)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20&#8211;49</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">175</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRC</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">family history, sedentary, sugar-sweetened beverage, Westernized dietary pattern</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">population-based, Ontario Cancer Registry (OCR)</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Demb 2020 (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cohort<break/>(1999-2016)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18-49&#160;</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 800</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The United States</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRC</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">iron-deficiency anaemia, haematochezia</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Veterans Health Administration (VHA)</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dash 2020 (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cohort<break/>(1995-2013)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;50</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The United States</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRC</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Obesity</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Black Women's Health Study</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low 2020 (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">case-control(1999-2014)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18&#8211;49</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">651</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The United States</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRC</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">male, smoking, non-aspirin users, lower BMIs, weight loss of<break/>5 kg or more</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Veteran&#8217;s Health Administration (VHA)</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gausman 2020 (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">case-control(2011-2017)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18&#8211;49</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">269</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">New York City</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRC</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">male, IBD, family history, obesity, smoking, diabetes,</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital-based</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L'Heureux 2019 (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">case-control (2008-2013)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;51</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8623</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Taiwan</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRC, colon cancer, rectal cancer</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">hypothyroidism</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">population-based, Taiwanese National Health Insurance Research Database</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liu 2019 (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cohort<break/>(1991-2011)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25-42</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">114</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The United States</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRC, colon cancer, rectal cancer</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">obese</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nurses&#8217; Health Study II</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Syed 2019 (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cohort<break/>(2012-2016)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25-49</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5710</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The United States</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRC</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">male, Caucasian, abdominal pain, rectal pain, altered bowel function, rectal bleeding, weight loss, family history, gastrointestinal malignancy, polyps, smoking, alcohol consumption, presence of colitis, obesity</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">population-based, commercial database (Explorys)</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glover 2019 (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cohort<break/>(2013-2018)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20-39</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1700</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The United States</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRC</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian, male, diabetes, smoking, obesity</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">population-based, commercial database (Explorys)</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nguyen 2018 (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cohort<break/>(1991-2011)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25&#8211;42</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">118</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The United States</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRC, colon cancer, rectal cancer</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sedentary TV viewing time</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nurses&#8217; Health Study II</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Levi 2017 (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cohort<break/>(1967-2010)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16-19</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1089</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Israel</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRC</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overweight, obesity</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Israeli National Cancer Registry (INCR) database</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kwak 2016 (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cohort<break/>(2011-2013)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20-39</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">497</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Korea</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">colorectal adenoma</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">smoking, alcohol consumption</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital-based</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wu 2013 (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cohort<break/>(2004-2005)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 50</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Taiwan</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRC</td><td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">the chronic kidney disease patients not undergoing dialysis</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Health Insurance Database 2005</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S&#248;ndergaard 2013 (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cohort<break/>(1978-2009)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;45</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1789</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Denmark</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRC</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">low education</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">data from the Central Population Register</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rosato 2013 (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">case-control (1985-2009)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;45</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">329</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Italy and Switzerland</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRC</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">family history, alcohol, processed meat</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital-based</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ghadirian 1998 (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">case-control (1989-1993)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;50</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">118</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Colon cancer</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ever married, family history, constipation, use of laxatives</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital-based</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negri 1998 (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">case-control (1992-1996)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;45</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">145</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Italy</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRC, colon cancer, rectal cancer</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">family history</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital-based</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fuchs 1994 (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cohort<break/>(1989-1992)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;50</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The United States</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRC</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">family history</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The Nurses' Health Study and The Health Professionals Follow-up Study.</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">St John 1993 (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">case-control (1952-1985)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;45</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Australia</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRC</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">family history</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">family medical hospital</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peter 1989 (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">case-control (1974-1982)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;45</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">147</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">United States-LA County</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRC, stratified (right-sided, traverse/descending, sigmoid, rectum)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">fumes, wood, metal dust, deep fried foods, barbecued, alcohol consumption, smoking, smoked meats</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital-based</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>CRC, colorectal cancer; MetS, metabolic syndrome; BMI, body mass index; F, female; M, male; IBD, inflammatory bowel disease.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><sec id="s3_1"><title>Study quality</title><p>The NOS was used to evaluate the quality of the studies. The included studies were of high quality, with scores ranging from 6 to 9 (out of 9), and an average score of 7.2 (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">
<bold>Table&#160;2</bold>
</xref>). Funnel plot results indicated that there was some publication bias (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">
<bold>Supplementary Material</bold>
</xref> Funnel plot).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table&#160;2</label><caption><p>Risk of bias and quality assessment.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Author</th><th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case/<break/>Representative</th><th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Representative/Nonexposed</th><th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Controls/Exposure</th><th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Definition/Outcome not present</th><th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confounding</th><th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exposure/Outcome</th><th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Method/Follow-up</th><th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nonresponse/Adequate follow-up</th><th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Score</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Puzzono 2022 (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nguyen 2022 (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">McDowell 2022 (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Li 2022 (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jin 2022 (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pang 2022 (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Danial 2022 (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Archambault 2021 (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kim 2021 (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zheng 2021 (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yue 2021 (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Schumacher 2021 (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nguyen 2021 (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Joh 2021 (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chen 2021 (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hur 2021 (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chang 2021 (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Demb 2020 (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dash 2020 (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low 2020 (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gausman 2020 (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L'Heureux 2019 (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liu 2019 (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Syed 2019 (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glover 2019 (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nguyen 2018 (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Levi 2017 (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kwak 2016 (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wu 2013 (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S&#248;ndergaard 2013 (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rosato 2013 (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ghadirian 1998 (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negri 1998 (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fuchs 1994 (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">St John 1993 (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peter 1989 (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>The NOS is a quality scale that evaluates studies based on 3 broad categories: selection (maximum of four stars); comparability (maximum of two stars); and exposure/outcome (maximum of three stars). *, one point; **, two points; -, no points.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3_2"><title>Demographics</title><p>A total of 18 studies (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>) examined the association of demographic factors with the development of EOCRC. Male sex (pooled OR=1.20; 95% CI, 1.08-1.33) (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>), Caucasian race (pooled OR=1.44; 95% CI, 1.15-1.80) (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>), and a family history of CRC (pooled OR=5.90; 95% CI, 3.67-9.48) (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>) were significantly associated with the development of EOCRC (<xref rid="f2" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figure&#160;2</bold>
</xref>). There was significant heterogeneity in the effect estimates for all reported demographic factors (I<sup>2</sup>&gt;60%). We did not find heterogeneity through sensitivity analysis. Based on the remaining studies, significant positive associations were found between a low education level (OR=1.64; 95%CI, 1.45-1.84) (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>) and a family history of cancer (OR=11.66; 95%CI, 10.97-12.39) (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>) and EOCRC. Ghadirian et&#160;al. found a negative association between married status (OR=0.58; 95%CI, 0.48-0.84) (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>) and EOCRC.</p><fig position="float" id="f2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure&#160;2</label><caption><p>Demographic risk factors for EOCRC. <bold>(A)</bold> Male; <bold>(B)</bold> Caucasian; <bold>(C)</bold> Family History.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fonc-13-1132306-g002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3_3"><title>Chronic conditions</title><p>A total of 20 studies (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>) examined the association between chronic conditions and EOCRC. IBD was significantly associated with the development of EOCRC (pooled OR=4.43; 95% CI, 4.05-4.84) (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>), but the heterogeneity between studies was high (I<sup>2</sup>&gt;60%). Three forms of obesity analysis were used in this study: (1) obesity (BMI&#8805;30 kg/m<sup>2</sup>), (2) overweight (30 kg/m<sup>2</sup>&gt;BMI&gt;24.9 kg/m<sup>2</sup>), and (3) abdominal obesity. Obesity (pooled OR=1.52; 95%CI, 1.20-1.91) (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>) and abdominal obesity (pooled OR=1.22; 95%CI, 1.16-1.30) (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>) showed significant associations with EOCRC, but overweight was not significantly associated with EOCRC (pooled OR=1.06; 95%CI, 0.87-1.29) (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). Heterogeneity was high in obesity (I<sup>2 =</sup> 97%) and overweight (I<sup>2 =</sup> 79%), but not in abdominal obesity (I<sup>2 =</sup> 0%). In the sensitivity analysis for overweight, after excluding the study of Low et&#160;al. (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>), the remaining studies were homogeneous (I<sup>2 =</sup> 43%), and the results showed that overweight was significantly associated with the development of EOCRC (pooled OR=1.18; 95% CI, 1.12-1.25) (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">
<bold>Supplementary Material</bold>
</xref> Forest plot A). Liu et&#160;al. (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>) found that for every 5-unit increase in BMI, the risk of EOCRC was 20% higher (RR=1.20; 95%CI, 1.05-1.38). We analyzed the associations of hyperlipidemia and triglycerides with EOCRC. Hyperlipidemia was not associated with EOCRC (pooled OR=1.37; 95% CI, 0.94-1.99) (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>), but triglycerides were significantly associated with EOCRC (pooled OR=1.12; 95% CI, 1.08-1.18) (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). For hyperlipidemia, the heterogeneity was high (I<sup>2 =</sup> 99%), while the studies on triglycerides were homogeneous (I<sup>2 =</sup> 47%). Six studies (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>) assessed the relationship between hypertension and EOCRC, and the results demonstrated that hypertension was not associated with the development of EOCRC (pooled OR=1.33; 95% CI, 0.88-2.01), but the heterogeneity was high (I<sup>2 =</sup> 99%). After excluding the study by Syed et&#160;al. (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>), the heterogeneity decreased to I<sup>2 =</sup> 41%. The comprehensive results showed that hypertension was associated with EOCRC (pooled OR=1.16; 95% CI, 1.12-1.21) (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">
<bold>Supplementary Material</bold>
</xref> Forest plot B). The combined results of 13 studies (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>) showed that there was no significant difference between EOCRC and diabetes (pooled OR=1.63; 95%CI, 0.84-3.16), but high heterogeneity existed among studies (I<sup>2 =</sup> 100%). Three studies (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>) investigated the association between metabolic syndrome and EOCRC, and the results showed that metabolic syndrome was a high-risk factor for EOCRC (pooled OR=1.29; 95%CI, 1.15-1.45), but there was heterogeneity among studies (I<sup>2 =</sup> 55%) (<xref rid="f3" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figure&#160;3</bold>
</xref>). According to the remaining studies, a significantly higher risk of developing EOCRC was associated with chronic kidney disease in patients not undergoing dialysis (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>), primary breast tumors (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>), abdominal pain (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>), iron-deficiency anemia (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>), hematochezia (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>), rectal pain (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>), intestinal function changes (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>), and weight loss (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). A significantly lower risk of developing EOCRC was associated with hyperthyroidism (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="f3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure&#160;3</label><caption><p>Chronic conditions risk factors for EOCRC. <bold>(A)</bold> IBD (Inflammatory bowel disease); <bold>(B)</bold> Obesity; <bold>(C)</bold> Overweight; <bold>(D)</bold> Abdominal Obesity; <bold>(E)</bold> Hyperlipidemia; <bold>(F)</bold> Triglycerides; <bold>(G)</bold> Hypertension; <bold>(H)</bold> Diabetes; <bold>(I)</bold> MetS (Metabolic Syndrome).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fonc-13-1132306-g003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3_4"><title>Lifestyle behaviors and environmental factors</title><p>Twenty-two studies (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>) evaluated the association between lifestyle or environmental factors and EOCRC. Smoking and drinking were identified through self-reporting. Self-reported smoking was divided into two categories (current or past smoker <italic toggle="yes">vs</italic>. never-smoker) or three categories (current smoker, past smoker, and never-smoker). This study conducted a meta-analysis in the form of two classifications (current or past smoker <italic toggle="yes">vs</italic> never-smoker). The results of 11 studies (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>) showed that smoking increased the risk of EOCRC (pooled OR=1.44; 95% CI, 1.10-1.88), but the heterogeneity was high (I<sup>2 =</sup> 99%). Each study classified alcohol consumption by the number of drinks per week or the amount of alcohol consumed. In this study, alcohol consumption was analyzed in the form of two categories (alcohol consumption <italic toggle="yes">vs</italic> never alcohol consumption). Ten studies (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>) showed that alcohol consumption increased the risk of EOCRC (pooled OR=1.41; 95% CI, 1.22-1.62), but the heterogeneity was high (I<sup>2 =</sup> 83%). Five studies (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>) illustrated that sedentary behaviors increased the incidence of EOCRC (pooled OR=1.24; 95% CI, 1.05-1.46), and there was homogeneity (I<sup>2 =</sup> 11%). The results showed that aspirin (pooled OR=0.91; 95% CI, 0.43-1.90) (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>) and nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) (pooled OR=1.05; 95% CI, 0.93-1.20) (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>) were not associated with the development of EOCRC. There was heterogeneity for aspirin (I<sup>2 =</sup> 77%), while homogeneity was observed for NSAIDs (I<sup>2 =</sup> 6%). Nguyen et&#160;al. (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>) found that oral antibiotics were associated with the development of EOCRC (OR=1.18, 95% CI, 1.07, 1.29), but an inconsistent result was found by Chang et&#160;al. (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>) (OR=0.78, 95% CI, 0.47, 1.30), while McDowell et&#160;al. (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>) found that antibiotic consumption was associated with colon cancer (OR=1.49, 95% CI, 1.07, 2.07), but not with rectal cancer (OR=1.17, 95% CI, 0.75, 1.84). In terms of diet, red meat (pooled OR=1.10; 95% CI, 1.04-1.16) (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>), Western dietary patterns (pooled OR=1.43; 95% CI, 1.18-1.73) (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>), and sugar-sweetened beverages (pooled OR=1.55; 95% CI, 1.23-1.95) (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>, <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>) were associated with the development of EOCRC. Processed meat was not associated with EOCRC (pooled OR=1.26; 95% CI, 0.95-1.66) (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>), while vitamin D was a protective factor on EOCRC (pooled OR=0.72; 95% CI, 0.56-0.92) (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>) (<xref rid="f4" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figure&#160;4</bold>
</xref>). Heterogeneity only existed in processed meat (I<sup>2 =</sup> 59%), but after excluding the study of Archambault et&#160;al. (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>), the studies were homogeneous (I<sup>2 =</sup> 0%). The results indicated that processed meat was associated with the development of EOCRC (pooled OR=1.53; 95% CI, 1.13-2.06) (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">
<bold>Supplementary Material</bold>
</xref> Forest plot C). Among the remaining studies, a significantly higher risk of developing EOCRC was associated with the empirical dietary index for hyperinsulinemia (EDIH) (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>), the empirical lifestyle index for hyperinsulinemia (ELIH) (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>), and exposure to dust (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>), fumes (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>), wood (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>), metal dust (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>), and sulfur microbial diet (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). A significantly lower risk of developing EOCRC was associated with vegetables, fruits, prudent diet, fish, and consumption of &#946;-carotene, vitamin C, vitamin E, and folic acid (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="f4" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure&#160;4</label><caption><p>Lifestyle risk factors for EOCRC. <bold>(A)</bold> Smoking; <bold>(B)</bold> Alcohol Consumed; <bold>(C)</bold> Sedentary; <bold>(D)</bold> Aspirin; <bold>(E)</bold> NSAID; <bold>(F)</bold> Red Meat; <bold>(G)</bold> Westernized Dietary Pattern; <bold>(H)</bold> Sugar-Sweetened Beverage; <bold>(I)</bold> Processed meat; <bold>(J)</bold> Vitamin D.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fonc-13-1132306-g004.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>CRC is a global public health problem that seriously threatens human health. Although the overall incidence and mortality of CRC have tended to stabilize or decline in recent years, the incidence and mortality of EOCRC have shown an increasing trend, and EOCRC is usually diagnosed at later stages with a poor prognosis. Identifying risk factors for EOCRC is essential to reduce the growing burden of this disease.</p><p>In this systematic review and meta-analysis, we identified risk factors associated with demographics (male, Caucasian, family history), chronic conditions (IBD, obesity, overweight, abdominal obesity, hypertension, triglycerides, metabolic syndrome), and lifestyle or environmental factors (smoking, alcohol consumption, sedentary behaviors, sugar-sweetened beverages, red meat, processed meat, and Western dietary patterns). Although some of the factors (hyperlipidemia, diabetes) were statistically non-significant, they were suggestive and non-negligible risk factors. The study also found that vitamin D was a protective factor for EOCRC. Other potential risk factors included a family history of cancer, a low education level, chronic kidney disease, primary breast tumors, abdominal pain, intestinal function changes, iron-deficiency anemia, hematochezia, weight loss, exposure to dust, and diet-related factors.</p><p>Male sex, Caucasian race, and a family history of CRC were risk factors for EOCRC. The results were the same as those exhibited by O&#8217;Sullivan et&#160;al. (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). Individuals with a family history or CRC had a higher risk of CRC than the general population. Screening based on a family history of CRC has become an important screening strategy for early detection and prevention of EOCRC. Previous research also showed that people with a family history of other cancers had a higher risk of developing EOCRC. Therefore, future research also needs to examine whether a family history of other cancers before the age of 50 is related to an increased risk of EOCRC (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). Research on a family history of other cancers may guide more precise targeted screening strategies.</p><p>This study compared the effects of different degrees of obesity on EOCRC. We found that weight gain in young adults was associated with the risk of EOCRC. The results of this study were consistent with those of Li et&#160;al. (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Since Glover et&#160;al. (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>) did not define obesity and Kwak et&#160;al. (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>) only compared individuals with BMI&#8805;25 kg/m<sup>2</sup> with the general population, these 2 studies were not included for the analysis in this study. Glover et&#160;al. (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>) found that obesity was a risk factor for EOCRC (OR=1.82; 95% CI, 1.62-2.04), but Kwak et&#160;al. (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>) suggested that obesity was not related to EOCRC. Liu et&#160;al. concluded that the risk of CRC increased by 20% for every 5 units of BMI increase. The results of this study also demonstrated that obese individuals had a higher risk of CRC than overweight individuals. The reason why obesity was related to EOCRC may be that obesity is involved in the occurrence and development of CRC by affecting metabolism and inflammatory factors, including insulin and insulin-like growth factors, sex hormones, and adipokines. Further research has found that obesity can promote the occurrence of CRC by affecting DNA methylation. In young mice, obesity can promote oxidation of long-chain fatty acids to increase the number of stem cells or stem cell-like cells in intestinal tissues (<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>). These findings also provide new clues to explain the mechanism by which obesity promotes EORC. Therefore, interventions to prevent obesity and strengthen obesity management in adolescents and young people are crucial to reduce the incidence of EOCRC.</p><p>No statistically significant difference was found between diabetes and hyperlipidemia and EOCRC in the present study, but this result was contrary to that reported by Breau et&#160;al. (<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>). Breau et&#160;al. assessed cross-sectional studies, while our study investigated case-control studies and cohort studies, and differences in the included literature may have influenced the results. In a Swedish national cohort study (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>), more than 100,000 patients diagnosed with diabetes before the age of 50 were included. Diabetes was shown to be associated with a 1.9-fold increased risk of EOCRC. However, some studies found that diabetes was not associated with EOCRC (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). Given the increasing prevalence of diabetes in young people and the potential impact of CRC screening guidelines, more studies are required to confirm this relationship. Hyperlipidemia and hypertension are both associated with the development of CRC, but there is insufficient research on the relationship with EOCRC. More studies are needed in the future to assess whether hyperlipidemia is associated with the development of EOCRC, and to include triglyceride and cholesterol levels in the analysis at the same time, thereby identifying individuals at a high risk of EOCRC and benefiting from earlier screening.</p><p>Poor lifestyles were associated with EOCRC. Smoking has always been recognized as a risk factor for EOCRC, but the results of O&#8217;Sullivan et&#160;al. (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>) suggested that smoking was not associated with the development of EOCRC, which was contrary to the results of this study. On the one hand, O&#8217;Sullivan et&#160;al. (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>) comprehensively analyzed the results of cross-sectional studies, case-control studies, and cohort studies; on the other hand, only 5 studies were included for the meta-analysis, which may have a certain impact on the results of the study. Nicotine, an alkaloid in tobacco, can induce and promote the proliferation of colon cancer cells and the formation of tumor blood vessels (<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>). Diet is an important factor affecting EOCRC. The Western diet, which is high in saturated fat, rich in red meat, and low in fiber, has become a well-known risk factor for CRC. Adherence to a healthier diet, such as the Mediterranean diet, can help prevent CRC (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>). Nguyen et&#160;al. (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>) suggested that a high-sulfur microbial diet would increase the incidence of EOCRC (OR=1.13; 95% CI, 1.10-1.56). Microbes can metabolize sulfur in the diet to produce hydrogen sulfide, which is a gastrointestinal carcinogen. A healthy diet allows a more beneficial intestinal microbiota and may reduce the risk of CRC. Therefore, it is necessary to take public health measures against the unhealthy lifestyles and eating habits of young people to reduce the incidence of EOCRC.</p><p>Low et&#160;al. (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>) found that aspirin had a protective effect on EOCRC, while McDowell et&#160;al. (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>) reported that aspirin was not associated with the development of EOCRC. Considering the chemical protective potential of aspirin against CRC, the relationship between aspirin and EOCRC needs to be further evaluated. Studies on whether antibiotics play a role in EOCRC have varied. McDowell et&#160;al. (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>) analyzed the effects of antibiotics on colon and rectal cancers separately and concluded that antibiotics only increased the risk of colon cancer. The correlation between different antibiotic types, different tumor sites and different ages needs further analysis. However, due to the limited number of studies included, whether these factors are related to the development of EOCRC remains to be further studied.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Limitations</title><p>1) Most of the included studies used data from databases, with Danial et&#160;al. (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>), Syed et&#160;al. (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>), and Glover et&#160;al. (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>) using the Explorys database, and Kim et&#160;al. (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>), Zheng et&#160;al. (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>), Yue et&#160;al. (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>), Nguyen et&#160;al. (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>), Joh et&#160;al. (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>), Hur et&#160;al. (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>), Liu et&#160;al. (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>) using the Nurses&#8217; Health Study II database, which made it possible for some data to be calculated multiple times. In addition, using the same database would lead to a decrease in the diversity of the population. 2) We only included studies published in English and may have omitted non-English studies. 3) We only searched for peer-reviewed journal studies and may have overlooked unpublished data. 4) Risk estimates for most risk factors were highly heterogeneous across studies. 5) Confounding factors were not controlled in some research results, which may lead to bias in the results. 6) Some of the results may have a publication bias.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s6"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Smoking, drinking, sedentary behaviors, red meat, processed meat, sugary drinks, and Western dietary patterns were modifiable risk factors for EOCRC. IBD, obesity, high triglycerides, and hypertension were risk factors that are difficult to be changed by interventions. Although our study identified risk factors for EOCRC, further research is needed for validation and explore other aspects of EOCRC etiology to inform primary and secondary prevention measures. At the same time, our study provides the basis for the future construction of EOCRC risk prediction models to identify high-risk individuals and develop more targeted screening strategies, which in turn can better allocate resources to those most in need to cope with the global growth of EOCRC.</p></sec><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s7"><title>Author contributions</title><p>All the authors contributed to the study design. QJ and XX screened abstracts and full-text articles for inclusion. QJ and PS appraised study quality. Any disagreements or uncertainties during the screening and quality appraisal process were referred to HH. QJ drafted the manuscript, which was reviewed, edited, and approved by HH. All authors contributed to the article and approved the submitted version.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors sincerely thank all colleagues of Nursing division of Colorectal for their generous support for the study.</p></ack><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s9"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s10"><title>Publisher&#8217;s note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s11"><title>Supplementary material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fonc.2023.1132306/full#supplementary-material" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fonc.2023.1132306/full#supplementary-material</ext-link>
</p><supplementary-material id="SM1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="DataSheet_1.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferlay</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soerjomataram</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torre</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jemal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Global cancer statistics 2018: GLOBOCAN estimates of incidence and mortality worldwide for 36 cancers in 185 countries</article-title>. <source>CA Cancer J Clin</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>68</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>394</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>424</lpage>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3322/caac.21492</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30207593</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sinicrope</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Increasing incidence of early-onset colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>386</volume>(<issue>16</issue>):<page-range>1547&#8211;58</page-range>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMra2200869</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35443109</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fedewa</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Colorectal cancer incidence patterns in the united states, 1974-2013</article-title>. <source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>109</volume>(<issue>8</issue>). doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jnci/djw322</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6059239</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28376186</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feletto</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>XQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lew</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>St John</surname><given-names>DJB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Macrae</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Trends in colon and rectal cancer incidence in Australia from 1982 to 2014: analysis of data on over 375,000 cases</article-title>. <source>Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>28</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>83</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>90</lpage>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/1055-9965.EPI-18-0523</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30530848</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Sullivan</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hilsden</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heitman</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The incidence of young-onset colorectal cancer in Canada continues to increase</article-title>. <source>Cancer Epidemiol</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>69</volume>:<elocation-id>101828</elocation-id>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.canep.2020.101828</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32998071</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lui</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsoi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>FCH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kyaw</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Global increasing incidence of young-onset colorectal cancer across 5 continents: a joinpoint regression analysis of 1,922,167 cases</article-title>. <source>Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>28</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<page-range>1275&#8211;82</page-range>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/1055-9965.EPI-18-1111</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31113868</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>You</surname><given-names>YN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bednarski</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez-Bigas</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Skibber</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Increasing disparities in the age-related incidences of colon and rectal cancers in the united states, 1975-2010</article-title>. <source>JAMA Surg</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>150</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>17</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>22</lpage>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamasurg.2014.1756</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25372703</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4666003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaborowski</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdile</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adamina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Warrier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wexner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Wilt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Characteristics of early-onset vs late-onset colorectal cancer: a review</article-title>. <source>JAMA Surg</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>156</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<page-range>865&#8211;74</page-range>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamasurg.2021.2380</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34190968</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karlitz</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lieu</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boland</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The rising tide of early-onset colorectal cancer: a comprehensive review of epidemiology, clinical features, biology, risk factors, prevention, and early detection</article-title>. <source>Lancet Gastroenterol Hepatol</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>7</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<page-range>262&#8211;74</page-range>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2468-1253(21)00426-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35090605</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bj&#248;rge</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Engeland</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tverdal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Body mass index in adolescence in relation to cause-specific mortality: a follow-up of 230,000 Norwegian adolescents</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>168</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<page-range>30&#8211;7</page-range>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aje/kwn096</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18477652</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hales</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fryar</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogden</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence of obesity and severe obesity among adults: united states, 2017-2018</article-title>. <source>NCHS Data Brief</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>360)</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32487284</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Risk factors associated with early-onset colorectal neoplasm in Chinese youth: a prospective population-based study</article-title>. <source>Front Oncol</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<elocation-id>702322</elocation-id>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fonc.2021.702322</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34692479</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8531514</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Low</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Demb</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Earles</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bustamante</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Risk factors for early-onset colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>159</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>492</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>501</lpage>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2020.01.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31926997</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7343609</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Sullivan</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sutherland</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Town</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Risk factors for early-onset colorectal cancer: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>20</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<page-range>1229&#8211;40</page-range>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cgh.2021.01.037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33524598</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Glover</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mansoor</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Panhwar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parasa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Epidemiology of colorectal cancer in average risk adults 20-39 years of age: a population-based national study</article-title>. <source>Dig Dis Sci</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>64</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<page-range>3602&#8211;9</page-range>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10620-019-05690-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6858534</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31175493</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frug&#233;</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heslin</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lipke</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Diet as a risk factor for early-onset colorectal adenoma and carcinoma: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Front Nutr</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<elocation-id>896330</elocation-id>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnut.2022.896330</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35757246</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9218641</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boakye</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmeister</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Association of body mass index with risk of early-onset colorectal cancer: systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Am J Gastroenterol</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>116</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<page-range>2173&#8211;83</page-range>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14309/ajg.0000000000001393</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8560162</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34309586</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moher</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liberati</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tetzlaff</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Preferred reporting items for systematic reviews and meta-analyses: the PRISMA statement</article-title>. <source>PloS Med</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>6</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<elocation-id>e1000097</elocation-id>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1000097</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19621072</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2707599</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stroup</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berlin</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morton</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olkin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rennie</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Meta-analysis of observational studies in epidemiology: a proposal for reporting. meta-analysis of observational studies in epidemiology (MOOSE) group</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source> (<year>2000</year>) <volume>283</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<page-range>2008&#8211;12</page-range>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.283.15.2008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10789670</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The Newcastle-Ottawa scale (NOS) for assessing the quality of non-randomised studies in meta-Analyses[C]</article-title>. <source>Symposium Systematic Reviews: Beyond Basics.</source> (<year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kwak</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>YO</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence of colorectal adenomas in asymptomatic young adults: a window to early intervention</article-title>? <source>Scand J Gastroenterol</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>51</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<page-range>731&#8211;8</page-range>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/00365521.2015.1130163</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26863602</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Puzzono</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mannucci</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Leo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zuppardo</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ditonno</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Diet and lifestyle habits in early-onset colorectal cancer. a pilot case-control study</article-title>. <source>Dig Dis</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>40</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<page-range>710&#8211;718</page-range>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000521932</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35086089</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Batyrbekova</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roelstraete</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khalili</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Antibiotic therapy and risk of early-onset colorectal cancer: a national case-control study</article-title>. <source>Clin Transl Gastroenterol</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<elocation-id>e437</elocation-id>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14309/ctg.0000000000000437</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8806371</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35029165</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mcdowell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perrott</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murchie</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cardwell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Samuel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Oral antibiotic use and early-onset colorectal cancer: findings from a case-control study using a national clinical database</article-title>. <source>Br J Cancer</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>126</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<page-range>957&#8211;67</page-range>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41416-021-01665-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8927122</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34921228</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boakye</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang-Claude</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmeister</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Associations of body mass index at different ages with early-onset colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>162</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<page-range>1088&#8211;97</page-range>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2021.12.239</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34914944</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association between metabolic syndrome and the risk of colorectal cancer diagnosed before age 50 years according to tumor location</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>163</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<page-range>637&#8211;48</page-range>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2022.05.032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35643169</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harra</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morin</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Faria</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghitulescu</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Understanding the burden of colorectal adenomas in patients younger than 50 years: a Large single-center retrospective cohort study</article-title>. <source>Dis Colon Rectum</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>65</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<page-range>901&#8211;8</page-range>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/DCR.0000000000002069</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34897208</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Danial</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Youssef</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maryam</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moein</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liliane</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Risk factors of young-onset colorectal cancer: analysis of a Large population-based registry</article-title>. <source>Can J Gastroenterol Hepatol</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>2022</volume>:<elocation-id>3582443</elocation-id>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2022/3582443</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35223684</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8866030</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Archambault</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Nongenetic determinants of risk for early-onset colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>JNCI Cancer Spectr</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>5</volume>(<issue>3</issue>). doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jncics/pkab029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8134523</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34041438</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lipsyc-Sharf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hur</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Total vitamin d intake and risks of early-onset colorectal cancer and precursors</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>161</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<page-range>1208&#8211;17</page-range>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2021.07.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8463427</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34245763</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hur</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Comprehensive assessment of diet quality and risk of precursors of early-onset colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>113</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<page-range>543&#8211;52</page-range>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jnci/djaa164</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8096368</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33136160</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yue</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hur</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tabung</surname><given-names>FK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Prospective evaluation of dietary and lifestyle pattern indices with risk of colorectal cancer in a cohort of younger women</article-title>. <source>Ann Oncol</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>32</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<page-range>778&#8211;86</page-range>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.annonc.2021.03.200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8862727</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33812017</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schumacher</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Attaluri</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McLemore</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Metabolic risk factors associated with early-onset colorectal adenocarcinoma: a case-control study at kaiser permanente southern California</article-title>. <source>Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>30</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<page-range>1792&#8211;8</page-range>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/1055-9965.EPI-20-1127</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34301728</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hur</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sikavi</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The sulfur microbial diet is associated with increased risk of early-onset colorectal cancer precursors</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>161</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<page-range>1423&#8211;32</page-range>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2021.07.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8545755</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34273347</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Joh</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hur</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nimptsch</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Joung</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Simple sugar and sugar-sweetened beverage intake during adolescence and risk of colorectal cancer precursors</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>161</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<page-range>128&#8211;42</page-range>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2021.03.028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8238879</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33753105</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hur</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Metabolic syndrome, metabolic comorbid conditions and risk of early-onset colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>Gut</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>70</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<page-range>1147&#8211;54</page-range>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/gutjnl-2020-321661</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8032822</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33037055</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hur</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Otegbeye</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Joh</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nimptsch</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Sugar-sweetened beverage intake in adulthood and adolescence and risk of early-onset colorectal cancer among women</article-title>. <source>Gut</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>70</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<page-range>2330&#8211;6</page-range>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/gutjnl-2020-323450</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8571123</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33958435</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>VC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cotterchio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tinmouth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Risk factors for early-onset colorectal cancer: a population-based case-control study in Ontario, Canada</article-title>. <source>Cancer Causes Control</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>32</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<page-range>1063&#8211;83</page-range>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10552-021-01456-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8416813</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34120288</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Demb</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doubeni</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mart&#237;nez</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Young-onset colorectal cancer risk among individuals with iron-deficiency anaemia and haematochezia</article-title>. <source>Gut</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>70</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<page-range>1529&#8211;37</page-range>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/gutjnl-2020-321849</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8284839</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33443020</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dash</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nomura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Obesity is an initiator of colon adenomas but not a promoter of colorectal cancer in the black women&#8217;s health study</article-title>. <source>Cancer Causes Control</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>31</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>291</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>302</lpage>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10552-020-01283-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32124186</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7144805</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gausman</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dornblaser</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anand</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Connell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Risk factors associated with early-onset colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>18</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<page-range>2752&#8211;9</page-range>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cgh.2019.10.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7153971</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31622737</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>L&#8217;Heureux</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wieland</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association between thyroid disorders and colorectal cancer risk in adult patients in Taiwan</article-title>. <source>JAMA Netw Open</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>2</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<elocation-id>e193755</elocation-id>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2019.3755</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31099862</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6537921</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zauber</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association of obesity with risk of early-onset colorectal cancer among women</article-title>. <source>JAMA Oncol</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>37</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>44</lpage>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamaoncol.2018.4280</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30326010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6382547</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Syed</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thakkar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Horne</surname><given-names>ZD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdul-Baki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kochhar</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farah</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Old vs new: risk factors predicting early onset colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>World J Gastrointest Oncol</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>11</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<page-range>1011&#8211;20</page-range>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4251/wjgo.v11.i11.1011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6883185</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31798781</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keum</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Sedentary behaviors, TV viewing time, and risk of young-onset colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>JNCI Cancer Spectr</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>2</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>y73</fpage>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jncics/pky073</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6361621</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30740587</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Levi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kark</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Twig</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Derazne</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tzur</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Adolescent body mass index and risk of colon and rectal cancer in a cohort of 1.79 million Israeli men and women: a population-based study</article-title>. <source>Cancer</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>123</volume>(<issue>20</issue>):<page-range>4022&#8211;30</page-range>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cncr.30819</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28736986</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Risk of colorectal cancer in chronic kidney disease: a matched cohort study based on administrative data</article-title>. <source>Ann Surg Oncol</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>20</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<page-range>3885&#8211;91</page-range>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1245/s10434-013-3065-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23807660</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>S&#248;ndergaard</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mortensen</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalton</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Osler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Social inequality in breast, lung and colorectal cancers: a sibling approach</article-title>. <source>BMJ Open</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>3</volume>(<issue>3</issue>). doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2012-002114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3612771</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23503576</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosato</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bosetti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Polesel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zucchetto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Negri</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Risk factors for young-onset colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>Cancer Causes Control</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>24</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<page-range>335&#8211;41</page-range>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10552-012-0119-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23224326</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghadirian</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maisonneuve</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perret</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lacroix</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boyle</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Epidemiology of sociodemographic characteristics, lifestyle, medical history, and colon cancer: a case-control study among French canadians in Montreal</article-title>. <source>Cancer Detect Prev</source> (<year>1998</year>) <volume>22</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>396</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>404</lpage>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1525-1500.1998.00058.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9727620</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Negri</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Braga</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>La Vecchia</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Franceschi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Filiberti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Montella</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Family history of cancer and risk of colorectal cancer in Italy</article-title>. <source>Br J Cancer</source> (<year>1998</year>) <volume>77</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<page-range>174&#8211;9</page-range>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/bjc.1998.28</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2151250</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9459165</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fuchs</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giovannucci</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Colditz</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Speizer</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Willett</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A prospective study of family history and the risk of colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source> (<year>1994</year>) <volume>331</volume>(<issue>25</issue>):<page-range>1669&#8211;74</page-range>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJM199412223312501</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7969357</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>St</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mcdermott</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hopper</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Debney</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cancer risk in relatives of patients with common colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source> (<year>1993</year>) <volume>118</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<page-range>785&#8211;90</page-range>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/0003-4819-118-10-199305150-00005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8470852</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garabrant</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mack</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A case-control study of occupational and dietary factors in colorectal cancer in young men by subsite</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source> (<year>1989</year>) <volume>49</volume>(<issue>19</issue>):<page-range>5459&#8211;68</page-range>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/bjc.1989.330</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2766308</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Breau</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Risk factors associated with young-onset colorectal adenomas and cancer: a systematic review and meta-analysis of observational research</article-title>. <source>Cancer Control</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>27</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1148411934</fpage>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1073274820976670</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8480354</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33274652</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>KU</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fallah</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sundquist</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sundquist</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Personal history of diabetes as important as family history of colorectal cancer for risk of colorectal cancer: a nationwide cohort study</article-title>. <source>Am J Gastroenterol</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>115</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<page-range>1103&#8211;9</page-range>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14309/ajg.0000000000000669</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32618661</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grimm</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mav</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmeister</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Transcriptome and DNA methylome analysis in a mouse model of diet-induced obesity predicts increased risk of colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>Cell Rep</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>22</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<page-range>624&#8211;37</page-range>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14309/ajg.0000000000001393</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5793878</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29346762</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrari</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jenab</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Norat</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moskal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Slimani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Lifetime and baseline alcohol intake and risk of colon and rectal cancers in the European prospective investigation into cancer and nutrition (EPIC)</article-title>. <source>Int J Cancer</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>121</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<page-range>2065&#8211;72</page-range>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ijc.22966</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17640039</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hojman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gehl</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Molecular mechanisms linking exercise to cancer prevention and treatment</article-title>. <source>Cell Metab</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>27</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>10</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21</lpage>. doi:&#160;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmet.2017.09.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29056514</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>