<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Am J Clin Oncol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Am J Clin Oncol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2035</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">lwwopen</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">COC</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>American Journal of Clinical Oncology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0277-3732</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1537-453X</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>Lippincott Open Access</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11837954</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11837954.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11837954</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11837954</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39498908</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/COC.0000000000001155</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AJCO-24-169</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-version article-version-type="Version of Record" vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf">3</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Articles: Thoracic</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Complications, Costs, and Health Care Resource Use with Tissue Biopsy Followed by Liquid Biopsy Versus Tissue Re-biopsy in Patients With Newly Diagnosed Metastatic Nonsmall-cell Lung Cancer</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names initials="A">Anne</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">*</xref><email>anne.shah@astrazeneca.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Apple</surname><given-names initials="J">Jon</given-names></name><degrees>PharmD, MS</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">*</xref><email>jon.apple@astrazeneca.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aslam</surname><given-names initials="S">Saad</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">&#8224;</xref><email>saslam30@hotmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Engel-Nitz</surname><given-names initials="NM">Nicole M.</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">&#8224;</xref><email>Nicole.engel-nitz@optum.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Le</surname><given-names initials="L">Lisa</given-names></name><degrees>MS</degrees><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">&#8224;</xref><email>lisa.le@optum.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Terpenning</surname><given-names initials="M">Marilou</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">&#8225;</xref><email>mterpenningmd@gmail.com</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>*</label>AstraZeneca Pharmaceuticals, PLC, Gaithersburg, MD</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>&#8224;</label>Optum, Eden Prairie, MN</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>&#8225;</label>Marilou Terpenning, MD, Ltd., Eagle, ID</aff><author-notes><corresp>Correspondence: Nicole M. Engel-Nitz, PhD, MN950-1000, 11000 Optum Circle, Eden Prairie, MN 55344. E-mail: <email>nicole.engel-nitz@optum.com</email>.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>3</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>05</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>48</volume><issue>3</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">482538</issue-id><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>135</lpage><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>19</day><month>02</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>20</day><month>02</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-02-23 05:25:28.283"><day>23</day><month>02</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2024 The Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-Non Commercial-No Derivatives License 4.0</ext-link> (CCBY-NC-ND), where it is permissible to download and share the work provided it is properly cited. The work cannot be changed in any way or used commercially without permission from the journal. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>
</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="coc-48-127.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="coc-48-127.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Objectives:</title><p>We compared complications, costs, and health care resource utilization (HCRU) of patients with newly diagnosed metastatic nonsmall-cell lung cancer (mNSCLC) who had a tissue biopsy followed by either liquid biopsy (TFLB) (identified with a novel algorithm) or tissue re-biopsy (TRB).</p></sec><sec><title>Methods:</title><p>This claims-based retrospective analysis included commercial and Medicare Advantage members in the Optum Research Database with mNSCLC (January 2017 to June 2021) and &#8805;2 tissue biopsy claims (7 to 90&#160;d apart) (TRB) or &#8805;1 tissue and &#8805;1 liquid biopsy claim within 90 days (TFLB). Patients in the TFLB group were matched 1:1 to patients in the TRB group using propensity score matching. Surgical biopsy-related complications and complication-related and all-cause medical costs and HCRU during the 6-month follow-up were compared.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>Both groups had 235 patients post-match. During the follow-up, the surgical biopsy-related complication rate was lower in the TFLB group than the TRB group (65.1% [153/235] vs. 84.7% [199/235], <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.001). Mean complication-related medical costs were significantly lower with TFLB ($8494 vs. $19,741, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.001) during the follow-up; mean (SD) duration of complication-related inpatient stays was significantly lower with TFLB (3.5 [7.0] vs. 6.6 [13.3]&#160;d, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.002). Mean all-cause medical costs were not significantly different between the groups; the TFLB group had fewer all-cause inpatient stays, inpatient days, and outpatient visits.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions:</title><p>Multiple tissue biopsy procedures may be associated with significantly higher biopsy complication rates, higher complication-related medical costs, and longer complication-related inpatient stays than TFLB. All-cause medical costs were similar between groups.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><title>Key Words:</title><kwd>costs</kwd><kwd>health economics</kwd><kwd>liquid biopsy</kwd><kwd>nonsmall-cell lung cancer</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>SDC</meta-name><meta-value>T</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name><meta-value>TRUE</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Lung cancer was projected to cause more than 127,000 deaths in the United States in 2023.<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> Worldwide, lung cancer leads to &#8764;1.8 million deaths annually.<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> The most common form, nonsmall-cell lung cancer (NSCLC), accounts for 80% to 85% of lung cancer cases.<sup><xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> This form is associated with high mortality, and patients with NSCLC have a 5-year relative survival rate of only 25%.<sup><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> More than 50% of patients with NSCLC have metastatic NSCLC (mNSCLC) at diagnosis, and patients with mNSCLC have an especially poor prognosis, with only 6% surviving 5 years after diagnosis.<sup><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup>
</p><p>Molecular-based therapies have improved outcomes such as objective response rate and progression-free survival for patients with mNSCLC that is driven by actionable mutations.<sup><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> Targeted therapies are recommended to treat mNSCLC with confirmed aberrations in several genes, including epidermal growth factor receptor (<italic toggle="yes">EGFR</italic>); KRAS proto-oncogene, GTPase (<italic toggle="yes">KRAS</italic>); ALK receptor tyrosine kinase (<italic toggle="yes">ALK</italic>); ROS proto-oncogene 1, receptor tyrosine kinase (<italic toggle="yes">ROS1</italic>); B-Raf proto-oncogene, serine/threonine kinase (<italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic>); neurotrophic tyrosine receptor kinase (<italic toggle="yes">NTRK</italic>); MET proto-oncogene, receptor tyrosine kinase (<italic toggle="yes">MET</italic>); ret proto-oncogene (<italic toggle="yes">RET</italic>); and erb-b2 receptor tyrosine kinase 2 (<italic toggle="yes">ERBB2</italic>).<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> NCCN Clinical Practice Guidelines in Oncology (NCCN Guidelines&#174;) for Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer recommend, when feasible, broad molecular profiling to identify these and other biomarkers to optimize targeted treatment.<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup>
</p><p>Until recently, tissue biopsy testing was the standard of care for pathologic confirmation of NSCLC and for predictive biomarker detection to guide targeted therapy use.<sup><xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> However, such procedures carry a risk of complications such as pneumonia and other infections, pneumothorax, hemothorax, hemoptysis, air embolism, breathing difficulties, severe chest pain, and, potentially, death, with a surgical mortality rate of 1.5% to 3.9%.<sup><xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> The European Society for Medical Oncology (ESMO)<sup><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> and the International Association for the Study of Lung Cancer (IASLC)<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> recommend next-generation sequencing (NGS) to facilitate simultaneous testing of multiple target genes in NSCLC samples. Simultaneous testing with NGS has transformed molecular analysis by identifying a range of actionable mutations at once rather than testing potential mutations individually.<sup><xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> In an economic model comparing actionable mutation testing with NGS to polymerase chain reaction testing in mNSCLC, NGS markedly shortened the time to appropriate targeted therapy while decreasing costs.<sup><xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup>
</p><p>As more targeted therapies become available, testing for all actionable mutations has presented challenges, including limited tissue availability and prolonged wait times.<sup><xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> In an observational study, patients with advanced NSCLC with actionable mutations had an average wait of 46.5 days from diagnosis to positive biomarker test.<sup><xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> Difficulty accessing some tumors and tumor heterogeneity may also limit the feasibility of tissue biopsy.<sup><xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> Such issues can lead to underreporting of genotypes and missed opportunities for targeted treatment.<sup><xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> Liquid biopsy, in which circulating tumor DNA is genotyped to identify mutations,<sup><xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> is gaining acceptance as a complement to tissue biopsy for genetic testing for NSCLC.<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> This technique can provide additional information to facilitate therapeutic decision-making in cases of insufficient biopsy tissue.<sup><xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> Liquid biopsy is also less invasive,<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> and results can be obtained more rapidly,<sup><xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> which improves disease management and prognosis.<sup><xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> Liquid biopsy, coupled with tissue biopsy, is predicted to identify actionable mutations more effectively than tissue biopsy alone while also reducing costs.<sup><xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup>
</p><p>Recommendations from IASLC and ESMO support the use of liquid biopsy in NSCLC. IASLC considers liquid biopsy testing a valid complement to tissue biopsy genotyping for tumors of patients with newly diagnosed advanced NSCLC.<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> ESMO recommends liquid biopsy NGS assays as a complement or alternative to tissue NGS to identify actionable mutations in treatment-naive patients with NSCLC, especially when tissue biopsy could delay treatment, when invasive procedures may pose a risk to the patient or may be contraindicated, or if bone is the only site for biopsy.<sup><xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> Liquid biopsy is increasingly used as a component of mNSCLC diagnosis to effectively genotype tumors and detect actionable gene mutations less invasively, but the role of liquid biopsy as a companion or follow-up test to avoid tissue re-biopsy (TRB) has not been compared with traditional biopsies in terms of complications, costs, and use of resources. Real-world data regarding complications and complication-related medical costs and health care resource use (HCRU) are needed.</p><p>This study, which used a newly developed algorithm to identify liquid biopsies in claims data, is the first claims-based analysis comparing outcomes of patients with mNSCLC who had a tissue biopsy followed by a liquid biopsy (TFLB) with outcomes of patients whose initial tissue biopsy was followed by a TRB. The surgical biopsy-related complications, complication-related medical costs and HCRU, and all-cause medical costs and HCRU 6 months after and including the date of the first tissue biopsy claim were compared between the 2 groups.</p><sec sec-type="methods"><title>METHODS</title><sec><title>Study Design and Data Source</title><p>This administrative claims-based retrospective analysis included commercial and Medicare Advantage Part D members diagnosed with mNSCLC between January 1, 2017, and June 30, 2021 (identification period). Data were obtained from the Optum Research Database (ORD), Optum&#8217;s proprietary administrative claims research database. The ORD, which is fully de-identified and compliant with the Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act of 1996, comprises medical and pharmacy claims data from 1993 to the present on more than 73 million lives. Institutional review board approval was not required because all patient data were anonymized.</p></sec><sec sec-type="subjects"><title>Patient Selection and Observation Period</title><p>Inclusion criteria for the study included &#8805;2 nondiagnostic claims with codes for lung cancer (International Statistical Classification of Diseases, Tenth Revision [ICD-10]: C34xx) in any position &#8805;30 and &#8804;180 days apart during the identification period (the date of the first claim was the diagnosis index date); and a metastatic code (visceral [ICD-10: C78.XX; C79.XX, C80.XX] or lymph node [ICD-10: C77.X]) in any position during the 60 days before or after the diagnosis index date (the date of the first metastatic claim was the metastatic index date; the study index date was the earliest of the diagnosis and the metastatic index dates). To identify relevant patients with biopsies, &#8805;2 biopsy claims were required; the first claim was required to have been for a tissue biopsy that occurred within 90 days of the index date (on or before January 1, 2021), and the second claim could be for a tissue biopsy (re-biopsy) or a liquid biopsy occurring on or within 90 days after the first tissue biopsy claim. An algorithm was developed to define applicable procedure codes to identify liquid biopsy within the genomic testing domain (Supplemental Digital Content 1 for details, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/AJCO/A540" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/AJCO/A540</ext-link>). Patients were required to have: evidence of systemic cancer treatment after the first tissue biopsy claim; continuous enrollment with medical and pharmacy benefits &#8805;6 months before the first tissue biopsy (baseline period) and &#8805;6 months after and including the date of the first tissue biopsy (follow-up period), unless the patient died before the end of the follow-up; and be 18 years or older of age on the study index date.</p><p>Exclusion criteria included &#8805;1 nondiagnostic claim for lung cancer before the diagnosis index date; a metastatic code before the metastatic index date; claims evidence of smallcell-lung cancer (SCLC) treatment; claims evidence of pregnancy or clinical trial participation during the study period; claims evidence of tissue or liquid biopsy during the baseline period; &#8805;2 nondiagnostic claims, 30 days apart, for another cancer (except basal cell carcinoma or squamous cell carcinoma) during the baseline period; or claims evidence of systemic anticancer treatment during the baseline period.</p><p>Study groups were assigned according to the number of claims for tissue biopsy and the time between biopsies: the TRB group had &#8805;2 claims for tissue biopsy &#8805;7 days and &#8804;90 days apart, and the TFLB group had &#8805;1 claim for tissue biopsy and &#8805;1 claim for liquid biopsy within 90 days. In both groups, the first tissue biopsy claim occurred on or before January 1, 2021.</p></sec><sec sec-type="subjects"><title>Patient Characteristics and Outcomes</title><p>Sex, age, insurance type, and geographic region were reported as of the study index date. The Quan-Charlson comorbidity score<sup><xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> and Charlson comorbidities were assessed during the baseline period. To control for possible confounding, patients in the TFLB group were matched 1:1 by demographic and clinical characteristics to patients in the TRB group using propensity score matching. Bivariate comparisons of demographics and clinical characteristics were used to assess the success of the matching procedure. Patients not matched were excluded from the post-match analysis. Surgical biopsy-related complications and pharmacy, complication-related, and all-cause medical costs (not including pharmacy costs) and associated HCRU were assessed during the follow-up period (ie, 6&#160;mo after and including the date of the first tissue biopsy for both groups) and were compared between the matched TFLB and TRB groups.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical Analyses</title><p>All statistical analyses were performed using SAS 9.4 software (SAS Institute Inc., Cary, NC). Numbers and percentages were provided for dichotomous and polychotomous variables. Means and SDs were determined for continuous variables. Bivariate comparisons of baseline characteristics and outcome measures were provided, and appropriate tests (eg, <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test, and Pearson &#967;<sup>2</sup> test) were used based on the distribution of the measure. Because of the substantial percentage of patients with no complication-related medical costs, complication-related costs were compared using a 2-part model (ie, a logistic model estimating the probability of any cost and a generalized linear model [GLM] with a gamma distribution and log link estimating the level of cost among patients with cost &gt;$0).<sup><xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> Models were adjusted for age group (18 to 44&#160;y, 45 to 64&#160;y, 65&#160;y or older), sex, consumer-driven health care plan use, urban/rural location, region of the United States (Northeast, Midwest, South, West), index year, baseline Charlson comorbidity score category (0, 1 to 2, 3 to 4, &#8805;5), and specific comorbid conditions (chronic pulmonary disease, renal disease, diabetes with chronic complications). Results are reported as the odds ratio for the logistic regression, cost ratio for the GLM, and average costs predicted for the cohorts.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec sec-type="subjects"><title>Disposition and Patient Characteristics</title><p>Of 56,986 commercial or Medicare Advantage Part D health plan members with &#8805;2 nondiagnostic claims for lung cancer during the identification period, 1469 met the additional study criteria (Fig. <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Of these patients, 247 had &#8805;1 liquid biopsy claim and 823 had &#8805;2 tissue biopsy claims. After propensity score matching, 235 patients with &#8805;2 tissue biopsy claims (TRB group) were matched to 235 patients with &#8805;1 tissue biopsy claim and &#8805;1 liquid biopsy claim (TFLB group). Patient characteristics, insurance coverage, Quan-Charlson comorbidity scores, and specific comorbid conditions were not significantly different between the matched groups (Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). More than half of patients (55.5%) were female, and the mean (SD) age was 68.5 (8.7) years. Approximately 76% of patients were covered by Medicare, and the remaining were covered by commercial insurance. Mean (SD) Quan-Charlson comorbidity score was 1.6 (1.7) overall. The most common Charlson comorbidity was chronic pulmonary disease (47.0% of the total matched population), followed by any malignancy (21.5%), renal disease (11.7%), diabetes with chronic complications (10.2%), mild liver disease (7.4%), congestive heart failure (6.6%), and rheumatologic disease (5.3%).</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p>Patient disposition. *The index date was the earlier of the lung cancer diagnosis and the metastatic diagnosis dates. <sup>&#8224;</sup>Includes having prior lung cancer diagnosis (ie, &#8805;1 nondiagnostic claims for lung cancer before the diagnosis date); evidence of another cancer, except basal cell carcinoma or squamous cell carcinoma (&#8805;2 nondiagnostic claims, &#8805;30 days apart during the baseline period); claims evidence of pregnancy during the study period; and claims evidence of being in a clinical trial during the study period. <sup>&#8225;</sup>Or &lt;6 months after the index date if there was evidence of death. <sup>&#167;</sup>Patients in the TFLB group were matched 1:1 by demographic and clinical characteristics to patients in the TRB group using propensity score matching to control for possible confounding. TFLB indicates tissue biopsy followed by liquid biopsy; TRB, tissue re-biopsy.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="coc-48-127-g001.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>TABLE 1</label><caption><p>Patient Characteristics and Insurance Coverage During the Baseline Period After Propensity Score Matching</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" axis="1" rowspan="1">Characteristic</th><th align="center" colspan="1" axis="1" rowspan="1">Total (N=470), n (%)</th><th align="center" colspan="1" axis="1" rowspan="1">TFLB (n=235), n (%)</th><th align="center" colspan="1" axis="1" rowspan="1">TRB (n=235), n (%)</th><th align="center" colspan="1" axis="1" rowspan="1">Difference (95% CI)<xref rid="T1fn1" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>
</th><th align="center" colspan="1" axis="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
<xref rid="T1fn2" ref-type="table-fn">&#8224;</xref>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Female</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">261 (55.5)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">133 (56.6)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">128 (54.5)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.1 (&#8722;6.9, 11.1)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.643</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mean age, years (SD)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68.5 (8.7)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68.5 (9.3)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68.5 (8.1)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;0.01 (&#8722;1.6, 1.6)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.987</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Insurance type</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Commercial</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">112 (23.8)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57 (24.3)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55 (23.4)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9 (&#8722;6.9, 8.6)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.829</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Medicare</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">358 (76.2)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">178 (75.7)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">180 (76.6)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;0.9 (&#8722;8.6, 6.9)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.829</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Region of the United States</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Midwest</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">72 (15.3)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42 (17.9)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30 (12.8)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.1 (&#8722;1.4, 11.6)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.124</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Northeast</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64 (13.6)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30 (12.8)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34 (14.5)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;1.7 (&#8722;7.9, 4.5)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.591</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;South</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">306 (65.1)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">149 (63.4)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">157 (66.8)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;3.4 (&#8722;12.0, 5.2)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.439</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;West</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28 (6.0)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14 (6.0)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14 (6.0)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0 (&#8722;4.3, 4.3)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Quan-Charlson comorbidity score, mean (SD)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.6 (1.7)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.6 (1.6)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.6 (1.8)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;0.03 (&#8722;0.3, 0.3)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.851</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Charlson comorbidities in &#8805;5.0% of patients</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Chronic pulmonary disease</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">221 (47.0)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">110 (46.8)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">111 (47.2)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;0.4 (&#8722;9.5, 8.6)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.926</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Any malignancy</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101 (21.5)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52 (22.1)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49 (20.9)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.3 (&#8722;6.2, 8.7)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.736</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Renal disease</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55 (11.7)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 (11.5)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28 (11.9)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;0.4 (&#8722;6.2, 5.4)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.886</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Diabetes<xref rid="T1fn3" ref-type="table-fn">&#8225;</xref>
</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48 (10.2)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 (11.5)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21 (8.9)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.6 (&#8722;2.9, 8.0)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.361</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Mild liver disease</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35 (7.4)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19 (8.1)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 (6.8)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.3 (&#8722;3.5, 6.0)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.598</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Congestive heart failure</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31 (6.6)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17 (7.2)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14 (6.0)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.3 (&#8722;3.2, 5.8)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.577</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Rheumatologic disease</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25 (5.3)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (4.3)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 (6.4)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;2.1 (&#8722;6.2, 1.9)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.304</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other" id="T1fn1"><label>*</label><p>Difference between the TFLB and the TRB groups. Wald 95% CIs were used for difference in means of continuous measures and for difference in percentages of binary measures.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="T1fn2"><label>&#8224;</label><p>Two-sample <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test was used for continuous measures. Pearson &#967;<sup>2</sup> test was used for binary measures.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="T1fn3"><label>&#8225;</label><p>With chronic complications.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>TFLB indicates tissue biopsy followed by liquid biopsy; TRB, tissue re-biopsy.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Surgical Biopsy-related Complications</title><p>During the 6-month follow-up, the percentage of patients with any surgical biopsy-related complication was significantly lower in the TFLB group than the TRB group (65.1% [153 of 235] vs. 84.7% [199 of 235]; difference [95% CI]: &#8722;19.6% [&#8722;27.2, &#8722;11.9]; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.001) (Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Percentages of patients with the complications of pneumothorax, prolonged air leak (&gt;5&#160;d), and infection (ie, pneumonia, mediastinitis, empyema, abscess) during the 6-month follow-up were significantly lower with TFLB than TRB. The percentage of patients with thrombotic complications, hemorrhage, cardiovascular complications, death, and change to intubation or mechanical ventilation did not differ between the 2 groups.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>TABLE 2</label><caption><p>Surgical Biopsy-related Complications During the 6-month Follow-up</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" axis="1" rowspan="1">Complication</th><th align="center" colspan="1" axis="1" rowspan="1">TFLB (n=235), n (%)</th><th align="center" colspan="1" axis="1" rowspan="1">TRB (n=235), n (%)</th><th align="center" colspan="1" axis="1" rowspan="1">Difference (95% CI)<xref rid="T2fn1" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>
</th><th align="center" colspan="1" axis="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
<xref rid="T2fn2" ref-type="table-fn">&#8224;</xref>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Any surgical biopsy-related complication</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">153 (65.1)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">199 (84.7)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;19.6 (&#8722;27.2, &#8722;11.9)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pneumothorax</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41 (17.4)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">108 (46.0)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;28.5 (&#8722;36.5, &#8722;20.5)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prolonged air leak (&gt;5&#160;d)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (1.3)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28 (11.9)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;10.6 (&#8722;15.0, &#8722;6.3)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Infection<xref rid="T2fn3" ref-type="table-fn">&#8225;</xref>
</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">54 (23.0)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">75 (31.9)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;8.9 (&#8722;17.0, &#8722;0.9)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.030</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Thrombotic complications<xref rid="T2fn4" ref-type="table-fn">&#167;</xref>
</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31 (13.2)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 (8.5)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.7 (&#8722;0.9, 10.3)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.103</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hemorrhage</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33 (14.0)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43 (18.3)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;4.3 (&#8722;10.9, 2.4)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.210</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cardiovascular complications</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">91 (38.7)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99 (42.1)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;3.4 (&#8722;12.3, 5.5)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.452</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Death</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.4)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (2.6)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;2.1 (&#8722;4.3, 0.05)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.057</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Change to intubation or mechanical ventilation</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46 (19.6)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50 (21.3)</td><td align="char" char="(" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;1.7 (&#8722;9.0, 5.6)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.647</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other" id="T2fn1"><label>*</label><p>Pearson &#967;<sup>2</sup> test.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="T2fn2"><label>&#8224;</label><p>Wald 95% CIs.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="T2fn3"><label>&#8225;</label><p>Pneumonia, mediastinitis, empyema, abscess.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="T2fn4"><label>&#167;</label><p>Pulmonary emboli, deep vein thromboses.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>TFLB indicates tissue biopsy followed by liquid biopsy; TRB, tissue re-biopsy.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Complication-related Medical Costs and HCRU</title><p>Mean complication-related medical costs in the 6-month follow-up were significantly lower for the TFLB group than the TRB group ($8494 vs. $19,741; difference [95% CI], &#8722;$11,248 [&#8722;$15,665, &#8722;$6830]; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.001) (Fig. <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>A). Mean complication-related medical costs for inpatient stays and office visits were also significantly lower for patients in the TFLB group (inpatient stays: $8076 vs. $18,918; difference [95% CI], &#8722;$10,842 [&#8722;$15,166, &#8722;$6518]; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.001; office visits: $20 vs. $51; difference [95% CI], &#8722;$31 [&#8722;$61, &#8722;$2]; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.038). Mean complication-related medical costs for outpatient visits and emergency department visits were similar between groups.</p><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 2</label><caption><p>Complication-related medical costs (A) and HCRU (B) during the 6-month follow-up. *Tested for significance with Wald 95% confidence limits for differences in means of continuous measures and <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> tests for continuous measures. <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8805;0.05 are not shown. &#8224;Not including pharmacy costs. HCRU indicates health care resource utilization; TFLB, tissue biopsy followed by liquid biopsy; TRB, tissue re-biopsy.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="coc-48-127-g002.jpg"/></fig><p>Mean complication-related HCRU, including inpatient days, inpatient stays, outpatient visits, and office visits, were significantly lower with TFLB than TRB during the follow-up (Fig. <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>B). The groups had similar mean numbers of complication-related emergency department visits.</p><p>Results of the propensity score matching analysis of complication-related medical costs during the 6-month follow-up were confirmed in a 2-part incremental adjusted costs model, in which estimated complication-related medical costs were $9862 lower for the TFLB group (Table <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3" orientation="portrait"><label>TABLE 3</label><caption><p>Adjusted Costs in a 2-part Generalized Linear Model of Complication-related Medical Costs During the 6-month Follow-up</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="2" axis="1">Cohort</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Logistic model of positive value versus $0 cost</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gamma model for nonzero cost</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="2" axis="1">Predicted value</th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="1" axis="1" rowspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th align="center" colspan="1" axis="1" rowspan="1">Cost ratio (95% CI)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TRB</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">$18,938</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TFLB</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.480 (0.320, 0.720)<break/>
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.001</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.643 (0.500, 0.827)<break/>
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.001</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">$9076</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>Models adjusted for age group (18 to 44&#160;y, 45 to 64&#160;y, 65&#160;y or older), sex, consumer-driven health care plan use, urban/rural location, region of the United States (Northeast, Midwest, South, West), index year, baseline Charlson comorbidity score category (0, 1 to 2, 3 to 4, &#8805;5), and specific comorbid conditions (chronic pulmonary disease, renal disease, diabetes with chronic complications).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>OR indicates odds ratio; TFLB, tissue biopsy followed by liquid biopsy; TRB, tissue re-biopsy.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>All-cause Medical Costs and HCRU</title><p>Mean all-cause medical costs, not including pharmacy costs, during the 6-month follow-up were comparable between the TFLB and TRB groups (Fig. <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>A). Mean costs for inpatient stays were significantly lower with TFLB than TRB ($12,924 vs. $29,512; difference [95% CI], &#8211;$16,588 [&#8211;$21,519, &#8211;$11,657]; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.001). Mean costs for office visits were significantly higher for TFLB than TRB ($23,977 vs. $14,204; difference [95% CI], $9773 [$4102, $15,445]; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.001). Mean (SD) all-cause pharmacy costs were significantly greater in the TFLB group ($21,634 [$37,114] vs. $4,618 [$11,364], difference [95% CI]: $17,015 [$12,031, $22,000]; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.001). Mean outpatient and emergency department visit costs were similar between groups.</p><fig position="float" id="F3" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 3</label><caption><p>All-cause medical costs (A) and HCRU (B) during the 6-month follow-up. *Tested for significance with Wald 95% confidence limits for differences in means of continuous measures and <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> tests for continuous measures. <sup>&#8224;</sup>Not including pharmacy costs. HCRU indicates health care resource utilization; TFLB, tissue biopsy followed by liquid biopsy; TRB, tissue re-biopsy. <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8805;0.05 are not shown.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="coc-48-127-g003.jpg"/></fig><p>Mean numbers of inpatient days, inpatient stays, and outpatient visits were significantly lower with TFLB than TRB (inpatient days: 5.4 vs. 9.5, difference [95% CI]: &#8722;4.2 [&#8722;6.4, &#8722;2.0]; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.001; inpatient stays: 0.7 vs. 1.2, difference [95% CI]: &#8722;0.4 [&#8722;0.6, &#8722;0.3]; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.001; outpatient visits: 36.7 vs. 44.7, difference [95% CI]: &#8722;8.0 [&#8722;13.4, &#8722;2.7]; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.003) (Fig. <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>B). The number of emergency department and office visits were similar between the groups. Likewise, mean (SD) number of all-cause pharmacy fills did not differ with TFLB vs. TRB (28.3 [17.3] vs. 27.0 [15.8], difference [95% CI]: 1.3 [&#8722;1.7, 4.3]; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.403).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>This is the first direct comparison of biopsy-related complications, costs, and HCRU in patients with mNSCLC who received TFLB with those who had a TRB. In this claims-based study, the overall rate of surgical biopsy-related complications was significantly lower for patients with mNSCLC who had TFLB than for patients who had a TRB. Patients in the TFLB group also had significantly lower complication-related medical costs, driven by decreased costs of inpatient stays and fewer and shorter inpatient stays, as well as fewer outpatient and office visits. A new algorithm that defined applicable codes to differentiate between genetic tests in solid tissue and liquid biopsy in claims data was developed and applied.</p><p>Identifying actionable mutations in mNSCLC with a tissue biopsy is associated with challenges. Diagnoses of mNSCLC are often based on small tissue biopsies or fine-needle aspirations, which may not procure sufficient tissue for genomic testing.<sup><xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> Turnaround time is another concern, as it typically takes 15 to 30 days for tissue biopsy results to become available, and the delay may be greater if TRB is needed.<sup><xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> While awaiting biopsy results, physicians may initiate nontargeted treatment, which increases mortality risk in patients with actionable mutations.<sup><xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> Tissue biopsy complications must also be considered; not only do biopsy-related complications significantly increase costs,<sup><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> but they are also potentially fatal.<sup><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup>
</p><p>Liquid biopsy brings value to diagnostics by addressing these issues. Complement liquid biopsy testing can identify actionable mutations in cases of insufficient tissue.<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> A historic disadvantage of liquid biopsy testing was that it was limited to a single gene testing of a particular mutation or cases of insufficient tissue;<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> however, advances have allowed NGS to be used in the liquid biopsy setting, permitting simultaneous testing for numerous actionable mutations.<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> For some mutations, detection is as effective in liquid biopsy as in tissue biopsy, and if the 2 tests are done together, more mutations are detected.<sup><xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup>
</p><p>Advances are needed to reliably detect some actionable aberrations with liquid biopsy. For example, negative liquid biopsy results for <italic toggle="yes">ALK</italic> mutations may require testing of a new tissue biopsy upon cancer progression,<sup><xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup> and negative results for <italic toggle="yes">ERBB2</italic> mutations should be confirmed with tissue immunohistochemistry or fluorescence <italic toggle="yes">in situ</italic> hybridization because of the high false-negative rate.<sup><xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup> In another example, testing for actionable overexpression of programmed cell death ligand 1 is typically performed with immunohistochemistry because the diagnosis depends on protein localization,<sup><xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> which cannot yet be detected by liquid biopsy. To address such issues, research to extend liquid biopsy use to cell-free RNA and circulating tumor RNA is underway, although no such tests have been approved.<sup><xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup> Consequently, additional tissue must be procured for RNA sequencing if no actionable mutation is found in the initial tissue biopsy and there is insufficient material for RNA sequencing.<sup><xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup> Sequencing cell free or circulating tumor RNA in liquid biopsies could avoid the need for such re-biopsies, making this a promising research area.</p><p>In a real-world analysis of clinicogenomic database outcomes for 6491 patients with NSCLC who had comprehensive genomic profiling using liquid or tissue biopsy, the percentage of patients with actionable genomic alterations and targeted therapy use were comparable between the liquid and tissue biopsy groups.<sup><xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup> For patients who received standard-of-care targeted therapy first-line, real-world, progression-free survival durations were also similar (liquid biopsy, 13.8&#160;mo vs. tissue biopsy, 10.6&#160;mo; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.217). Further, in a prospective observational trial of 282 patients with untreated mNSCLC, an actionable mutation was detected in a liquid biopsy in 27.3% of patients and in a tissue biopsy in 21.3%; using tissue and liquid biopsy together increased actionable mutation detection by 48%.<sup><xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> In addition, the turnaround time was significantly faster with liquid versus tissue biopsy (9 vs. 15&#160;d).<sup><xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> The temporal benefit of liquid biopsy extends to the time to targeted treatment. For patients who received targeted therapy first-line, those who underwent liquid biopsy had a time to targeted treatment of 18 days compared with 31 days for patients who underwent tissue biopsy (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.0008).<sup><xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup>
</p><p>The less invasive nature of liquid biopsy is also advantageous. In this study, biopsy-related complications were 19.6% lower with TFLB than TRB. Biopsy-related complications of pneumothorax, prolonged air leak, and infection were significantly lower in the TFLB group (differences of &#8722;28.5%, &#8722;10.6%, and &#8722;8.9%, respectively). No complications were significantly higher with TFLB.</p><p>The TFLB group also had significantly lower complication-related medical costs driven by decreased costs of inpatient stays and complication-related HCRU. These cost advantages align with results from a Markov model of patients with mNSCLC and a history of never or light smoking, in which complement liquid biopsy testing was predicted to increase detection of actionable mutations and targeted therapy use and decrease costs compared with tissue biopsy testing alone.<sup><xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> Total all-cause medical costs (not including pharmacy costs) for the TFLB and TRB groups were comparable despite patients in the TRB group incurring costs of tissue re-biopsy. Total all-cause costs with TFLB were driven by higher costs for office and outpatient visits, which could reflect costs of office-administered immunotherapy and/or chemotherapy. The high comorbidity and malignancy burdens in both groups could have led to substantial ongoing costs, which were not necessarily related to mNSCLC or the type of biopsy conducted.</p><sec><title>Strengths</title><p>This is the first claims-based study to compare complications, costs, and HCRU between patients with mNSCLC who had TFLB or TRB. A new algorithm was developed and used to identify liquid biopsies in claims data. Results apply to a range of patients in the United States, as the sample was geographically diverse and included commercially insured and Medicare Advantage patients.</p></sec><sec><title>Limitations</title><p>As with all retrospective databases, lack of randomization and subsequent bias introduced the potential for confounding, misclassification, limited generalizability, and random error. The study is limited to medical claims and may be missing information reported in electronic medical records or charts. Results may not be generalizable to patients who are uninsured or are insured through Medicaid because of the population selected. Our study focused on patients with newly diagnosed mNSCLC, thus omitting those diagnosed at early stages or those with recurring lung cancer.</p><p>Other limitations include those inherent to claims data, including that biopsies taken as part of a clinical trial are not observed in claims data. In addition, diagnosis codes may be incorrectly coded or included as rule-out criteria rather than actual disease; the requirement for &#8805;2 nondiagnostic lung cancer claims was included to decrease this type of error.</p></sec><sec><title>Future Studies</title><p>Additional studies could extend this analysis to patients with earlier stage or recurring NSCLC. Further, the newly developed liquid biopsy algorithm could be applied to SCLC to determine if the results described herein extend to other lung cancer types. Finally, liquid biopsy procedures within genomic testing must be comprehensively identified and standardized to promote the widespread application of this technique.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>CONCLUSIONS</title><p>This large, retrospective matched cohort study examined the real-world health care outcomes associated with TFLB versus TRB in patients with newly diagnosed mNSCLC using a novel algorithm to identify liquid biopsy claims. Compared with the TFLB group, the TRB group had a significantly greater rate of biopsy complications overall, and of infections, pneumothorax, and prolonged air leak specifically. The TRB group had higher complication-related medical costs and HCRU driven by the number and duration of inpatient stays and the numbers of outpatient and office visits. Our findings demonstrate that the established benefits of complement liquid biopsy, including increased sample availability, improved mutation detection, and rapid turnaround, can be attained safely and cost-effectively.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><fig id="s001" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="coc-48-127-s001.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></fig></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p>The data contained in the database used for the study contain proprietary elements owned by Optum and, therefore, cannot be broadly disclosed or made publicly available at this time. The disclosure of these data to third parties assumes certain data security and privacy protocols are in place and that the third party has executed a standard license agreement which includes restrictive covenants governing the use of the data.</p></fn><fn fn-type="supported-by"><p>This study was funded by AstraZeneca. The funding body also contributed to data interpretation and manuscript development. Programming support for the analytic dataset was provided by Tom Horstman and Lynn Wacha; additional analytic support was provided by Mary Grace Johnson, PharmD, MSPH, and Jennifer Friderici, MS; and project management support was provided by Sarah Hague (all from Optum, Eden Prairie, MN, USA). Medical writing support was provided by Caryne Craige, PhD, Jennifer Gibson, PharmD, and Kathryn Fogarty, PhD (all of Kay Square Scientific, Newtown Square, PA, USA).</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>A.S. and J.A. are employees of AstraZeneca Pharmaceuticals PLC. S.A. was an employee and shareholder of UnitedHealth Group at the time of the study. N.M.E.-N. and L.L. are employees of Optum and shareholders of UnitedHealth Group. M.T. is a consultant for Optum and employee of Marilou Terpenning, MD, Ltd. This study was funded by AstraZeneca. The funding body also contributed to data interpretation and manuscript development. Optum provided funds for writing support, which was provided by Caryne Craige, PhD (Kay Square Scientific, Newtown Square, PA), Jennifer Gibson, PharmD (Kay Square Scientific, Newtown Square, PA), and Kathryn Fogarty, PhD (Kay Square Scientific, Newtown Square, PA) in alignment with Good Publication Practice (GPP) guidelines.</p></fn><fn fn-type="supplementary-material"><p>Supplemental Digital Content is available for this article. Direct URL citations are provided in the HTML and PDF versions of this article on the journal's website, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.amjclinicaloncology.com" ext-link-type="uri">www.amjclinicaloncology.com</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>National Cancer Institute</collab></person-group>. <comment>Cancer stat facts: lung and bronchus cancer. Accessed August 10, 2023.</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://seer.cancer.gov/statfacts/html/lungb.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://seer.cancer.gov/statfacts/html/lungb.html</ext-link> &#8203;&#8203;&#8203;&#8203;</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferlay</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Global Cancer Statistics 2020: GLOBOCAN Estimates of Incidence and Mortality Worldwide for 36 Cancers in 185 Countries</article-title>. <source>CA Cancer J Clin</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>71</volume>:<fpage>209</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>249</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33538338</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3322/caac.21660</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>American Cancer Society</collab></person-group>. <comment>Key statistics for lung cancer. 2023. Accessed October 10, 2023.</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cancer.org/cancer/types/lung-cancer/about/key-statistics.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cancer.org/cancer/types/lung-cancer/about/key-statistics.html</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Howlader</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Noone</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krapcho</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <comment>SEER cancer statistics review, 1975-2016. 2020. Accessed May 22, 2023.</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://seer.cancer.gov/csr/1975_2016/" ext-link-type="uri">https://seer.cancer.gov/csr/1975_2016/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>K&#246;nig</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Savic Prince</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rothschild</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Targeted therapy in advanced and metastatic non-small cell lung cancer. An update on treatment of the most important actionable oncogenic driver alterations</article-title>. <source>Cancers (Basel)</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>804</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33671873</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/cancers13040804</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7918961</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><comment>Referenced with permission from the NCCN Clinical Practice Guidelines in Oncology (NCCN Guidelines) for Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer V.2.2024. National Comprehensive Cancer Network, Inc. 2024. All rights reserved. Accessed February 27, 2024. To view the most recent and complete version of the guideline, go online to NCCN.org. NCCN makes no warranties of any kind whatsoever regarding their content, use or application and disclaims any responsibility for their application or use in any way</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choudhury</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Complementing tissue testing with plasma mutation profiling improves therapeutic decision-making for patients with lung cancer</article-title>. <source>Front Med (Lausanne)</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>758464</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35223889</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fmed.2022.758464</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8873935</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Osarogiagbon</surname><given-names>RU</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Acquiring tissue for advanced lung cancer diagnosis and comprehensive biomarker testing: a national Lung Cancer Roundtable best-practice guide</article-title>. <source>CA Cancer J Clin</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>73</volume>:<fpage>358</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>375</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36859638</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3322/caac.21774</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Complications and economic burden associated with obtaining tissue for diagnosis and molecular analysis in patients with non-small-cell lung cancer in the United States</article-title>. <source>J Oncol Pract</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>e717</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>e727</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31237806</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1200/JOP.18.00762</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lorenz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blum</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Complications of percutaneous chest biopsy</article-title>. <source>Semin Intervent Radiol</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>188</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>193</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21326762</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1055/s-2006-941449</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3036363</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ofiara</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Navasakulpong</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beaudoin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Optimizing tissue sampling for the diagnosis, subtyping, and molecular analysis of lung cancer</article-title>. <source>Front Oncol</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>253</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25295226</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fonc.2014.00253</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4170137</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Penault-Llorca</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garrido</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Expert opinion on NSCLC small specimen biomarker testing&#8212;Part 1: tissue collection and management</article-title>. <source>Virchows Arch</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>481</volume>:<fpage>335</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>380</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35857102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00428-022-03343-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9485167</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Handy</surname><given-names>JR</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Skokan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rauch</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Results of lung cancer screening in the community</article-title>. <source>Ann Fam Med</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>243</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>249</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32393560</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1370/afm.2519</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7214008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>National Lung Screening Trial Research Team</collab><name name-style="western"><surname>Aberle</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Reduced lung-cancer mortality with low-dose computed tomographic screening</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>365</volume>:<fpage>395</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>409</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21714641</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMoa1102873</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4356534</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mosele</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Remon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mateo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Recommendations for the use of next-generation sequencing (NGS) for patients with metastatic cancers: a report from the ESMO Precision Medicine Working Group</article-title>. <source>Ann Oncol</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>1491</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1505</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32853681</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.annonc.2020.07.014</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rolfo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mack</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scagliotti</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Liquid biopsy for advanced NSCLC: a consensus statement from the International Association for the Study of Lung Cancer</article-title>. <source>J Thorac Oncol</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>1647</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1662</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34246791</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jtho.2021.06.017</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vanderpoel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Emond</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Total cost of testing for genomic alterations associated with next-generation sequencing versus polymerase chain reaction testing strategies among patients with metastatic non-small cell lung cancer</article-title>. <source>J Med Econ</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>457</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>468</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35289703</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/13696998.2022.2053403</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gutierrez</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lanman</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Genomic profiling of advanced non-small cell lung cancer in community settings: gaps and opportunities</article-title>. <source>Clin Lung Cancer</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>651</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>659</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28479369</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cllc.2017.04.004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sugihara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Initial versus early switch to targeted therapy during first-line treatment among patients with biomarker-positive advanced or metastatic non-small cell lung cancer in the United States</article-title>. <source>Cancer Treat Res Commun</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>100761</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ctarc.2023.100761</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37717466</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ezeife</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spackman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Juergens</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The economic value of liquid biopsy for genomic profiling in advanced non-small cell lung cancer</article-title>. <source>Ther Adv Med Oncol</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>17588359221112696</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35923926</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/17588359221112696</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9340413</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Corcoran</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chabner</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Application of cell-free DNA analysis to cancer treatment</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>379</volume>:<fpage>1754</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1765</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30380390</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMra1706174</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Black</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical implications of plasma-based genotyping with the delivery of personalized therapy in metastatic non-small cell lung cancer</article-title>. <source>JAMA Oncol</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>173</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>180</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30325992</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamaoncol.2018.4305</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6396811</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Page</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drusbosky</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dada</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical outcomes for plasma-based comprehensive genomic profiling versus standard-of-care tissue testing in advanced non-small cell lung cancer</article-title>. <source>Clin Lung Cancer</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>72</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>81</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34782240</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cllc.2021.10.001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guirado</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fern&#225;ndez Mart&#237;n</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fern&#225;ndez Villar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical impact of delays in the management of lung cancer patients in the last decade: systematic review</article-title>. <source>Clin Transl Oncol</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>1549</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1568</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35257298</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s12094-022-02796-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8900646</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pascual</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Attard</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bidard</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>ESMO recommendations on the use of circulating tumour DNA assays for patients with cancer: a report from the ESMO Precision Medicine Working Group</article-title>. <source>Ann Oncol</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>750</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>768</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35809752</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.annonc.2022.05.520</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Quan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Couris</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Updating and validating the Charlson comorbidity index and score for risk adjustment in hospital discharge abstracts using data from 6 countries</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>173</volume>:<fpage>676</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>682</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21330339</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/aje/kwq433</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blough</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Madden</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hornbrook</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Modeling risk using generalized linear models</article-title>. <source>J Health Econ</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>153</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>171</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10346351</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0167-6296(98)00032-0</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liam</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mallawathantri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fong</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Is tissue still the issue in detecting molecular alterations in lung cancer?</article-title><source>Respirology</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>933</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>943</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32335992</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/resp.13823</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leighl</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Page</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raymond</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical utility of comprehensive cell-free DNA analysis to identify genomic biomarkers in patients with newly diagnosed metastatic non-small cell lung cancer</article-title>. <source>Clin Cancer Res</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>4691</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4700</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30988079</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-19-0624</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kris</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Using multiplexed assays of oncogenic drivers in lung cancers to select targeted drugs</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>311</volume>:<fpage>1998</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2006</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24846037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.2014.3741</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4163053</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Apple</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shenolikar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Silva</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Real-world outcomes among patients with EGFR-mutated non-small cell lung cancer treated with EGFR tyrosine kinase inhibitors versus immunotherapy or chemotherapy in the first-line setting</article-title>. <source>Cancer Med</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>13415</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>13425</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37306623</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/cam4.6052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10315796</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Madison</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schrock</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castellanos</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Retrospective analysis of real-world data to determine clinical outcomes of patients with advanced non-small cell lung cancer following cell-free circulating tumor DNA genomic profiling</article-title>. <source>Lung Cancer</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>148</volume>:<fpage>69</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>78</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32823229</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.lungcan.2020.07.033</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hofman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Detecting resistance to therapeutic ALK inhibitors in tumor tissue and liquid biopsy markers: an update to a clinical routine practice</article-title>. <source>Cells</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>168</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33467720</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/cells10010168</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7830674</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ying</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Consensus for HER2 alterations testing in non-small-cell lung cancer [published correction appears in ESMO Open. 2022 Jun;7(3):100482]</article-title>. <source>ESMO Open</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>100395</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35461023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.esmoop.2022.100482</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9046799</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Satturwar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Girolami</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Munari</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Program death ligand-1 immunocytochemistry in lung cancer cytological samples: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Diagn Cytopathol</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>50</volume>:<fpage>313</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>323</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35293692</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/dc.24955</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9310737</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cab&#250;s</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lagarde</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Curado</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Current challenges and best practices for cell-free long RNA biomarker discovery</article-title>. <source>Biomark Res</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>62</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35978416</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s40364-022-00409-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9385245</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brockley</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>VGP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forder</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Sequence-based platforms for discovering biomarkers in liquid biopsy of non-small-cell lung cancer</article-title>. <source>Cancers (Basel)</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>2275</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37190212</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/cancers15082275</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10136462</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hondelink</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Solleveld-Westerink</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Optimizing mutation and fusion detection in NSCLC by sequential DNA and RNA sequencing</article-title>. <source>J Thorac Oncol</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>1000</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1014</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32014610</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jtho.2020.01.019</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>