<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">AJOG Glob Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">AJOG Glob Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">4305</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">ajoggr</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>AJOG Global Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2666-5778</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10009524</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10009524.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10009524</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10009524</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36922957</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.xagr.2022.100158</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2666-5778(22)00106-X</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100158</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Understanding social needs in pregnancy: Prospective validation of a digital short-form screening tool and patient survey</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0001"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peahl</surname><given-names initials="AF">Alex F.</given-names></name><degrees>MD, MSc</degrees><email>alexfrie@med.umich.edu</email><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="cor0001" ref-type="corresp">&#8270;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0002"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rubin-Miller</surname><given-names initials="L">Lily</given-names></name><degrees>MPH</degrees><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0003"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paterson</surname><given-names initials="V">Victoria</given-names></name><degrees>MPH</degrees><xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0004"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jahnke</surname><given-names initials="HR">Hannah R.</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0005"><name name-style="western"><surname>Plough</surname><given-names initials="A">Avery</given-names></name><degrees>MPH</degrees><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0006"><name name-style="western"><surname>Henrich</surname><given-names initials="N">Natalie</given-names></name><degrees>PhD, MPH</degrees><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0007"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moss</surname><given-names initials="C">Christa</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0008"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names initials="N">Neel</given-names></name><degrees>MD, MPP</degrees><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">5</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI (Dr Peahl)</aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label>Institute for Healthcare Policy and Innovation, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI (Dr Peahl)</aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label>Maven Clinic, New York, NY (Dr Peahl, Ms Rubin-Miller, Dr Jahnke, Ms Plough, and Drs Henrich, Moss, and Shah)</aff><aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label>Warren Alpert Medical School, Brown University, Providence, Rhode Island (Paterson)</aff><aff id="aff0005"><label>5</label>Harvard Medical School Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Boston, MA (Dr Shah)</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor0001"><label>&#8270;</label>Corresponding author: Alex Friedman Peahl, MD, MSc. <email>alexfrie@med.umich.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>2</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>06</day><month>1</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><issue>1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">422146</issue-id><elocation-id>100158</elocation-id><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>06</day><month>01</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>14</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-03-16 12:10:56.800"><day>16</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2023 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><abstract id="abs0001"><sec><title>BACKGROUND</title><p>Social determinants of health significantly affect health outcomes, yet are infrequently addressed in prenatal care.</p></sec><sec><title>OBJECTIVE</title><p>This study aimed to improve the efficiency and experience of addressing social needs in pregnancy through: (1) testing a digital short-form screening tool; and (2) characterizing pregnant people's preferences for social needs screening and management.</p></sec><sec><title>STUDY DESIGN</title><p>We developed a digital short-form social determinants of health screening tool from PRAPARE (Protocol for Responding to and Assessing Patients&#8217; Assets, Risks, and Experiences), and a survey to query patients&#8217; preferences for addressing social needs. Instruments were administered online to peripartum participants, with equal representation of patients with public and private insurance. We calculated the sensitivity and specificity of the short-form tool vs PRAPARE. Quantitative responses were characterized using descriptive statistics. Free-text responses were analyzed with matrix and thematic coding. Survey data were analyzed by subgroups of historically marginalized populations.</p></sec><sec><title>RESULTS</title><p>A total of 215 people completed the survey. Participants were predominantly White (167; 77.7%) and multiparous (145; 67.4%). Unmet social needs were prevalent with both the short-form tool (77.7%) and PRAPARE (96.7%). The sensitivity (79.3%) and specificity (71.4%) of the short-form screener were high for detecting any social need. Most participants believed that it was important for their pregnancy care team to know their social needs (material: 173, 80.5%; support: 200, 93.0%), and over half felt comfortable sharing their needs through in-person or digital modalities if assistance was or was not available (material: 117, 54.4%; support: 122, 56.7%). Free-text themes reflected considerations for integrating social needs in routine prenatal care. Acceptability of addressing social needs in pregnancy was high among all groups.</p></sec><sec><title>CONCLUSION</title><p>A digital short-form social determinants of health screening tool performs well when compared with the gold standard. Pregnant people accept social needs as a part of routine pregnancy care. Future work is needed to operationalize efficient, effective, patient-centered approaches to addressing social needs in pregnancy.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group id="keys0001"><title>Key words</title><kwd>digital health</kwd><kwd>disparities</kwd><kwd>food insecurity</kwd><kwd>housing insecurity</kwd><kwd>postpartum care</kwd><kwd>prenatal care</kwd><kwd>preventive care</kwd><kwd>social determinants</kwd><kwd>social isolation</kwd><kwd>social needs</kwd><kwd>telemedicine</kwd><kwd>transportation barriers</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="para9001">
<boxed-text id="tbox0002" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>AJOG Global Reports at a Glance</title></caption><sec id="sec0001"><title>Why was this study conducted?</title><p id="para0009">Although social determinants of health (SDoH) affect 40% of health outcomes, they are infrequently screened for or addressed in routine prenatal care. This study sought to test a digital 3-question screening tool and assess pregnant people's preferences for screening and managing social needs in pregnancy.</p></sec><sec id="sec0002"><title>Key findings</title><p id="para0010">Pregnant and postpartum people agree that social needs are an important part of prenatal care and are comfortable sharing their needs and receiving assistance through a variety of modalities, both in-person and digital. A digital short-form screening tool had high sensitivity for detecting unmet social needs. Few differences were found between participants who were and were not from historically marginalized groups.</p></sec><sec id="sec0003"><title>What does this add to what is known?</title><p id="para0011">This study demonstrates how digital social needs screening and management in pregnancy can be efficient and patient-centered, even in the absence of tangible assistance.</p></sec></boxed-text>
</p><sec id="sec0004"><title>Introduction</title><p id="para0012">Social determinants of health (SDoH), the nonmedical factors that affect people's ability to live, work, and play, account for over 40% of health outcomes.<xref rid="bib0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="bib0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="bib0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> The effects of social needs are even more profound for pregnant people, whose health is intimately linked to that of their infants and families.<xref rid="bib0004" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> SDoH can influence health outcomes through multiple pathways, including increasing chronic conditions, limiting access to evidence-based services, and directly contributing to adverse pregnancy outcomes, such as poor nutrition leading to low-birthweight infants.<xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> Therefore, leading professional organizations have called for incorporating SDoH into routine prenatal care.<xref rid="bib0001" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></p><p id="para0013">Despite their critical importance, SDoH are infrequently screened for or addressed in routine prenatal care because of multiple barriers.<xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="bib0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> First, it is challenging to integrate additional workflows into busy clinical practices.<xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> Digital screening, including SMS- or app-based tools, has been used in primary care to efficiently expand detection of common conditions, with high acceptability and improved detection when compared with clinic-administered screening.<xref rid="bib0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="bib0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="bib0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> However, existing screening tools are long, posing a potential challenge to their use as digital screening tools where participation is sensitive to instrument length.<xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref></p><p id="para0014">In addition, SDoH screening and management processes have historically been developed without patients&#8217; input. As few as 20% of patients with identified needs in primary-care settings are followed up with offered assistance, and even fewer receive services.<xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref> Finally, current SDoH practices are not equitable.<xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref> Screening is often limited to patients presumed to have low income, as identified by their clinical site (eg, Federally Qualified Health Center) or insurance type (eg, Medicaid).<xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref> Yet, patients with private insurance may also face unmet social needs, including underinsurance and low income.<xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib0026" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref> Patient-centered approaches to SDoH in pregnancy, including screening and management, are critical to improve intergenerational health outcomes.</p><p id="para0015">Our overall objective was to improve the experience and efficiency of SDoH screening and management for pregnant patients. We designed and tested a 3-question digital SDoH screener, which we compared with the current reference standard of SDoH screening.<xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> In addition, we queried pregnant and postpartum people's preferences for screening and managing SDoH in pregnancy, and how those preferences differ by patient characteristics (insurance type, presence of social needs, and race) to inform new, patient-centered approaches to addressing social needs in pregnancy.</p></sec><sec id="sec0005"><title>Methods</title><sec id="sec0006"><title>Survey development</title><p id="para0016">We developed a 3-question SDoH screening tool adapted from the PRAPARE (Protocol for Responding to and Assessing Patients&#8217; Assets, Risks, and Experiences) tool, a national standardized tool for risk assessment of patients&#8217; social risk factors, which includes 21 questions.<xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> We iteratively refined the tool, incorporating feedback from our interprofessional group, including practicing obstetrician-gynecologists (A.F.P., N.S.) and experts in maternity care innovation (A.P.), epidemiology (H.R.J.), and population health (C.M.) to create the most efficient tool that screened for key domains of PRAPARE. We removed questions with duplicate content and that did not reflect active needs, until we had reduced the screening tool to 3 questions covering 10 domains (<xref rid="tbl0005" ref-type="table">Box</xref>; Appendix A). We did not include domains that reflected risk of unmet social needs but were not unmet social needs themselves, such as public insurance. All included questions incorporated the patient's assessment of their social need. For example, for social isolation, we asked, &#8220;Do you feel lonely or isolated from those around you?&#8221; We assessed the reading level of the short-form screening tool using the readability function in Microsoft Word. The Flesch&#8211;Kincaid score was 69, indicating a sixth- to seventh-grade reading level.<xref rid="bib0027" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref> We administered the short form and PRAPARE via a survey to compare the short form with the reference-standard measurement tool.</p><p id="para0017">We also developed a survey to assess patients&#8217; preferences for screening and managing (addressing) SDoH in pregnancy. We hypothesized that patients might have different attitudes and preferences for material needs (ie, tangible needs such as those related to food insecurity) and support needs (ie, needs for connection to others such as those resulting from social isolation). We assessed if participants believed that it is important for their pregnancy care team to know their social needs and if they were comfortable sharing their needs if assistance was and was not available. Finally, we assessed participants&#8217; preferences for screening for social needs and providing linkage to resources through multiple modalities: text message, email, app, conversation with a care team member, and conversation with a nonmedical health worker. All attitude and preference questions included 4-point Likert scale responses from &#8220;strongly disagree&#8221; to &#8220;strongly agree.&#8221; Two free-text questions were included to rapidly gather rich data: &#8220;What concerns do you have about sharing your social needs with your pregnancy care team?&#8221; and &#8220;How could your pregnancy care team support your material and support needs?&#8221;</p><p id="para0018">We performed cognitive testing with the 3-question screening tool and survey with 5 people who were pregnant at the time or up to 1 year postpartum. Question clarifications were incorporated. The survey was uploaded using the Centiment online platform and pilot-tested with 10 participants. No further revisions were made. Pilot responses were included in the final sample.</p></sec><sec id="sec0007"><title>Recruitment</title><p id="para0019">We used the Centiment survey recruitment platform to obtain a cross-sectional sample of participants across the United States. Centiment recruits thousands of individuals from across the United States using social media websites, and then matches them to surveys on the basis of specific inclusion criteria. The general population of Centiment users matches United States Census Bureau demographics in age, race, and geography, providing a diverse pool. All recruitment, matching, and payment are conducted through their online platform. Inclusion criteria were pregnant or postpartum people from 24 weeks&#8217; gestational age to 1 year postpartum who were able to consent and complete the survey in English. We sampled equal numbers of participants with public and private insurance, given the difference in available social services by insurance and the potential influence on patients&#8217; responses. Participants were invited at regular intervals, with careful monitoring of the desired sample size until the recruitment goal was met. Participants who started the survey but did not complete it were excluded. This included 32 total participants, 2 of whom completed no demographic data. Of the remaining 30, 15 were pregnant and 15 were postpartum; 18 had public insurance and 12 had private insurance. Participants received $3 for the &lt;10-minute survey. Participant demographics were collected through eligibility questions (insurance, pregnancy) and self-reported survey questions (age, race, ethnicity, parity) developed from the US Census and previous surveys with pregnant people.<xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib0029" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref> Self-reported race was included as a social, not biologic, construct, as a proxy for systemic and institutional racism and experience of discrimination. We selected 200 participants to gain a broad understanding of participants&#8217; attitudes and preferences and in keeping with other validation studies of short-form screening tools.<xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="bib0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="bib0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> This study protocol was designated as exempt under 45 CFR &#167; 46.104(d)(2) by Western Institutional Review Board, an independent ethical review board headquartered in Washington State.</p></sec><sec id="sec0008"><title>Analysis</title><p id="para0020">All survey questions were tabulated using basic descriptive statistics. We calculated the sensitivity and specificity of the short-form screening tool compared with PRAPARE for any need, material needs, and social needs. We calculated the proportion of participants who expressed specific attitudes toward addressing social needs. We calculated our study's power to detect a difference in screening tools. Based on the social needs prevalence of &gt;70% and the sensitivity of the 3-question screening tool (70%), and assuming &gt;90% sensitivity of PRAPARE, power to detect differences between the tools was &gt;0.8 with at least 75 total participants (31 with social needs and 44 without social needs).<xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33</sup></xref></p><p id="para0021">For free-response data, we used a combined matrix and thematic qualitative analysis using Microsoft Excel. Free responses were categorized as positive or negative attitudes. Then, emerging subthemes were defined in the codebook and iteratively reviewed by 2 authors until consensus was reached. We categorized subthemes by levels of influence: patient and provider/health system. Free-text responses were analyzed by V.P. for consistency, and A.P. provided continuous feedback to resolve uncertainties. Themes and the final matrix table were reviewed with the larger group of multidisciplinary coauthors during 2 meetings, with clarifications of the codebook. We tabulated counts of specific themes.</p><p id="para0022">All quantitative and qualitative analyses were performed for the full cohort and by 3 historically marginalized subgroups based on: (1) presence of social needs (any needs vs no need), as identified by the short-form screener; (2) payer type (public vs private); and (3) race. We used bivariate statistics to calculate differences across groups for quantitative variables and the prevalence of qualitative themes. We conducted the subgroup analysis of social needs using the short-form screener (vs PRAPARE) because our goal was to explore differences between groups with and without social needs, as opposed to PRAPARE, which also includes people at risk of unmet social needs. Missing data were &lt;5% for all quantitative variables, and were not imputed. Statistical significance was set at <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;.05 with 2-sided tests. All statistical analyses were conducted in R, version 3.6.3 (R Core Team, Vienna, Austria).<xref rid="bib0034" ref-type="bibr"><sup>34</sup></xref></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec0009"><title>Results</title><p id="para0023">In total, 215 pregnant and postpartum people completed the survey. Participants were predominantly White (167; 77.7%), non-Hispanic (185; 86.0%), and multiparous (145; 67.4%). By design, participants were equally divided between public and private insurance (private: 106 [49.3%]; public: 109 [51.7%]) (<xref rid="tbl0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0001" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Participant demographics and social needs by insurance type</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0001">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Demographics and social needs</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Overall (N=215)</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Private insurance (N=106)</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Public insurance (N=109)</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Race<xref rid="tb1fn1" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.07</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Multiracial</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (2.8%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (1.9%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (3.7%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Missing</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 (4.2%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (4.7%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (3.7%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;White</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">167 (77.7%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">86 (81.1%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">81 (74.3%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Other</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.5%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.9%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Asian or Asian American</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (2.8%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (4.7%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.9%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Black or African American</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25 (11.6%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (6.6%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18 (16.5%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ethnicity<xref rid="tb1fn1" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.71</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Hispanic, Latino/a, or Spanish origin</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28 (13.0%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 (15.1%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 (11.0%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Not Hispanic, Latino/a, or Spanish origin</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">185 (86.0%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">89 (84.0%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96 (88.1%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Mean (SD)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.6 (5.71)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.2 (5.21)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.1 (5.80)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Median (min&#8211;max)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.0 (18.0&#8211;43.0)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.5 (18.0&#8211;42.0)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.0 (18.0&#8211;43.0)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pregnancy status</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.008</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Currently pregnant</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100 (46.5%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">59 (55.7%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41 (37.6%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Postpartum (up to 1 year after childbirth)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">115 (53.5%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47 (44.3%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68 (62.4%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">First child</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.47</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;No</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">145 (67.4%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">69 (65.1%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">76 (69.7%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Yes</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70 (32.6%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37 (34.9%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33 (30.3%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Material needs</td><td colspan="4" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Housing<xref rid="tb1fn1" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">59 (27.4%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18 (17.0%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41 (37.6%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Food<xref rid="tb1fn1" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">80 (37.2%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25 (23.6%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55 (50.5%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Utilities<xref rid="tb1fn2" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67 (31.2%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22 (20.8%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45 (41.3%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Medicine or any health care<xref rid="tb1fn1" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66 (30.7%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 (25.5%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39 (35.8%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.09</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Phone/internet<xref rid="tb1fn1" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">59 (27.4%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 (15.1%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43 (39.4%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Supplies for infant and family<xref rid="tb1fn1" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94 (43.7%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36 (34.0%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">58 (53.2%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.006</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Work/employment<xref rid="tb1fn2" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">81 (37.7%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29 (27.4%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52 (47.7%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Support needs</td><td colspan="4" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Care for family<xref rid="tb1fn2" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56 (26.0%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26 (24.5%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30 (27.5%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.57</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Social isolation<xref rid="tb1fn2" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">89 (41.4%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35 (33.0%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">54 (49.5%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.002</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Intimate partner violence<xref rid="tb1fn2" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">174 (80.9%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">90 (84.9%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">84 (77.1%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.38</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Need categories</td><td colspan="4" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Material need</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">140 (65.1%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56 (52.8%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">84 (77.1%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Support need</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">124 (57.7%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53 (50.0%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">71 (65.1%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.02</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Any need</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">167 (77.7%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70 (66.0%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97 (89.0%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><italic toggle="yes">SD</italic>, standard deviation.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tb1fn1"><label>a</label><p id="notep0006">0% to 1%&#8212;prefer not to say</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tb1fn2"><label>b</label><p id="notep0007">1% to 2%&#8212;prefer not to say.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><attrib>Peahl. Social determinants of health in pregnancy. Am J Obstet Gynecol Glob Rep 2023.</attrib></table-wrap></p><p id="para0024">Screen-positive rates for social needs were high with both the short-form screening tool and PRAPARE, but were consistently lower with the short-form tool across all domains: material needs (65.1% vs 67.9%), support needs (57.7% vs 81.4%), and any positive response (77.7% vs 96.7%) (<xref rid="sec0017" ref-type="fn">Appendix A</xref>). This resulted in moderate to high sensitivity and specificity of the short-form screener across most domains: material needs (sensitivity: 84.2%; specificity: 75.4%), support needs (sensitivity: 63.4%; specificity: 67.5%), and any positive response (sensitivity: 79.3%; specificity: 71.4%) (<xref rid="tbl0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The most prevalent unmet social needs were similar but not identical between the short-form screener and PRAPARE (short-form screening tool: supplies for family and infant, 43.7%; social isolation, 41.4%; work/employment, 37.7%; and food, 37.2%; PRAPARE: social isolation, 72.1%; medicine or any healthcare, 36.7%; transportation-limited access to healthcare, 36.3%; clothing, 35.3%; and food, 34.4%) (<xref rid="sec0017" ref-type="fn">Appendix A</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0002" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Sensitivity and specificity of the short-form social needs screening tool compared with PRAPARE</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0002">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Social needs category</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sensitivity</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Specificity</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Material needs</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">84.2%</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">75.4%</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Support needs</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63.4%</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67.5%</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Any positive response</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">79.3%</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">71.4%</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><italic toggle="yes">PRAPARE</italic>, Protocol for Responding to and Assessing Patients&#8217; Assets, Risks, and Experiences.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><attrib>Peahl. Social determinants of health in pregnancy. Am J Obstet Gynecol Glob Rep 2023.</attrib></table-wrap></p><p id="para0025">Most participants believed it was important for their pregnancy care team to know about their social needs (material: 173 [80.5%]; support: 200 [93.0%]) and felt comfortable sharing their needs if assistance was available (material: 182 [84.7%]; support: 186 [86.5%]). Many participants were comfortable sharing their needs if assistance was not available (material: 117 [54.4%]; support: 122 [56.7%]). Over 75% of participants found each potential method of screening for addressing social needs acceptable. The methods preferred by most participants were identical for screening and management of both material and support needs: conversation with a care team member, email, and text message (<xref rid="tbl0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0003" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Proportion of participants reporting attitudes and preferences for screening for social needs by payer status</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0001a">Table 3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">Survey question</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Overall (N=215)</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Private Insurance (n=106)</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Public Insurance (n=109)</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="6" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"><bold>Attitudes</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"><bold>It is important for my care team to know my needs:</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">Material</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">173 (80.5%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">87 (82.1%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">86 (78.9%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.56</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">Support</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">200 (93.0%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99 (93.4%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101 (92.7%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.83</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"><bold>I am comfortable sharing my needs:</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">Material</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">182 (84.7%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">87 (82.1%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95 (87.2%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.30</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">Support</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">186 (86.5%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">91 (85.8%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95 (87.2%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.78</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"><bold>I am comfortable sharing my needs if my care team cannot help meet them:</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">Material</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">117 (54.4%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55 (51.9%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">62 (56.9%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.46</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">Support</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">122 (56.7%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56 (52.8%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66 (60.6%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.25</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"><bold>Preferences</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"><bold>How acceptable are the following ways to ask you questions about your needs?</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Text</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Material</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">170 (79.1%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">77 (72.6%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93 (85.3%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Support</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">177 (82.3%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">82 (77.4%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95 (87.2%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.06</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Email</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Material</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">185 (86.0%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92 (86.8%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93 (85.3%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.76</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Support</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">180 (83.7%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">87 (82.1%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93 (85.3%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.52</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">App</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Material</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">165 (76.7%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">81 (76.4%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">84 (77.1%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.91</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Support</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">163 (75.8%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">81 (76.4%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">82 (75.2%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.84</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Conversation with a care team member</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Material</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">198 (92.1%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97 (91.5%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101 (92.7%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.75</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Support</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">199 (92.6%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101 (95.3%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98 (89.9%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.13</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Conversation with a non-medical health worker</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Material</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">164 (76.3%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">82 (77.4%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">82 (75.2%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.71</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Support</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">170 (79.1%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">86 (81.1%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">84 (77.1%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.46</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Other<xref rid="tb3fn1" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="6" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"><bold>If you needed assistance for a material need, how acceptable are the following ways to receive these resources?</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Text</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Material</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">188 (87.4%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88 (83.0%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100 (91.7%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.05</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Support</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">189 (87.9%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93 (87.7%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96 (88.1%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.94</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Email</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Material</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">200 (93.0%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99 (93.4%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101 (92.7%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.83</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Support</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">193 (89.8%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96 (90.6%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97 (89.0%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.70</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">App</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Material</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">175 (81.4%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88 (83.0%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">87 (79.8%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.55</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Support</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">177 (82.3%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">85 (80.2%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92 (84.4%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.42</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Conversation with a care team member</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Material</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">203 (94.4%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99 (93.4%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">104 (95.4%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.52</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Support</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">198 (92.1%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99 (93.4%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99 (90.8%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.49</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Conversation with a non-medical health worker</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Material</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">187 (87.0%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94 (88.7%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93 (85.3%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.46</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Support</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">178 (82.8%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">90 (84.9%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88 (80.7%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.42</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Other<xref rid="tb3fn2" ref-type="table-fn">&#8270;&#8270;</xref></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tb3fn1"><label>&#8270;</label><p id="notep0001a">Other material=family/friends (14), phone call (5), other (5), *Other social=family/friends (12), phone call (4), other (6)</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tb3fn2"><label>&#8270;&#8270;</label><p id="notep0003a">Other material=family/friends (6), phone call (1), other (11), **Other social=family/friends (6), phone call (3), other (11)</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="para0026">Key themes from the qualitative analysis reflected positive and negative attitudes toward addressing social needs in routine prenatal care (<xref rid="tbl0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). On the individual level, participants with positive attitudes reflected <bold>no concerns</bold> about screening, and felt &#8220;open&#8221; to the process. They believed that social needs were <bold>part of healthcare</bold>, and connected social needs care to existing services, such as screening for intimate partner violence: &#8220;questions about the safety of my home already come up&#8230; so it isn't that big a stretch to ask if I feel isolated from my community.&#8221; Individual-level drivers of negative attitudes included concerns that sharing social needs could result in <bold>negative emotions</bold> such as being &#8220;embarrassed&#8221; or &#8220;feeling like a burden.&#8221; Some participants preferred to keep their <bold>social needs private</bold>: &#8220;it [my social needs] seems person[al], my pregnancy care team feels more clinical.&#8221;<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0004" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Qualitative analysis of free-response questions on attitudes toward screening and management of social needs</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0004">Table 4</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Theme</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n (%)</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Example quotes from participants&#8217; free-text responses</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">Patient-level attitudes toward screening and management of social needs</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">Positive attitudes</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No concerns about sharing needs:<break/>patient reports that they have no concerns about sharing social needs.</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68 (31.6)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8220;Not concerned at all.&#8221;<break/>&#8220;None, I'm pretty open<italic toggle="yes">.</italic>&#8221;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Belief that social needs are part of healthcare:<break/>patient believes that the care team should know about social needs for routine care.</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (2.8)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8220;Questions about the safety of my home already come up&#8230; and questions about mental health as is related to perinatal/postpartum depression are already asked, so it isn't that big a stretch to ask whether I feel isolated from my community.&#8221;<break/>&#8220;No concerns. They should know.&#8221;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" valign="top" rowspan="1">Negative attitudes</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Concerns about emotional consequences:<break/>patient has concerns about negative emotions associated with screening and management.</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17 (7.9)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8220;Don't like sharing my needs with people because I feel like a burden or like I'm being difficult.&#8221;<break/>&#8220;Sharing a material need with anyone just feels worse than struggling. And I tend to avoid it unless it's for my baby.&#8221;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" valign="top" rowspan="1">Provider- and health system-level attitudes toward screening and management of social needs</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" valign="top" rowspan="1">Positive attitudes</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Empathy:<break/>providers can encourage patients to share needs or provide support through demonstrating empathy.</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29 (13.5)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8220;Just being there to listen.&#8221;<break/>&#8220;Continue supporting me in my health decisions.&#8221;<break/>&#8220;By listening to what I have to say first instead of cutting me off.&#8221;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Linkage:<break/>providers can support social needs through giving information or linking to resources.</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44 (20.5)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8220;Providing a list of places or things to help with certain situations.&#8221;<break/>&#8220;By providing me with the right resources in the community and setting me up with them so I have the help and support I need.&#8221;<break/>&#8220;Tell me what is best for my baby and me.&#8221;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reaching out:<break/>providers can support patients by checking in.</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 (7.0)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8220;By checking in every couple of days and asking how mom and the family are doing.&#8221;<break/>&#8220;Call me.&#8221;<break/>&#8220;Reaching out.&#8221;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" valign="top" rowspan="1">Negative attitudes</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Concern for provider judgment:<break/>patient is concerned about being judged by the care team, limiting their willingness to share social needs.</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22 (10.2)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8220;Judgments of not being an adequate mother.&#8221;<break/>&#8220;I am worried I would be judged.&#8221;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Belief that no one will help:<break/>patients fear that providers will not be able to help, including not having sufficient resources, or will be unwilling to help them.</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 (7.4)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8220;I don't like to share [needs] with any entity that can't help.&#8221;<break/>&#8220;Feeling like it isn't [the provider's] place to help with that problem.&#8221;<break/>&#8220;I do not believe they can.&#8221;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Concern for provider indifference:<break/>patients are concerned about whether their social needs will be met with sympathy or care.</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (4.7)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8220;They don't care at all, not really, and they barely ask, and they don't even talk to you for that long.&#8221;<break/>&#8220;[I am concerned] that they don't take my needs seriously.&#8221;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fear of retribution:<break/>patients fear that their need or request for social needs will threaten their ability to parent.</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (3.7)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8220;Afraid social services could possibly try to take my child.&#8221;<break/>&#8220;That it will cause me to lose my child even though it's not my fault, and I'm doing the best I can right now.&#8221;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Concern about social needs being shared with others:<break/>patient prefers to keep social needs private and are concerned about confidentiality</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17 (7.9)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8220;My personal information being known by people I don't know.&#8221;<break/>&#8220;It getting to the wrong person.&#8221;<break/>&#8220;I feel that certain things/topics should be kept private.&#8221;</td></tr></tbody></table><attrib>Peahl. Social determinants of health in pregnancy. Am J Obstet Gynecol Glob Rep 2023.</attrib></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0005" orientation="portrait"><label>Box</label><caption><p>Short-form social needs screening tool</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0005">Box</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Question</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Response options</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">In the past year, have you or any family members you live with been unable to get any of the following when it was really needed?</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8226; Housing<break/>&#8226; Food<break/>&#8226; Utilities (eg, water, gas, electricity)<break/>&#8226; Medicine or any healthcare<break/>&#8226; Phone/internet<break/>&#8226; Supplies for infant and family<break/>&#8226; Work/employment<break/>&#8226; Care for children, elders, or household members with disabilities</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Do you feel lonely or isolated from those around you?</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8226; Yes<break/>&#8226; No<break/>&#8226; I prefer not to say</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Do you feel physically and emotionally safe?</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8226; Yes<break/>&#8226; No<break/>&#8226; I prefer not to say</td></tr></tbody></table><attrib>Peahl. Social determinants of health in pregnancy. Am J Obstet Gynecol Glob Rep 2023.</attrib></table-wrap></p><p id="para0027">On the provider and health system level, participants identified facilitators of addressing social needs in pregnancy. First, provider <bold>empathy</bold> could both encourage participants to share social needs and help them feel supported. If needs were identified, participants desired support through <bold>linkage</bold> to social needs information or resources and &#8220;<bold>reaching out</bold>&#8221; to see how the participant is doing. Several barriers were also identified. Some participants expressed concerns about provider <bold>indifference</bold> to their social needs, and that providers would not &#8220;take my needs seriously.&#8221; Participants were also concerned that their team would not <bold>be willing or able to help</bold> them. They worried that providers might <bold>judge</bold> them for unmet social needs and view them as &#8220;not being an adequate mother.&#8221; At the most extreme, participants worried about <bold>retribution</bold> for sharing their social needs, including losing their ability to parent: &#8220;[sharing my social needs] will cause me to lose my child, even though it's not my fault and I'm doing the best I can now.&#8221;</p><p id="para0028">Analyses revealed some differences across subgroups. Participants with public insurance vs those with private insurance were younger (28.0&#177;5.8 vs 32.2&#177;5.2) and had higher rates of all unmet social needs (<xref rid="tbl0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). More participants with at least 1 social need vs those without any social needs were Black (14.4% vs 2.1%), Hispanic (15.0% vs 6.3%), or postpartum (58.7% vs 35.4%) (<xref rid="sec0017" ref-type="fn">Appendix B</xref>).</p><p id="para0029">Black and Hispanic participants were more likely than White participants to report having at least 1 social need (Black: 95.7%; Hispanic: 89.3%; White: 74.3%; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=.02), including high rates of unmet needs for housing (Black: 25.0%; Hispanic: 60.9%; White: 22.3%), infant supplies (Black: 60.7%; Hispanic: 60.9%; White: 36.5%), social isolation (Black: 50.0%; Hispanic: 60.9%; White: 39.2%), and concerns for safety (Black: 32.1%; Hispanic: 30.4%; White: 14.2%) (<xref rid="sec0017" ref-type="fn">Appendix C</xref>).</p><p id="para0030">There were no differences across subgroups&#8217; reported importance of social needs screening or comfort sharing social needs (<xref rid="tbl0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>; Appendix 4 and 5). Similarly, all subgroups rated all methods of screening and management positively. More participants with vs without any social need preferred text messages for screening for support needs (86.2% vs 68.8%; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;.01) (<xref rid="sec0017" ref-type="fn">Appendix D</xref>). More participants with public vs private insurance preferred text messages for screening for material needs (85.3% vs 72.6%; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=.02) (<xref rid="tbl0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Fewer Black participants preferred conversations with their care team or nonmedical professionals for screening and managing material and support needs compared with Hispanic and White participants (<xref rid="sec0017" ref-type="fn">Appendix E</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec0010"><title>Comment</title><sec id="sec0011"><title>Principal findings</title><p id="para0031">In this national survey of pregnant and postpartum people, we found that a digital short-form screening tool had high sensitivity and specificity for detecting material and overall needs, and moderate sensitivity and specificity for detecting support needs. Over three-quarters of participants reported at least 1 social need. Most thought that it was important for their pregnancy care team to know their needs and felt comfortable sharing their needs if assistance was available. Over half of participants still felt comfortable sharing their needs even if assistance was not available. Participants identified a variety of acceptable methods for screening and management of social needs, with subtle differences in preferences between key demographic groups. Thematic analysis revealed key facilitators and barriers of implementing social needs screening at multiple levels.</p></sec><sec id="sec0012"><title>Results in the context of what is known</title><p id="para0032">An ideal screening tool identifies a condition that can be intervened on, has high sensitivity, and is easily deployed.<xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref> Our short-form screening tool meets these criteria, screening for critical prenatal risk factors with good performance when compared with the current gold standard, PRAPARE.<xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> PRAPARE has been widely implemented across multiple populations with good feasibility and acceptability,<xref rid="bib0036" ref-type="bibr"><sup>36</sup></xref> and is designed to identify both active needs and &#8220;risk&#8221; of social needs, irrespective of a person's preference for assistance. Thus, PRAPARE may identify people for social services that are not needed or wanted. A more discriminating tool may be useful, particularly in resource-limited settings, to identify the people with the most significant needs. Finally, knowledge of unmet social needs is actionable through a variety of interventions, including care adaptations and referrals to community resources.<xref rid="bib0017" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref></p><p id="para0033">The prevalence of social needs was over 75% with both screening tools, similar to the high rate of unmet social needs in general low-income populations.<xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref> We lack national prevalence data on social needs in pregnancy for many reasons: although national organizations recommend social needs screening, uptake has been limited.<xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> Even when social needs screening is done, access to data is limited. Billing codes for SDoH (&#8220;Z codes&#8221;) are rarely used,<xref rid="bib0038" ref-type="bibr"><sup>38</sup></xref> and data collected for social services is often available only for pragmatic care coordination. Finally, widely available zip code&#8211;based measures such as the Social Vulnerability Index extrapolate neighborhood-level social factors but cannot accurately capture individual experience.<xref rid="bib0039" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39</sup></xref> Thus, our understanding of which needs are most prevalent, where, and for whom is limited.</p><p id="para0034">Specific contextual factors may have affected the prevalence of specific social needs identified in our study, particularly those with highest prevalence. This study was performed during the national formula shortage, limiting access to infant supplies. Furthermore, because this study was performed in the postacute COVID-19 pandemic period, it is possible that peripartum people were practicing social distancing, affecting their experience of social isolation.<xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr"><sup>40</sup></xref> Social isolation is not limited to the pandemic, and may occur with routine seasonal illness, limited ability to travel, or demands of parenthood. This finding is particularly salient given the known negative health consequences of social isolation in pregnancy.<xref rid="bib0041" ref-type="bibr"><sup>41</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib0042" ref-type="bibr"><sup>42</sup></xref></p><p id="para0035">Little data explores pregnant patients&#8217; preferences for addressing social needs in pregnancy. Data from the general population demonstrate high acceptability of clinical SDoH programs.<xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref> In pregnancy, qualitative studies yield similar findings,<xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> but these have been largely single-site studies with specific patient populations. Our diverse sample of patients with diverse demographic characteristics expands these findings to broader patient populations.</p></sec><sec id="sec0013"><title>Clinical implications</title><p id="para0036">Social needs significantly affect pregnancy outcomes; for example, food insecurity may affect glycemic control. Transportation barriers may preclude care access. Social isolation may increase postpartum depression. Our study demonstrates that social needs programs delivered through multiple modalities are acceptable to pregnant people. Digital deployment of social needs screening in particular may fit existing infrastructure and resources in clinical settings.</p><p id="para0037">Importantly, in our study, social needs were prevalent among participants with both private and public insurance. In many settings, screening for social needs is tied to payer type, with social needs screening and support offered predominantly through Medicaid.<xref rid="bib0043" ref-type="bibr"><sup>43</sup></xref> Our study highlights the critical importance of universal social needs screening and management programs.</p><p id="para0038">Many providers and health systems express concerns about screening for SDoH if resources are not available to meet social needs.<xref rid="bib0044" ref-type="bibr"><sup>44</sup></xref> Importantly, fewer participants in our survey were willing to share their needs if assistance was not available, although over half were still comfortable sharing this information. Participants in our survey highlighted ways in which a care team could provide support beyond linkage to resources, including showing empathy and &#8220;reaching out.&#8221; We did not assess participants&#8217; comfort in sharing their social needs if these interventions were available in the absence of tangible assistance: it is possible that patients may be more willing to share their social needs if they know that their hardship will not be met with indifference. Defining the prevalence of social needs is a critical step in garnering resources to address them. These care team supports may be important temporizing methods while health systems and communities continue to develop resources to address the myriad unmet social needs faced by pregnant people and their families.</p><p id="para0039">Participants had significant concerns about sharing their social needs, including worries about facing judgment about their fitness for parenthood and potential loss of custody of their children. Social needs programs must incorporate best practices such as trauma-informed care<xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr"><sup>45</sup></xref> and humble inquiry<xref rid="bib0046" ref-type="bibr"><sup>46</sup></xref> to create a welcoming, supportive environment for patients. To this end, some screening tools include a question about the participant's desire for assistance, to support autonomy and respect of the person undergoing social needs screening.<xref rid="bib0047" ref-type="bibr"><sup>47</sup></xref> The addition of this kind of language may be beneficial, particularly for people from historically marginalized populations. Regardless of the approach, all members of the care team must be prepared to treat each pregnant and postpartum person with dignity and respect.</p></sec><sec id="sec0014"><title>Research implications</title><p id="para0040">Our study provides initial proof of concept of a short-form screening tool in prenatal care. Future work is needed to validate the tool in real-world clinical practice across more diverse populations with more robust confirmatory questionnaires, outside of a paid, online survey. Although all methods of screening for social needs and connecting people to resources were rated favorably by most participants, many more participants reported comfort with completing these activities with a care team member. Given the known barriers to technology, including device access and digital literacy, and the sensitivity of social needs, it will be important to understand pregnant people's concerns about completing these activities digitally. Although digital deployment of social needs interventions can assist with scalability, effectiveness hinges on acceptability. As programs are initiated, implementation science can provide important insights building on the multilevel barriers identified in this study.</p><p id="para0041">Our qualitative work revealed important themes about patients&#8217; attitudes toward addressing social needs. These views are particularly important to understand in historically marginalized groups who face a higher burden of medical and mental health conditions, experience higher rates of unmet social needs, and are simultaneously more likely to be disenfranchised from the health system.<xref rid="bib0048" ref-type="bibr"><sup>48</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib0049" ref-type="bibr"><sup>49</sup></xref> Qualitative methods informed by human-centered design (a method for designing solutions from the user's perspective) can help develop social needs programs <italic toggle="yes">for</italic> pregnant people <italic toggle="yes">by</italic> pregnant people<italic toggle="yes">.</italic><xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr"><sup>50</sup></xref> These methods may improve success rates of social needs programs in primary-care settings, where only a fraction of patients are followed up with offered assistance.</p><p id="para0042">Importantly, the themes that arose in our study came from free-text responses to open-ended questions, to which many participants did not provide responses. Caution should be used when interpreting the quantitative comparisons between groups, and the lack of statistical significance should not be interpreted as homogeneity among groups. It is notable that so many patients reflected the same experiences, hopes, and concerns about social needs screening. Assessing these themes in more quantitative ways across diverse populations will be helpful for understanding potential differential effects and unintended consequences of social needs screening on historically marginalized groups, particularly for pregnant people from historically marginalized racial and ethnic groups, people living on low income, and people with unmet social needs.</p><p id="para0043">Finally, the short-form screening tool provides an important option for inquiring about SDoH in research. The efficient 3-question tool adds minimal burden to research participants while providing important context on the patient's unmet social needs. Greater understanding of SDoH across a variety of research questions will generate important data to understand the effects of unmet social needs on care access, outcomes, and experience.</p></sec><sec id="sec0015"><title>Strengths and limitations</title><p id="para0044">Our study has several strengths, including a national sample, with characteristics comparable to national estimates of insurance coverage and race and ethnicity.<xref rid="bib0048" ref-type="bibr"><sup>48</sup></xref> Our short-form screening tool is tested against the national gold standard for assessing social needs. In addition, our focus on participants&#8217; perspectives provides an important contribution to the literature. Our rich qualitative data complement our robust quantitative data, and provide unique insights on addressing social needs in pregnancy.</p><p id="para0045">Our study does have limitations. It was conducted during the postacute COVID-19 pandemic period, which may have affected the prevalence of unmet social needs. Participants in our study may have been more likely to have unmet social needs because they registered for a paid online survey platform and completed the survey for compensation. Although the higher prevalence allows us to have more confidence in our screening tool test characteristics, it limits the generalizability of our findings on the prevalence of unmet social needs. In addition, the survey was conducted only in English. We therefore, cannot comment on the preferences or experience of people who do not speak English as their primary language. Similarly, our study population included a relatively small number of participants from historically marginalized groups, including Black and Hispanic people, and we were underpowered to detect differences in preferences between groups. Future work is needed to validate these preferences in diverse groups to ensure that social needs interventions are designed for all people and do not further exacerbate existing inequities. Finally, our qualitative data were limited to short free-response questions.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec0016"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="para0046">In sum, pregnant and postpartum people agree that social needs are an important part of prenatal care and are comfortable sharing their needs and receiving assistance through a variety of modalities, including digital services. A short-form screening tool has high sensitivity for detecting unmet social needs, and may alleviate some barriers to addressing social needs in pregnancy. Pregnant people experience unmet social needs, regardless of whether care teams systematically screen for them or identify them incidentally. This study provides important insights for expanding social needs programs to all patients, in an effective, efficient, and patient-centered manner.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebibl1"><title>References</title><ref id="bib0001"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0001"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</collab></person-group><part-title>Frequently asked questions</part-title><year>2019</year><publisher-name>Social determinants of health</publisher-name><comment>Available at:</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/nchhstp/socialdeterminants/faq.html" id="interref0002">https://www.cdc.gov/nchhstp/socialdeterminants/faq.html</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0002"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0002"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>The Sycamore Institute</collab></person-group><part-title>Tennessee health &amp; well-being index</part-title><year>2022</year><comment>Available at:</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.sycamoreinstitutetn.org/tn-health-well-being-index/" id="interref0003">https://www.sycamoreinstitutetn.org/tn-health-well-being-index/</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0003">US Department of Health and Human Services. Healthy people 2030. Social determinants of health. Available at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://health.gov/healthypeople/priority-areas/social-determinants-health" id="interref0004">https://health.gov/healthypeople/priority-areas/social-determinants-health</ext-link>. Accessed 26 September 2022.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib0004"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0004"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lorch</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Enlow</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of social determinants in explaining racial/ethnic disparities in perinatal outcomes</article-title><source>Pediatr Res</source><volume>79</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>147</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26466077</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/pr.2015.199</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11836890</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0005"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0005"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marmot</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Friel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Houweling</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Closing the gap in a generation: health equity through action on the social determinants of health</article-title><source>The Lancet</source><volume>372</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>1661</fpage><lpage>1669</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(08)61690-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18994664</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0006"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0006"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Committee on Health Care for Underserved Women</collab></person-group><article-title>ACOG Committee Opinion No. 729: importance of social determinants of health and cultural awareness in the delivery of reproductive health care</article-title><source>Obstet Gynecol</source><volume>131</volume><year>2018</year><comment>e43&#8211;8</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/AOG.0000000000002459</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29266079</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0007"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0007"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>National Academies. Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine</collab></person-group><part-title>Integrating social care into the delivery of health care: moving upstream to improve the nation's health</part-title><year>2019</year><comment>Available at:</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.nationalacademies.org/our-work/integrating-social-needs-care-into-the-delivery-of-health-care-to-improve-the-nations-health" id="interref0005">https://www.nationalacademies.org/our-work/integrating-social-needs-care-into-the-delivery-of-health-care-to-improve-the-nations-health</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31940159</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0008">American Academy of Family Physicians. AAFP committed to addressing the social determinants of health, striving for health equity. 2023. Available at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.aafp.org/news/media-center/kits/social-determinants-of-health.html" id="interref0006">https://www.aafp.org/news/media-center/kits/social-determinants-of-health.html</ext-link>. Accessed 26 September 2022.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib0009"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0009"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>American College of Nurse-Midwives</collab></person-group><part-title>Our philosophy of care</part-title><year>2022</year><comment>Available at:</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.midwife.org/Our-Philosophy-of-Care" id="interref0007">https://www.midwife.org/Our-Philosophy-of-Care</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0010"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0010"><comment>Electronic address: pubs@smfm.org</comment><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Society for Maternal-Fetal Medicine (SMFM)</collab><name name-style="western"><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gandhi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><collab>Publications Committee</collab></person-group><article-title>Society for Maternal-Fetal Medicine Consult Series #62: best practices in equitable care delivery-addressing systemic racism and other social determinants of health as causes of obstetrical disparities</article-title><source>Am J Obstet Gynecol</source><volume>227</volume><year>2022</year><comment>B44&#8211;59</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ajog.2022.04.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35378098</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0011"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0011"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peahl</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zahn</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turrentine</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Michigan plan for appropriate tailored healthcare in pregnancy prenatal care recommendations</article-title><source>Obstet Gynecol</source><volume>138</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>593</fpage><lpage>602</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34352810</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/AOG.0000000000004531</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12101528</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0012"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0012"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heaman</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sword</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Barriers and facilitators related to use of prenatal care by inner-city women: perceptions of health care providers</article-title><source>BMC Pregnancy Childbirth</source><volume>15</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>2</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25591945</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12884-015-0431-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4302607</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0013"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0013"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tucker Edmonds</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mogul</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shea</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding low-income African American women's expectations, preferences, and priorities in prenatal care</article-title><source>Fam Community Health</source><volume>38</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>157</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25739062</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/FCH.0000000000000066</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0014"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0014"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reyes</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akanyirige</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wishart</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Interventions addressing social needs in perinatal care: a systematic review</article-title><source>Health Equity</source><volume>5</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>100</fpage><lpage>118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33778313</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1089/heq.2020.0051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7990569</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0015"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0015"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peahl</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moniz</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heisler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Experiences with prenatal care delivery reported by Black patients with low income and by health care workers in the US: a qualitative study</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><volume>5</volume><year>2022</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e2238161</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.38161</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9593232</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36279136</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0016"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0016"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>National Association of Community Health Centers</collab></person-group><part-title>Protocol for responding to and assessing patient assets, risks, and experiences (PRAPARE)</part-title><year>2016</year><comment>Available at:</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://prapare.org/the-prapare-screening-tool/" id="interref0008">https://prapare.org/the-prapare-screening-tool/</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0017"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0017"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Plunkett</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Universal screening for perinatal depression</article-title><source>NeoReviews</source><volume>19</volume><year>2018</year><comment>e143&#8211;51</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0018"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0018"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McNeely</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Subramaniam</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Performance of the Tobacco, Alcohol, Prescription Medication, and Other Substance Use (TAPS) Tool for substance use screening in primary care patients</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><volume>165</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>690</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27595276</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7326/M16-0317</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5291717</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0019"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0019"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>TV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Screening for health-related social needs in pediatric value-based care: moving from why to how</article-title><source>JAMA Pediatr</source><volume>176</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34633414</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamapediatrics.2021.3598</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0020"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0020"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guille</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maldonado</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A non-randomized trial of in-person versus text/telephone screening, brief intervention and referral to treatment for pregnant and postpartum women</article-title><source>Psychiatr Res Clin Pract</source><volume>3</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>172</fpage><lpage>183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36101654</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1176/appi.prcp.20210027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9175992</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0021"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0021"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Revilla</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ochoa</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ideal and maximum length for a web survey</article-title><source>International Journal of Market Research</source><volume>59</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>557</fpage><lpage>565</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0022"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0022"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bunce</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cowburn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Adoption of social determinants of health EHR tools by community health centers</article-title><source>Ann Fam Med</source><volume>16</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>399</fpage><lpage>407</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30201636</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1370/afm.2275</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6131002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0023"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0023"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schickedanz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>YR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impact of social needs navigation on utilization among high utilizers in a large Integrated health system: a quasi-experimental study</article-title><source>J Gen Intern Med</source><volume>34</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>2382</fpage><lpage>2389</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31228054</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11606-019-05123-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6848288</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0024"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0024"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fraze</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brewster</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beidler</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Colla</surname><given-names>CH.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of screening for food insecurity, housing instability, utility needs, transportation needs, and interpersonal violence by US physician practices and hospitals</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><volume>2</volume><year>2019</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e1911514</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2019.11514</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6752088</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31532515</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0025"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0025"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bleacher</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>English</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leblanc</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dickinson</surname><given-names>LM.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Associations between patients&#8217; unmet social needs and self-reported health confidence at one primary care clinic</article-title><source>J Prim Care Community Health</source><volume>11</volume><year>2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2150132720921329</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/2150132720921329</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7232046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32410492</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0026">Keisler-Starkey K, Bunch LN. Health insurance coverage in the United States: 2019.:26.<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.census.gov/content/dam/Census/library/publications/2022/demo/p60-278.pdf" id="interref0009z">https://www.census.gov/content/dam/Census/library/publications/2022/demo/p60-278.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib0027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0027">Microsoft Support. Get your document's readability and level statistics. 2022. Available at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://support.microsoft.com/en-us/office/get-your-document-s-readability-and-level-statistics-85b4969e-e80a-4777-8dd3-f7fc3c8b3fd2" id="interref0009">https://support.microsoft.com/en-us/office/get-your-document-s-readability-and-level-statistics-85b4969e-e80a-4777-8dd3-f7fc3c8b3fd2</ext-link>. Accessed 20 December 2022.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib0028"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0028"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peahl</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berlin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Patient and provider perspectives of a new prenatal care model introduced in response to the coronavirus disease 2019 pandemic</article-title><source>Am J Obstet Gynecol</source><volume>224</volume><year>2021</year><comment>384.e1&#8211;11</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ajog.2020.10.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7543890</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33039393</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0029"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0029"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>United States Census Bureau</collab></person-group><part-title>2020 Census</part-title><year>2022</year><comment>Available at:</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.census.gov/2020census" id="interref0010">https://www.census.gov/2020census</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0030"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0030"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Psychometric evaluation of the Diabetes Self-Management Instrument Short Form (DSMI-20)</article-title><source>Appl Nurs Res</source><volume>29</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26856494</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.apnr.2015.04.013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0031"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0031"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Terkawi</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Backonja</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abolkhair</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Development and validation of Arabic version of the Neuropathic Pain Questionnaire-Short Form</article-title><source>Saudi J Anaesth</source><volume>11</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>S53</fpage><lpage>S62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28616004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4103/sja.SJA_86_17</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5463567</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0032"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0032"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jumbo</surname><given-names>SU</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>MacDermid</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Packham</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Athwal</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Faber</surname><given-names>KJ.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reproducibility: reliability and agreement parameters of the Revised Short McGill Pain Questionnaire Version-2 for use in patients with musculoskeletal shoulder pain</article-title><source>Health Qual Life Outcomes</source><volume>18</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>365</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33176784</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12955-020-01617-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7661222</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0033"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0033"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bujang</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adnan</surname><given-names>TH.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Requirements for minimum sample size for sensitivity and specificity analysis</article-title><source>J Clin Diagn Res</source><volume>10</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>YE01</fpage><lpage>YE06</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7860/JCDR/2016/18129.8744</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5121784</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27891446</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0034">R Core Team. R: a language and environment for statistical computing. 2021. Available at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.r-project.org/" id="interref0011">https://www.r-project.org/</ext-link>. Accessed January 20, 2022.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib0035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0035">World Health Organization. Screening programmes: a short guide. Increased effectiveness, maximize benefits and minimize harm. 2020. Available at:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/handle/10665/330829/9789289054782-eng.pdf" id="interref0012">https://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/handle/10665/330829/9789289 054782-eng.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed October 15, 2022.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib0036"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0036"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Protocol for Responding to and Accessing Patients&#8217; Assets, Risks, and Experiences</collab></person-group><part-title>Measuring patient social risk to drive care transformation: the PRAPARE experience</part-title><year>2022</year><comment>Available at:</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://prapare.org/knowledge-center/whitepapers-and-publications/measuring-patient-social-risk-to-drive-care-transformation-the-prapare-experience/" id="interref0013">https://prapare.org/knowledge-center/whitepapers-and-publications/measuring-patient-social-risk-to-drive-care-transformation-the-prapare-experience/</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0037"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0037"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Kaiser Permanente</collab></person-group><part-title>Social needs survey key findings</part-title><year>2019</year><comment>Published online:</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://about.kaiserpermanente.org/content/dam/internet/kp/comms/import/uploads/2019/06/KP-Social-Needs-Survey-Key-Findings.pdf" id="interref0013s">https://about.kaiserpermanente.org/content/dam/internet/kp/comms/import/uploads/2019/06/KP-Social-Needs-Survey-Key-Findings.pdf</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0038">Kepper MM, Walsh-Bailey C, Prusaczyk B, Zhao M, Herrick C, Foraker R, 2022. The adoption of social determinants of health documentation in clinical settings. <italic toggle="yes">Health Services Research</italic>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/1475-6773.14039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9836948</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35862115</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib0039"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0039"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</collab></person-group><part-title>Agency for Toxic Substances and Disease Registry/Geospatial Research, Analysis, and Services Program</part-title><year>2022</year><publisher-name>CDC/ATSDR Social Vulnerability Index 2018 Database US</publisher-name><comment>Available at:</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.atsdr.cdc.gov/placeandhealth/svi/data_documentation_download.html" id="interref0014">https://www.atsdr.cdc.gov/placeandhealth/svi/data_documentation_download.html</ext-link><comment>Accesses October 15, 2022</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0040"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0040"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shuman</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiangong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mourning the experience of what should have been&#8221;: experiences of peripartum women during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>Matern Child Health J</source><volume>26</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>102</fpage><lpage>109</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34993749</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10995-021-03344-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8739000</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0041"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0041"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Molyneaux</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rochat</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Milgrom</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Non-psychotic mental disorders in the perinatal period</article-title><source>The Lancet</source><volume>384</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>1775</fpage><lpage>1788</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(14)61276-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25455248</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0042"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0042"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McLeish</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Redshaw</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mothers&#8217; accounts of the impact on emotional wellbeing of organised peer support in pregnancy and early parenthood: a qualitative study</article-title><source>BMC Pregnancy Childbirth</source><volume>17</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>28</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28086827</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12884-017-1220-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5237175</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0043"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0043"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hinton</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><collab>Aug 05 LSP, 2021</collab></person-group><part-title>Medicaid authorities and options to address social determinants of health (SDOH) - issue brief</part-title><year>2021</year><publisher-name>KFF</publisher-name><comment>Available at:</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.kff.org/report-section/medicaid-authorities-and-options-to-address-social-determinants-of-health-sdoh-issue-brief/" id="interref0015">https://www.kff.org/report-section/medicaid-authorities-and-options-to-address-social-determinants-of-health-sdoh-issue-brief/</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0044"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0044"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schickedanz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamity</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinician experiences and attitudes regarding screening for social determinants of health in a large integrated health system</article-title><source>Med Care</source><volume>57</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>S197</fpage><lpage>S201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31095061</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/MLR.0000000000001051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6721844</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0045"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0045"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Owens</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Terrell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Low</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Universal precautions: the case for consistently trauma-informed reproductive healthcare</article-title><source>Am J Obstet Gynecol</source><volume>226</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>671</fpage><lpage>677</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34418349</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ajog.2021.08.012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0046"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0046"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schein</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schein</surname><given-names>PA.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Humble inquiry: The gentle art of asking instead of telling</part-title><year>2021</year><publisher-name>Berrett-Koehler Publishers</publisher-name><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://books.google.com/books?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;id=XJjyDwAAQBAJ&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PP&amp;dq=The+Gentle+Art+of+Asking+Instead+of+Telling.+&amp;ots=LdKyorwp6y&amp;sig=fA-Tyn_kugBcEyn8bdcd2GkSLVg#v=onepage&amp;q=The%20Gentle%20Art%20of%20Asking%20Instead%20of%20Telling.&amp;f=false" id="interref0016g">https://books.google.com/books?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;id=XJjyDwAAQBAJ&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PP&amp;dq=The+Gentle+Art+of+Asking+Instead+of+Telling.+&amp;ots=LdKyorwp6y&amp;sig=fA-Tyn_kugBcEyn8bdcd2GkSLVg#v=onepage&amp;q=The%20Gentle%20Art%20of%20Asking%20Instead%20of%20Telling.&amp;f=false</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0047"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0047"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Social Interventions Research and Evaluation Network</collab></person-group><part-title>Screening tools comparison tables</part-title><year>2018</year><comment>Available at:</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://sirenetwork.ucsf.edu/tools-resources/resources/screening-tools-comparison-tables" id="interref0016">https://sirenetwork.ucsf.edu/tools-resources/resources/screening-tools-comparison-tables</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0048"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0048"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Osterman</surname><given-names>MJK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Timing and adequacy of prenatal care in the United States, 2016</article-title><source>Natl Vital Stat Rep</source><volume>67</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29874159</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0049"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0049"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Admon</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Winkelman</surname><given-names>TNA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moniz</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heisler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalton</surname><given-names>VK.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Disparities in chronic conditions among women hospitalized for delivery in the United States, 2005-2014</article-title><source>Obstet Gynecol</source><volume>130</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>1319</fpage><lpage>1326</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29112666</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/AOG.0000000000002357</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5709216</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0050"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0050"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wheelock</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bechtel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leff</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human-centered design and trust in medicine</article-title><source>JAMA</source><volume>324</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>2369</fpage><lpage>2370</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33320236</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.2020.21080</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="sec0018" sec-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix</label><title>Supplementary materials</title><p id="para0047a">
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ecom0001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc1.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><alt-text>Image, application 1</alt-text></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec><ack id="ack0001"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p id="para0048">The authors are grateful to the survey participants who provided the data analyzed in this research. We are also grateful to Kyle Magida, MSc for reviewing the analytic code.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="d35e1142"><p id="notep0001">Patient consent was obtained at the time of the survey.</p></fn><fn id="d35e1145"><p id="notep0002">This research was funded by Maven Clinic through the employment of authors. L.R.M., H.R.J., A.P., N.H., C.M., and N.S. hold positions at Maven Clinic and have equity in Maven Clinic, and A.F.P. and V.P. are paid consultants for Maven Clinic.</p></fn><fn id="d35e1148"><p id="notep0003"><bold>Cite this article as:</bold> Peahl AF, Rubin-Miller L, Paterson V, et al. Understanding social needs in pregnancy: prospective validation of a digital short-form screening tool and patient survey. Am J Obstet Gynecol Glob Rep 2023;XX:x.ex&#8211;x.ex.</p></fn><fn id="sec0017" fn-type="supplementary-material"><p id="para0009a">Supplementary material associated with this article can be found in the online version at doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.xagr.2022.100158" id="interref0001">10.1016/j.xagr.2022.100158</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article></pmc-articleset>