<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Epidemiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Epidemiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">745</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">intjepid</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ije</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Epidemiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0300-5771</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1464-3685</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12133260</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12133260.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12133260</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12133260</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40461104</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ije/dyaf076</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">dyaf076</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Cohort Profile</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection"><subject>AcademicSubjects/MED00860</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Cohort Profile: The Ontario Mental Health and Intersectionality Data Surveillance (Ontario-MINDS) Cohort</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names initials="KK">Kelly K</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Department of Epidemiology and Biostatistics, Schulich School of Medicine and Dentistry, Western University</institution>, London, ON, <country country="CA">Canada</country></aff><aff>
<institution>Department of Psychiatry, Schulich School of Medicine and Dentistry, Western University</institution>, London, ON, <country country="CA">Canada</country></aff><aff>
<institution>ICES Western, London Health Sciences Centre Research Institute</institution>, London, ON, <country country="CA">Canada</country></aff><aff>
<institution>Children&#8217;s Health Research Institute</institution>, London, ON, <country country="CA">Canada</country></aff><xref rid="dyaf076-cor1" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names initials="R">Rebecca</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Department of Epidemiology and Biostatistics, Schulich School of Medicine and Dentistry, Western University</institution>, London, ON, <country country="CA">Canada</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rotenberg</surname><given-names initials="M">Martin</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Centre for Addiction and Mental Health</institution>, Toronto, ON, <country country="CA">Canada</country></aff><aff>
<institution>Department of Psychiatry, University of Toronto</institution>, Toronto, ON, <country country="CA">Canada</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names initials="J">Jordan</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Hamilton Health Sciences</institution>, Hamilton, ON, <country country="CA">Canada</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Le</surname><given-names initials="B">Britney</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>ICES Western, London Health Sciences Centre Research Institute</institution>, London, ON, <country country="CA">Canada</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="dyaf076-cor1">Corresponding author. Department of Epidemiology and Biostatistics, Western University, Western Centre for Public Health and Family Medicine, 3rd Floor, 1465 Richmond Street, London, ON N6G 2M1, Canada. E-mail: <email>kelly.anderson@schulich.uwo.ca</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>6</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2025-06-03"><day>03</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>54</volume><issue>3</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">486702</issue-id><elocation-id>dyaf076</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>05</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="editorial-decision"><day>29</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>08</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>03</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>03</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-06-07 12:25:24.773"><day>07</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2025. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the International Epidemiological Association.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs licence (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial reproduction and distribution of the work, in any medium, provided the original work is not altered or transformed in any way, and that the work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact reprints@oup.com for reprints and translation rights for reprints. All other permissions can be obtained through our RightsLink service via the Permissions link on the article page on our site&#8212;for further information please contact journals.permissions@oup.com.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="dyaf076.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="dyaf076.pdf"/><kwd-group><kwd>children and youth</kwd><kwd>mental disorders</kwd><kwd>substance-use disorders</kwd><kwd>birth cohort</kwd><kwd>health administrative data</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Children&#8217;s Health Research Institute</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="7"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><boxed-text id="dyaf076-BOX1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Key Features</label><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>The Ontario Mental health and Intersectionality Data Surveillance (Ontario-MINDS) retrospective cohort was established to address the lack of longitudinal population-based data on child and youth mental health. The cohort includes youth born between 1992 and 1996 who resided in the province at any point prior to 12 years of age (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;831&#8202;957), created using population-based health administrative data.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The cohort includes sub-cohorts: (i) the MOMBABY sub-cohort, which includes linkages to maternal socio-demographic and clinical data, and (ii) a migrant sub-cohort, which identifies first- and second-generation migrants by using linkages to immigration data.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The cohort is followed up to age 30 years in the health administrative data to ascertain health service contacts for mental and substance-use disorders, with continuous follow-up for 87.5% of the cohort as of 2022. Incident cases of psychotic disorder have also been identified.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The data holdings include numerous socio-environmental variables, such as neighbourhood-level marginalization indicators and migrant status. The application of validated algorithms has enabled us to identify factors such as multimorbidity and health service encounters for adverse childhood experiences, and primary data linkages have facilitated the exploration of novel exposures, such as green space and air pollution throughout childhood.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Collaborations with investigators interested in life-course approaches to youth physical and mental health are welcomed. Use of the Ontario-MINDS cohort may be granted with the permission of the principal investigator (PI) to those who meet pre-specified criteria for confidential access. Please contact the project PI with any inquiries (<email>kelly.anderson@schulich.uwo.ca</email>).</p></list-item></list></boxed-text><sec><title>Why was the cohort set up?</title><p>The twenty-first century has brought a burgeoning recognition of the central role of mental health and illness to overall population health. Mental and substance-use disorders are among the top five leading contributors to the global burden of illness, largely owing to the young age at first onset [<xref rid="dyaf076-B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. It is estimated that one in five adolescents has a mental or substance-use disorder that will persist into adulthood [<xref rid="dyaf076-B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] and nearly 75% of lifetime mental disorders have an onset before the age of 25&#8201;years [<xref rid="dyaf076-B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Among children and youth, mental and substance-use disorders are the leading contributor to the total burden of illness in high-income countries and are responsible for the largest proportion of years lived with disability [<xref rid="dyaf076-B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="dyaf076-B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. However, these estimates do not reflect the full impact of these illnesses on the young people affected. The first onset of mental and substance-use disorders typically occurs during adolescence and early adulthood [<xref rid="dyaf076-B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], which may lead to disruptions in social, academic, and professional development. If left untreated, mental disorders among children and adolescents may recur and become chronic [<xref rid="dyaf076-B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="dyaf076-B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], potentially leading to poor trajectories into adulthood. These public health impacts are further compounded by the 7- to 10-year reduction in life expectancy faced by people with mental and substance-use disorders, largely attributable to the high prevalence of comorbid physical health conditions and a 12-fold higher risk of suicide [<xref rid="dyaf076-B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Suicide is currently the second-leading cause of death among young people between 15 and 24&#8201;years of age in Canada [<xref rid="dyaf076-B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] and &gt;75% of youth suicides involve a history of depression [<xref rid="dyaf076-B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].</p><p>Mental and substance-use disorders among children and youth are expected to become one of the most pressing public health challenges of our time [<xref rid="dyaf076-B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. However, efforts to address the substantial public health burden of these conditions are hindered by a lack of longitudinal population-based data [<xref rid="dyaf076-B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. The Ontario Mental health and Intersectionality Data Surveillance (Ontario-MINDS) cohort is a population-based retrospective cohort of Ontario children born between 1992 and 1996. The overarching aim of this research programme is to begin to fill the gap in longitudinal population-based research on mental and substance-use disorders among Canadian children and youth. With funding from the Children&#8217;s Health Research Institute in London, Ontario, the cohort was created in 2022 by using multiple linked health administrative databases housed at ICES (formerly the Institute for Clinical Evaluative Sciences), which is an independent, non-profit research institute that collates data from the Ontario healthcare system.</p></sec><sec><title>Who is in the cohort?</title><p>The Ontario-MINDS cohort includes youth born between 1992 and 1996 who were either born in Ontario or who resided in the province at any point prior to 12&#8201;years of age (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;831&#8202;957)&#8212;the latter group would include youth who moved to Ontario from other provinces as well as first-generation migrants who landed in Ontario. We selected 12&#8201;years of age to ensure the availability of at least one childhood data point for everyone in the cohort.</p><p>To build the cohort, we identified all people registered for the Ontario Health Insurance Plan (OHIP) with a birth date between 1 January 1992 and 31 December 1996. We excluded people for whom the start of OHIP eligibility occurred after age 12&#160;years, people who were no longer eligible for OHIP by age 12&#160;years, and where death occurred on or before the 12th birthday. We also excluded people with missing or invalid sex, and those who resided outside of Ontario. The date of OHIP eligibility was considered to be the index date. A flow chart showing the derivation of the Ontario-MINDS cohort is presented in <xref rid="dyaf076-F1" ref-type="fig">Figure&#160;1</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="dyaf076-F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Flow chart showing the derivation of the Ontario-MINDS cohort.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="dyaf076f1.jpg"><alt-text>Flow chart showing how the Ontario-MINDS cohort was derived and the numbers of children excluded.</alt-text></graphic></fig><p>The Ontario-MINDS cohort includes two sub-cohorts that can be used to address specific research questions:</p><list list-type="roman-lower"><list-item><p>The MOMBABY sub-cohort includes youth who are also linked to the ICES MOMBABY dataset (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;560&#8202;262). The MOMBABY dataset includes information on hospital births in Ontario and facilitates linkages with maternal data within the health administrative datasets. This sub-cohort can be used to examine perinatal exposures (e.g. maternal infection during pregnancy) or to obtain information on maternal socio-demographic or clinical factors (e.g. maternal history of mental illness).</p></list-item><list-item><p>The migrant sub-cohort (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;158&#8202;785) includes first-generation migrants who landed in Ontario prior to the age of 12&#160;years (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;84&#8202;785), as well as second-generation migrants whose mothers landed in Ontario after 1985 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;74&#8202;000). First-generation migrants were identified through linkages with the Immigration, Refugees, and Citizenship Canada&#8217;s Permanent Resident Database [Immigration, Refugees and Citizenship Canada (IRCC)-PR] [<xref rid="dyaf076-B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Second-generation migrants were identified by obtaining maternal data from the MOMBABY database and linking with the IRCC-PR database.</p></list-item></list><p>ICES is a prescribed entity under Ontario&#8217;s Personal Health Information Protection Act (PHIPA), which authorizes the collection of personal health information, without consent, for the purposes of health system analysis and evaluation. The use of the data in this project is authorized under section 45 of PHIPA and does not require review by a research ethics board.</p></sec><sec><title>How often have they been followed up?</title><p>The Ontario-MINDS cohort is based on routinely collected health administrative data, which allow the ongoing follow-up of cohort members. Follow-up begins at the start of OHIP eligibility (i.e. the index date) and continues until the termination of OHIP coverage (due to outmigration from Ontario), death, or the end of data availability at ICES. Ongoing updates to the follow-up period are planned as additional years of health administrative data become available.</p><p>Approximately 12.5% of the cohort (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;103&#8202;664) had been lost to follow-up as of 2022 (<xref rid="dyaf076-F2" ref-type="fig">Figure&#160;2</xref>) and the median follow-up time was 27.4&#8201;years (Interquartile Range&#8201;=&#8201;25.8, 29.0). There are no differences in socio-demographic characteristics of youth lost to follow-up (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S1</xref>) except that the proportion of first-generation migrants is significantly higher among people lost to follow-up (13.7%) relative to those with complete follow-up (9.7%).</p><fig position="float" id="dyaf076-F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Entry and exit into the Ontario-MINDS cohort (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;831&#8202;957), defined based on OHIP eligibility.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="dyaf076f2.jpg"><alt-text>Bar chart showing the number of children who entered and exited the Ontario-MINDS cohort each year.</alt-text></graphic></fig></sec><sec><title>What has been measured?</title><p>The ICES data holdings are predominantly derived from the publicly funded healthcare system in Ontario, known as the OHIP, which covers medically necessary services for nearly the entire population. In addition to the standard health system data&#8212;including outpatient physician visits, emergency department (ED) visits, hospitalizations, and vital status&#8212;ICES has linked a wide range of data holdings from other sectors and population-health surveys. These data holdings are routinely updated, with new linkages regularly available, thus providing a rich source of data on a vast array of exposures, confounding factors, and outcomes; some key variable definitions are described below.</p><sec><title>Mental health outcomes</title><p>The primary outcomes of interest in the Ontario-MINDS cohort are indicators of physician-based health service use for mental and substance-use disorders. Acute care visits include ED visits and hospitalizations, identified based on diagnostic codes. We also identified outpatient physician visits for mental and substance-use disorders by using OHIP billings. The diagnostic codes for the visits are categorized by using a standardized definition developed at ICES [<xref rid="dyaf076-B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], which includes the following categories: psychotic disorders, mood or anxiety disorders, other selected disorders (e.g. eating disorders, personality disorders), deliberate self-harm, substance-use disorders, and neurodevelopmental disorders (e.g. autism, attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder). ICES has also validated an algorithm to identify cases of non-affective psychotic disorders [<xref rid="dyaf076-B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="dyaf076-B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Suicide and mortality data are available through linkages with the Office of the Registrar General-Deaths Vital Statistics Database.</p></sec><sec><title>Selected socio-environmental and clinical data</title><p>There are numerous variables within the health administrative data that are of interest for advancing our understanding of mental and substance-use disorders among youth. For example, information on neighbourhood-level marginalization derived from census data&#8212;known as the Ontario Marginalization Index (ON-Marg) [<xref rid="dyaf076-B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]&#8212;is linked to the ICES data by using residential postal codes. The ON-Marg provides validated indicators across four dimensions: (i) material resources, which are derived from census items related to income, educational attainment, family structure, and housing&#8212;this indicator allows the assessment of socio-economic position; (ii) households and dwellings, which are derived from census items related to types of residences (e.g. owned vs. rented, apartments), household information (e.g. living alone, marital status), and population in- and outmigration&#8212;these map directly onto commonly used indicators of area-level social fragmentation [<xref rid="dyaf076-B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]; (iii) age and labour force, which are derived from census items related to the economic vitality of the area, including the proportion of the population who are older adults and children, as well as people unable to work due to disability; and (iv) racialized and newcomer populations, which are derived from census items related to visible minority groups and migrant status.</p><p>We can also apply existing algorithms to identify other determinants of mental and substance-use disorders. For example, we have applied the Johns Hopkins Adjusted Clinical Groups System to the outpatient and hospitalization data to identify comorbid physical health conditions and multimorbidity [<xref rid="dyaf076-B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. We have also adapted existing algorithms for identifying adverse childhood experiences in health administrative data [<xref rid="dyaf076-B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], which have enabled us to identify people who had health service encounters for experiences of abuse, neglect, or household dysfunction during childhood.</p><p>Finally, primary data linkages will enable us to explore novel antecedents of mental and substance-use disorders. For example, we have linked data from the Canadian Urban Environmental Health Research Consortium (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://canue.ca" ext-link-type="uri">https://canue.ca</ext-link>). This primary data linkage will allow us to explore the cumulative effects of environmental factors throughout childhood, such as green space and air pollution, on the subsequent risk of mental and substance-use disorders during adolescence and early adulthood.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>What has it found?</title><p>Socio-demographic characteristics of the Ontario-MINDS cohort at 12&#8201;years of age are presented in <xref rid="dyaf076-T1" ref-type="table">Table&#160;1</xref>. Most youth entered the cohort prior to age 4&#160;years, meaning that we can ascertain exposures of interest throughout most of the childhood. Based on linkages to IRCC data, 10.2% of the cohort are first-generation migrants and 8.9% of the cohort are second-generation migrants. Within the migrant sub-cohort, 16.8% of first-generation migrants (9.0% of total sub-cohort) arrived in Canada with refugee status and the most common regions of birth were South Asia (14.4%), East Asia (12.0%), Europe (8.7%), and North Africa and the Middle East (7.9%).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="dyaf076-T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Characteristics of the Ontario-MINDS cohort at age 12&#8201;years (<italic toggle="yes">N&#8201;</italic>=<italic toggle="yes">&#8201;</italic>831&#8202;957)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="char" char="(" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="char" char="(" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="char" char="(" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristic</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Full cohort (<italic toggle="yes">n&#8201;</italic>=<italic toggle="yes">&#8201;</italic>831</bold>&#8202;<bold>957)</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>MOMBABY sub-cohort (<italic toggle="yes">n&#8201;</italic>=<italic toggle="yes">&#8201;</italic>560</bold>&#8202;<bold>262)</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Migrant sub-cohort (<italic toggle="yes">n&#8201;</italic>=<italic toggle="yes">&#8201;</italic>158</bold>&#8202;<bold>785)</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age at cohort entry (years) [<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;0&#8211;4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">739&#8202;843 (88.9)</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96&#8202;755 (60.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;5&#8211;9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59&#8202;958 (7.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39&#8202;333 (24.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;10&#8211;12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32&#8202;156 (3.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22&#8202;697 (14.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex assigned at birth [<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">404&#8202;812 (48.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">273&#8202;112 (48.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76&#8202;946 (48.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">427&#8202;145 (51.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">287&#8202;150 (51.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81&#8202;839 (51.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rurality [<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Urban</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">728&#8202;815 (87.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">490&#8202;401 (87.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">155&#8202;719 (98.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Rural</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100&#8202;882 (12.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68&#8202;753 (12.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2688 (1.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neighbourhood material resources [<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Quintile 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">176&#8202;187 (21.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">124&#8202;257 (22.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26&#8202;813 (16.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Quintile 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">168&#8202;101 (20.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">118&#8202;738 (21.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25&#8202;896 (16.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Quintile 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">157&#8202;701 (19.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">107&#8202;742 (19.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28&#8202;446 (17.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Quintile 4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">148&#8202;014 (17.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97&#8202;649 (17.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30&#8202;530 (19.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Quintile 5 (most marginalized)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">168&#8202;276 (20.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">103&#8202;707 (18.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45&#8202;821 (28.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neighbourhood age and labour force [<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Quintile 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">222&#8202;036 (26.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">143&#8202;721 (25.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57&#8202;402 (36.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Quintile 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">190&#8202;534 (22.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">128&#8202;031 (22.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41&#8202;268 (26.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Quintile 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">156&#8202;036 (18.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">106&#8202;847 (19.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26&#8202;755 (16.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Quintile 4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">135&#8202;466 (16.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94&#8202;166 (16.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18&#8202;012 (11.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Quintile 5 (most marginalized)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">114&#8202;207 (13.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79&#8202;328 (14.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14&#8202;069 (8.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neighbourhood racialized/newcomer population [<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Quintile 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">117&#8202;990 (14.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85&#8202;376 (15.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4030 (2.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Quintile 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">133&#8202;025 (16.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">98&#8202;289 (17.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6090 (3.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Quintile 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">147&#8202;580 (17.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">109&#8202;055 (19.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11&#8202;899 (7.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Quintile 4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">173&#8202;595 (20.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">122&#8202;168 (21.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29&#8202;377 (18.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Quintile 5 (most marginalized)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">246&#8202;089 (29.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">137&#8202;205 (24.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">106&#8202;110 (66.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neighbourhood households and dwellings [<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Quintile 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">209&#8202;932 (25.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">148&#8202;539 (26.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40&#8202;309 (25.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Quintile 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">169&#8202;061 (20.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">118&#8202;701 (21.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24&#8202;784 (15.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Quintile 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">149&#8202;646 (18.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">104&#8202;425 (18.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20&#8202;064 (12.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Quintile 4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">150&#8202;114 (18.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99&#8202;703 (17.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28&#8202;659 (18.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Quintile 5 (most marginalized)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">139&#8202;526 (16.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80&#8202;725 (14.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43&#8202;690 (27.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Migrant status [<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Non-migrant</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">673&#8202;172 (80.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">486&#8202;230 (86.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;First-generation migrant</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84&#8202;785 (10.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84&#8202;785 (53.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Second-generation migrant</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74&#8202;000 (8.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74&#8202;000 (13.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74&#8202;000 (46.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Migrant class [<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Canadian-born</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74&#8202;000 (46.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Immigrant</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70&#8202;532 (44.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Refugee</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14&#8202;245 (9.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Region of birth [<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Canada</td><td rowspan="8" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td rowspan="8" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74&#8202;000 (46.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Europe</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13&#8202;818 (8.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Caribbean</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2998 (1.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;South Asia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22&#8202;838 (14.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;East Asia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19&#8202;123 (12.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Latin America</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5235 (3.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;North Africa and Middle East</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12&#8202;555 (7.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Africa</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4463 (2.8)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn1"><p>Values not summing to 100% are due to missing data (&lt;2.5% per variable).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Throughout childhood, adolescence, and early adulthood (follow-up to 2022), 70.6% of the Ontario-MINDS cohort had at least one physician visit with a diagnostic code for a mental or substance-use disorder and 6.2% had at least one acute care encounter (ED or hospitalization). The 6-month prevalence of any visit for a mental or substance-use disorder was 10.5%, which aligns with estimates of physician-based mental health service use from other youth samples in Ontario [<xref rid="dyaf076-B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>].</p><p>A summary of the diagnoses assigned to the visits is presented in <xref rid="dyaf076-F3" ref-type="fig">Figure&#160;3</xref>. More than half of the cohort (55.8%) had at least one visit related to mood or anxiety disorders throughout childhood, adolescence, and early adulthood. Other common reasons for encounters with physician-based services included other mental disorders (29.7%) and neurodevelopmental disorders (26.8%). The incidence of non-affective psychotic disorder in the study cohort was 137.3 per 100&#8202;000 person-years (95% confidence interval&#8201;=&#8201;135.3, 139.4), which is aligned with other Canadian estimates of the incidence of psychotic disorders for this age group obtained from health administrative data [<xref rid="dyaf076-B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="dyaf076-B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>].</p><fig position="float" id="dyaf076-F3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Frequency of health service use for mental and substance-use disorders among youth in the Ontario-MINDS cohort (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;831&#8202;957) by diagnosis assigned to the visit. Event rates represent children with at least one visit for each diagnosis group.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="dyaf076f3.jpg"><alt-text>Bar chart showing the proportion of children who had a physician visit for each diagnostic category of mental and substance-use disorders.</alt-text></graphic></fig><p>We currently have several projects underway to explore childhood antecedents to youth mental and substance-use disorders by using the Ontario-MINDS cohort, with a particular focus on socio-environmental exposures and intersectional approaches. In one study, we have modelled trajectories of neighbourhood-level income throughout childhood (<xref rid="dyaf076-F4" ref-type="fig">Figure&#160;4</xref>) and examined the association with subsequent use of health services for mental and substance-use disorder up to age 25&#8211;30&#8201;years. We found clear socio-economic gradients in the use of acute care services for mental and substance-use disorders, but few differences in outpatient visits. In a separate study, we have used the Ontario-MINDS cohort to estimate the risk of psychotic disorders among first- and second-generation migrant groups&#8212;this represents the first Canadian data to date on second-generation migrant groups showing no excess risk of psychotic disorder overall, relative to non-migrants, in contrast to international evidence [<xref rid="dyaf076-B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].</p><fig position="float" id="dyaf076-F4" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Trajectories of neighbourhood income quintile from birth to age 12&#160;years, identified by using longitudinal latent class models.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="dyaf076f4.jpg"><alt-text>A graph showing the different trajectories of neighbourhood income quintile from birth to age 12 year, which include stable moderate/high income, upwardly mobile income, downwardly mobile income, and stable low income.</alt-text></graphic></fig></sec><sec><title>What are the main strengths and weaknesses?</title><p>The Ontario-MINDS cohort represents the largest Canadian birth cohort to date [<xref rid="dyaf076-B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], with comprehensive coverage of youth born between 1992 and 1996, and continuous follow-up to age 25&#8211;30&#8201;years. Furthermore, the cohort is dynamic, allowing in-migration up to age 12&#8201;years, meaning that first-generation migrant groups are also included in the sample. Linkages with hospital birth records also enable the ascertainment of maternal socio-demographic and clinical information for a subset of the cohort. The number of research questions that can be explored in the linked health administrative data is vast and this data platform will enable innovative lines of inquiry to be pursued. This work will advance public health approaches to mental and substance-use disorders among youth by providing information for population-health surveillance, identifying determinants of illness and disparities across population subgroups, and supporting improvements in mental health services and systems of care.</p><p>Despite these strengths, several limitations to the data should be noted. Our ascertainment of service contacts for mental and substance-use disorders are limited to physician-based services, meaning that we have missed service contacts with other types of mental health service providers, such as psychologists and social workers. This is particularly an issue for contacts that occurred prior to age 18&#8201;years, as child and adolescent mental health services are delivered across multiple sectors [<xref rid="dyaf076-B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Future planned linkages with data from the Ontario Ministry of Children, Community, and Social Services, as well as existing linkages with population-health surveys, will enhance our ability to further explore use of non-physician-based mental health services. In addition, although we are able to identify cases of non-affective psychotic disorder by using a validated algorithm [<xref rid="dyaf076-B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], we are limited in our ability to identify cases of other types of mental and substance-use disorders. This is due to a lack of specificity in the diagnostic codes used in the outpatient data, which only include three digits, whereas four digits are needed to distinguish between some types of mental disorders. As such, our outcomes are predominantly focused on health service use for mental and substance-use disorders, rather than diagnosed cases. Finally, we are unable to identify fathers in the health administrative data, as the hospital birth records in MOMBABY do not include paternity information. Consequently, we are unable to identify second-generation migrants for whom the father had a history of migration and we cannot account for paternal risk factors or history of mental illness in our analyses. However, we can identify siblings born to the same mother within the MOMBABY sub-cohort.</p></sec><sec><title>Can I get hold of the data? Where can I find out more?</title><p>The Ontario-MINDS cohort is held securely in coded form at ICES. Collaborations with investigators who are interested in life-course approaches to youth physical and mental health are welcomed, particularly collaborations that could facilitate linkages with other datasets containing information on socio-environmental exposures or clinical outcomes. Legal data-sharing agreements between ICES and its data providers prohibit ICES from making the dataset publicly available; however, use of the Ontario-MINDS cohort may be granted with the permission of the principal investigator (PI) for those who meet pre-specified criteria for confidential access, available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.ices.on.ca/DAS" ext-link-type="uri">www.ices.on.ca/DAS</ext-link>. Please contact the project PI with any inquiries (<email>kelly.anderson@schulich.uwo.ca</email>).</p></sec><sec><title>Ethics approval</title><p>ICES is a prescribed entity under Ontario&#8217;s PHIPA, which authorizes the collection of personal health information, without consent, for the purposes of health system analysis and evaluation. The use of the data in this project is authorized under section 45 of PHIPA and does not require review by a research ethics board.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="sup1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>dyaf076_Supplementary_Data</label><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="dyaf076_supplementary_data.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="ack1"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We are grateful to Lixia Zhang for analytic support on this work. This study was supported by ICES, which is funded by an annual grant from the Ontario Ministry of Health (MOH) and the Ministry of Long-Term Care. This document used data adapted from the Statistics Canada Postal CodeOM Conversion File, which is based on data licensed from Canada Post Corporation, and/or data adapted from the Ontario Ministry of Health Postal Code Conversion File, which contains data copied under license from &#169;Canada Post Corporation and Statistics Canada. Parts of this material are based on data and/or information compiled and provided by CIHI, Ontario MOH, and IRCC. The analyses, conclusions, opinions, and statements expressed herein are solely those of the authors and do not reflect those of the data sources; no endorsement is intended or should be inferred. We thank the Toronto Community Health Profiles Partnership for providing access to the Ontario Marginalization Index.</p></ack><sec><title>Author contributions</title><p>Study conception and acquisition of funding: K.K.A. Input on cohort creation and included variables: K.K.A., R.R., M.R., J.E., B.L. Cohort creation and data analysis: B.L. Drafting of manuscript: K.K.A., R.R. Revising manuscript for intellectual content: M.R., J.E., B.L. Final approval of published version: K.K.A., R.R., M.R., J.E., B.L.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplementary data</title><p>
<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary data</xref> is available at IJE online.</p><p>Conflict of interest: None declared.</p></sec><sec><title>Funding</title><p>The creation of the Ontario-MINDS cohort was funded by the Children&#8217;s Health Research Institute (London, Ontario) and by a Petro Canada Young Innovator Award (to K.K.A.). K.K.A. is supported by a Tier 2 Canada Research Chair in Public Mental Health Research.</p></sec><sec><title>Use of artificial intelligence (AI) tools</title><p>The authors declare that AI tools were not used in the preparation of this manuscript.</p></sec><ref-list id="ref1"><title>References</title><ref id="dyaf076-B1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Whiteford</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Degenhardt</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rehm</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#160;<etal>et al</etal> &#160;<article-title>Global burden of disease attributable to mental and substance use disorders: findings from the Global Burden of Disease Study 2010</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> &#160;<year>2013</year>;<volume>382</volume>:<fpage>1575</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>86</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23993280</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(13)61611-6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="dyaf076-B2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Heimer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Giedd</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#160;<etal>et al</etal> &#160;<article-title>Adolescent mental health&#8212;Opportunity and obligation</article-title>. <source>Science</source> &#160;<year>2014</year>;<volume>346</volume>:<fpage>547</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25359951</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.1260497</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5069680</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="dyaf076-B3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kessler</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Berglund</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Demler</surname><given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Merikangas</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Walters</surname><given-names>EE.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#160;<article-title>Lifetime prevalence and age-of-onset distributions of DSM-IV disorders in the National Comorbidity Survey Replication</article-title>. <source>Arch Gen Psychiatry</source> &#160;<year>2005</year>;<volume>62</volume>:<fpage>593</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>602</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15939837</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/archpsyc.62.6.593</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="dyaf076-B4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Erskine</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Moffitt</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Copeland</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#160;<etal>et al</etal> &#160;<article-title>A heavy burden on young minds: the global burden of mental and substance use disorders in children and youth</article-title>. <source>Psychol Med</source> &#160;<year>2015</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>1551</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>63</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25534496</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1017/S0033291714002888</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5922255</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="dyaf076-B5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Baranne</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Falissard</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#160;<article-title>Global burden of mental disorders among children aged 5&#8211;14 years</article-title>. <source>Child Adolesc Psychiatry Ment Health</source> &#160;<year>2018</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>19</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29682005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13034-018-0225-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5896103</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="dyaf076-B6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lewinsohn</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rohde</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Seeley</surname><given-names>JR.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#160;<article-title>Natural course of adolescent major depressive disorder: I. Continuity into young adulthood</article-title>. <source>J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry</source> &#160;<year>1999</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>56</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>63</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9893417</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/00004583-199901000-00020</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="dyaf076-B7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kim-Cohen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Caspi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Moffitt</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Harrington</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Milne</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Poulton</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#160;<article-title>Prior juvenile diagnoses in adults with mental disorder: developmental follow-back of a prospective-longitudinal cohort</article-title>. <source>Arch Gen Psychiatry</source> &#160;<year>2003</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>709</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>17</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12860775</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/archpsyc.60.7.709</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="dyaf076-B8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Plana-Ripoll</surname><given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Agerbo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#160;<etal>et al</etal> &#160;<article-title>A comprehensive analysis of mortality-related health metrics associated with mental disorders: a nationwide, register-based cohort study</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> &#160;<year>2019</year>;<volume>394</volume>:<fpage>1827</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>35</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31668728</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(19)32316-5</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="dyaf076-B9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Statistics Canada</collab>. <italic toggle="yes">Table 13&#8211;10-0394&#8211;01: Leading Causes of Death, Total Population, by Age Group, Canada</italic>. <year>2022</year>. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www150.statcan.gc.ca/t1/tbl1/en/tv.action?pid=1310039401&amp;pickMembers%5B0%5D=2.22&amp;pickMembers%5B1%5D=3.1&amp;cubeTimeFrame.startYear=2016&amp;cubeTimeFrame.endYear=2020&amp;referencePeriods=20160101%2C20200101" ext-link-type="uri">https://www150.statcan.gc.ca/t1/tbl1/en/tv.action?pid=1310039401&amp;pickMembers%5B0%5D=2.22&amp;pickMembers%5B1%5D=3.1&amp;cubeTimeFrame.startYear=2016&amp;cubeTimeFrame.endYear=2020&amp;referencePeriods=20160101%2C20200101</ext-link> (12 July 2022, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="dyaf076-B10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#160;<article-title>Suicide in children and adolescents: a 10-year retrospective review</article-title>. <source>Am J Forensic Med Pathol</source> &#160;<year>2005</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>309</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>15</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16304461</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/01.paf.0000188169.41158.58</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="dyaf076-B11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Georgiades</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#160;<article-title>Expanding the evidence for population mental health in Canada: a call to action for evidence-informed policy and practice</article-title>. <source>Health Promot Chronic Dis Prev Can</source> &#160;<year>2021</year>;<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>321</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34569769</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.24095/hpcdp.41.11.01</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8639175</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="dyaf076-B12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lebenbaum</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#160;<etal>et al</etal> &#160;<article-title>Describing the linkages of the immigration, refugees and citizenship Canada permanent resident data and vital statistics death registry to Ontario&#8217;s administrative health database</article-title>. <source>BMC Med Inform Decis Mak</source> &#160;<year>2016</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>135</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27769227</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12911-016-0375-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5073414</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="dyaf076-B13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kurdyak</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Guttmann</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#160;<article-title>Developing indicators for the child and youth mental health system in Ontario</article-title>. <source>Healthc Q</source> &#160;<year>2016</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>6</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.12927/hcq.2016.24865</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27808015</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="dyaf076-B14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kurdyak</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vigod</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#160;<article-title>Validation of a population-based algorithm to detect chronic psychotic illness</article-title>. <source>Can J Psychiatry</source> &#160;<year>2015</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>362</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26454558</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/070674371506000805</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4542516</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="dyaf076-B15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Norman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>MacDougall</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#160;<etal>et al</etal> &#160;<article-title>Estimating the incidence of first-episode psychosis using population-based health administrative data to inform early psychosis intervention services</article-title>. <source>Psychol Med</source> &#160;<year>2019</year>;<volume>49</volume>:<fpage>2091</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30311590</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1017/S0033291718002933</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="dyaf076-B16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Matheson</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Moloney</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>van Ingen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#160;<italic toggle="yes">2016 Ontario Marginalization Index: User Guide</italic>. Public Health Ontario; <year>2018</year>. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.publichealthontario.ca/-/media/Documents/O/2017/on-marg-userguide.pdf?sc_lang=en&amp;hash=9811CC2601A3E4533468CBBF9C1E52AA" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.publichealthontario.ca/-/media/Documents/O/2017/on-marg-userguide.pdf? sc_lang=en&amp;hash=9811CC2601A3E4533468CBBF9C1E52AA</ext-link> (18 July 2022, date last accessed).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.17269/s41997-021-00552-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8975983</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34432255</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="dyaf076-B17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ku</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Compton</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Druss</surname><given-names>BG.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#160;<article-title>Social fragmentation and schizophrenia: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>J Clin Psychiatry</source> &#160;<year>2021</year>;<volume>83</volume>:<fpage>21r13941</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4088/JCP.21r13941</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34875149</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="dyaf076-B18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Johns Hopkins ACG<sup>&#174;</sup> System. <italic toggle="yes">ACG System Version 11.0 Technical Reference Guide</italic>. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.hopkinsacg.org/document/acg-system-version-11-technical-reference-guide/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.hopkinsacg.org/document/acg-system-version-11-technical-reference-guide/</ext-link> (7 August 2022, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="dyaf076-B19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Henkhaus</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzales</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Buntin</surname><given-names>MB.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#160;<article-title>An algorithm using administrative data to measure adverse childhood experiences (ADM&#8208;ACE)</article-title>. <source>Health Serv Res</source> &#160;<year>2022</year>;<volume>57</volume>:<fpage>963</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>72</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35275403</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/1475-6773.13972</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9264467</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="dyaf076-B20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Comeau</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Georgiades</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#160;<article-title>Characterizing mental health related service contacts in children and youth: a linkage study of health survey and administrative data</article-title>. <source>Child Adolesc Psychiatry Ment Health</source> &#160;<year>2022</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>48</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35729646</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13034-022-00483-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9215063</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="dyaf076-B21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fuhrer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Abrahamowicz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Malla</surname><given-names>AK.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#160;<article-title>The incidence of first-episode schizophrenia-spectrum psychosis in adolescents and young adults in Montreal: an estimate from an administrative claims database</article-title>. <source>Can J Psychiatry</source> &#160;<year>2012</year>;<volume>57</volume>:<fpage>626</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>33</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23072954</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/070674371205701007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="dyaf076-B22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Selten</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>van der Ven</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Termorshuizen</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#160;<article-title>Migration and psychosis: a meta-analysis of incidence studies</article-title>. <source>Psychol Med</source> &#160;<year>2020</year>;<volume>50</volume>:<fpage>303</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>13</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30722795</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1017/S0033291719000035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7083571</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="dyaf076-B23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Joly</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Boivin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Junker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bocking</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>SA.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#160;<article-title>An inventory of Canadian pregnancy and birth cohort studies: research in progress</article-title>. <source>BMC Pregnancy Childbirth</source> &#160;<year>2012</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>117</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23101595</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-2393-12-117</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3542086</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>