<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Korean Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Korean Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">658</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jkms</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JKMS</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Korean Medical Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1011-8934</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1598-6357</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11106559</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11106559.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11106559</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11106559</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38769923</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3346/jkms.2024.39.e164</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject><subj-group subj-group-type="subheading"><subject>Respiratory Diseases &amp; Critical Care Medicine</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Clinical Characteristics and Frequency of Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease Exacerbations in Korean Patients: Findings From the KOCOSS Cohort 2012&#8211;2021</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4533-7937</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Rhee</surname><given-names initials="CK">Chin Kook</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6298-2204</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names initials="JY">Joon Young</given-names></name><xref rid="A2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5814-6104</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names initials="YB">Yong-Bum</given-names></name><xref rid="A3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9969-2657</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names initials="KH">Kwang Ha</given-names></name><xref rid="A4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Division of Pulmonary and Critical Care Medicine, Department of Internal Medicine, Seoul St. Mary&#8217;s Hospital, College of Medicine, The Catholic University of Korea, Seoul, <country>Korea</country>.</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Division of Pulmonary and Critical Care Medicine, Department of Internal Medicine, Incheon St. Mary&#8217;s Hospital, College of Medicine, The Catholic University of Korea, Seoul, <country>Korea</country>.</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Division of Pulmonary, Allergy and Critical Care Medicine, Department of Internal Medicine, Hallym University Kangdong Sacred Heart Hospital, Seoul, <country>Korea</country>.</aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Division of Pulmonary, Allergy and Critical Care Medicine, Department of Internal Medicine, Konkuk University Medical Center, Konkuk University School of Medicine, Seoul, <country>Korea</country>.</aff><author-notes><corresp>Address for Correspondence: Kwang Ha Yoo, MD, PhD. Division of Pulmonary, Allergy and Critical Care Medicine, Department of Internal Medicine, Konkuk University Medical Center, Konkuk University School of Medicine, 120 Neungdong-ro, Gwangjin-gu, Seoul 05030, Korea. <email>20010025@kuh.ac.kr</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>20</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>08</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>39</volume><issue>19</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">462765</issue-id><elocation-id>e164</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>4</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>20</day><month>05</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>22</day><month>05</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-05-22 05:25:13.557"><day>22</day><month>05</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2024 The Korean Academy of Medical Sciences.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="jkms-39-e164.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Acute exacerbations of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (AECOPD) exert a substantial burden on patients and healthcare systems; however, data related to the frequency of AECOPD in the Korean population are limited. Therefore, this study aimed to describe the frequency of severe, and moderate or severe AECOPD, as well as clinical and demographic characteristics of patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) in South Korea.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>Data from patients aged &gt; 40 years with post-bronchodilator forced expiratory volume in 1 second (FEV<sub>1</sub>)/forced vital capacity &#8804; 70% of the normal predicted value from the Korea COPD Subgroup Study database were analyzed (April 2012 to 2021). The protocol was based on the EXAcerbations of COPD and their OutcomeS International study. Data were collected retrospectively for year 0 (0&#8211;12 months before study enrollment) based on patient recall, and prospectively during years 1, 2, and 3 (0&#8211;12, 13&#8211;24, and 25&#8211;36 months after study enrollment, respectively). The data were summarized using descriptive statistics.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Data from 3,477 Korean patients (mean age, 68.5 years) with COPD were analyzed. Overall, most patients were male (92.3%), former or current smokers (90.8%), had a modified Medical Research Council dyspnea scale score &#8805; 1 (83.3%), and had moderate airflow limitation (54.4%). The mean body mass index (BMI) of the study population was 23.1 kg/m<sup>2</sup>, and 27.6% were obese or overweight. Hypertension was the most common comorbidity (37.6%). The mean blood eosinophil count was 226.8 cells/&#956;L, with 21.9% of patients having &#8805; 300 cells/&#956;L. A clinically insignificant change in FEV<sub>1</sub> (+1.4%) was observed a year after enrollment. Overall, patients experienced a mean of 0.2 severe annual AECOPD and approximately 1.1 mean moderate or severe AECOPD. Notably, the rates of severe AECOPD remained generally consistent over time. Compared with patients with no exacerbations, patients who experienced severe exacerbations had a lower mean BMI (21.7 vs. 23.1 kg/m<sup>2</sup>; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001) and lower lung function parameters (all <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> values &lt; 0.001), but reported high rates of depression (25.5% vs. 15.1%; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.044) and anxiety (37.3% vs. 16.7%; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001) as a comorbidity.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Findings from this Korean cohort of patients with COPD indicated a high exacerbation burden, which may be attributable to the unique characteristics of the study population and suboptimal disease management. This highlights the need to align clinical practices with the latest treatment recommendations to alleviate AECOPD burden in Korea.</p></sec><sec><title>Trial Registration</title><p>ClinicalTrials.gov Identifier: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT05750810" ext-link-type="uri">NCT05750810</ext-link></p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="graphical"><title>Graphical Abstract</title><p>
<graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jkms-39-e164-abf001.jpg"/>
</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease</kwd><kwd>Exacerbation</kwd><kwd>KOCOSS Cohort</kwd><kwd>Respiratory Function Tests</kwd><kwd>Registries</kwd><kwd>South Korea</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source country="KR"><institution-wrap><institution>AstraZeneca Korea</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="CrossRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100004599</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source country="KR"><institution-wrap><institution>Korea Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="CrossRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100003669</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>2016ER670100</award-id><award-id>2016ER670101</award-id><award-id>2016ER670102</award-id><award-id>2018ER670100</award-id><award-id>2018ER670101</award-id><award-id>2018ER670102</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) is a &#8220;heterogeneous lung condition characterized by chronic respiratory symptoms (dyspnea, cough, sputum production, and/or exacerbations) due to abnormalities of the airways (bronchitis, bronchiolitis) and/or alveoli (emphysema) that cause persistent, often progressive, airflow obstruction.&#8221;<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> COPD is a major cause of morbidity and is the third leading cause of death worldwide.<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref><xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref><xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> Analysis of data from the Korea National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey (KNHANES) between 2015 and 2019 revealed that the overall prevalence of COPD in South Korea was 12.9%.<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Over the 5-year survey period, the annual prevalence of COPD remained constant, ranging between 11.5% and 13.6%.<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Across all age groups (40&#8211;49, 50&#8211;59, 60&#8211;69, and &#8805; 70 years), the highest prevalence of COPD was observed in patients aged &#8805; 70 years (30.4%), with the prevalence also being higher in males than females (19.9% vs. 6.4%).<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Based on longitudinal data from the National Health Insurance Service (NHIS), a key institution that provides healthcare insurance to all citizens in South Korea,<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> the 5-year mortality of Korean patients with COPD was 25.4%, and this increased rapidly with age.<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> Overall, COPD exerts a substantial socioeconomic burden in South Korea<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> and ranks as the third leading cause of total disability-adjusted life years, accounting for 6.2% of the burden associated with non-communicable diseases.<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> The total (direct and indirect) estimated costs of COPD in 2015 in Korea were 1245 million United States (US) dollars (1,408 billion Korean won), with direct costs comprising &#8804; 20% of the total estimated costs and the costs of nursing, lost productivity, and premature deaths representing &#8804; 80% of total costs.<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></p><p>Acute exacerbations of COPD (AECOPD) are key indicators of disease progression and are defined as worsening of symptoms (cough, breathlessness, and sputum purulence and volume) beyond normal daily variation and often associated with increased local and systemic inflammation.<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref><xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> Patients with COPD who have frequent exacerbations (vs. those with less frequent exacerbations) have an accelerated decline in lung function, worsened quality of life, poorer health status, and increased hospital admissions.<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> Recurring AECOPD also increases the risk of future multiple AECOPD events, with the risk of mortality increasing with the frequency and severity of AECOPD.<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref><xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> Indeed, the EXAcerbations of COPD and their OutcomeS (EXACOS)-UK study involving 340,515 patients with COPD found that increasing number and severity of exacerbations were associated with an increased risk of subsequent exacerbations, all-cause mortality, and COPD-related mortality.<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> Furthermore, even a single moderate event was shown to increase the risk of future events.<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> However, there are sparse data on the frequency of moderate or severe, or severe, AECOPD in the Korean population.</p><p>The Korea COPD Subgroup Study (KOCOSS) is a nationwide, multicenter, prospective cohort study-involving patients with COPD recruited from 54 tertiary medical centers in South Korea, mostly comprising patients with mild-to-moderate airflow limitation.<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> This database has been used to explore various aspects of COPD in South Korea.<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref><xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref><xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref><xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref><xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> The main aim of the present study was to describe the frequency of moderate or severe, or severe, AECOPD in addition to the clinical and demographic characteristics of patients with COPD in South Korea.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>METHODS</title><sec><title>Study design and patient population</title><p>This was a retrospective analysis of data collected both retrospectively and prospectively from the KOCOSS database, which contains data on patients with COPD. The study protocol was based on the EXACOS International program (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:clinical-trial" xlink:href="NCT05750810">NCT05750810</ext-link>),<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> which was adapted for the Korean population. EXACOS International is an observational, cross-sectional study designed to understand the burden of severe COPD exacerbations and the association between the frequency of severe exacerbations and clinical and healthcare resource utilization (HCRU) outcomes in less well-resourced countries.<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></p><p>The present analysis included patients with COPD aged &gt; 40 years and diagnosed by a pulmonologist, with post-bronchodilator forced expiratory volume in 1 second (FEV<sub>1</sub>)/forced vital capacity (FVC) &#8804; 70% of the normal predicted value from the KOCOSS database. Data from patients with COPD were extracted and analyzed (April 2012 to 2021). Data, including exacerbation-related data, were retrospectively collected (through patient recall) for year 0 (0&#8211;12 months before study enrollment). Based on data collected retrospectively one year prior to enrollment, patients were categorized according to exacerbator type (non-exacerbator vs. severe exacerbator). Patients were then followed up for 3 years, with years 1, 2, and 3 (0&#8211;12, 13&#8211;24, and 25&#8211;36 months after study enrollment, respectively) comprising prospective data collection (with data collected by research nurses and clinicians in case report forms and recorded by clinicians). At enrollment, patients were also enquired if they were currently being treated for asthma. Patients were categorized based on their body mass index (BMI) as underweight (BMI &lt; 18.5 kg/m<sup>2</sup>), normal (18.5 kg/m<sup>2</sup> &#8804; BMI &#8805; 24.9 kg/m<sup>2</sup>), overweigh (25.0 kg/m<sup>2</sup> &#8804; BMI &#8805; 29.9 kg/m<sup>2</sup>), and obese (BMI &#8805; 30.0 kg/m<sup>2</sup>).</p></sec><sec><title>Study objectives and outcomes</title><p>The primary objectives were to estimate the frequency of severe AECOPD and to describe lung function changes over time, as assessed by post-bronchodilator FEV<sub>1</sub> measurements. The number of severe AECOPD was counted at the initial visit in recall of previous 1-year events and prospectively measured during the 3-year follow-up period.</p><p>The secondary objective was to assess patients&#8217; scores on the modified Medical Research Council (mMRC) dyspnea scale measured at enrollment. Parameters for which data was collected at enrollment included demographic information, the frequency of moderate or severe, and severe AECOPD, comorbidities, smoking status, Global Initiative for Chronic Obstructive Lung Disease (GOLD) grade of airflow limitation measurements, COPD medications, and peripheral blood eosinophil levels.</p><p>An AECOPD was considered moderate if the use of systemic corticosteroids or antibiotics was required, and severe if hospitalizations (with or without intensive care unit) or an emergency department visit were required to manage worsening of symptoms. The number of moderate and severe AECOPD was prospectively measured at 1-year follow-up visits.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Data were summarized using descriptive statistics. Continuous measures were described using means and standard deviations (SDs), and categorical measures were reported using numbers and proportions. Count variables were expressed as rates per person-year. Groups were compared using standard univariate statistical methods, including the chi-square test or the Fisher&#8217;s exact test for categorical variables and the analysis of variance test for continuous variables.</p><p>No power calculations were performed as the objectives of this study were primarily descriptive.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ethics-statement"><title>Ethics statement</title><p>The study protocol was reviewed and approved by the Institutional Review Board of the Konkuk University Medical Center (approval No. KUMC2022-07-009). Informed consent was obtained from all patients when they were enrolled in the KOCOSS study and was therefore not required for the present study.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>Patient and disease characteristics</title><p>A total of 3,477 Korean patients with COPD were included from the KOCOSS database. <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> shows patients&#8217; demographic and clinical characteristics.<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref> Overall, the mean age of the study population was 68.5 years. Most patients were men (92.3%) and current or former smokers (90.8%). Hypertension was the most common comorbidity (37.6%), and 32.5% of patients reported depression or anxiety. The mean BMI of the study population was 23.1 kg/m<sup>2</sup>, with 27.6% of patients being obese or overweight. Over half of all patients had received primary and/or secondary school education (51.0.%), while 34.1% and 14.8% had obtained high school and university and/or post-university education, respectively. Most patients had moderate airflow limitation (GOLD grade 2: 54.4%), followed by those with severe or very severe airflow limitation (GOLD grades 3/4: 31.1%). The severity of breathlessness on exertion based on the mMRC dyspnea scale was reported as grade 0 in 16.7% of patients, while 50.0% reported grade 1 and 33.4% reported grade &#8805; 2, respectively. One year prior to enrollment, 17.5%, 9.7%, and 19.8% of patients experienced &#8805; 1 moderate, severe, or moderate or severe exacerbations, respectively. Of the 3,367 patients for whom baseline FEV<sub>1</sub> data was collected, one year follow up data was available for 45.1% of patients (n = 1,520). Based on paired <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test, a statistically significant, though small, mean change in % FEV<sub>1</sub> (+ 1.4%) was observed from enrollment to year 1 (change from 57.42% to 58.86%).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Demographics and clinical characteristics of Korean patients with COPD from the KOCOSS cohort</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jkms-39-e164-i001.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><col width="3.12%" span="1"/><col width="3.12%" span="1"/><col width="70.13%" span="1"/><col width="23.64%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(211,212,235)" valign="top">Characteristics</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(211,212,235)" valign="top">Values (N = 3,477)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1" valign="top">Age, yr</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Mean &#177; SD</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">68.5 &#177; 8.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Median (min, max)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">69 (31.0, 98.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Sex</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Male</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">3,208 (92.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Female</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">269 (7.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1" valign="top">BMI, kg/m<sup>2</sup>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Mean &#177; SD</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">23.1 &#177; 3.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Median (min, max)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">23.1 (13.55, 45.06)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Underweight</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">299 (8.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Normal</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">2,219 (63.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Overweight</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">862 (24.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Obese</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">97 (2.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Education level</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Primary and/or secondary school</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">1,756 (51.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">High school</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">1,175 (34.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">University and/or post-university</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">510 (14.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Missing</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">36</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1" valign="top">Tobacco smoking status (n = 3,470)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Ex-smoker</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">2,233 (64.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Current smoker</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">917 (26.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Non-smoker</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">320 (9.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Comorbidities</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Hypertension (n = 3,472)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">1,304 (37.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Anxiety (n = 1,898)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">352 (18.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Diabetes<sup>a</sup> (n = 3,472)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">604 (17.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Depression (n = 1,510)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">212 (14.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Gastroesophageal reflux disease (n = 3,468)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">276 (8.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Acute myocardial infarction (n = 3,471)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">167 (4.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Congestive heart failure (n = 3,470)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">124 (3.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Stroke (n = 2,048)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">67 (3.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Renal failure (n = 2,048)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">34 (1.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1" valign="top">COPD GOLD grade of airflow limitation (n = 3,367)<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">GOLD 1 (mild)<sup>c</sup>: FEV<sub>1</sub> &#8805; 80% predicted</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">488 (14.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">GOLD 2 (moderate)<sup>c</sup>: FEV<sub>1</sub> 50&#8211;79% predicted</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1,832 (54.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">GOLD 3 (severe)<sup>c</sup>: FEV<sub>1</sub> 30&#8211;49% predicted</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">882 (26.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">GOLD 4 (very severe)<sup>c</sup>: FEV<sub>1</sub> &lt; 30% predicted</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">165 (4.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">mMRC dyspnea scale score (n = 3,470)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Grade 0</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">579 (16.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Grade 1</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">1,734 (50.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Grade 2</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">762 (22.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Grade 3</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">342 (9.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Grade 4</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">53 (1.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1" valign="top">Moderate exacerbations during one year prior to enrollment</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">No</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1,692 (82.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">360 (17.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Missing</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1,425</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Severe exacerbations during one year prior to enrollment</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">No</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">1,853 (90.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">199 (9.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Missing</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">1,425</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1" valign="top">Moderate or severe exacerbations during one year prior to enrollment</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">No</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1,645 (80.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">407 (19.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Missing</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1,425</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Post-bronchodilator FEV<sub>1 </sub>(%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Observed value at baseline (n = 3,367)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Mean &#177; SD</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">59.6 &#177; 18.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Median (min, max)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">59.0 (9.0, 136.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Missing number</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">110</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Observed value one year after enrollment (n = 1,547)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Mean &#177; SD</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">58.8 &#177; 18.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Median (min, max)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">59.0 (15.0, 121.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Missing</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">1,930</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Change from baseline, % (n = 1,520)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Mean &#177; SD</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">1.4 &#177; 9.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Median (min, max)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">1.0 (&#8722;56.0, 57.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Missing</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">1,957</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value<sup>d</sup>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">&lt; 0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1" valign="top">Blood eosinophil levels, cells/&#956;L (n = 3,005)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Mean &#177; SD</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">226.8 &#177; 246.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Median (min, max)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">161.6 (0, 3,989.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Missing</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">472</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">&lt; 100 cells/&#956;L</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1,512 (50.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">&#8805; 100 cells/&#956;L</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1,493 (49.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">100&#8211;299 cells/&#956;L</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">834 (27.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">&#8805; 300 cells/&#956;L</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">659 (21.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Prescribed treatments<sup>e</sup> (n = 2,975)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">LABA + LAMA (total)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">911 (30.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">LABA + LAMA (combination in single device)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">879 (29.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Theophylline</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">788 (26.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">ICS + LABA + LAMA (total)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">730 (24.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">ICS + LABA + LAMA (combination in single device)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">642 (21.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">LAMA</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">620 (20.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">ICS + LABA (combination in single device)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">390 (13.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Roflumilast</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">205 (6.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">LABA</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">169 (5.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">ICS</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">9 (0.3)</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><p>Values are presented as number (%).</p><p>COPD = chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, KOCOSS = Korea COPD Subgroup Study, SD = standard deviation, max = maximum, min = minimum, BMI = body mass index, GOLD = Global Initiative for Chronic Obstructive Lung Disease, mMRC = modified Medical Research Council, FEV<sub>1</sub> = forced expiratory volume in 1 second, LABA = long-acting &#946;-agonist, LAMA = long-acting muscarinic antagonist, ICS = inhaled corticosteroids, SABA = short-acting &#946;<sub>2</sub>-agonist, OCS = oral corticosteroid.</p><p><sup>a</sup>Whether the diabetes was type 1 or type 2 was not recorded, although most South Koreans with diabetes have type 2 diabetes.<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></p><p><sup>b</sup>According to the latest measurement.</p><p><sup>c</sup>Severity of airflow limitation described per GOLD 2023.</p><p><sup>d</sup>Calculated using paired <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test/Wilcoxon signed-rank test.</p><p><sup>e</sup>These are the treatments prescribed in the year prior to enrollment. Data on SABA, OCS maintenance, and other medication prescriptions were not collected from the registry.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Approximately half of all patients had a blood eosinophil count &#8805; 100 cells/&#956;L (49.7%), with a mean &#177; SD of 226.8 &#177; 246.6 cells/&#956;L. Over one fifth of patients had a blood eosinophil count &#8805; 300 cells/&#956;L.</p></sec><sec><title>Prescribed COPD medications</title><p>Long-acting &#946;-agonists (LABA) plus long-acting muscarinic antagonists (LAMA) were the most commonly prescribed medication (30.6%), with 29.5% receiving LABA plus LAMA in a single device (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Other commonly prescribed treatments were theophylline (26.5%) and a combination of inhaled corticosteroids (ICS) plus LABA plus LAMA (24.5%; triple therapy), with 21.6% receiving triple therapy in a single device. Among those with blood eosinophil counts &#8805; 300 cells/&#956;L (n = 659), prescription data was available for 550 patients, of which 227 were prescribed an ICS-containing inhaler (41.3%).</p></sec><sec><title>COPD exacerbations</title><p>The mean number of severe annual exacerbations was 0.2 each for years 1&#8211;3, with a mean of 1.1 moderate or severe exacerbations in years 1 and 3 and 0.9 in year 2 (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Overall, 40.8%, 36.1% and 39.4% of patients experienced &#8805; 1 exacerbation during years 1, 2, and 3, respectively (<xref rid="S6" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Moderate or severe exacerbations and severe exacerbations observed in Korean patients with COPD from the KOCOSS cohort</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jkms-39-e164-i002.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><col width="3.16%" span="1"/><col width="33.68%" span="1"/><col width="15.79%" span="1"/><col width="15.79%" span="1"/><col width="15.79%" span="1"/><col width="15.79%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(211,212,235)" valign="top">Exacerbation</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(211,212,235)" valign="top">Year 0<sup>a</sup></th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(211,212,235)" valign="top">Year 1<sup>a</sup></th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(211,212,235)" valign="top">Year 2<sup>a</sup></th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(211,212,235)" valign="top">Year 3<sup>a</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Moderate or severe exacerbations<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">No. of patients</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">-</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1,551</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1,369</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1,042</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Mean &#177; SD</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">-</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1.1 &#177; 2.0</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.9 &#177; 1.9</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1.1 &#177; 2.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Median (min, max)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">-</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0 (0, 15.0)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0 (0, 13.0)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0 (0, 16.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Missing</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">-</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1,926</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">2,108</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">2,435</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Severe exacerbations</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">No. of patients</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">2,052</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">1,551</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">1,369</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">1,042</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Mean &#177; SD</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">0.1 &#177; 0.5</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">0.2 &#177; 0.7</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">0.2 &#177; 0.6</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">0.2 &#177; 0.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Median (min, max)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">0.0 (0.0, 11.0)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">0.0 (0.0, 10.0)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">0.0 (0.0, 7.0)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">0.0 (0.0, 8.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Missing</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">1,425</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">1,926</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">2,108</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">2,435</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><p>COPD = chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, KOCOSS = Korea COPD Subgroup Study, - = data not available, SD = standard deviation, max = maximum, min = minimum.</p><p><sup>a</sup>Year 0 involved retrospective data collection and comprised data for 0&#8211;12 months before study enrollment. Years 1&#8211;3 involved prospectively collected (from the perspective of the KOCOSS cohort) follow-up data 0&#8211;12 months (year 1), 13&#8211;24 months (year 2), and 25&#8211;36 months (year 3) after study enrollment.</p><p><sup>b</sup>Data for year 0 for moderate or severe exacerbations were unavailable.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>A comparison of mMRC dyspnea scale score according to exacerbator type (no exacerbations vs. moderate to severe exacerbations) is shown in <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. The demographic and clinical characteristics of the study population were largely comparable when patients were stratified based on exacerbator type (non-exacerbator vs. severe exacerbator); however, a few notable differences were observed (<xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). The proportion of patients experiencing severe exacerbations showed an increasing trend with age, with the highest burden reported among those aged &#8805; 70 years. Just over half of patients who experienced severe exacerbations were aged &#8805; 70 years (50.8%). Compared with patients with no exacerbations, those with severe exacerbations had a lower mean BMI (21.7 vs. 23.1 kg/m<sup>2</sup>; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001) and lower lung function parameters (all <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> values &lt; 0.001). Although patients with severe exacerbations had numerically higher mean blood eosinophil counts, the difference was not statistically significant (227 vs. 219 cells/&#956;L; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.698). A higher proportion of patients with severe exacerbations reported depression (25.5% vs. 15.1%; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.044) and anxiety (37.3% vs. 16.7%; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001) as a comorbidity. Overall, more patients with severe exacerbations vs. no exacerbations were prescribed roflumilast (10.8% vs. 6.4%), theophylline (35.5% vs. 27.0%), ICS + LABA + LAMA (44.1% vs. 20.4%).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>mMRC dyspnea scale score of Korean patients with COPD from the KOCOSS cohort according to exacerbator type (no exacerbations vs. moderate to severe exacerbations) based on data collected retrospectively one year prior to enrollment</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jkms-39-e164-i003.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><col width="26.44%" span="1"/><col width="26.22%" span="1"/><col width="38.89%" span="1"/><col width="8.44%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(211,212,235)" valign="top">mMRC dyspnea scale scores</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(211,212,235)" valign="top">No exacerbations (n = 1,642)</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(211,212,235)" valign="top">Moderate to severe exacerbations (n = 405)</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(211,212,235)" valign="top"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Grade 0</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">268 (16.3)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">26 (6.4)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="5" valign="top">&lt; 0.001<sup>a</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Grade 1</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">900 (54.8)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">152 (37.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Grade 2</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">330 (20.1)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">150 (37.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Grade 3</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">126 (7.7)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">65 (16.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Grade 4</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">18 (1.1)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">12 (3.0)</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><p>Values are presented as number (%).</p><p>mMRC = modified Medical Research Council, COPD = chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, KOCOSS = Korea COPD Subgroup Study.</p><p><sup>a</sup>Calculated using chi-squared test.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Demographic and clinical characteristics of Korean patients with COPD from the KOCOSS cohort according to exacerbator type (non-exacerbator vs. severe exacerbator) based on data collected retrospectively one year prior to enrollment</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jkms-39-e164-i004.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><col width="2.6%" span="1"/><col width="37.09%" span="1"/><col width="25.6%" span="1"/><col width="26.68%" span="1"/><col width="8.03%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(211,212,235)" valign="top">Characteristics</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(211,212,235)" valign="top">No exacerbations (n = 1,645)</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(211,212,235)" valign="top">Severe exacerbations (n = 199)</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(211,212,235)" valign="top"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Age, yr (n = 1,844)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Mean &#177; SD</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">68.6 &#177; 7.8</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">69.5 &#177; 7.5</td><td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.156</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Age group, yr</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="5" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">0.059</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">40&#8211;49</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">16 (1.0)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">0 (0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">50&#8211;59</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">206 (12.5)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">14 (7.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">60&#8211;69</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">624 (37.9)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">84 (42.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">&#8805; 70</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">799 (48.6)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">101 (50.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Sex</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Male (n = 1,844)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1,541 (93.7)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">179 (89.9)</td><td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.047</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">BMI, kg/m<sup>2</sup> (n = 1,844)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Mean &#177; SD</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">23.1 &#177; 3.4</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">21.7 &#177; 3.2</td><td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Education level (n = 1,835)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="4" valign="top">0.109</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Primary and/or secondary school</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">864 (52.8)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">119 (60.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">High school</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">542 (33.1)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">59 (29.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">University and/or post-university</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">231 (14.1)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">20 (10.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Tobacco smoking status (n = 1,841)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="4" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">0.352</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Ex-smoker</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">1,054 (64.2)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">138 (69.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Current smoker</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">458 (27.9)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">47 (23.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Non-smoker</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">130 (7.9)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">14 (7.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Comorbidities</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Hypertension (n = 1,843)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">595 (36.2)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">77 (38.7)</td><td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.489</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Anxiety (n = 881)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">133 (16.7)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">31 (37.3)</td><td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Diabetes<sup>a</sup> (n = 1,843)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">285 (17.3)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">33 (16.6)</td><td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.791</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Depression (n = 633)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">87 (15.1)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">14 (25.5)</td><td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.044</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Gastroesophageal reflux disease (n = 1,840)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">121 (7.4)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">14 (7.0)</td><td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.863</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Acute myocardial infarction (n = 1,842)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">64 (3.9)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">12 (6.1)</td><td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.147</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Congestive heart failure (n = 1,843)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">48 (2.9)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">10 (5.0)</td><td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.108</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Stroke (n = 960)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">22 (2.5)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">2 (2.3)</td><td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.886</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Renal failure (n = 960)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">6 (0.7)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1 (1.1)</td><td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.491</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Lung function parameters (n = 1,836)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">FVC, L</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">3.36 &#177; 0.82</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">2.99 &#177; 0.78</td><td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">FVC, %</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">60 (18)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">48 (16)</td><td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">FEV<sub>1</sub>, L</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">1.75 &#177; 0.59</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">1.36 &#177; 0.50</td><td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">FEV<sub>1</sub>, %</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">82 (16)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">76 (18)</td><td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">FEV<sub>1</sub>/FVC, %</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">52 (12)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">46 (11)</td><td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Blood eosinophil levels, cells/&#956;L (n = 1,551)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Mean &#177; SD</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">219 &#177; 216</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">227 &#177; 273</td><td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.698</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><p>Values are presented as number (%).</p><p>COPD = chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, KOCOSS = Korea COPD Subgroup Study, SD = standard deviation, BMI = body mass index, FVC = forced vital capacity, FEV<sub>1</sub> = forced expiratory volume in 1 second.</p><p><sup>a</sup>Whether the diabetes was type 1 or type 2 was not recorded, although most South Koreans with diabetes have type 2 diabetes.<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Stratification of patients by blood eosinophil counts (&lt; 300 vs. &#8805; 300 cells/&#956;L), BMI categories (underweight, normal, overweight, and obese), and presence of comorbidities is shown in <xref rid="S1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Tables 1</xref>, <xref rid="S2" ref-type="supplementary-material">2</xref>, <xref rid="S3" ref-type="supplementary-material">3</xref>, respectively. Overall, the proportion of patients experiencing &#8805; 1 moderate to severe exacerbations was significantly greater in those with higher blood eosinophil counts (48.1% vs. 39.0%; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.006), those who were underweight (53.2% vs. 41.0%, 36.6%, and 31.6% [normal, overweight, and obese, respectively]; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.005), and those who reported anxiety (39.5% vs. 27.4%; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.010), depression (42.6% vs. 24.4%; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.004), gastroesophageal reflux disease (52.8% vs. 39.9%; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.005), and renal failure (100.0% vs. 30.5%; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.009) as a comorbidity. A similar trend was observed when patients were further stratified by number of exacerbations in year 1 (&#8805; 2 vs. &lt; 2 exacerbations; <xref rid="S4" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 4</xref>). A higher proportion of patients who reported &#8805; 2 vs. &lt; 2 exacerbations had anxiety (29.3% vs. 19.0%; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.033), depression (42.1% vs. 15.8%; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#8804; 0.001) and gastroesophageal reflux disease (11.5% vs. 7.3%; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.011). Additionally, the subgroup of patients experiencing &#8805; 2 vs. &lt; 2 exacerbations also had lower FEV<sub>1</sub> (48% vs. 60%; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001) and FEV<sub>1</sub>/FVC (47% vs. 52%; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001), and higher mean blood eosinophil counts 275 vs. 217 cells/&#956;L (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.002).</p></sec><sec><title>Change in FEV<sub>1</sub> during the follow-up years</title><p>Overall, the mean &#177; SD FEV<sub>1</sub> did not change substantially from year 0 (1.62 &#177; 0.54 L) to year 3 (1.61 &#177; 0.55 L); however, a small increase was observed during years 1 and 2 (1.64 &#177; 0.55 and 1.65 &#177; 0.55 L, respectively; <xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>). Compared with patients with blood eosinophil counts &lt; 300 cells/&#956;L those with &#8805; 300 cells/&#956;L showed an increase in FEV<sub>1</sub> between year 0 and year 1 (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A</xref>). Additionally, between year 1 and year 3, the greatest decline in lung function was observed in patients with blood eosinophil counts &#8805; 300 cells/&#956;L who experienced exacerbations (&#8722;24.0 mL; <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1B</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T5" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><title>Change in FEV<sub>1</sub> in Korean patients with COPD from the KOCOSS cohort during the follow-up years (N = 473)</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jkms-39-e164-i005.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><col width="32.33%" span="1"/><col width="36.98%" span="1"/><col width="30.7%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(211,212,235)" valign="top">Years</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(211,212,235)" valign="top">FEV<sub>1</sub>, L</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(211,212,235)" valign="top">SEM</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Year 0</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1.62 &#177; 0.54</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.025</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Year 1</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">1.64 &#177; 0.55</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">0.025</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Year 2</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1.65 &#177; 0.55</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.026</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">Year 3</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">1.61 &#177; 0.55</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(224,224,241)" valign="top">0.025</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><p>Values are presented as mean &#177; standard deviation.</p><p>FEV<sub>1</sub> = forced expiratory volume in 1 second, COPD = chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, KOCOSS = Korea COPD Subgroup Study, SEM = standard error of mean.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>Change in FEV1 according to BEC and exacerbation. (<bold>A</bold>) Change in FEV<sub>1</sub> between years 0&#8211;3 and (<bold>B</bold>) decline in FEV<sub>1</sub> between year 1 and year 3 in Korean patients with COPD from the KOCOSS cohort based on blood eosinophil counts (&lt; 300 vs. &#8805; 300 cells/&#956;L), and a history of exacerbations. BEC &lt; 300 cells/&#956;L without exacerbations (n = 114); BEC &#8805; 300 cells/&#956;L without exacerbations (n = 35); BEC &lt; 300 cells/&#956;L with exacerbations (n = 83); BEC &#8805; 300 cells/&#956;L with exacerbations (n = 36).</title><p>BEC = blood eosinophil count, FEV<sub>1</sub> = forced expiratory volume in 1 second, COPD = chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, KOCOSS = Korea COPD Subgroup Study.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jkms-39-e164-g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Patients treated for asthma</title><p>Of the 3,477 patients analyzed, 6.9% (n = 240) reported being treated for asthma. Data for blood eosinophil count was available for 218 patients, who had a mean &#177; SD of 218 &#177; 234 cells/&#956;L. Overall, 20.2% of patients had blood eosinophil counts &#8805; 300 cells/&#956;L. Similar to the overall population, the subgroup of patients treated for asthma reported hypertension as the most common comorbidity (37.1%), followed by anxiety (22.5%) and depression (18.1%; <xref rid="S5" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 5</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Mortality</title><p>Patients were followed-up for a mean &#177; SD number of 1,073 &#177; 954 days. During the follow-up period, deaths were reported in 2.0% of patients (n = 69/3,407). Cause of death was available for 38 patients; of these, 39.4% (n = 15) died due to a respiratory cause, while 18.4% (n = 7), 7.9% (n = 3), 5.3% (n = 2), and 28.9% (n = 11) died due to lung cancer, other cancer, heart disease, and other causes, respectively.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Our findings from this large sample of Korean patients with COPD from the KOCOSS cohort demonstrated that moderate or severe exacerbations occurred frequently, likely due to the unique characteristics of this Asian study population and suboptimal disease management. Overall, patients experienced a mean of 0.2 severe annual AECOPD and approximately 1.1 mean moderate or severe AECOPD. Notably, the rates of severe AECOPDs remained generally consistent over time.</p><p>Although substantial heterogeneity in clinical characteristics and treatment patterns has been observed among patients with COPD from Asian countries,<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> studies comparing Western and Asian COPD cohorts are scarce. Findings from numerous real-world studies and randomized clinical trials have shown that Asian patients with COPD, including those from Korea, are more likely to be men, of an older age, with a lower mean BMI (&lt; 25 kg/m<sup>2</sup>), and with more severe airflow limitation than those from other regions.<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref><xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref><xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref><xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref><xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref><xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> These findings are consistent with our study results, where the mean age of patients was 68.5 years, 92.3% were male, and the mean BMI was 23.1 kg/m<sup>2</sup>. Notably, the majority of patients in our study had a BMI &lt; 25 kg/m<sup>2</sup> (72.4%), with 8.6% reporting a BMI &lt; 18.5 kg/m<sup>2</sup>; these patients also experienced a high exacerbation-related burden. This is a matter of concern because findings from the KOCOSS cohort demonstrated that decreased weight negatively influenced COPD prognosis and that the risk of COPD-related hospitalization was highest among those who were underweight (BMI &lt; 18.5) kg/m<sup>2</sup>.<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></p><p>The finding that most patients in the present study were men is unsurprising given the overall very low rates of smoking reported in women in South Korea.<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> Indeed, non-smoking Korean patients with COPD are more likely to be women<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>; therefore, the total smoking-related burden is approximately 2-fold higher in men.<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> In the present cohort, 90.8% of patients were current or ex-smokers, which may explain the moderate-to-severe airflow limitation observed in 80.6% of the study population. Indeed, persistent smoking causes progressive and irreversible airflow limitation, while smoking cessation reduces the progression of COPD and improves patients&#8217; health-related quality of life.<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> Notably, findings from a secondary analysis of KNHANES, conducted over a 9-year period from 2007 to 2015, demonstrated that current and former smoking was associated with an increased prevalence of major smoking-related diseases among both men and women, including COPD.<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> Therefore, clinicians should strongly enforce the need for smoking cessation to reduce exacerbation risk.<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> In addition to tobacco smoking, clinicians should consider the distinctive features of Asian patients with COPD, such as high exposure to biomass smoke and air pollution, low BMI, and increased prevalence of tuberculosis as risk factors for increased disease burden, including exacerbations.<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref><xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref><xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></p><p>Of concern, the mean number of moderate or severe AECOPD observed in the present study (1.1) was considerably greater than that reported in cohorts from other countries, such as the US (0.37),<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> Japan (0.28),<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> and Singapore (0.51).<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> However, findings from a study that compared sociodemographic and clinical characteristics of patients with COPD from the US and Korea reported significantly milder symptoms, including cough, sputum, and dyspnea, and fewer exacerbations in the latter group.<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> Our findings confirm the high prevalence of dyspnea in this cohort of patients, with 83.3% and 33.3% of the study population exhibiting mMRC scores &#8805; 1 and &#8805; 2, respectively. Notably, the mMRC score correlates with health status<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> and is predictive of the future risk of mortality.<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> However, patients with mMRC scores &lt; 1 may also experience considerable symptoms and health status impairment; therefore, clinicians should thoroughly assess symptom burden and exacerbation frequency.<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></p><p>Overall, a considerable exacerbation burden was observed in this study population, which may be explained by the high rate of comorbidities.<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref><xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref><xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> Chronic comorbidities in patients with COPD are common and associated with both frequent and increased exacerbation risk.<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> Indeed, results from a nationwide cohort study evaluating NHIS data from 12,554 Korean patients with COPD also demonstrated that comorbidities are more common in those with severe exacerbations than in those without severe exacerbations.<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> Additionally, anxiety and/or depression, which were reported in 32.5% of the study population, are associated with poor prognosis and an increased risk of exacerbations,<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref><xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> thereby underscoring the importance of routine evaluation of mental health to improve treatment outcomes. Indeed, a significantly higher proportion of patients in our study with anxiety or depression, than those without, experienced moderate to severe exacerbations. In line with a previous study involving Korean patients with COPD,<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> a statistically significant association between severe exacerbations and cardiovascular comorbidities was only observed with heart failure. Heart failure and COPD represent significant global health challenges, contributing to substantial morbidity and mortality.<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> Additionally, heart failure been shown to be associated with poor COPD-related outcomes,<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref><xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> highlighting the need for greater collaboration between cardiologists, pulmonologists and primary care physicians.</p><p>Interestingly, the comorbidity burden in Korean patients with COPD is reported to be lower than that reported in the US, which has documented that COPD-related comorbidities tend to vary by race and ethnicity.<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref><xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Therefore, treatment strategies for COPD need to consider racial differences and be personalized to individual patient needs. In our study population, hypertension was the most common comorbidity, reported in 37.6% of patients. This finding is consistent with previous studies involving Korean patients with COPD<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref><xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref><xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>; however, in general, the prevalence of hypertension as a comorbidity is reported to be lower in Korean patients than in US patients with COPD.<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></p><p>In line with the observation that Asian patients with COPD experience relatively less decline in FEV<sub>1</sub> than patients with COPD from other countries,<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> we also observed a small change (1.4%) in % FEV<sub>1</sub> 1 year after enrollment; however, this decline in lung function was likely not clinically meaningful. The rate of annual FEV<sub>1</sub> decline is highly variable in patients with COPD and has been shown to be independently associated with emphysema severity.<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> However, patients with COPD who are able to sustain progressive lung function decline, also known as &#8220;sustainers,&#8221; have relatively higher blood eosinophil levels, with a mean of 233 cells/&#956;L<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>; this observation is consistent with our study (mean blood eosinophil count: 226.8 cells/&#956;L). Indeed, in this cohort of patients, the decline in FEV<sub>1</sub> was higher in patients with blood eosinophil counts &#8805; 300 cells/&#956;L compared with those with blood eosinophil counts &lt; 300 cells/&#956;L. Interestingly, 21.9% of the study population had blood eosinophil counts &#8805; 300 cells/&#956;L, which is also associated with an increased risk of COPD exacerbation.<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref><xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref> This is consistent with our study findings, which found that the exacerbation-related burden was significantly higher in patients with blood eosinophil counts &#8805; 300 vs. &lt; 300 cells/&#956;L (48.1% vs. 39.0%; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.006). Of note, a substantial proportion of patients with blood eosinophil counts &#8805; 300 cells/&#956;L were also prescribed an ICS-containing medication (41.3%); this may explain, in part, the initial increase in FEV<sub>1</sub> observed in this group vs. those with blood eosinophil counts &lt; 300 cells/&#956;L between year 0 and year 1. Indeed, use of ICS-containing medications in patients with high blood eosinophil counts (&#8805; 150 cells/&#956;L) is associated with improvement in FEV<sub>1</sub>.<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref> Therefore, blood eosinophil counts are useful in predicting the magnitude of the effect of ICS and serve in the selection of effective COPD management strategies.<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></p><p>Our study has some limitations. A relatively large amount of data were missing, which is quite common in real-world databases.<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref> This highlights the need for caution when interpreting these results, and the importance of maintaining accurate medical records to ensure optimal, patient-centric treatment plans. Since the patients included in the KOCOSS database were mainly treated at tertiary medical centers, our study population may not have accurately represented the general COPD population. Additionally, the KOCOSS database was initiated in 2012, patients enrolled at that time may have been prescribed ICS plus LABA for severe COPD (according to the GOLD 2012 strategy document), whereas those enrolled later would likely have been prescribed LABA plus LAMA or LABA plus LAMA plus ICS (triple therapy). Data from year 0 could have been affected by patient recall bias, potentially leading to an underestimation of actual exacerbation rates. Although recall bias is also an inherent limitation of observational studies, this bias was minimized by prospectively collecting data during years 1&#8211;3.<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref> Since the KOCOSS database was not initially funded by any specific organization, some patients in the database were lost to follow-up. Although the protocol planned to collect data on HCRU by number of severe AECOPD, such data were not available and, therefore, were not collected. Nevertheless, our study presents original findings from one of the largest Asian cohorts of patients with COPD, which are broadly generalizable. Additionally, no other large cohorts of patients with COPD have been enrolled prospectively and followed up. Notably, our study integrates the KOCOSS cohort into the EXACOS platform, thus benefiting from prospectively collected data from KOCOSS in the context of a standardized platform. EXACOS is a &#8220;unified platform&#8221; and is the first attempt to collect COPD data in a single standardized format. This will enable a comparison of demographic characteristics and results across Western and Asian populations as well as other individual countries. EXACOS is investigating the burden of severe AECOPD and the association between the frequency of severe AECOPD and clinical and HCRU outcomes in other countries, such as the UK, as well as in less well-resourced countries.<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> Our study also provides crucial data on the rates of moderate or severe COPD exacerbations, which have not specifically been previously reported in Korean patients. Additionally, our study results can enhance understanding of COPD in an Asian setting, for which data are currently lacking.<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></p><p>In conclusion, these findings from the KOCOSS cohort indicate a high burden of AECOPD in South Korea, which may be attributable to the unique characteristics of the study population and suboptimal disease management. Our study better characterizes the patient population with COPD in South Korea and its exacerbation-related burden. Altogether, our findings on AECOPD prevalence have the potential to inform therapeutic decisions related to COPD management in the Korean population and illustrate the need to integrate evidence-based recommendations in routine clinical practice.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title><p>Medical writing was provided by Steven Tresker, who, when he wrote the manuscript, provided professional services to Cactus Life Sciences (part of Cactus Communications), and by Praveen Kaul of Cactus Life Sciences. The writing assistance was funded by AstraZeneca.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="supported-by"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> This study was funded by AstraZeneca. This research was also supported by funds (2016ER670100, 2016ER670101, 2016ER670102, and 2018ER670100, 2018ER670101, 2018ER670102) from the Research of Korea Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Disclosure:</bold> CKR received consulting/lecture fees from AstraZeneca, Bayer, Bayer, GlaxoSmithKline, MSD, Mundipharma, Novartis, Sanofi, Takeda, and Teva. KHY is an advisory board member for Ankook, AstraZeneca, Boehringer Ingelheim, GlaxoSmithKline, Hyundai, MSD, Mundipharma, Novartis, Nycomed, Takeda, and Teva. JYC and YBP have no potential conflicts of interest to disclose.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Data Sharing Statement:</bold> Data underlying the findings described in this manuscript may be obtained in accordance with AstraZeneca&#8217;s data sharing policy described at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://astrazenecagrouptrials.pharmacm.com/ST/Submission/Disclosure" ext-link-type="uri">https://astrazenecagrouptrials.pharmacm.com/ST/Submission/Disclosure</ext-link>. Data for studies directly listed on Vivli can be requested through Vivli at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.vivli.org" ext-link-type="uri">www.vivli.org</ext-link>. Data for studies not listed on Vivli could be requested through Vivli at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://vivli.org/members/enquiries-about-studies-not-listed-on-the-vivli-platform/" ext-link-type="uri">https://vivli.org/members/enquiries-about-studies-not-listed-on-the-vivli-platform/</ext-link>. AstraZeneca Vivli member page is also available, outlining further details: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://vivli.org/ourmember/astrazeneca/" ext-link-type="uri">https://vivli.org/ourmember/astrazeneca/</ext-link>. The datasets supporting the conclusions of this article are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p><bold>Author Contributions:</bold>
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><p><bold>Conceptualization:</bold> Rhee CK, Choi JY, Park YB, Yoo KH.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Data curation:</bold> Rhee CK, Choi JY.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Formal analysis:</bold> Rhee CK, Choi JY.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Investigation:</bold> Choi JY.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Methodology:</bold> Rhee CK, Choi JY.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Software:</bold> Choi JY.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Validation:</bold> Choi JY.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Writing - review &amp; editing:</bold> Rhee CK, Choi JY, Park YB, Yoo KH.</p></list-item></list></p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>Global Initiative for Chronic Obstructive Lung Disease (GOLD)</collab><source>2023 GOLD report</source><date-in-citation content-type="updated">Updated 2023</date-in-citation><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed March 25, 2024</date-in-citation><comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://goldcopd.org/2023-gold-report-2/#" ext-link-type="uri">https://goldcopd.org/2023-gold-report-2/#</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>World Health Organization</collab><source>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD)</source><date-in-citation content-type="updated">Updated 2023</date-in-citation><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed March 27, 2023</date-in-citation><comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/chronic-obstructive-pulmonary-disease-(copd)" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/chronic-obstructive-pulmonary-disease-(copd)</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>YB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Um</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical characteristics of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease in female patients: findings from a KOCOSS cohort</article-title><source>Int J Chron Obstruct Pulmon Dis</source><year>2020</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>2217</fpage><lpage>2224</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33061339</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2147/COPD.S269579</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7519806</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanania</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) is a major cause of morbidity and mortality worldwide</article-title><source>Respir Med</source><year>2012</year><volume>106</volume><issue>Suppl 2</issue><fpage>S1</fpage><lpage>S2</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0954-6111(12)00464-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23290699</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rhee</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Min</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>YI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Recent prevalence of and factors associated with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease in a rapidly aging society: Korea National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey 2015&#8211;2019</article-title><source>J Korean Med Sci</source><year>2023</year><volume>38</volume><issue>14</issue><elocation-id>e108</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37038644</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3346/jkms.2023.38.e108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10086381</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>National Health Insurance Service</collab><source>Health security system</source><date-in-citation content-type="updated">Updated 2020</date-in-citation><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed March 27, 2023</date-in-citation><comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.nhis.or.kr/english/wbheaa02300m01.do" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.nhis.or.kr/english/wbheaa02300m01.do</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rhee</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mortality of patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: a nationwide populationbased cohort study</article-title><source>Korean J Intern Med</source><year>2019</year><volume>34</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1272</fpage><lpage>1278</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31610634</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3904/kjim.2017.428</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6823577</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rhee</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>YI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Direct and indirect costs of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease in Korea</article-title><source>Tuberc Respir Dis (Seoul)</source><year>2019</year><volume>82</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30302958</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4046/trd.2018.0035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6304326</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The non-communicable disease burden in Korea: findings from the 2012 Korean Burden of Disease Study</article-title><source>J Korean Med Sci</source><year>2016</year><volume>31</volume><issue>Suppl 2</issue><fpage>S158</fpage><lpage>S167</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27775253</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3346/jkms.2016.31.S2.S158</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5081297</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Whittaker</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rubino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>M&#252;llerov&#225;</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Varghese</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Frequency and severity of exacerbations of COPD associated with future risk of exacerbations and mortality: a UK routine health care data study</article-title><source>Int J Chron Obstruct Pulmon Dis</source><year>2022</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>427</fpage><lpage>437</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35264849</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2147/COPD.S346591</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8901192</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wedzicha</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brill</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allinson</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Donaldson</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms and impact of the frequent exacerbator phenotype in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</article-title><source>BMC Med</source><year>2013</year><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>181</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23945277</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1741-7015-11-181</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3750926</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rothnie</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>M&#252;llerov&#225;</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smeeth</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quint</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Natural history of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease exacerbations in a general practice-based population with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</article-title><source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>2018</year><volume>198</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>464</fpage><lpage>471</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29474094</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1164/rccm.201710-2029OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6118021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Um</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>YB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical impacts of the classification by 2017 GOLD guideline comparing previous ones on outcomes of COPD in real-world cohorts</article-title><source>Int J Chron Obstruct Pulmon Dis</source><year>2018</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>3473</fpage><lpage>3484</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30498337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2147/COPD.S177238</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6207379</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical characteristics of non-smoking chronic obstructive pulmonary disease patients: findings from the KOCOSS cohort</article-title><source>COPD</source><year>2022</year><volume>19</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>174</fpage><lpage>181</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35392750</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/15412555.2022.2053088</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>TO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rhee</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Adherence to the GOLD guideline in COPD management of South Korea: findings from KOCOSS study 2011&#8211;2018</article-title><source>Chonnam Med J</source><year>2019</year><volume>55</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30740340</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4068/cmj.2019.55.1.47</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6351324</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chon</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rhee</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characteristics of patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease at the first visit to a pulmonary medical center in Korea: the Korea COPD Subgroup Study team cohort</article-title><source>J Korean Med Sci</source><year>2016</year><volume>31</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>553</fpage><lpage>560</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27051239</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3346/jkms.2016.31.4.553</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4810338</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Byun</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Na</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prediction of first acute exacerbation using COPD subtypes identified by cluster analysis</article-title><source>Int J Chron Obstruct Pulmon Dis</source><year>2019</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1389</fpage><lpage>1397</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31388298</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2147/COPD.S205517</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6607981</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>National Library of Medicine</collab><source>Exacerbations and their outcomes international (EXACOS International)</source><date-in-citation content-type="updated">Updated 2023</date-in-citation><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed March 27, 2023</date-in-citation><comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://classic.clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT05750810?cond=EXACOS&amp;draw=2&amp;rank=1" ext-link-type="uri">https://classic.clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT05750810?cond=EXACOS&amp;draw=2&amp;rank=1</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>National Library of Medicine</collab><source>Exacerbations and their outcomes international (EXACOS International) (EXACOS-Intl)</source><date-in-citation content-type="updated">Updated 2023</date-in-citation><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed March 27, 2023</date-in-citation><comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT04928417" ext-link-type="uri">https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT04928417</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Milne</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yunus</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rhee</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsunaga</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Current chronic obstructive pulmonary disease treatment status in Asia: a position statement of the Asian Pacific Society of Respirology</article-title><source>Tuberc Respir Dis (Seoul)</source><year>2022</year><volume>85</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>279</fpage><lpage>282</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35501669</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4046/trd.2022.0020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9263343</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ryu</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Understanding racial differences of COPD patients with an ecological model: two large cohort studies in the US and Korea</article-title><source>Ther Adv Chronic Dis</source><year>2021</year><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>2040622320982455</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33613934</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/2040622320982455</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7841674</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fukuchi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahayiddin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Celli</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Decramer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Efficacy of tiotropium in COPD patients from Asia: a subgroup analysis from the UPLIFT trial</article-title><source>Respirology</source><year>2011</year><volume>16</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>825</fpage><lpage>835</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21539680</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1440-1843.2011.01982.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Joi</surname><given-names>YR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Racial differences in comorbidity profile among patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</article-title><source>BMC Med</source><year>2018</year><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>178</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30285854</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12916-018-1159-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6171244</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wedzicha</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ichinose</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Humphries</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fogel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thach</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Indacaterol/glycopyrronium versus salmeterol/fluticasone in Asian patients with COPD at a high risk of exacerbations: results from the FLAME study</article-title><source>Int J Chron Obstruct Pulmon Dis</source><year>2017</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>339</fpage><lpage>349</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28176893</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2147/COPD.S125058</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5261570</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miravitlles</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sliwinski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Costello</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparison of clinical baseline characteristics between Asian and Western COPD patients in a prospective, international, multicenter study</article-title><source>Int J Chron Obstruct Pulmon Dis</source><year>2019</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1595</fpage><lpage>1601</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31440042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2147/COPD.S208245</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6664421</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jo</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>YI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Racial differences in prevalence and clinical characteristics of asthma-chronic obstructive pulmonary disease overlap</article-title><source>Front Med (Lausanne)</source><year>2021</year><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>780438</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34881272</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fmed.2021.780438</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8645561</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jo</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impact of BMI on exacerbation and medical care expenses in subjects with mild to moderate airflow obstruction</article-title><source>Int J Chron Obstruct Pulmon Dis</source><year>2018</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>2261</fpage><lpage>2269</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30100716</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2147/COPD.S163000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6067770</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khang</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long-term trends in smoking prevalence and its socioeconomic inequalities in Korea, 1992&#8211;2016</article-title><source>Int J Equity Health</source><year>2019</year><volume>18</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>148</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31533732</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12939-019-1051-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6751588</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zahra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheong</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Burden of disease attributable to smoking in Korea</article-title><source>Asia Pac J Public Health</source><year>2017</year><volume>29</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28198651</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/1010539516675696</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Papadopoulos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vardavas</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Limperi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Linardis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Georgoudis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Behrakis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Smoking cessation can improve quality of life among COPD patients: validation of the clinical COPD questionnaire into Greek</article-title><source>BMC Pulm Med</source><year>2011</year><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>13</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21352544</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-2466-11-13</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3050875</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of smoking on disease risk among South Korean adults</article-title><source>Tob Induc Dis</source><year>2018</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>45</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31516443</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.18332/tid/94472</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6659552</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rhee</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chau</surname><given-names>NQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yunus</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsunaga</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perng</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><collab>on behalf the COPD Assembly of the APSR</collab><article-title>Management of COPD in Asia: a position statement of the Asian Pacific Society of Respirology</article-title><source>Respirology</source><year>2019</year><volume>24</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1018</fpage><lpage>1025</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31276272</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/resp.13633</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rhee</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology, burden, and policy of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease in South Korea: a narrative review</article-title><source>J Thorac Dis</source><year>2021</year><volume>13</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>3888</fpage><lpage>3897</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34277078</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.21037/jtd-20-2100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8264691</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quibrera</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carretta</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bleecker</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowler</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Frequency of exacerbations in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: an analysis of the SPIROMICS cohort</article-title><source>Lancet Respir Med</source><year>2017</year><volume>5</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>619</fpage><lpage>626</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28668356</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2213-2600(17)30207-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5558856</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chubachi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haraguchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kameyama</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsutsumi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impact of mild exacerbation on COPD symptoms in a Japanese cohort</article-title><source>Int J Chron Obstruct Pulmon Dis</source><year>2016</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1269</fpage><lpage>1278</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27354785</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2147/COPD.S105454</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4907494</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sim</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yii</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bahety</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loh</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Navarro Rojas</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characteristics of patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease treated with long-acting bronchodilators in a real-world setting in Singapore: a single-senter observational study</article-title><source>Int J Chron Obstruct Pulmon Dis</source><year>2022</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1349</fpage><lpage>1363</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35711173</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2147/COPD.S357820</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9192350</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bestall</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garrod</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garnham</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wedzicha</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Usefulness of the Medical Research Council (MRC) dyspnoea scale as a measure of disability in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</article-title><source>Thorax</source><year>1999</year><volume>54</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>581</fpage><lpage>586</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10377201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/thx.54.7.581</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1745516</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishimura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Izumi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsukino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oga</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dyspnea is a better predictor of 5-year survival than airway obstruction in patients with COPD</article-title><source>Chest</source><year>2002</year><volume>121</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1434</fpage><lpage>1440</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12006425</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1378/chest.121.5.1434</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exploring the impact of number and type of comorbidities on the risk of severe COPD exacerbations in Korean Population: a Nationwide Cohort Study</article-title><source>BMC Pulm Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>151</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33957924</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12890-021-01497-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8101227</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Westerik</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Metting</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Boven</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tiersma</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kocks</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schermer</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Associations between chronic comorbidity and exacerbation risk in primary care patients with COPD</article-title><source>Respir Res</source><year>2017</year><volume>18</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>31</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28166777</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12931-017-0512-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5294875</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carriere</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comorbidity as a contributor to frequent severe acute exacerbation in COPD patients</article-title><source>Int J Chron Obstruct Pulmon Dis</source><year>2016</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1857</fpage><lpage>1865</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27536097</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2147/COPD.S103063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4976810</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laurin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moullec</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bacon</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lavoie</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of anxiety and depression on chronic obstructive pulmonary disease exacerbation risk</article-title><source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>2012</year><volume>185</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>918</fpage><lpage>923</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22246177</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1164/rccm.201105-0939PP</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mart&#237;nez-Gestoso</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garc&#237;a-Sanz</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carreira</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salgado</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Calvo-&#193;lvarez</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doval-Oubi&#241;a</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impact of anxiety and depression on the prognosis of copd exacerbations</article-title><source>BMC Pulm Med</source><year>2022</year><volume>22</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>169</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35488330</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12890-022-01934-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9052487</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petrie</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jhund</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chalmers</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McMurray</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heart failure and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: diagnostic pitfalls and epidemiology</article-title><source>Eur J Heart Fail</source><year>2009</year><volume>11</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>130</fpage><lpage>139</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19168510</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/eurjhf/hfn013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2639415</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sadatsafavi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>FitzGerald</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk of cardiovascular comorbidity in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Lancet Respir Med</source><year>2015</year><volume>3</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>631</fpage><lpage>639</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26208998</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2213-2600(15)00241-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishimura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Makita</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Konno</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nasuhara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Annual change in pulmonary function and clinical phenotype in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</article-title><source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>2012</year><volume>185</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>44</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22016444</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1164/rccm.201106-0992OC</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Juthong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaenmuang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association between blood eosinophils with exacerbation and patient-reported outcomes in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease patients in an endemic area for parasitic infections: a prospective study</article-title><source>J Thorac Dis</source><year>2020</year><volume>12</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>4868</fpage><lpage>4876</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33145060</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.21037/jtd-19-4101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7578515</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lamb</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chase</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saferali</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Blood eosinophil count thresholds and exacerbations in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</article-title><source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source><year>2018</year><volume>141</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>2037</fpage><lpage>2047.e10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29709670</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jaci.2018.04.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5994197</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalin</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>L&#248;kke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kristiansen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Birkefoss</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A systematic review of blood eosinophils and continued treatment with inhaled corticosteroids in patients with COPD</article-title><source>Respir Med</source><year>2022</year><volume>198</volume><elocation-id>106880</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35599064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.rmed.2022.106880</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morel</surname><given-names>AEG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Varga</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heymans</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dongen</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schaik</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tulder</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dealing with missing data in real-world data: a scoping review of simulation studies</article-title><source>Res Sq</source><year>2022</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roche</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reddel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brusselle</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Papi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Quality standards for real-world research. Focus on observational database studies of comparative effectiveness</article-title><source>Ann Am Thorac Soc</source><year>2014</year><volume>11</volume><issue>Suppl 2</issue><fpage>S99</fpage><lpage>S104</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24559028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1513/AnnalsATS.201309-300RM</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Investigation of the clinical, radiological and biological factors associated with disease progression, phenotypes and endotypes of COPD in China (COMPASS): study design, protocol and rationale</article-title><source>ERJ Open Res</source><year>2021</year><volume>7</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>00201</fpage><lpage>02021</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34527722</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1183/23120541.00201-2021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8435791</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ku</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and socioeconomic burden of diabetes mellitus in South Korean adults: a population-based study using administrative data</article-title><source>BMC Public Health</source><year>2021</year><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>548</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33743612</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12889-021-10450-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7980668</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIALS</title><supplementary-material id="S1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Supplementary Table 1</title><p>Proportion of Korean patients with COPD from the KOCOSS cohort experiencing &#8805; 1 exacerbations by blood eosinophil counts based on prospective 1-year follow-up data</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jkms-39-e164-s001.doc" id="d66e3671" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="S2" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Supplementary Table 2</title><p>Proportion of Korean patients with COPD from the KOCOSS cohort experiencing &#8805; 1 exacerbation by BMI categories based on prospective 1-year follow-up data</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jkms-39-e164-s002.doc" id="d66e3676" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="S3" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Supplementary Table 3</title><p>Korean patients with COPD from the KOCOSS cohort experiencing &#8805; 1 exacerbation by presence of comorbidities based on prospective 1-year follow-up data</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jkms-39-e164-s003.doc" id="d66e3681" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="S4" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Supplementary Table 4</title><p>Demographic and clinical characteristics of Korean patients with COPD from the KOCOSS cohort based on number of exacerbations in year 1 (&#8805; 2 vs. &lt; 2 exacerbations)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jkms-39-e164-s004.doc" id="d66e3686" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="S5" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Supplementary Table 5</title><p>Comorbidities reported by Korean patients with COPD from the KOCOSS cohort who were also being treated for asthma</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jkms-39-e164-s005.doc" id="d66e3691" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="S6" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Supplementary Fig. 1</title><p>Proportion of Korean patients with COPD from the KOCOSS cohort who experienced exacerbations during years 1, 2, and 3.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jkms-39-e164-s006.doc" id="d66e3696" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="S7" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Supplementary Reference</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jkms-39-e164-s007.doc" id="d66e3700" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec></back></article></pmc-articleset>