<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">medRxiv</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3854</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">medrxiv</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MEDRXIV</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>medRxiv</journal-title></journal-title-group><publisher><publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Preprints</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11275668</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11275668.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11275668</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11275668</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39072031</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2024.07.18.24310648</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">1</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Gender Differences in the Diagnosis of Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease after Spirometry</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8490-4899</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Moffett</surname><given-names initials="AT">Alexander T.</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="A2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="A3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3603-4769</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Halpern</surname><given-names initials="SD">Scott D.</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="A2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="A3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="A4" ref-type="aff">4</xref><xref rid="A5" ref-type="aff">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9588-3819</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Weissman</surname><given-names initials="GE">Gary E.</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="A2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="A3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="A4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Division of Pulmonary, Allergy, and Critical Care Medicine, Department of Medicine, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA, USA</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Palliative and Advanced Illness Research (PAIR) Center, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA, USA</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Leonard Davis Institute of Health Economics, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA, USA</aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Department of Biostatistics, Epidemiology and Informatics, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA, USAs</aff><aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Department of Medical Ethics and Health Policy, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA, USA</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="con" id="FN1"><p id="P1"><bold>Contributions</bold>: All authors fulfill ICMJE criteria for authorship.</p></fn><corresp id="CR1"><bold>Corresponding Author</bold>: Alexander T. Moffett, Hospital of the University of Pennsylvania, Division of Pulmonary, Allergy, and Critical Care Medicine, 3400 Spruce Street, Philadelphia, PA 19104, <email>amoffett@upenn.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">467544</issue-id><elocation-id>2024.07.18.24310648</elocation-id><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>26</day><month>07</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>27</day><month>07</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-03-11 00:25:17.147"><day>11</day><month>03</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License</ext-link>, which allows reusers to distribute, remix, adapt, and build upon the material in any medium or format for noncommercial purposes only, and only so long as attribution is given to the creator.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="nihpp-2024.07.18.24310648v1.pdf"/><self-uri content-type="pdf">nihpp-2024.07.18.24310648.pdf</self-uri><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="published-article" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="letter" journal-id="Ann Am Thorac Soc" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pubmed" xlink:href="39589282"><article-title>Sex Differences in the Diagnosis of Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease after Spirometry</article-title><volume>22</volume><issue>3</issue><date><day>1</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date><fpage>466</fpage><lpage>468</lpage><source>Annals of the American Thoracic Society</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1513/AnnalsATS.202404-402RL</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39589282</pub-id></related-article><abstract id="ABS1"><sec id="S1"><title>Background</title><p id="P2">Women are more likely than men to report delays in the diagnosis of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), though the etiology of these delays is unknown. We sought to test whether delays in COPD diagnosis persist after the performance of spirometry.</p></sec><sec id="S2"><title>Methods</title><p id="P3">We used the Optum Labs Data Warehouse to identify patients 18 years of age and older without a prior diagnosis of COPD, with a post-bronchodilator forced expiratory volume in 1 second (FEV<sub>1</sub>) to forced vital capacity (FVC) ratio of less than 0.7 on spirometry. We used a Cox proportional hazards model to compare the time to diagnosis after spirometry in men and women, adjusting for age, race, ethnicity, tobacco use, and post-bronchodilator FEV<sub>1</sub>/FVC.</p></sec><sec id="S3"><title>Results</title><p id="P4">The probability of receiving a COPD diagnosis after the performance of spirometry was lower among women than men (adjusted hazard ratio [aHR] 0.66, 95% confidence interval [CI] 0.50 to 0.88)</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="P5">In this retrospective cohort study of patients with spirometric evidence of obstruction, the time to diagnosis of COPD was greater among women than men. While previous vignette-based studies have found that gender differences in the diagnosis of COPD resolve with the performance of spirometry, we found that gender differences persist after spirometry has been performed. Clinicians were less likely to diagnose COPD in women even when spirometry supported this diagnosis.</p></sec></abstract><funding-group><award-group id="award01"><funding-source>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute of the National Institutes of Health</funding-source><award-id>F32HL167456</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S5"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P6">Women are more likely than men to report delays in the diagnosis of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD).<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> However, the etiology of these delays is unknown. Vignette-based studies, involving hypothetical patients who differ only by gender, have found that while physicians are less likely to consider COPD as an initial diagnosis in women, this difference resolves with the performance of spirometry.<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> The implication is that delays in the diagnosis of COPD in women are due to delays in the performance of spirometry. If this hypothesis were true, increasing access to spirometry would yield diagnostic equity in men and women. However, this hypothesis has not been tested with clinical data. We sought to test the alternate hypothesis&#8212;that gender differences in the diagnosis of COPD persist after the performance of spirometry&#8212;by comparing the time to diagnosis of COPD in men and women with spirometric evidence of obstruction.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Methods</title><p id="P7">We used the Optum Labs Data Warehouse (OLDW)&#8212;a database consisting of de-identified administrative claims and electronic health record data from across the United States&#8212;to identify patients 18 years of age and older with a post-bronchodilator forced expiratory volume in 1 second (FEV<sub>1</sub>) to forced vital capacity (FVC) ratio of less than 0.7 on spirometry performed between 2007 and 2020.<sup><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> A clinical encounter with a diagnosis code for COPD&#8212;including chronic bronchitis and emphysema&#8212;was interpreted as a diagnosis of COPD. We excluded patients who had been diagnosed with COPD prior to the performance of spirometry. To better measure the relationship between spirometry and the diagnosis of COPD, we also excluded patients with a positive bronchodilator response, who are more likely to be diagnosed with asthma.</p><p id="P8">We used a cause-specific Cox proportional hazards model to estimate the time to diagnosis of COPD, accounting for death as a competing risk. The primary exposure was patient gender, with age, race, ethnicity, tobacco use, and post-bronchodilator FEV<sub>1</sub>/FVC included as covariates.</p><p id="P9">As the most recent Global Initiative for Chronic Obstructive Lung Disease (GOLD) guidelines recommend repeating spirometry, prior to the diagnosis of COPD, in patients with a post-bronchodilator FEV<sub>1</sub>/FVC &#8805; 0.6, in a sensitivity analysis we further compared the time to diagnosis in patients with an FEV<sub>1</sub>/FVC &lt; 0.6.<sup><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Results</title><p id="P10">OLDW included post-bronchodilator spirometry measurements for 4193 patients, of whom 906 had a post-bronchodilator FEV<sub>1</sub>/FVC &lt; 0.7. Of these patients 863 were without a prior diagnosis of COPD, and of the remaining patients, 565 were without a post-bronchodilator response. This cohort consisted of 292 men (52.0%) and 273 women (48.0%) (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The median age was 56 years (interquartile range [IQR] 22). A history of tobacco use was documented for 380 patients (67.6%). The median post-bronchodilator FEV<sub>1</sub>/FVC was 0.64 (IQR 0.10). The median follow up time after spirometry was 24 months (IQR 33). COPD was diagnosed in 200 (35.4%) patients and 20 patients (3.5%) died without a diagnosis of COPD, while 345 patients (61.1%) were right censored.</p><p id="P11">The probability of receiving a COPD diagnosis after the performance of spirometry was lower among women than men (adjusted hazard ratio [aHR] 0.66, 95% confidence interval [CI] 0.50 to 0.88) (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). In our model, the mean time to diagnosis after spirometry was greater in women (106.5 months [95% CI 86.2 to 127.7]) than men (89.7 months [95% CI 72.9 to 106.6]). The probability of receiving a COPD diagnosis was higher in older patients (aHR 1.05 per year of age [95% CI 1.03 to 1.06]) and in patients with a history of tobacco use (aHR 3.61 [95% CI 2.35 to 5.55]). The sensitivity analysis among patients with an FEV<sub>1</sub>/FVC &lt; 0.6 also revealed a lower probability of COPD diagnosis in women than men (aHR 0.61, 95% CI 0.38 to 0.98).</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P12">In this retrospective cohort study of patients with spirometric evidence of obstruction, the time to diagnosis of COPD was greater among women than men. While previous vignette-based studies have found that gender differences in the diagnosis of COPD resolve with the performance of spirometry, we found that gender differences persist after spirometry has been performed. In our cohort, clinicians were less likely to diagnose COPD in women even when spirometry supported this diagnosis.</p><p id="P13">Despite the presence of spirometric evidence supporting the diagnosis of COPD, less than half of the patients in our cohort received this diagnosis at any point during follow up, while one fourth of the patients did not receive any diagnosis with which to explain their documented obstruction. More patients were diagnosed with asthma than with COPD and the preference of physicians for this diagnosis&#8212;in a cohort defined by the presence of a post-bronchodilator FEV<sub>1</sub>/FVC &lt; 0.7 and the absence of a bronchodilator response&#8212;is unexpected, particularly as asthma and COPD are not mutually exclusive diagnoses.<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> While previous studies involving the performance of spirometry have also found low rates of obstructive lung disease diagnosis as well as a preference for the diagnosis of asthma over COPD, our study is the first to suggest that this preference is present even in patients for whom spirometry has already been performed.<sup><xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> Our study suggests that the underdiagnosis of COPD stems from more than just the underuse of spirometry.<sup><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup></p><p id="P14">Our study has several important limitations. First, though spirometric evidence of obstruction is necessary for the diagnosis of COPD, it is not sufficient, with the diagnosis dependent as well upon the presence of appropriate symptoms or risk factors.<sup><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> Data regarding the presence of symptoms and risk factors are not included in the OLDW and gender differences in symptoms and risk factors may account for some proportion of the diagnostic differences identified in this study. Second, though our cohort was drawn from a national database, the inclusion of PFT data in this database was subject to selection bias, potentially limiting the generalizability of our findings.</p><p id="P15">In summary, in a retrospective cohort of patients with spirometric evidence of obstruction, the time to diagnosis of COPD was greater among women than men. Further work is needed to understand the etiology of this difference.</p></sec></body><back><ack id="S9"><title>Funding:</title><p id="P16">Research reported in this publication was supported by the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute of the National Institutes of Health under Award Number F32HL167456. The content is solely the responsibility of the authors and does not necessarily represent the official views of the National Institutes of Health.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raparla</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Plauschinat</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <etal/><article-title>Gender differences in symptoms and care delivery for chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</article-title>. <source>J Womens Health</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>1267</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>74</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1089/jwh.2012.3650</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3518541</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23210491</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tashkin</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Pye</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Gender bias in the diagnosis of COPD</article-title>. <source>Chest</source><year>2001</year>;<volume>119</volume>:<fpage>1691</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11399692</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1378/chest.119.6.1691</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miravitlles</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de la Roza</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Naberan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal/> [<article-title>Attitudes toward the diagnosis of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease in primary care</article-title>]. <source>Arch Bronconeumol</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>3</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16426516</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s1579-2129(06)60106-7</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Optum Labs</collab>. <source>Optum Labs and Optum Labs Data Warehouse (OLDW) descriptions and citation</source>. <publisher-name>Eden Prairie: Optum Labs</publisher-name>, <year>2023</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Agust&#237;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Celli</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Criner</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <etal/><article-title>Global Initiative for Chronic Obstructive Lung Disease 2023 report: GOLD executive summary</article-title>. <source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>2023</year>;<fpage>207</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1164/rccm.202301-0106PP</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10111975</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36856433</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Postma</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Rabe</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name>. <article-title>The asthma-COPD overlap syndrome</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>373</volume>:<fpage>1241</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26398072</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMra1411863</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tinkelman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nordyke</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Halbert</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Misdiagnosis of COPD and asthma in primary care patients 40 years of age and over</article-title>. <source>J Asthma</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>75</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>80</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16448970</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/02770900500448738</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>TV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kinney</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Comellas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal/><article-title>Prevalence of abnormal spirometry in individuals with a smoking history and no known obstructive lung disease</article-title>. <source>Respir Med</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>208</volume>:<fpage>107126</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36717002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.rmed.2023.107126</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9990311</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hangaard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Helle</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Hejlesen</surname><given-names>OK</given-names></name>. <article-title>Causes of misdiagnosis of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: A systematic scoping review</article-title>. <source>Respir Med</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>129</volume>:<fpage>63</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>84</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28732838</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.rmed.2017.05.015</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Diab</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gershon</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sin</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>, <etal/><article-title>Underdiagnosis and overdiagnosis of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</article-title>. <source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>198</volume>:<fpage>1130</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29979608</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1164/rccm.201804-0621CI</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1:</label><caption><p id="P17">Cumulative incidence function for the diagnosis of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease in men and women, adjusting for age, race, ethnicity, tobacco use, and FEV<sub>1</sub>/FVC. Shaded areas represent 95% confidence intervals. FEV<sub>1</sub> = forced expiratory volume in 1 second; FVC = forced vital capacity.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihpp-2024.07.18.24310648v1-f0001.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1:</label><caption><p id="P18">Patient Characteristics<xref rid="TFN1" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="none"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Men</bold> (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 292)</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Women</bold> (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 273)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Age, years</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57 (19)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (23)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">
<bold>Race</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Asian</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 11</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Black</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (9.2)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (9.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;White</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">245 (83.9)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220 (80.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Other</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt; 11</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt; 11</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">
<bold>Ethnicity</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Hispanic</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (9.2)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (8.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Non-Hispanic</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">265 (90.8)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250 (91.6)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">
<bold>History of Tobacco Use</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206 (70.5)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">174 (63.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86 (29.5)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99 (36.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>FEV<sub>1</sub>/FVC</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64 (0.11)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63 (0.10)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Follow Up, months</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (31)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (33)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">
<bold>Diagnosis After Spirometry</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Asthma</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130 (44.5)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">139 (50.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Bronchiectasis</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 11</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">121 (41.4)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79 (28.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Cystic Fibrosis</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Any of the Above</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">222 (76.0)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">190 (69.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;None of the Above</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70 (24.0)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83 (30.4)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">
<bold>Treatment After Spirometry</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Short-Acting <italic toggle="yes">&#946;</italic><sub>2</sub> Agonist</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">160 (54.8)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">149 (54.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Long-Acting <italic toggle="yes">&#946;</italic><sub>2</sub> Agonist</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">121 (41.4)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">123 (45.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Long-Acting Muscarinic Antagonist</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (14.7)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (12.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Inhaled Corticosteroid</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">146 (50.0)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">146 (53.5)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TFN1"><label>*</label><p id="P19">Values are medians (IQR) for continuous variables and counts (percentage) for categorical variables.</p></fn><fn id="TFN2"><p id="P20">Definition of abbreviations: FEV<sub>1</sub> = forced expiratory volume in 1 second; FVC = forced vital capacity; IQR = interquartile range.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></floats-group></article></pmc-articleset>