<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2786</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">medicine</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MD</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0025-7974</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1536-5964</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer Health</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10019112</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10019112.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10019112</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10019112</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36930094</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000032911</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" article-version-type="Version of Record">3</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>4300</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Research Article</subject><subject>Observational Study</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Prevalence and association of diabetic nephropathy in newly diagnosed Chinese patients with diabetes in the Hebei province: A single-center case-control study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names initials="X">Xiaoya</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><email>q651943@163.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names initials="N">Ninglin</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="c1" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names initials="X">Xianghui</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><email>t685835@163.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="X">Xiaolei</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><email>p954312@163.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yange</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><email>g487171@163.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names initials="J">Jie</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><email>w738860@163.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label> Department of Endocrinology, Hebei Hospital of Traditional Chinese Medicine, Shijiazhuang, China.</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1">*Correspondence: Ninglin Kang, Department of Endocrinology, Hebei Hospital of Traditional Chinese Medicine, No. 389 Zhongshan East Road, Shijiazhuang, Hebei 050000, China (e-mail: <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="449100596@qq.com">449100596@qq.com</email>).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>17</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>102</volume><issue>11</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">431438</issue-id><elocation-id>e32911</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>12</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>1</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>1</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>17</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>17</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-05-04 23:25:13.090"><day>04</day><month>05</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2023 the Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-Non Commercial License 4.0 (CCBY-NC)</ext-link>, where it is permissible to download, share, remix, transform, and buildup the work provided it is properly cited. The work cannot be used commercially without permission from the journal.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="medi-102-e32911.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="medi-102-e32911.pdf"/><abstract><p>Diabetes is a chronic disease and has huge pressure on patients and the medical system, especially for patients with diabetic complications, for example, diabetic nephropathy. Diabetic nephropathy is a diabetic complication associated with damage to the kidney. To improve the quality of life of patients with diabetes, it is necessary to understand the factors that are associated with diabetic nephropathy. The objective of the study was to find the prevalence of diabetic nephropathy in newly diagnosed patients with diabetes and to develop the association between clinicopathological parameters and diabetic nephropathy. In a case-control study, demographics, anthropometric, and clinicopathological parameters of a total of 305 newly diagnosed patients with diabetes (the fasting blood glucose &#8805; 7.0&#8201;mM/L and/or glycosylated hemoglobin &#8805; 6.5&#8201;mM/L) in Hebei province were included in the analysis. If the urine albumin to creatinine ratio was &#8805; 30 (microalbuminuria) then patients were considered diabetic nephropathy. Among enrolled patients, 206 (68%) were males and 99 (32%) were females and they were 46 to 71 years old. Demographic variables and health-related behaviors were the same among patients with diabetes either with nephropathy (case group, n = 135) or patients without nephropathy (control group, n = 170, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; .05 for all). The prevalence of diabetic nephropathy was 44%. Female to male ratio was 1:1.7 in the case group. Patients with diabetic nephropathy had higher body weight (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .0001), waist circumference (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .0006), and body mass index (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .0002) than those of patients without nephropathy. Abnormal urinary globulin (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .041, odd ratio (OR): 1.1231) was associated with diabetic nephropathy. Aspartate transaminase (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .0651, OR: 0.8541), alkaline phosphatase (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .0661, OR: 0.8122), hypertension (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .0821, OR: 0.8214), and blood urea nitrogen (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .0842, OR: 0.9411) were not significantly associated with diabetic neuropathy. However, they are near the statistical cutoff value. The prevalence of diabetic nephropathy in newly diagnosed diabetic patients of Hebei province is higher than those of the other provinces. Urinary globulin excretion had a weak association with the presence of nephropathy defined by urinary albumin excretion in patients with diabetes. The presence of other diabetic complications is also an essential parameter for diabetic nephropathy. Males are more susceptible to diabetic nephropathy than females if diabetic (Evidence Level: V; Technical Efficacy: Stage 3).</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>albuminuria</kwd><kwd>creatinine</kwd><kwd>diabetes</kwd><kwd>diabetic complications</kwd><kwd>diabetic nephropathy</kwd><kwd>globulin</kwd><kwd>inflammation</kwd><kwd>microalbuminuria</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name><meta-value>TRUE</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>1. Introduction</title><p>Diabetes mellitus is a chronic hyperglycemic condition, a metabolic disease, and it is due to metabolic disorders.<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</sup> The incidences of diabetes is higher in recent eras.<sup>[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</sup> According to the International Diabetes Federation, there will be a huge numbers of patients with diabetes in the future.<sup>[<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]</sup> Diabetes is a chronic disease and has huge pressure on patients and the medical system, especially for patients with diabetic complications, for example, diabetic nephropathy (diabetes related renal impairment).<sup>[<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</sup> The life expectancy of patients with diabetes, especially patients with diabetic complications, is shorter than those of normal individuals.<sup>[<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</sup> One diabetic complication, for example, is diabetic nephropathy and it is responsible for cardiovascular diseases.<sup>[<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</sup> COVID-19 patients who had diabetes suffered a lot and had higher mortality than normal COVID-19-positive patients.<sup>[<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</sup> To improve the quality of life of patients with diabetes, it is necessary to understand the factors that are associated with diabetic nephropathy (diabetic kidney injury or diabetic kidney disease). Diabetic nephropathy is associated with inflammation.<sup>[<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</sup> Neuregulin-4<sup>[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]</sup> and the other biomarkers<sup>[<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</sup> have been reported to be associated with diabetic nephropathy. An early biomarker may proceed earlier diagnosis, treatment reduces diabetic nephropathy prevalence and slows diabetic nephropathy progression.<sup>[<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]</sup> The prevalence of diabetic nephropathy among Chinese diabetic Mellitus patients is 22%.<sup>[<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</sup> However, the prevalence and association of diabetic nephropathy among newly diagnosed patients with diabetes in Hebei province of China are not available.</p><p>Globulin is a serum protein called immunoglobulin because it is associated with immune functions.<sup>[<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</sup> The main components of globulin are &#945;<sub>1</sub>, &#945;<sub>2</sub>, <italic toggle="yes">&#946;</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">&#947;</italic>. Globulin is associated with liver function.<sup>[<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]</sup> Cross-sectional studies reported that urinary globulin has positive association with diabetic nephropathy.<sup>[<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]</sup> A further case-control study is required to investigate the role of diabetic complication besides of urinary globulin in diabetic nephropathy.</p><p>The objectives of the single-center case-control study were to find the prevalence of diabetic nephropathy in newly diagnosed patients with diabetes in Hebei province of China and to develop the association between clinicopathological parameters of patients with diabetes and the prevalence of diabetic nephropathy.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>2. Materials and methods</title><sec><title>2.1. Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p>The designed protocol (approval no. HHTCM2022046 dated 15 July 2018) was approved by the Hebei Hospital of Traditional Chinese Medicine review board. Written informed consent was taken from participants before the study. The study follows the law of China and the V2008 Declarations of Helsinki.</p></sec><sec><title>2.2. Inclusion criteria</title><p>Only newly diagnosed patients with diabetes aged more than 18 years were included in the study.</p></sec><sec><title>2.3. Exclusion criteria</title><p>Patients who had no data for urinary globulin (immunoglobulin), albumin, and/or creatinine in the records were excluded from the study. Patients with kidney diseases other than diabetic nephropathy (e.g., kidney cancer) were excluded.</p></sec><sec><title>2.4. Outcome measures</title><p>Demographic variables (gender, age, and ethnicity), anthropometric parameters (height, body weight, waist circumference, and body mass index [BMI]), health-related behaviors (drinker and smoker), and clinicopathological parameters (blood glucose, glycosylated hemoglobin, urine albumin, urine creatinine, liver functions enzymes) were evaluated.</p></sec><sec><title>2.5. Diabetes mellitus</title><p>The fasting blood glucose of 7.0&#8201;mM/L or more and/or glycosylated hemoglobin 6.5&#8201;mM/L or more was considered diabetes mellitus.<sup>[<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]</sup></p></sec><sec><title>2.6. Diabetic nephropathy</title><p>If the urine albumin to creatinine ratio was 30 or more (microalbuminuria) then patients were considered diabetic nephropathy.<sup>[<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</sup></p></sec><sec sec-type="subjects"><title>2.7. Patients without nephropathy</title><p>If the urine albumin to creatinine ratio was less than 30 (non-albuminuria) then patients were considered without nephropathy.<sup>[<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</sup></p></sec><sec><title>2.8. Body mass index</title><p>From 18.5 to 24.9&#8201;kg/m<sup>2</sup> was considered a normal BMI, from 25 to 29.9&#8201;kg/m<sup>2</sup> was considered overweight, and 30&#8201;kg/m<sup>2</sup> or more was considered obese.<sup>[<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</sup></p></sec><sec><title>2.9. Health-related behaviors</title><p>A person who had more than 12 drinks per year was considered a drinker.<sup>[<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]</sup> A person who smokes more than 100 cigars was considered a smoker.<sup>[<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]</sup></p></sec><sec><title>2.10. Hypertension</title><p>Systolic blood pressure of 140&#8201;mm Hg or more and/or diastolic blood pressure of 90&#8201;mm Hg or more was considered hypertension.<sup>[<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]</sup> Patients taking antihypertensive agents were classified as hypertensive subjects.</p></sec><sec><title>2.11. Urinary globulin</title><p>ELISA test (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA) was used for the measurement of urinary globulin (immunoglobulin).</p><p>The other clinicopathological parameters were evaluated by the ELISA test method.</p></sec><sec><title>2.12. Statistical analysis</title><p>Categoric variables are depicted as frequency (percentage). Continuous normal variables are depicted as mean &#177; standard deviation (SD). Continuous non- normal variables are depicted as median (range). InStat 3.01, GraphPad Software, San Diego, CA was used for statistical analysis purposes. The Fisher&#8217;s exact test or the Chi-Square test was used for the statistical analysis of categoric variables. An unpaired <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test was used for statistical analysis of continuous normal variables with equal SDs and for normal variables with unequal SDs, an unpaired <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test with Welch correction was used for statistical analysis. For continuous abnormal variables, the Mann&#8211;Whitney test was used for statistical analysis. The distribution of SDs within the group among continuous variables was checked whether distributed equally or not using the Brown&#8211;Forsythe test. Distribution of variables whether normal or non-normal were checked visually by the histogram method. Multiple regression analysis was performed to establish an association between outcome measures and diabetic nephropathy.<sup>[<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]</sup> All results were considered significant for less than .05 <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value at a 95% confidence interval.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>3. Results</title><sec><title>3.1. Study population</title><p>From January 15, 2018, to May 17, 2020, a total of 352 patients were diagnosed with diabetes mellitus (fasting blood glucose &#8805; 7.0&#8201;mM/L and/or glycosylated hemoglobin &#8805; 6.5&#8201;mM/L) at the Hebei Hospital of Traditional Chinese Medicine, Shijiazhuang, Hebei, China, and the referring hospitals. Among 352 patients, 47 patients had no data for urinary globulin, albumin, and/or creatinine in their records. Therefore, these were excluded from the study. Demographic variables, anthropometric parameters, and clinicopathological parameters of a total of 305 patients with diabetes were included in the analysis. The summary diagram of the study is presented in Figure <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>The summary diagram of the study. Diabetic nephropathy: the urine albumin to creatinine ratio &#8805; 30 (microalbuminuria). Patients without nephropathy: the urine albumin to creatinine ratio &lt; 30.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="medi-102-e32911-g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>3.2. Outcome measures</title><p>A total of 206 (68%) males and 99 (32%) females from age 46 to 71 years were included in the analysis. The prevalence of diabetic nephropathy was 44%. No significant differences were reported for demographic variables of patients with diabetes between those who had diabetic nephropathy (case group, urine albumin to creatinine ratio &#8805; 30) and patients without nephropathy (control group, urine albumin to creatinine ratio &lt; 30; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; .05 for all). Female to male ratio was 1: 1.7 in the case group (Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographics variables of patients with diabetes.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Parameters</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetic nephropathy</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients without nephropathy</th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Comparison between groups</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Number of patients with diabetes</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">305</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">135</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">170</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Df</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Gender</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206 (68)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85 (63)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">121 (71)</td><td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">.1406 (Fisher&#8217;s exact test)</td><td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.6336&#8211;1.053</td><td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99 (32)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (37)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (29)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Age (yr)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minimum</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td><td align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">&lt;.1319 (Mann&#8211;Whitney test)</td><td align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Ethnicity</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Han Chinese</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">267 (88)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">119 (88)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">148 (87)</td><td align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">.9072 (&#967;<sup>2</sup> test)</td><td align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mongolian</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (11)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (10)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (12)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tibetan</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>Categoric variables are presented as frequency (percentage). Continuous abnormal variables are depicted as median (range).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value &lt; .05 is considered significant.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>Diabetic nephropathy: the urine albumin to creatinine ratio &#8805; 30 (microalbuminuria).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>Patients without nephropathy: the urine albumin to creatinine ratio &lt; 30.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>CI = confidence interval (using the approximation of Katz.), Df = degree of freedom, N/A = not applicable, &#967;<sup>2</sup>-test = Chi-Square test.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Patients with diabetic nephropathy had higher body weight, waist circumference, and BMI than those of patients without nephropathy (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .05 for all, <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test, Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Anthropometric parameters of patients with diabetes.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameters</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetic nephropathy</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients without nephropathy</th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Comparison between groups</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of patients with diabetes</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">305</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">135</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">170</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95 % CI</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Df</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Height (cm)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">163.21&#8201;&#177;&#8201;13.22</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">160.15&#8201;&#177;&#8201;13.17</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">162.14&#8201;&#177;&#8201;17.18</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.2674 (Unpaired <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;1.534 to 5.514</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">303</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body weight (kg)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.18&#8201;&#177;&#8201;11.12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.51&#8201;&#177;&#8201;9.12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.12&#8201;&#177;&#8201;10.15</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.0001 (Unpaired <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test with Welch correction)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;7.566 to &#8722;3.214</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">298</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Waist circumference (cm)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">109.52&#8201;&#177;&#8201;6.19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">110.11&#8201;&#177;&#8201;9.15</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">107.15&#8201;&#177;&#8201;4.15</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.0006 (Unpaired <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test with Welch correction)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;4.636 to &#8722;1.284</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">177</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body mass index (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.47&#8201;&#177;&#8201;3.75</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.12&#8201;&#177;&#8201;4.15</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.51&#8201;&#177;&#8201;3.12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.0002 (Unpaired <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test with Welch correction)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;2.457 to &#8722;0.7631</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">242</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>Variables are presented as mean &#177; standard deviation (SD).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>The <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value &lt; .05 is considered significant.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>Diabetic nephropathy: the urine albumin to creatinine ratio &#8805; 30 (microalbuminuria).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>Patients without nephropathy: the urine albumin to creatinine ratio &lt; 30.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>CI = confidence interval (using the approximation of Katz.), Df = degree of freedom.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Health-related behaviors were the same among patients with diabetes either with nephropathy or patients without nephropathy (Table <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">3</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; .05 for both, Fisher&#8217;s exact test).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Health-related behaviors of patients with diabetes.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameters</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetic nephropathy</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients without nephropathy</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Comparison between groups</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of patients with diabetes</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">305</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">135</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">170</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drinker</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">165 (54)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75 (56)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90 (52)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.7287</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8226&#8211;1.367</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoker</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">169 (55)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78 (58)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91 (54)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.4878</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8522&#8211;1.423</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>Variables are presented as frequency (percentage).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>Fisher&#8217;s exact test was used for statistical analysis.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>The <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value &lt; .05 is considered significant.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>Diabetic nephropathy: the urine albumin to creatinine ratio &#8805; 30 (microalbuminuria).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>Patients without nephropathy: the urine albumin to creatinine ratio &lt; 30.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>CI = confidence interval (using the approximation of Katz.), N/A = not applicable.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>All clinicopathological parameters were more abnormal for diabetic nephropathic patients than those of patients without nephropathy (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .0001, for all, Mann&#8211;Whitney test or Fisher exact test, Table <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">4</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Clinicopathological parameters of patients with diabetes.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Parameters</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetic nephropathy</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients without nephropathy</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comparison between groups</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Number of patients with diabetes</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">305</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">135</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">170</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Hypertension</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">205 (67)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120 (89)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85 (50)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.0001<xref rid="tab4fn5" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref> (Fisher&#8217;s exact test)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">% HbA1C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minimum</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">&lt;.0001 (Mann&#8211;Whitney test)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Fasting blood glucose (mM/L)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minimum</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">&lt;.0001 (Mann&#8211;Whitney test)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Urine albumin (g/L)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minimum</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">&lt;.0001 (Mann&#8211;Whitney test)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Urine creatinine (g/L)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minimum</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1400</td><td align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">&lt;.0001 (Mann&#8211;Whitney test)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1500</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1500</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1420</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1045</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1470</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Urine albumin to creatinine ratio (&#956;g/mg)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minimum</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.67</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.53</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.67</td><td align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">&lt;.0001 (Mann&#8211;Whitney test)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.63</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.05</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.76</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Alanine transaminase (U/L)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minimum</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">.009 (Mann&#8211;Whitney test)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">High-density lipoprotein (mM/L)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minimum</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">&lt;.0001 (Mann&#8211;Whitney test)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Aspartate transaminase (U/L)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minimum</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">.0086 (Mann&#8211;Whitney test)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Urinary globulin (immunoglobulin; g/L)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minimum</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">&lt;.0001 (Mann&#8211;Whitney test)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Alkaline phosphatase (U/L)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minimum</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">&lt;.0001 (Mann&#8211;Whitney test)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Blood urea nitrogen (mM/L)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minimum</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">&lt;.0001 (Mann&#8211;Whitney test)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>Categoric variables are presented as frequency (percentage). Continuous abnormal variables are presented as median (range).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>The <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value &lt; .05 is considered significant.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>Diabetic nephropathy: the urine albumin to creatinine ratio &#8805; 30 (microalbuminuria).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>Patients without nephropathy: the urine albumin to creatinine ratio &lt; 30.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="tab4fn5"><label>*</label><p>95% CI: confidence interval (using the approximation of Katz.): 2.413 to 6.311, HbA1C: Glycated hemoglobin.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>A total of 285 (93%) were taking one or two oral hypoglycemic agents. A total of 130 (96%) from the diabetic nephropathy, case group and 155 (91%) patients without the nephropathy, control group were taking one or two oral hypoglycemic agents (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .1018, Fisher&#8217;s exact test).</p></sec><sec><title>3.3. Association between outcome measures and diabetic nephropathy</title><p>Abnormal urinary globulin (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .041, multivariate analysis) was reported as a significant biomarker for diabetic nephropathy. Aspartate transaminase (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .0651, multivariate analysis), alkaline phosphatase (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .0661, multivariate analysis), hypertension (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .0821, multivariate analysis), and blood urea nitrogen (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .0842, multivariate analysis) were not significantly associated with diabetic neuropathy. However, they are near the statistical cutoff value. Association between outcome measures and diabetic nephropathy is reported in Table <xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">5</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T5" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Association between outcome measures and diabetic nephropathy.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameters</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Odd ratio</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95 % CI</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body weight (&#8805;60&#8201;kg vs &lt;60&#8201;kg)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9854</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8524&#8211;1.0112</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.0681</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Waist circumference (&#8805;95&#8201;cm vs &lt; 95&#8201;cm)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8245</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7421&#8211;0.9852</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.0692</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body mass index (Obese vs non-obese)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9254</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8254&#8211;0.9852</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.0741</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension (hypertensive vs non-hypertensive)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8214</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7142&#8211;0.8123</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.0821</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% HbA1C (&#8805;6.5 vs &lt;6.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6524</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8214&#8211;0.0941</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.0714</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fasting blood glucose (&#8805;7&#8201;mM/L vs &lt; 7&#8201;mM/L)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7422</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9214&#8211;0.9824</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.0821</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alanine transaminase (abnormal vs normal)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8122</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0821&#8211;0.0824</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.0824</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High-density lipoprotein (abnormal vs normal)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1421</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0841&#8211;0.9849</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.0952</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aspartate transaminase (abnormal vs normal)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8541</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7741&#8211;0.8841</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.0651</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urinary globulin (abnormal<xref rid="tab5fn5" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref> vs normal)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1231</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2451&#8211;1.8521</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.041</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alkaline phosphatase (abnormal vs normal)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8411</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7841&#8211;0.9841</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.0661</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blood urea nitrogen (abnormal vs normal)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9411</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8414&#8211;0.9841</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.0842</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>Multivariate analysis,</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>An odd ratio of more than 1 and a <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value less than .05 was considered significant.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>Patients without nephropathy were considered the control group.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>CI = confidence interval, HbA1C = Glycated hemoglobin.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="tab5fn5"><label>*</label><p>Significant biomarker for diabetic neuropathy.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>4. Discussion</title><p>The current study reported that higher urinary globulin is associated with diabetic nephropathy. The results of the current study are parallel with those of cross-sectional studies.<sup>[<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]</sup> A cross-sectional study<sup>[<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</sup> was performed on the Chinese population on the NHANES official website, but inclusion criteria were limited. A cross-sectional study performed on the Egyptian population<sup>[<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]</sup> had a small sample size. A cross-sectional study performed on the Chinese population<sup>[<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]</sup> was more skewed toward all diabetic complications. Renal injuries increase the urinary concentration of globulin.<sup>[<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]</sup> Also, available studies<sup>[<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]</sup> are cross-sectional studies that provide differences, not true changes.<sup>[<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]</sup> Urinary globulin is a biomarker for the prognosis of diabetic nephropathy.</p><p>Aspartate transaminase and alkaline phosphatase were not significantly associated with diabetic neuropathy. However, they are near the statistical cutoff value. Not only kidney functions but urine globulin is also associated with liver functions.<sup>[<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]</sup> Besides urinary globulin, the duration of diabetes and the presence of other diabetic complications are also essential parameters for diabetic nephropathy.</p><p>Hypertension and blood urea nitrogen were not significantly associated with diabetic neuropathy. However, they are near the statistical cutoff value. Diabetic nephropathy complication is very common in hypertensive patients.<sup>[<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]</sup> Since some antihypertensive agents such as angiotensin receptor blockers could affect urinary albumin excretion, these medications were considered an important clinical parameter for microalbuminuria.</p><p>Higher numbers of male patients reported diabetic neuropathy than female patients. The results of gender bias in the prevalence of diabetic neuropathy are consistent with those of cross-sectional studies<sup>[<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]</sup> and a meta-analysis<sup>[<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</sup> but are not consistent with those of a cross-sectional study.<sup>[<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]</sup> More awareness and early diagnosis of diabetic neuropathy among Chinese males than among Chinese females are responsible for the higher prevalence of diabetic neuropathy in males.<sup>[<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]</sup> Also, smoking which is a risk factor for diabetic nephropathy in Chinese diabetic males,<sup>[<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]</sup> is reported more common in males than females. Further sex-oriented research is required.</p><p>The prevalence of diabetic nephropathy in the Hebei province of China was reported higher than a meta-analysis on patients with type 2 diabetes in the other provinces of China (44% vs 22%).<sup>[<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</sup> Also, 20 to 30 percent rate of diabetic kidney disease has been reported in the Turkish patients with type 2 diabetes.<sup>[<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]</sup> The prevalence of diabetic nephropathy shows geographical and gender variation in China.<sup>[<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</sup> National strategies for screening and treatment of diabetic nephropathy are required in China.</p><p>The limitations of the study include the single center nature of the work, the study applies to the Han Chinese population, and data are not generalized. Furthermore, patients were diabetic only, the association between urinary globulin and non-diabetic kidney damage is not developed. Besides urinary globulin, the association between serum globulin levels and diabetic nephropathy is not developed. The association of the other pathological parameters was found insignificant, but the justification for the same was not provided. Patients with a urine albumin to creatinine ratio &#8805; 30 were enrolled in the study. However, patients with diabetes may have renal damage without microalbuminuria.<sup>[<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]</sup> Since patients with diabetic nephropathy had a very low level of urinary albumin excretion, the presence of nephropathy must be determined by multiple measurements of urinary albumin. In addition, it is questionable that patients with normo-albuminuria and overt renal dysfunction were classified into patients without the nephropathy group. To suggest the diagnostic value of urinary globulin for diabetic nephropathy, sensitivity and specificity analyses are essential. The diagnostic benefits of urinary globulin with those of known biomarkers such as urinary <italic toggle="yes">&#946;</italic><sub>2</sub>-microglobulin are required to compare. In addition, it has been revealed that urinary levels of <italic toggle="yes">&#946;</italic><sub>2</sub>-microglobulin are increased in diabetic nephropathy.<sup>[<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]</sup></p></sec><sec><title>5. Conclusion</title><p>The prevalence of diabetic nephropathy in the Hebei province of China is reported higher than in the other provinces of China. Urinary globulin excretion is associated (a weak association) with the presence of nephropathy defined by urinary albumin excretion in patients with diabetes. Urinary globulin is a biomarker for the prognosis of diabetic nephropathy. Urinary globulin may provide information for a biopsy of the kidney in cases of patients with diabetes. The duration of diabetes and the presence of other diabetic complications are also essential parameters for diabetic nephropathy. Han Chinese males in the Hebei province of China are more susceptible to diabetic nephropathy than females if diabetic. Antihypertensive agents could affect urinary albumin excretion.</p></sec><sec><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors are thankful to the medical and non-medical staff of the Hebei Hospital of Traditional Chinese Medicine, Shijiazhuang, Hebei, China.</p></sec><sec><title>Author contributions</title><p><bold>Conceptualization:</bold> Xiaoya Ren, Xianghui Yu.</p><p><bold>Formal analysis:</bold> Yange Tang.</p><p><bold>Funding acquisition:</bold> Ninglin Kang, Yange Tang.</p><p><bold>Investigation:</bold> Xiaolei Li.</p><p><bold>Methodology:</bold> Xianghui Yu, Xiaolei Li, Yange Tang, Jie Wu.</p><p><bold>Resources:</bold> Xiaoya Ren, Xianghui Yu, Yange Tang.</p><p><bold>Software:</bold> Xiaoya Ren, Xianghui Yu, Jie Wu.</p><p><bold>Supervision:</bold> Xiaoya Ren, Ninglin Kang, Jie Wu.</p><p><bold>Validation:</bold> Xiaolei Li, Jie Wu.</p><p><bold>Visualization:</bold> Ninglin Kang, Xiaolei Li.</p><p><bold>Writing &#8211; original draft:</bold> Xiaoya Ren.</p><p><bold>Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing:</bold> Xiaoya Ren.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="abbr"><p>
<def-list><title>Abbreviations:</title><def-item><term>BMI</term><def><p>body mass index</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Case group</term><def><p>diabetic nephropathy: urine albumin to creatinine ratio &#8805; 30</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Control group</term><def><p>patients without nephropathy: urine albumin to creatinine ratio &lt; 30</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ELISA test</term><def><p>Enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay test</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SD</term><def><p>standard deviation</p></def></def-item></def-list>
</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p>This study was supported by the Hebei Provincial Administration of Traditional Chinese Medicine (No. 2022046).</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>The datasets generated during and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>How to cite this article: Ren X, Kang N, Yu X, Li X, Tang Y, Wu J. Prevalence and association of diabetic nephropathy in newly diagnosed Chinese patients with diabetes in the Hebei province: A single-center case-control study. Medicine 2023;102:11(e32911).</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>[1]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>American Diabetes Association</collab>. <article-title>(2) Classification and diagnosis of diabetes.</article-title><source>Diabetes Care</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>Suppl</issue>):<fpage>S8</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>16</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2337/dc15-S005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25537714</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>[2]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wojciechowska</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krajewski</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bolanowski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Diabetes and cancer: a review of current knowledge.</article-title><source>Exp Clin Endocrinol Diabetes</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>124</volume>:<fpage>263</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>75</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27219686</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1055/s-0042-100910</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>[3]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lovic</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piperidou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zografou</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The growing epidemic of diabetes mellitus.</article-title><source>Curr Vasc Pharmacol</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>104</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30961501</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2174/1570161117666190405165911</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>[4]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clotman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Twickler</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Diabetes or endocrinopathy admitted in the COVID-19 ward.</article-title><source>Eur J Clin Invest</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>50</volume>:<fpage>e13262</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32383239</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/eci.13262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7262001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>[5]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khavjou</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saydah</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Estimating state-level health burden of diabetes: diabetes-attributable fractions for diabetes complications.</article-title><source>Am J Prev Med</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>232</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>40</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30554974</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.amepre.2018.09.023</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>[6]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Livingstone</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Looker</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Estimated life expectancy in a Scottish cohort with type 1 diabetes, 2008-2010.</article-title><source>JAMA</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>37</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>44</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.2014.16425</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4426486</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25562264</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>[7]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahajan</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Costacou</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A contemporary estimate of total mortality and cardiovascular disease risk in young adults with type 1 diabetes: The pittsburgh epidemiology of diabetes complications study.</article-title><source>Diabetes Care</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>2296</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>303</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27654986</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2337/dc16-1162</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5127232</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>[8]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leon-Abarca JA</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rehan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iftikhar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The impact of COVID-19 in diabetic kidney disease and chronic kidney disease: a population-based study.</article-title><source>Acta Biomed</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>91</volume>:<fpage>e2020161</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33525210</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.23750/abm.v91i4.10380</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7927495</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>[9]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kocak</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aktas</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erkus</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Mean platelet volume to lymphocyte ratioas a novel marker for diabetic nephropathy.</article-title><source>J Coll Physicians Surg Pak</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>844</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30369376</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.29271/jcpsp.2018.11.844</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>[10]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kocak</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aktas</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Atak</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Is Neuregulin-4 a predictive marker of microvascular complications in type 2 diabetes mellitus?</article-title><source>Eur J Clin Invest</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>50</volume>:<fpage>e13206</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31999832</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/eci.13206</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>[11]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bilgin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurtkulagi</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Atak Tel</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Does C-reactive protein to serum Albumin Ratio correlate with diabEtic nephropathy in patients with Type 2 dIabetes MEllitus? The CARE TIME study.</article-title><source>Prim Care Diabetes</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>1071</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34497035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.pcd.2021.08.015</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>[12]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kocak</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aktas</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duman</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Monocyte lymphocyte ratio as a predictor of diabetic kidney injury in type 2 diabetes mellitus; the MADKID study.</article-title><source>J Diabetes Metab Disord</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>997</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1002</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33553019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s40200-020-00595-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7843868</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>[13]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kocak</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aktas</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duman</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Is Uric Acid elevation a random finding or a causative agent of diabetic nephropathy?</article-title><source>Rev Assoc Med Bras</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>65</volume>:<fpage>11551156</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1160</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1590/1806-9282.65.9.1156</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31618330</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>[14]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence of diabetic nephropathy among patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus in China: a meta-analysis of observational studies.</article-title><source>J Diabetes Res</source>. <year>2020</year>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>11</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1155/2020/2315607</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7023800</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32090116</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>[15]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association between globulin and diabetic nephropathy in type2 diabetes mellitus patients: a cross-sectional study.</article-title><source>Front Endocrinol</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>890273</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fendo.2022.890273</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9311329</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35898464</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>[16]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Inamine</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schnabl</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Immunoglobulin A and liver diseases.</article-title><source>J Gastroenterol</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>691</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>700</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29075899</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00535-017-1400-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5971039</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>[17]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdou</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anani</surname><given-names>HAA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Urinary IgG, serum CX3CL1 and miRNA-152-3p: as predictors of nephropathy in Egyptian type 2 diabetic patients.</article-title><source>Tissue Barriers</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1994823</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34689723</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/21688370.2021.1994823</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9359404</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>[18]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cederholm</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bosaeus</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barazzoni</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Diagnostic criteria for malnutrition - An ESPEN consensus statement.</article-title><source>Clin Nutr</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>335</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>40</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25799486</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.clnu.2015.03.001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>[19]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ricci</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schutte</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schutte</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Trends in alcohol consumption in relation to cause-specific and all-cause mortality in the United States: a report from the NHANES linked to the US mortality registry.</article-title><source>Am J Clin Nutr</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>111</volume>:<fpage>580</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31978218</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/ajcn/nqaa008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>[20]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence and patterns of tobacco smoking among Chinese adult men and women: findings of the 2010 national smoking survey.</article-title><source>J Epidemiol Community Health</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>71</volume>:<fpage>154</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>61</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27660401</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/jech-2016-207805</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5284482</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>[21]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujishima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kodama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsuchihashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Achievement rate of blood pressure &lt;140/90 mmHg and &lt;130/80 mmHg in subjects with hypertension; findings from a Japanese health checkup in 2017.</article-title><source>Clin Exp Hypertens</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>648</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>55</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32419520</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/10641963.2020.1764017</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>[22]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aziz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jalilpiran</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nekouimehr</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Dietary protein sources and risk of diabetic nephropathy in women: a case-control study.</article-title><source>BMC Endocr Disord</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>174</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34452618</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12902-021-00841-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8393448</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>[23]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Associations between the neutrophil-to-lymphocyte ratio and diabetic complications in adults with diabetes: a cross-sectional study.</article-title><source>J Diabetes Res</source>. <year>2020</year>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1155/2020/6219545</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7206875</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32405503</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>[24]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khater</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohamed</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arisha</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Stabilized-chitosan selenium nanoparticles efficiently reduce renal tissue injury and regulate the expression pattern of aldose reductase in the diabetic-nephropathy rat model.</article-title><source>Life Sci</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>279</volume>:<fpage>119674</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34081992</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.lfs.2021.119674</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>[25]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wagnew</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eshetie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kibret</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Diabetic nephropathy and hypertension in diabetes patients of sub-Saharan countries: a systematic review and meta-analysis.</article-title><source>BMC Res Notes</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>565</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30081966</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13104-018-3670-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6080368</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>[26]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lyles</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bent-Shaw</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>.; <collab>Pathways Authors</collab>. <article-title>Pathways Authors. Risk factor, age and sex differences in chronic kidney disease prevalence in a diabetic cohort: The pathways study.</article-title><source>Am J Nephrol</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>245</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>51</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22964976</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1159/000342210</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3510352</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>[27]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roche</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Factors associated with a diabetes diagnosis and late diabetes diagnosis for males and females.</article-title><source>J Clin Transl Endocrinol</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>77</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>84</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29159087</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jcte.2014.07.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5685052</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>[28]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Smoking as a risk factor for diabetic nephropathy: a meta-analysis.</article-title><source>Int Urol Nephrol</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>49</volume>:<fpage>1801</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28631246</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11255-017-1638-3</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>[29]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Papadopoulou-Marketou</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paschou</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marketos</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Diabetic nephropathy in type 1 diabetes.</article-title><source>Minerva Med</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>109</volume>:<fpage>218</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>28</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29205998</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.23736/S0026-4806.17.05496-9</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>[30]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kocak</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aktas</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duman</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Type 2 diabetes mellitus is more commonly well controlled in younger men compared to older men.</article-title><source>Aging Male</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>906</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>10</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31156011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/13685538.2019.1621833</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>[31]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dihazi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>M&#252;ller</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Characterization of diabetic nephropathy by urinary proteomic analysis: identification of a processed ubiquitin form as a differentially excreted protein in diabetic nephropathy patients.</article-title><source>Clin Chem</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>1636</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>45</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17634209</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1373/clinchem.2007.088260</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>