<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">AJPM Focus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">AJPM Focus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">4511</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">ajpmfocus</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>AJPM Focus</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2773-0654</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11214170</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11214170.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11214170</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11214170</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38947491</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.focus.2024.100233</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2773-0654(24)00051-8</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100233</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Screening for Unhealthy Alcohol Use Among Patients With Multiple Chronic Conditions in Primary Care</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0001"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rockwell</surname><given-names initials="MS">Michelle S.</given-names></name><degrees>PhD, RD</degrees><email>msrock@vt.edu</email><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="cor0001" ref-type="corresp">&#8270;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0002"><name name-style="western"><surname>Funk</surname><given-names initials="AJ">Adam J.</given-names></name><degrees>BS</degrees><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0003"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huffstetler</surname><given-names initials="AN">Alison N.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">4</xref><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0004"><name name-style="western"><surname>Villalobos</surname><given-names initials="G">Gabriela</given-names></name><degrees>MSW</degrees><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0005"><name name-style="western"><surname>Britz</surname><given-names initials="JB">Jacqueline B.</given-names></name><degrees>MD, MSPH</degrees><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0006"><name name-style="western"><surname>Webel</surname><given-names initials="B">Benjamin</given-names></name><degrees>BA</degrees><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0007"><name name-style="western"><surname>Richards</surname><given-names initials="A">Alicia</given-names></name><degrees>MS</degrees><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0008"><name name-style="western"><surname>Epling</surname><given-names initials="JW">John W.</given-names></name><degrees>MD, MSEd</degrees><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0009"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sabo</surname><given-names initials="RT">Roy T.</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0010"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krist</surname><given-names initials="AH">Alex H.</given-names></name><degrees>MD, MPH</degrees><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label>Department of Family &amp; Community Medicine, Carilion Clinic and Virginia Tech Carilion School of Medicine, Roanoke, Virginia</aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label>Department of Biostatistics, School of Public Health, Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, Virginia</aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label>Department of Family Medicine &amp; Population Health, Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, Virginia</aff><aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label>INOVA Family Practice Residency, Fairfax, Virginia</aff><aff id="aff0005"><label>5</label>The Robert Graham Center, Washington, District of Columbia</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor0001"><label>&#8270;</label>Address correspondence to: Michelle S. Rockwell, PhD, RD, Department of Family &amp; Community Medicine, Virginia Tech Carilion School of Medicine, 1 Riverside Circle, Suite 102, Roanoke VA 24016. <email>msrock@vt.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>8</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>07</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><issue>4</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">462455</issue-id><elocation-id>100233</elocation-id><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>07</day><month>05</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>29</day><month>06</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-07-01 12:25:12.487"><day>01</day><month>07</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2024 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><abstract id="abs0001"><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Unhealthy alcohol use increases the risk for and exacerbation of chronic health conditions. As such, screening, prevention, and management of unhealthy alcohol use is especially critical to improving health outcomes for patients with multiple chronic health conditions. It is unclear to what extent multiple chronic condition status is a barrier to screening for unhealthy alcohol use in the primary care setting. The authors hypothesized that patients with multiple chronic conditions would be at lower odds of being screened for unhealthy alcohol use than patients without multiple chronic conditions.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>The authors performed a secondary analysis of electronic health record data for patients from 67 primary care practices in Virginia (2020&#8211;2023). Using the Center for Medicare and Medicaid Services&#8217; chronic disease framework, they classified patients by multiple chronic condition status: no multiple chronic conditions, physical multiple chronic conditions, mental health multiple chronic conditions, and physical and mental health multiple chronic conditions. They used multiple logistic regressions with an added practice-level random effect to analyze the relationship between multiple chronic condition status and the odds of receiving an alcohol-related assessment, of being screened for unhealthy alcohol use with a U.S. Preventive Services Task Force&#8211;recommended instrument, and of screening positive for unhealthy alcohol use within the past 2 years.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Within a final cohort of <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=11,789, a total of 6,796 patients (58%) had multiple chronic conditions (29% physical multiple chronic conditions, 4% mental health multiple chronic conditions, and 25% physical and mental health multiple chronic conditions). In all, 69% of patients were screened for unhealthy alcohol use, whereas 16% were screened with a U.S. Preventive Services Task Force&#8211;recommended instrument, and 7% screened positive for unhealthy alcohol use. Patients with physical and mental health multiple chronic conditions had 0.9 times lower odds of receiving any screening for unhealthy alcohol use than those with no multiple chronic conditions (95% CI=0.8, 1.0; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>=0.0240), whereas patients with only physical multiple chronic conditions or only mental health multiple chronic conditions had similar odds. There was no difference in the odds of being screened with a U.S. Preventive Services Task Force&#8211;recommended instrument on the basis of multiple chronic condition status. Patients with mental health multiple chronic conditions and physical and mental health multiple chronic conditions had 1.8 and 1.5 times greater odds of screening positive for unhealthy alcohol use, respectively (95% CI=1.3, 2.7; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>=0.0014 and 95% CI=1.2, 1.8; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>=0.0003).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Although patients with chronic mental health conditions were more likely to screen positive for unhealthy alcohol use than patients without multiple chronic conditions, Virginia primary care patients with physical and mental health multiple chronic conditions were less likely to receive an alcohol-related assessment during the past 2 years. Given the overall modest rate of screening with a U.S. Preventive Services Task Force&#8211;recommended instrument, further efforts are needed to create the conditions for high-quality alcohol-related preventive service delivery in primary care, particularly for patients with high complexity and/or mental health conditions.</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="author-highlights" id="abs0002"><title>HIGHLIGHTS</title><p><list list-type="simple" id="celist0001"><list-item id="celistitem0001"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="para0005">Among Virginia primary care patients, 69% were assessed for unhealthy alcohol use, but only 16% were screened with a USPSTF&#8211;recommended instrument.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0002"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="para0006">Patients with physical and mental health multiple chronic conditions had lower odds of receiving an assessment for unhealthy alcohol use than patients with no multiple chronic conditions.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0003"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="para0007">Further efforts are needed to improve the delivery of alcohol preventive services in primary care.</p></list-item></list></p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="graphical" id="abs0003"><title>Graphical abstrct</title><p><fig id="fig0001" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><alt-text id="alttx001">Image, graphical abstract</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="celink0001" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ga1.jpg"/></fig></p></abstract><kwd-group id="keys0001"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Clinical preventive services</kwd><kwd>USPSTF</kwd><kwd>multimorbidity</kwd><kwd>risky drinking</kwd><kwd>alcohol use disorder</kwd><kwd>mental health</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec0001"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p id="para0008">More than 100 million Americans (40% of the U.S. population) suffer from multiple chronic conditions (MCCs), the co-occurrence of 2 or more long-term health conditions lasting longer than 1 year.<xref rid="bib0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="bib0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="bib0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> MCCs are associated with functional decline, morbidity, mortality, and increased healthcare utilization and costs.<xref rid="bib0004" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> For every U.S. dollar spent on health care, &gt;75 cents goes to caring for patients with MCCs.<xref rid="bib0003" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> With the national and global prevalence of MCCs on the rise, there have been numerous calls for improved systems of care for this complex patient population.<xref rid="bib0001" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></p><p id="para0009">High-quality primary care is one approach to enhancing health outcomes for patients with MCCs. The delivery of on-time clinical preventive services is an important function of primary care. For example, the U.S. Preventive Services Task Force (USPSTF) recommends that persons aged &gt;18 years be screened for unhealthy alcohol use (UAU) in primary care, with brief intervention, medication therapy, and referral for additional treatment provided when warranted.<xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> The prevention, detection, and management of UAU carry particular value for patients with MCCs because UAU can exacerbate most chronic conditions and increase the risk of developing additional chronic conditions.<xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="bib0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> Furthermore, some health conditions are associated with increased risk for UAU.<xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="bib0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="bib0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="bib0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></p><p id="para0010">Numerous barriers to the delivery of alcohol preventive services have been identified,<xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> but the degree to which MCC status influences the likelihood of being screened for UAU is not well understood. Given the competing demands associated with caring for high-complexity patients and the time and resource limitations faced by primary care teams, it is reasonable to hypothesize that patients with MCCs are less likely to be screened for UAU during primary care visits than patients without MCCs. However, Ornstein et al.<xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref> and Chatterton and colleagues<xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref> reported higher rates of screening for UAU in patients with MCCs than in those without MCCs in 2010&#8211;2011 and 2014&#8211;2016, respectively, even when controlling for visit frequency. Because MCC rates continue to rise, and many factors contribute to increased demands on primary care, it is important to evaluate whether or not rates have changed in recent years. In addition, the previous studies assess the influence of any type of MCC on the likelihood of receiving screening for UAU.<xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="bib0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> There is some evidence that preventive service delivery rates vary by MCC type (e.g., physical conditions, mental health conditions, both physical and mental health conditions),<xref rid="bib0027" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref> but it is unclear to what extent MCC type influences the odds of screening for UAU in primary care.</p><p id="para0011">The identification of alcohol screening patterns among different MCC patient groups would provide insight into patient complexity as a barrier to preventive service delivery and inform interventions to improve care for a high-priority patient population. Thus, the purpose of this study was to evaluate variation in screening for UAU on the basis of MCC status and MCC type in the Virginia primary care setting. The authors hypothesized lower rates of screening for UAU in patients with MCCs than in those with no MCCs and that patients with both physical and mental health chronic conditions would be screened at the lowest rates.</p></sec><sec id="sec0002"><title>METHODS</title><p id="para0012">The authors performed a cross-sectional secondary analysis of electronic health record (EHR) data collected from 67 primary care practices participating in a statewide intervention to improve screening and management of UAU between 2020 and 2023 (R18HS027077). Family medicine, general internal medicine, and women's health clinics representing health systems, community health centers, and private clinics throughout the Commonwealth of Virginia were included in the cohort. Details about the protocol and study recruitment have been previously published.<xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib0029" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref> Briefly, as part of a pragmatic immediate versus delayed RCT, practices were randomized to receive 6 months of practice facilitation (e.g., academic detailing/education, workflow coaching, performance feedback delivered by a trained facilitator) immediately or after a 6-month delay. Facilitators guided practices to improve their processes and clinic workflow to support the screening of all adult patients for UAU with a validated USPSTF-recommended instrument such as the Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test-Concise<xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref> or Single-Item Alcohol Screening Questionnaire,<xref rid="bib0031" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref> without regard for MCCs.</p><p id="para0013">Data analyzed for this report were collected at baseline and 3 and 6 months after the onset of practice facilitation or during the 6 months prior to practice facilitation for delayed facilitation (usual care) practices. The IRB of Carilion Clinic approved this study (IRB Number 23-1909). The informed consent requirement was waived on the basis of the collection of deidentified data unable to be linked to patient identifiers.</p><sec id="sec0003"><title>Study Sample</title><p id="para0014">From the EHR for up to 180 randomly selected patients (aged 18&#8211;79 years) seen in each practice within the previous 90 days, the study team extracted demographics (age, sex, race, ethnicity, and insurer) and problem list and visit diagnosis codes (ICD-10) through automated report or manual chart review, depending on what was available within each practice. The only patients who met age and visit criteria who were excluded from the sample were those whose visit to primary care was for a nonoffice visit (e.g., laboratory test, procedure, vaccine). The extraction process was internally validated by the study team.</p></sec><sec id="sec0003a"><title>Measures</title><p id="para0014a">The authors also extracted the following alcohol screening outcomes for the previous 2 years through manual chart review: (1) evidence of any alcohol-related screening or assessment in the social history, structured data, clinician note, or problem list/visit diagnosis areas of the patient's chart; (2) whether a USPSTF-recommended instrument (e.g., Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test-Concise or Single-Item Alcohol Screening Questionnaire) was used for the assessment (primary outcome); and (3) any positive identification of UAU based on National Institute for Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism (Appendix A, available online, provides additional details about alcohol screening outcomes). A 10% sample of each practice's extraction was assessed for quality assurance. If errors were detected, the full chart review was repeated and checked by 2 team members.</p><p id="para0015">Using the Center for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services Chronic Conditions algorithm,<xref rid="bib0032" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref> the study team classified patients by MCC status as informed by the methods of Ukhanova et al.<xref rid="bib0027" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref>: 0 or 1 chronic condition (MCC<sub>0</sub>), &#8805;2 physical chronic conditions and 0 mental health chronic conditions (physical MCCs [MCC<sub>P</sub>]), &#8805;2 mental health chronic conditions and 0 physical chronic conditions (mental health MCCs [MCC<sub>MH</sub>]), and &#8805;1 physical chronic condition and &#8805;1 mental health chronic condition (physical and mental health MCCs [MCC<sub>P+MH</sub>]). Widely applied in the health services research literature,<xref rid="bib0027" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="bib0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="bib0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> the Center for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services algorithm uses ICD-10 codes to associate patients with 29 physical and 8 mental chronic health conditions (Appendix B, available online, provides the list of conditions).</p></sec><sec id="sec0004"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p id="para0016">The study team performed descriptive analyses of demographics, chronic conditions, and alcohol screening outcomes, both overall and stratified by MCC status. Differences in demographics across MCC status were assessed through chi-square tests (categorical variables) and ANOVA (continuous variables). Using multiple logistic regression, the authors evaluated the relationship between MCC status and alcohol screening outcomes, adjusting for demographics, treatment (immediate versus delayed intervention), and study timepoint. A mixed model was fit, adding a random practice intercept to the multiple logistic regression. ORs, 95% CIs, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-values, and calculated intraclass correlation coefficients<xref rid="bib0032" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33</sup></xref> are reported. All statistical analyses were performed at Virginia Commonwealth University using SAS, Version 9.4 (SAS Institute, Cary, NC), in September 2023.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec0005"><title>RESULTS</title><p id="para0017">Within a final cohort of 11,789 patients (aged 49.7 years, 61% female, 64% White, 50% rural, 24% Medicaid/Medicare&#8211;Medicaid dual eligible/uninsured), more than half of patients were classified as having MCCs (3,476 [29%] MCC<sub>P</sub>; 419 [4%] MCC<sub>MH</sub>; and 2,901 [25%] MCC<sub>P+MH</sub>) (<xref rid="tbl0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) (Appendix B, available online, provides the list of 29 physical chronic conditions and 8 mental chronic conditions). There were differences in the makeup of each MCC group across age (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.001), sex (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.001), race (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.001), ethnicity (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.001), insurer (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.001), rurality (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.001), and treatment (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.001) but not timepoint (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>=0.448) (<xref rid="tbl0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Overall, 69% of patients received an alcohol-related screening or assessment during the past 2 years, but only 16% were screened with a USPSTF-recommended instrument (<xref rid="tbl0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref><xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref>). A total of 770 patients (7%) screened positive for UAU (<xref rid="tbl0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref><xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0001" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic and Clinical Characteristics of Primary Care Patients With MCCs</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0001">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Characteristic</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Overall (N=11,789)</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Physical MCCs (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=3,476)</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mental MCCs (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=419)</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Physical and mental MCCs (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=2,901)</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No MCCs (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=4,993)</th><th align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M1" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> test <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Mean (SD)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49.7 (16.6)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.2 (11.4)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.3 (11.9)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53.7 (14.1)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40.8 (15.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex, n (%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Female</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7,206 (61.1%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1765 (50.8%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">314 (74.9%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,000 (68.9%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,127 (62.6%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Male</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,578 (38.8%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1709 (49.2%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">105 (25.1%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">900 (31.1%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,863 (37.3%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Nonbinary</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (0.0%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.0%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.0%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (0.1%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Race, n (%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;White</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7,550 (64.0%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2072 (59.6%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">324 (77.3%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,147 (74.0%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,007 (60.2%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Black</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,167 (18.4%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">828 (23.8%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50 (11.9%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">506 (17.4%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">783 (15.7%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Asian</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">596 (5.1%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">159 (4.6%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (1.9%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52 (1.8%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">377 (7.6%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;American Indian</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22 (0.2%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (0.1%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (0.1%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13 (0.3%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Native Hawaiian or Pacific Islander</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19 (0.2%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (0.1%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.2%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.0%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 (0.2%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Multiple races</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">77 (0.7%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (0.3%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (0.7%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 (0.5%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48 (1.0%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Other</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">250 (2.1%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">79 (2.3%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (1.4%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37 (1.3%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">128 (2.6%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Not reported</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,108 (9.4%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">317 (9.1%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 (6.4%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">139 (4.8%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">625 (12.5%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ethnicity, n (%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Hispanic or Latino</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">921 (7.8%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">312 (9.0%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 (3.8%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">136 (4.7%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">457 (9.0%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Non-Hispanic or Latino</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9,369 (79.5%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2772 (79.7%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">355 (84.7%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,514 (86.7%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,728 (74.7%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Not reported</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,499 (12.7%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">392 (11.3%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48 (11.5%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">251 (8.7%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">808 (16.2%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Insurer, n (%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Commercial or private</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6,585 (55.9%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1369 (39.4%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">277 (66.1%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,296 (44.7%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,643 (73.0%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Medicaid</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,576 (13.4%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">377 (10.8%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">108 (25.8%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">505 (17.4%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">586 (11.7%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Medicare</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,731 (23.2%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1421 (40.9%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19 (4.5%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">945 (32.6%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">346 (6.9%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Dual Medicare and Medicaid</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48 (0.4%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19 (0.5%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.2%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19 (0.7%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 (0.2%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Self-pay/uninsured</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">720 (6.1%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">270 (7.8%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (2.6%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103 (3.6%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">336 (6.7%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Tricare</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">129 (1.1%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 (0.6%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (0.7%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33 (1.1%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73 (1.5%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rurality, n (%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Rural</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5,890 (50.0%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1845 (53.1%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">223 (53.2%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,732 (59.7%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,090 (41.9%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Suburban or town</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,120 (34.9%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1063 (30.6%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">135 (32.2%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">715 (24.6%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,207 (44.2%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;City</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,779 (15.1%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">568 (16.3%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61 (14.6%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">454 (15.6%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">696 (13.9%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Intervention, n (%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Immediate</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5,610 (47.6%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1524 (43.8%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">196 (46.8%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,225 (42.2%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,665 (53.4%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Delayed</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6,179 (52.4%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1952 (56.2%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">223 (53.2%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,676 (57.8%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,328 (46.6%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Timepoint, n (%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Baseline</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,000 (33.9%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1152 (33.1%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">137 (32.7%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,032 (35.6%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,679 (33.6%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;3 months</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,905 (33.1%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1151 (33.1%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">144 (34.4%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">932 (32.1%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,678 (33.6%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;6 months</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,884 (32.9%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1173 (33.7%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">138 (32.9%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">937 (32.3%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,636 (32.8%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MCC<sub>P</sub></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Mean (SD)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.70 (1.68)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.22 (1.29)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.48 (1.46)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.337 (0.473)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MCC<sub>MH</sub></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Mean (SD)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.504 (0.813)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.35 (0.585)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.46 (0.707)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.147 (0.354)</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>MCC, multiple chronic condition; MCC<sub>MH</sub>, mental health multiple chronic condition; MCC<sub>P</sub>, physical multiple chronic condition.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0002" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Alcohol Screening Outcomes for Primary Care Patients With MCCs</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0002">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Outcome</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Overall (N=11,789), n (%)</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Physical MCCs (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=3,476), n (%)</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mental MCCs (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=419), n (%)</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Physical and mental MCCs (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=2,901), n (%)</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No MCCs (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=4,993), n (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Any alcohol assessment in the past 2 years</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Received</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8,092 (68.6%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,309 (66.4%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">297 (70.9%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,969 (67.9%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,517 (70.4%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Did not receive</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,697 (31.4%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,167 (33.6%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">122 (29.1%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">932 (32.1%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,476 (29.6%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Alcohol screening with USPSTF-recommended instrument in the past 2 years</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Received</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,907 (16.2%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">567 (16.3%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64 (15.3%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">550 (19.0%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">726 (14.5%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Did not receive</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6,185 (52.5%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,742 (50.1%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">233 (55.6%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,419 (48.9%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,791 (55.9%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Unknown (no assessment)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,697 (31.4%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,167 (33.6%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">122 (29.1%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">932 (32.1%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,476 (29.6%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unhealthy alcohol use categorization</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Positive</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">770 (6.5%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">195 (5.6%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40 (9.5%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">238 (8.2%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">297 (5.9%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Negative</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7,349 (62.3%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,120 (61.0%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">259 (61.8%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,745 (60.2%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,235 (64.6%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Unknown</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,670 (31.1%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,161 (33.4%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">120 (29.6%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">918 (31.6%)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,471 (29.5%)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="spara004"><p><italic toggle="yes">Note:</italic> Rurality was determined from practice ZIP codes using the National Center for Education Statistics&#8217; EDGE program.<xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref></p></fn><fn id="spara005"><p>EDGE, Education Demographic and Geographic Estimates; MCC, multiple chronic condition; USPSTF, U.S. Preventive Services Task Force.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="para0018">From the multiple regression analyses, there was no difference in the likelihood of receiving any alcohol-related assessment between each MCC group and MCC<sub>0</sub> group. However, patients with MCC<sub>P+MH</sub> had 1.4 times greater odds of being screened with a USPSTF-recommended instrument than patients with MCC<sub>0</sub> (95% CI=1.2, 1.6; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.001), whereas patients with only MCC<sub>P</sub> or only MCC<sub>MH</sub> had similar odds (<xref rid="tbl0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref><xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref>). Patients with MCC<sub>MH</sub> or MCC<sub>P+MH</sub> had 1.7 times and 1.4 times greater odds of screening positive for UAU than those with MCC<sub>0</sub> (95% CI=1.2, 2.5; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>=0.003 and 95% CI=1.2, 1.8; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.001, respectively), whereas those with MCC<sub>P</sub> were not statistically different from those with MCC<sub>0</sub> (<xref rid="tbl0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0003" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Logistic Regression Results: Variation in Alcohol Screening Outcomes Based on MCC Status</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0003">Table 3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MCC status</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Any alcohol-related assessment (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=11,789), OR (95% CI); <italic toggle="yes">p</italic></th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Screening with USPSTF-recommended instrument (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=8,092), OR (95% CI); <italic toggle="yes">p</italic></th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Positive screening for unhealthy alcohol use (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=8,119), OR (95% CI); <italic toggle="yes">p</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Multiple logistic models: OR compared with MCC<sub>0</sub></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;MCC<sub>P</sub></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.929 (0.830, 1.040); 0.2015</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.087 (0.925, 1.277); 0.3094</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.856 (0.685, 1.071); 0.1742</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;MCC<sub>MH</sub></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.001 (0.800, 1.253); 0.9904</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.992 (0.724, 1.357); 0.9581</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.735 (1.203, 2.503); 0.0032</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;MCC<sub>P+MH</sub></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.961 (0.861, 1.073); 0.4788</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.396 (1.198, 1.626); &lt;0.0001</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.449 (1.185, 1.773); 0.0003</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mixed multiple logistics models with practice random effect: OR compared with MCC<sub>0</sub></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;ICC</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.336</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.781</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.123</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;MCC<sub>P</sub></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.923 (0.812, 1.048); 0.2170</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.827 (0.622, 1.098); 0.1893</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.902 (0.715, 1.137); 0.3817</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;MCC<sub>MH</sub></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.998 (0.777, 1.282); 0.9895</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.298 (0.757, 2.227); 0.3429</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.844 (1.266, 2.687); 0.0014</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;MCC<sub>P+MH</sub></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.865 (0.762, 0.981); 0.0240</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.038 (0.783, 1.378); 0.7937</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.484 (1.198, 1.837); 0.0003</bold></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="spara007"><p><italic toggle="yes">Note:</italic> Bold font indicates statistical significance (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.05).</p></fn><fn id="spara008"><p>ICC, intraclass correlation coefficient; MCC, multiple chronic condition; MCC<sub>MH</sub>, mental health multiple chronic condition; MCC<sub>P</sub>, physical multiple chronic condition; MCC<sub>P+MH</sub>, physical and mental health multiple chronic condition; USPSTF, U.S. Preventive Services Task Force.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="para0019">However, when adding the random practice intercept, patients with MCC<sub>P+MH</sub> had 0.9 times lower odds of receiving any screening (95% CI=0.8, 1.0; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>=0.0240) (<xref rid="tbl0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). There was no difference between each MCC group and MCC<sub>0</sub> group in the likelihood of being screened with a USPSTF-recommended instrument. Patients with MCC<sub>MH</sub> and MCC<sub>P+MH</sub> had 1.8 and 1.5 times greater odds of screening positive than those with MCC<sub>0</sub> (95% CI=1.3, 2.7; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>=0.001 and 95% CI=1.2, 1.8; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.001, respectively), whereas those with MCC<sub>P</sub> were not statistically different from those with MCC<sub>0</sub> (<xref rid="tbl0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Intraclass correlation coefficients for the 3 models were 0.34, 0.78, and 0.12, respectively, indicating that practices were strongly associated with the use of a USPSTF-recommended instrument.</p></sec><sec id="sec0006"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p id="para0020">Despite the potential for preventing disease and improving population health outcomes, clinical preventive services such as alcohol screening and counseling are delivered at suboptimal rates in U.S. primary care.<xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="bib0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="bib0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="bib0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="bib0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> Previous studies report greater odds of screening for UAU among patients with MCCs in primary care, independent of visit frequency.<xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref> However, the present investigation showed that within a diverse, statewide cohort of over 11,000 patients, those with MCCs had similar or lower odds of receiving an alcohol-related screening or assessment in primary care. Furthermore, fewer than 1 in 4 patients who received an alcohol-related assessment were screened with a USPSTF-recommended instrument, which is more reliable in detecting UAU. These findings may reflect current demands, stress, and resource limitations faced by primary care teams. Continued efforts are needed to promote the delivery of high-quality alcohol screening services in primary care.</p><p id="para0021">Although the USPSTF recommends that all adults be screened for UAU,<xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> it is especially critical for patients with MCCs who may be at greater risk for UAU and who are likely to experience greater consequences of UAU than those without MCCs.<xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="bib0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="bib0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="bib0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="bib0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> UAU exacerbates most chronic physical and mental health chronic conditions and increases the risk for developing other chronic health conditions. Timko and colleagues<xref rid="bib0026" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref> outline 3 mechanisms by which UAU exacerbates chronic conditions: through a direct impact, by increasing disease risk factors, and by reducing capacity for self-management of chronic conditions. In addition, in this study, patients with mental health chronic conditions (with or without physical chronic conditions) had significantly greater odds of screening positive for UAU, which is consistent with the literature.<xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="bib0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="bib0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="bib0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> Thus, because patients with MCCs are described as a high-risk population and national priority for improved health outcomes,<xref rid="bib0001" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> results of this investigation may inform initiatives to improve clinic workflows and practice and care team capacity for providing alcohol screening services to this important population.</p><p id="para0022">The delivery of alcohol preventive services is especially essential in the primary care setting. Primary care is the entry to health care for many patients, and primary care teams coordinate patients&#8217; care around MCCs.<xref rid="bib0026" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref> Individuals with access to primary care and who have increasing frequency of primary care visits have lower likelihood of risky drinking.<xref rid="bib0044" ref-type="bibr"><sup>44</sup></xref> Increasing access to primary care has been shown to increase the odds of screening for UAU among socioeconomically disadvantaged patients, particularly those with MCCs.<xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr"><sup>45</sup></xref> Furthermore, brief interventions for UAU can be successfully delivered in primary care<xref rid="bib0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="bib0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, <xref rid="bib0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref> and have been shown effective in reducing UAU.</p><p id="para0023">In this study, a relatively high proportion of patients (69%) received some type of alcohol-related assessment. However, similar to others,<xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib0038" ref-type="bibr"><sup>38</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib0039" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib0049" ref-type="bibr"><sup>49</sup></xref> the study team identified low rates of screening for UAU with a USPSTF-recommended instrument (16%). Although this study found MCC status to influence the odds of receiving an alcohol-related assessment (MCC<sub>P+MH</sub>), the low proportion of patients assessed through USPSTF-recommended instrument suggests additional barriers to delivery of high-quality alcohol preventive services in primary care. Potential barriers include limited EHR capacity, clinician training, and reimbursement for screening services.<xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref> The coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic may have also interrupted typical clinic workflow around screening for UAU. Future efforts to enhance primary care screening for UAU should build on previous successful initiatives through consideration of clinical complexity, contemporary context, and other identified barriers.<xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr"><sup>40</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr"><sup>50</sup></xref></p><sec id="sec0007"><title>Limitations</title><p id="para0024">This study used a large, statewide cohort that represented the demographic diversity of the state of Virginia<xref rid="bib0029" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref> to evaluate the relationship between MCC status and alcohol-related outcomes in real-world primary care practices. Unlike previous literature, this study examined variation by MCC type (physical versus mental health conditions), which increases translatability of findings into primary care practice. This analysis incorporates &gt;35 chronic conditions, all shown to be impacted by UAU,<xref rid="bib0001" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> and both patient- and practice-level factors previously shown to influence alcohol screening.<xref rid="bib0046" ref-type="bibr"><sup>46</sup></xref></p><p id="para0025">Data used for this study were limited to those that were available in the EHR, which may not always accurately reflect chronic condition diagnoses or alcohol screening services delivered. However, the large sample size represented 67 different practices, which limits the influence of any particular practice or care teams whose documentation was incomplete or inaccurate. Patient surveys collected in conjunction with this study (but reported elsewhere) indicate strong agreement between alcohol screening outcomes data documented in the EMR and those by patient surveys.<xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr"><sup>40</sup></xref> In addition, the secondary outcome of likelihood of positive screening for UAU was limited to patients who had received an alcohol-related screening or assessment. As such, approximately 30% of the cohort was not included in screening result outcome.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec0008"><title>CONCLUSIONS</title><p id="para0026">During 2020&#8211;2023, 69% of Virginia primary care patients received an alcohol-related assessment, but only 1 in 4 of these involved screening for UAU with a USPSTF-recommended instrument. Patients with MCCs had the same or lower odds of receiving assessment or screening for UAU during the previous 2 years. These findings contradict previous literature, which revealed higher likelihood of screening among patients with MCCs.<xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref> Patients with MCCs are a uniquely complex, challenging, and costly population to treat in primary care.<xref rid="bib0001" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib0051" ref-type="bibr"><sup>51</sup></xref> Considering the increased risk of UAU in patients with MCCs; the role of UAU in the exacerbation of chronic health conditions; and the importance of screening for UAU to the primary, secondary, and tertiary prevention and management of MCCs, continued efforts are needed to create the conditions for the delivery of alcohol-related preventive services in primary care, particularly to patients with high complexity and/or mental health conditions.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebibl1"><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="bib0001"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0001"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bierman</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Malley</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transforming care for people with multiple chronic conditions: Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality's research agenda</article-title><source>Health Serv Res</source><volume>56</volume><issue>suppl 1</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>973</fpage><lpage>979</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1475-6773.13863</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34378192</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8515222</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0002"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0002"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kishore</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of multiple chronic conditions by U.S. state and territory, 2017</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>15</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e0232346</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0232346</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7199953</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32369509</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0003"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0003"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buttorff</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruder</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bauman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Multiple chronic conditions in the United States</part-title><year>2017</year><publisher-name>RAND Corporation</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Santa Monica, CA</publisher-loc><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7249/TL221</pub-id><comment>Published</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="tboref0001">Multiple Chronic Conditions Chartbook. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ahrq.gov/sites/default/files/wysiwyg/professionals/prevention-chronic-care/decision/mcc/mcchartbook.pdf" id="interref002151">https://www.ahrq.gov/sites/default/files/wysiwyg/professionals/prevention-chronic-care/decision/mcc/mcchartbook.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed November 1, 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib0005"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0005"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kazibwe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nikolaidis</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Linnosmaa</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rijken</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Olmen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Costs of multimorbidity: a systematic review and meta-analyses</article-title><source>BMC Med</source><volume>20</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>234</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12916-022-02427-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35850686</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9295506</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0006"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0006"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>BW.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Management of individuals with multiple chronic conditions: a continuing challenge</article-title><source>Am J Manag Care</source><volume>27</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>256</fpage><lpage>260</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.37765/ajmc.2021.88665</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34156219</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0007">Hu XJ, Wang HHX, Li YT, et al. Healthcare needs, experiences and treatment burden in primary care patients with multimorbidity: an evaluation of process of care from patients&#8217; perspectives. <italic toggle="yes">Health Expect</italic>. 2022;25(1):203&#8211;213.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/hex.13363</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8849236</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34585465</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib0008"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0008"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Savitz</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bayliss</surname><given-names>EA.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Emerging models of care for individuals with multiple chronic conditions</article-title><source>Health Serv Res</source><volume>56</volume><issue>suppl 1</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>980</fpage><lpage>989</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1475-6773.13774</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34387358</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8515217</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0009"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0009"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>U.S. Preventive Services Task Force</collab><name name-style="western"><surname>Curry</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krist</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Screening and behavioral counseling interventions to reduce unhealthy alcohol use in adolescents and adults: U.S. Preventive Services Task Force recommendation statement</article-title><source>JAMA</source><volume>320</volume><issue>18</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>1899</fpage><lpage>1909</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2018.16789</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30422199</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0010"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0010"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Esser</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sherk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Estimated deaths attributable to excessive alcohol use among U.S. adults aged 20 to 64 years, 2015 to 2019</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><volume>5</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2022</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e2239485</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.39485</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9627409</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36318209</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0011"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0011"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCambridge</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alcohol complicates multimorbidity in older adults</article-title><source>BMJ</source><volume>365</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>l4304</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.l4304</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31248871</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0012"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0012"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rehm</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gmel</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gmel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The relationship between different dimensions of alcohol use and the burden of disease-an update</article-title><source>Addiction</source><volume>112</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>968</fpage><lpage>1001</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/add.13757</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28220587</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5434904</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0013"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0013"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>GBD 2020 Alcohol Collaborators</collab></person-group><article-title>Population-level risks of alcohol consumption by amount, geography, age, sex, and year: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2020</article-title><source>Lancet</source><volume>400</volume><issue>10347</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>235</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(22)00847-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35843246</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9289789</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0014"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0014"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Palzes</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parthasarathy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Associations between psychiatric disorders and alcohol consumption levels in an adult primary care population</article-title><source>Alcohol Clin Exp Res</source><volume>44</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>2536</fpage><lpage>2544</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/acer.14477</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33151592</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7756330</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0015"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0015"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasin</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>BF.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The National Epidemiologic Survey on Alcohol and Related Conditions (NESARC) Waves 1 and 2: review and summary of findings</article-title><source>Soc Psychiatry Psychiatr Epidemiol</source><volume>50</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>1609</fpage><lpage>1640</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00127-015-1088-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26210739</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4618096</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0016"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0016"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Keyes</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cerd&#225;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Havens</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galea</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding the rural&#8211;urban differences in nonmedical prescription opioid use and abuse in the United States</article-title><source>Am J Public Health</source><volume>104</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>e52</fpage><lpage>e59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2105/AJPH.2013.301709</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24328642</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3935688</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0017"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0017"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blazer</surname><given-names>DG.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Substance use disorders and psychiatric comorbidity in mid and later life: a review</article-title><source>Int J Epidemiol</source><volume>43</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>304</fpage><lpage>317</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ije/dyt173</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24163278</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3997371</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0018"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0018"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caniglia</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association of alcohol screening scores with adverse mental health conditions and substance use among U.S. adults</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><volume>3</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e200895</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.0895</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7068229</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32163167</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0019"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0019"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sterling</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palzes</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Associations between medical conditions and alcohol consumption levels in an adult primary care population</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><volume>3</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e204687</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.4687</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7221504</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32401315</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0020"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0020"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guillaume</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goyder</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Barriers and facilitators to implementing screening and brief intervention for alcohol misuse: a systematic review of qualitative evidence</article-title><source>J Public Health (Oxf)</source><volume>33</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>412</fpage><lpage>421</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pubmed/fdq095</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21169370</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0021"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0021"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ros&#225;rio</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Angus</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pas</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fitzgerald</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factors influencing the implementation of screening and brief interventions for alcohol use in primary care practices: a systematic review using the COM-B system and Theoretical Domains Framework</article-title><source>Implement Sci</source><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>6</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13012-020-01073-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33413487</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7791720</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0022"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0022"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McNeely</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rieckmann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Barriers and facilitators affecting the implementation of substance use screening in primary care clinics: a qualitative study of patients, providers, and staff</article-title><source>Addict Sci Clin Pract</source><volume>13</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>8</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13722-018-0110-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29628018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5890352</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0023"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0023"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huffstetler</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Epling</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krist</surname><given-names>AH.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The need for electronic health records to support delivery of behavioral health preventive services</article-title><source>JAMA</source><volume>328</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>707</fpage><lpage>708</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2022.13391</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35925570</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9423001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0024"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0024"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ornstein</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Litvin</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wessell</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nietert</surname><given-names>PJ.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preventive services delivery in patients with chronic illnesses: parallel opportunities rather than competing obligations</article-title><source>Ann Fam Med</source><volume>11</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>344</fpage><lpage>349</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1370/afm.1502</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23835820</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3704494</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0025"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0025"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chatterton</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Agnoli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fenton</surname><given-names>JJ.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alcohol screening during U.S. primary care visits, 2014&#8211;2016</article-title><source>J Gen Intern Med</source><volume>37</volume><issue>15</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>3848</fpage><lpage>3852</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11606-021-07369-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35048299</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9640516</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0026"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0026"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Timko</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vittorio</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cucciare</surname><given-names>MA.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Screening and brief intervention for unhealthy substance use in patients with chronic medical conditions: a systematic review</article-title><source>J Clin Nurs</source><volume>25</volume><issue>21&#8211;22</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>3131</fpage><lpage>3143</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jocn.13244</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27140392</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6430571</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0027"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0027"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ukhanova</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tillotson</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Uptake of preventive services among patients with and without multimorbidity</article-title><source>Am J Prev Med</source><volume>59</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>621</fpage><lpage>629</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amepre.2020.04.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32978012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7577968</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0028"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0028"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huffstetler</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuzel</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sabo</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Practice facilitation to promote evidence-based screening and management of unhealthy alcohol use in primary care: a practice-level randomized controlled trial</article-title><source>BMC Fam Pract</source><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>93</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12875-020-01147-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32434467</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7240919</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0029"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0029"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krist</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huffstetler</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Villalobos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Use of population health data to promote equitable recruitment for a primary care practice implementation trial addressing unhealthy alcohol use</article-title><source>J Clin Transl Sci</source><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>e110</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/cts.2023.530</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37250994</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10225269</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0030"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0030"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>WHO</collab></person-group><part-title>AUDIT : the alcohol use disorders identification test : guidelines for use in primary health care</part-title><year>2023</year><publisher-name>WHO</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Geneva, Switzerland</publisher-loc><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/publications-detail-redirect/WHO-MSD-MSB-01.6a" id="interref0003">https://www.who.int/publications-detail-redirect/WHO-MSD-MSB-01.6a</ext-link><comment>Published November 18, 2001. Accessed June 25</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0031"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0031"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allensworth-Davies</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saitz</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Primary care validation of a single-question alcohol screening test</article-title><source>J Gen Intern Med</source><volume>24</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>783</fpage><lpage>788</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11606-009-0928-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19247718</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2695521</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0032">Home. Chronic Conditions Data Warehouse. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www2.ccwdata.org" id="interref0004">https://www2.ccwdata.org</ext-link>. Accessed June 25, 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib0033"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0033"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weeks</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huynh</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weinstein</surname><given-names>JN.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of year-to-year patient-specific comorbid conditions reported in the Medicare chronic conditions data warehouse</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><volume>3</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e2018176</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.18176</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7530630</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33001199</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0034"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0034"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Donnell</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of multiple chronic conditions in the United States&#8217; Medicare population</article-title><source>Health Qual Life Outcomes</source><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>82</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1477-7525-7-82</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19737412</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2748070</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0035"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0035"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deyo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hemingway</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>DR.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identifying patients with undiagnosed chronic conditions: an examination of patient costs before chronic disease diagnosis</article-title><source>J Am Coll Radiol</source><volume>12</volume><issue>12, pt B</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>1388</fpage><lpage>1394</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacr.2015.09.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26614884</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0036"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0036"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jarr&#237;n</surname><given-names>OF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nyandege</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grafova</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Validity of Race and ethnicity codes in medicare administrative data compared with gold-standard self-reported race collected during routine home health care visits</article-title><source>Med Care</source><volume>58</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>e1</fpage><lpage>e8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MLR.0000000000001216</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31688554</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6904433</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0037">Geverdt D. <italic toggle="yes">ZIP Code Tabulation Area (ZCTA) Locale Assignments File Documentation</italic>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib0038"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0038"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Subbaraman</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lui</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karriker-Jaffe</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Greenfield</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mulia</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Predictors of alcohol screening quality in a U.S. general population sample and subgroups of heavy drinkers</article-title><source>Prev Med Rep</source><volume>29</volume><year>2022</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">101932</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pmedr.2022.101932</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9501990</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36161112</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0039"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0039"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bendtsen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spak</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Improving the delivery of brief interventions for heavy drinking in primary health care: outcome results of the Optimizing Delivery of Health Care Intervention (ODHIN) five-country cluster randomized factorial trial</article-title><source>Addiction</source><volume>111</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>1935</fpage><lpage>1945</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/add.13476</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27237081</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0040"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0040"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huffstetler</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Villalobos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The current state of alcohol screening and management in Virginia primary care practices: an evaluation of preventive service use</article-title><source>Med Clin North Am</source><volume>107</volume><issue>6S</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>e1</fpage><lpage>e17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mcna.2023.07.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38609278</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11370272</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0041"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0041"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McGlynn</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Asch</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The quality of health care delivered to adults in the United States</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><volume>348</volume><issue>26</issue><year>2003</year><fpage>2635</fpage><lpage>2645</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMsa022615</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12826639</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0042"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0042"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Borsky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ngo-Metzger</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bierman</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meyers</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Few Americans receive all high-priority, appropriate clinical preventive services</article-title><source>Health Aff (Millwood)</source><volume>37</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>925</fpage><lpage>928</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1377/hlthaff.2017.1248</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29863918</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0043"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0043"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bachhuber</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Grady</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Delivery of screening and brief intervention for unhealthy alcohol use in an urban academic Federally Qualified Health Center</article-title><source>Addict Sci Clin Pract</source><volume>12</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>33</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13722-017-0100-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29212532</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5719726</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0044"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0044"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cherpitel</surname><given-names>CJ.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Access to health care and heavy drinking in patients with diabetes or hypertension: implications for alcohol interventions</article-title><source>Subst Use Misuse</source><volume>47</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>726</fpage><lpage>733</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/10826084.2012.665558</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22432456</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3328624</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0045"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0045"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>AZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karriker-Jaffe</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bensley</surname><given-names>KMK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Subbaraman</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Delk</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mulia</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Residence in a Medicaid-expansion state and receipt of alcohol screening and brief counseling by adults with lower incomes: is increased access to primary care enough?</article-title><source>Alcohol Clin Exp Res (Hoboken)</source><volume>47</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>1390</fpage><lpage>1405</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/acer.15102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37421544</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10524486</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0046"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0046"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Babor</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Higgins-Biddle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dauser</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burleson</surname><given-names>JA.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alcohol screening and brief intervention in primary care settings: implementation models and predictors</article-title><source>J Stud Alcohol</source><volume>66</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2005</year><fpage>361</fpage><lpage>368</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15288/jsa.2005.66.361</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16047525</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0047"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0047"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism (NIAAA)</collab></person-group><part-title>The importance of alcohol screening, brief intervention, and referral to treatment in closing the alcohol use disorder treatment gap</part-title><year>2024</year><publisher-name>National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism (NIAAA)</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Rockville, MD</publisher-loc><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.niaaa.nih.gov/news-events/research-update/importance-alcohol-screening-brief-intervention-and-referral-treatment-closing-alcohol-use-disorder" id="interref0005">https://www.niaaa.nih.gov/news-events/research-update/importance-alcohol-screening-brief-intervention-and-referral-treatment-closing-alcohol-use-disorder</ext-link><comment>Published 2023. Accessed January 7</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0048"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0048"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seale</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A multisite initiative to increase the use of alcohol screening and brief intervention through resident training and clinic systems changes</article-title><source>Acad Med</source><volume>90</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>1707</fpage><lpage>1712</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">10.1097/ACM.0000000000 000846</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26200578</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/ACM.0000000000000846</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0049"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0049"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bobb</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Integrating alcohol-related prevention and treatment into primary care: a cluster randomized implementation trial</article-title><source>JAMA Intern Med</source><volume>183</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>319</fpage><lpage>328</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamainternmed.2022.7083</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36848119</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9972247</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0050"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0050"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dzidowska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KSK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wylie</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A systematic review of approaches to improve practice, detection and treatment of unhealthy alcohol use in primary health care: a role for continuous quality improvement</article-title><source>BMC Fam Pract</source><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>33</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12875-020-1101-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32054450</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7020510</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0051"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0051"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Holmen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sallinen</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Working with patients suffering from chronic diseases can be a balancing act for health care professionals - a meta-synthesis of qualitative studies</article-title><source>BMC Health Serv Res</source><volume>20</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>98</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12913-019-4826-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32039723</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7011477</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="sec0012" sec-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix</label><title>Supplementary materials</title><p id="para0027a">
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ecom0001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc1.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><alt-text>Image, application 1</alt-text></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec><ack id="ack0001"><sec id="sec0009"><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title><p id="para0028">The sponsor of this study had no role in the design of this study; collection, analysis, and interpretation of data; writing of the report; or decision of where to submit.</p><p id="para0029">This work was supported by a grant from the Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality (R18HS027077, principal investigator: AHK).</p><p id="para0030">Preliminary findings from this study were presented as an oral presentation at the 2022 Annual Meeting of the North American Primary Care Research Group (Rockwell).</p><p id="para0031">JWE and AHK served on the U.S. Preventive Services Task Force for the 2020 Recommendation for Unhealthy Alcohol Use in Adolescents and Adults: Screening and Behavioral Counseling Interventions Recommendation. No other disclosures were reported.</p></sec><sec id="sec0010"><title>CRediT AUTHOR STATEMENT</title><p id="para0032">Michelle S. Rockwell: Investigation, Methodology, Project administration, Writing - original draft. Adam J. Funk: Formal analysis, Writing - reviewing &amp; editing. Alison N. Huffstetler: Investigation, Methodology, Supervision, Writing - reviewing &amp; editing. Gabriela Villalobos: Data curation, Investigation, Project administration, Writing - reviewing &amp; editing. Jacqueline B. Britz: Supervision, Writing - reviewing &amp; editing. Benjamin Webel: Investigation, Project administration, Writing - reviewing &amp; editing. Alicia Richards: Formal analysis. John W. Epling: Conceptualization, Supervision, Writing - reviewing &amp; editing. Roy T. Sabo: Formal analysis, Supervision. Alex H. Krist: Conceptualization, Methodology, Supervision, Writing - reviewing &amp; editing.</p></sec></ack><fn-group><fn id="sec0011" fn-type="supplementary-material"><p id="para0008a">Supplementary material associated with this article can be found in the online version at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.focus.2024.100233" id="interref0001">doi:10.1016/j.focus.2024.100233</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article></pmc-articleset>