<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JAMA Netw Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JAMA Netw Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3211</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jamasd</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>JAMA Network Open</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2574-3805</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>JAMA Network</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10276300</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10276300.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10276300</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10276300</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37326989</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.18626</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">zoi230569</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="category" specific-use="electronic"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Investigation</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="online-only"><subject>Online Only</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="subject-area"><subject>Surgery</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Trends in the Use of Gabapentinoids and Opioids in the Postoperative Period Among Older Adults</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="headline">Postoperative Use of Gabapentinoids and Opioids Among Older Adults</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Postoperative Use of Gabapentinoids and Opioids Among Older Adults</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bongiovanni</surname><given-names initials="T">Tasce</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><degrees>MPP</degrees><xref rid="zoi230569aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gan</surname><given-names initials="S">Siqi</given-names></name><degrees>MPH</degrees><xref rid="zoi230569aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="zoi230569aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Finlayson</surname><given-names initials="E">Emily</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="zoi230569aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ross</surname><given-names initials="JS">Joseph S.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><degrees>MHS</degrees><xref rid="zoi230569aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><xref rid="zoi230569aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref><xref rid="zoi230569aff6" ref-type="aff">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names initials="JD">James D.</given-names></name><degrees>MPH</degrees><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="zoi230569aff7" ref-type="aff">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boscardin</surname><given-names initials="WJ">W. John</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="zoi230569aff8" ref-type="aff">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref><xref rid="zoi230569aff9" ref-type="aff">
<sup>9</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Steinman</surname><given-names initials="MA">Michael A.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="zoi230569aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="zoi230569aff10" ref-type="aff">
<sup>10</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="zoi230569aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Surgery, University of California, San Francisco, School of Medicine</aff><aff id="zoi230569aff2"><label>2</label>Division of Geriatrics, University of California, San Francisco, School of Medicine</aff><aff id="zoi230569aff3"><label>3</label>Northern California Institute for Research and Education, San Francisco</aff><aff id="zoi230569aff4"><label>4</label>Center for Outcomes Research and Evaluation, Yale&#8211;New Haven Hospital, New Haven, Connecticut</aff><aff id="zoi230569aff5"><label>5</label>Section of General Internal Medicine, Yale University School of Medicine, New Haven, Connecticut</aff><aff id="zoi230569aff6"><label>6</label>Department of Health Policy and Management, Yale University School of Public Health, New Haven, Connecticut</aff><aff id="zoi230569aff7"><label>7</label>Division of Hospital Medicine, University of California, San Francisco, School of Medicine</aff><aff id="zoi230569aff8"><label>8</label>Department of Medicine, University of California, San Francisco, School of Medicine</aff><aff id="zoi230569aff9"><label>9</label>Department of Epidemiology and Biostatistics, University of California, San Francisco, School of Medicine</aff><aff id="zoi230569aff10"><label>10</label>San Francisco Veterans Affairs Medical Center, San Francisco, California</aff><author-notes><title>Article Information</title><p><bold>Accepted for Publication:</bold> May 2, 2023.</p><p content-type="published-online"><bold>Published:</bold> June 16, 2023. doi:<uri content-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.18626</uri></p><p content-type="open-access-note"><bold>Open Access:</bold> This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/pages/cc-by-license-permissions" ext-link-type="uri">CC-BY License</ext-link>. &#169; 2023 Bongiovanni T et al. <italic toggle="yes">JAMA Network Open</italic>.</p><corresp id="zoi230569cor1"><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Tasce Bongiovanni, MD, MPP, 513 Parnassus Ave, HSW 1600, San Francisco, CA 94143-0790 (<email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="tasce.bongiovanni@ucsf.edu">tasce.bongiovanni@ucsf.edu</email>).</corresp><p content-type="author-contributions"><bold>Author Contributions:</bold> Ms Gan and Dr Boscardin had full access to all of the data in the study and take responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Concept and design:</italic> Bongiovanni, Finlayson, Steinman.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</italic> Bongiovanni, Gan, Ross, Harrison, Boscardin, Steinman.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Drafting of the manuscript:</italic> Bongiovanni, Gan, Harrison.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Critical revision of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</italic> Bongiovanni, Finlayson, Ross, Harrison, Boscardin, Steinman.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Statistical analysis:</italic> Gan, Boscardin.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Obtained funding:</italic> Bongiovanni.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Administrative, technical, or material support:</italic> Bongiovanni, Harrison, Steinman.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Supervision:</italic> Boscardin, Steinman.</p><p content-type="COI-statement"><bold>Conflict of Interest Disclosures:</bold> Dr Bongiovanni reported receiving grant funding from the National Institutes of Health (NIH) and Robert Wood Johnson Foundation during the conduct of the study. Dr Finlayson reported being a founder of Ooney Inc outside the submitted work. Dr Ross reported receiving grant funding from the US Food and Drug Administration, Johnson &amp; Johnson, Medical Device Innovation Consortium, the Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality (AHRQ), the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI) of the NIH, and Arnold Ventures LLC outside the submitted work and testifying as an expert witness at the request of the relator&#8217;s attorneys, the Greene Law Firm, in a qui tam suit alleging violations of the False Claims Act and Anti-Kickback Statute against Biogen Inc that was settled September 2022. Dr Harrison reported receiving grant funding from the National Institute on Aging (NIA) of the NIH and nonfinancial support from the National Center for Advancing Translational Sciences (NCATS) during the conduct of the study. Dr Steinman reported receiving grant funding from the NIH during the conduct of the study; royalties from UpToDate for chapter authorship; honoraria for guideline development from American Geriatrics Society outside the submitted work; and serving as an unpaid expert witness in litigation that alleged illegal marketing of gabapentin for off-label uses. No other disclosures were reported.</p><p content-type="funding-statement"><bold>Funding/Support:</bold> This study was supported by grant K23AG073523 from the NIA of the NIH (Drs Bongiovanni and Harrison); grant P0553126 from the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation (Dr Bongiovanni); grant KL2TR001870 from the NCATS of the NIH (Dr Harrison); research support through Yale University from Johnson &amp; Johnson to develop methods of clinical trial data sharing (Dr Ross); the Medical Device Innovation Consortium as part of the National Evaluation System for Health Technology (Dr Ross); the US Food and Drug Administration for the Yale-Mayo Clinic Center by grant U01FD005938 from the Excellence in Regulatory Science and Innovation program (Dr Ross); grant R01HS022882 from the AHRQ (Dr Ross); grants R01HS025164 and R01HL144644 from the NHLBI of the NIH (Dr Ross); the Laura and John Arnold Foundation to establish the Good Pharma Scorecard at Bioethics International (Dr Ross); and grants R01AG058616 (Dr Finlayson), R01AG067507 (Dr Finlayson), P01 AG066605 (Dr Boscardin), P30 P30AG044281 (Dr Boscardin), K24AG049057 (Dr Steinman), R24AG064025 (Dr Steinman), and P30AG044281 (Dr Steinman) from the NIH.</p><p><bold>Role of the Funder/Sponsor:</bold> The funding organizations had no role in the design and conduct of the study; collection, management, analysis, and interpretation of the data; preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript; and decision to submit the manuscript for publication.</p><p><bold>Disclaimer:</bold> The content is solely the responsibility of the authors and does not necessarily represent the official views of the NIH or the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation.</p><p content-type="data-sharing-statement"><bold>Data Sharing Statement:</bold> See <xref rid="note-ZOI230569-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>.</p></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2023-06-16T10:00"><day>16</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>6</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>6</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">438556</issue-id><elocation-id>e2318626</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>31</day><month>1</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>2</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>16</day><month>06</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>18</day><month>06</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-07-23 00:25:10.147"><day>23</day><month>07</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright 2023 Bongiovanni T et al. <italic toggle="yes">JAMA Network Open</italic>.</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the CC-BY License.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2318626.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pdf-version" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2318626.pdf">jamanetwopen-e2318626.pdf</self-uri><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="silverchair" xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamanetworkopen/fullarticle/10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.18626"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="correction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="correction" vol="6" journal-id="JAMA Netw Open" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC10359958"><article-title>Error in Funding/Support Information</article-title><volume>6</volume><issue>7</issue><date><day>20</day><month>7</month><year>2023</year></date><elocation-id>e2327045</elocation-id><source>JAMA Network Open</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.27045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10359958</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37471091</pub-id></related-article><abstract abstract-type="key-points"><title>Key Points</title><sec id="ab-zoi230569-1"><title>Question</title><p>Is postoperative use of gabapentinoids, a medication framed as opioid sparing, increasing, and is gabapentinoid use associated with decreased opioid prescribing among older adults?</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi230569-2"><title>Findings</title><p>In this serial cross-sectional study of postoperative pain medication prescribing for common surgical procedures in 494&#8201;922 Medicare recipients, gabapentinoid prescribing increased over a 5-year period from 2% to 5%. In this same period, opioid prescribing increased from 56% to 59%, as did concomitant prescribing.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi230569-3"><title>Meaning</title><p>These findings suggest that postoperative gabapentinoid prescribing for older adults is rising in addition to rather than instead of opioid use, a combination recommended to be avoided in older adults.</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="teaser" specific-use="electronic"><p>This cross-sectional study describes trends in prescribing of postoperative gabapentinoids and concomitant opioids by examining nationally representative Medicare data for multiple surgical procedures and variation by procedure type.</p></abstract><abstract><sec id="ab-zoi230569-4"><title>Importance</title><p>In response to the opioid epidemic, recommendations from some pain societies have encouraged surgeons to embrace multimodal pain regimens with the intent of reducing opioid use in the postoperative period, including by prescribing gabapentinoids.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi230569-5"><title>Objective</title><p>To describe trends in postoperative prescribing of both gabapentinoids and opioids after a variety of surgical procedures by examining nationally representative Medicare data and further understand variation by procedure.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi230569-6"><title>Design, Setting, and Participants</title><p>This serial cross-sectional study of gabapentinoid prescribing from January 1, 2013, through December 31, 2018, used a 20% US Medicare sample. Gabapentinoid-naive patients 66 years or older undergoing 1 of 14 common noncataract surgical procedures performed in older adults were included. Data were analyzed from April 2022 to April 2023.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi230569-7"><title>Exposure</title><p>One of 14 common surgical procedures in older adults.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi230569-8"><title>Main Outcomes and Measures</title><p>Rate of postoperative prescribing of gabapentinoids and opioids, defined as a prescription filled between 7 days before the procedure and 7 days after discharge from surgery. Additionally, concomitant prescribing of gabapentinoids and opioids in the postoperative period was assessed.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi230569-9"><title>Results</title><p>The total study cohort included 494&#8201;922 patients with a mean (SD) age of 73.7 (5.9) years, 53.9% of whom were women and 86.0% of whom were White. A total of 18&#8201;095 patients (3.7%) received a new gabapentinoid prescription in the postoperative period. Of those receiving a new gabapentinoid prescription, 10&#8201;956 (60.5%) were women and 15 529 (85.8%) were White. After adjusting for age, sex, race and ethnicity, and procedure type in each year, the rate of new postoperative gabapentinoid prescribing increased from 2.3% (95% CI, 2.2%-2.4%) in 2014 to 5.2% (95% CI, 5.0%-5.4%) in 2018 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001). While there was variation between procedure types, almost all procedures saw an increase in both gabapentinoid and opioid prescribing. In this same period, opioid prescribing increased from 56% (95% CI, 55%-56%) to 59% (95% CI, 58%-60%) (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001). Concomitant prescribing also increased from 1.6% (95% CI, 1.5%-1.7%) in 2014 to 4.1% (95% CI, 4.0%-4.3%) in 2018 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001).</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi230569-10"><title>Conclusions and Relevance</title><p>The findings of this cross-sectional study of Medicare beneficiaries suggest that new postoperative gabapentinoid prescribing increased without a subsequent downward trend in the proportion of patients receiving postoperative opioids and a near tripling of concurrent prescribing. Closer attention needs to be paid to postoperative prescribing for older adults, especially when using multiple types of medications, which can have adverse drug events.</p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="H1-1-ZOI230569"><title>Introduction</title><p>Postoperative pain management is a critical part of surgical care,<sup><xref rid="zoi230569r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> and pain control is increasingly evaluated as part of quality measurement efforts. Pain control not only enhances patient satisfaction with care, but also speeds recovery and aids in patients&#8217; ability to participate in rehabilitation. In response to the opioid epidemic and with the goal of improving pain control, surgeons have increasingly initiated multimodal pain regimens to treat pain with a goal of reducing opioid use in the postoperative period. This regimen includes a wide range of nonopioid medications, including gabapentinoids.<sup><xref rid="zoi230569r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> Studies indicate that a single preoperative dose of a gabapentinoid is associated with a decrease in postoperative pain and opioid consumption at 24 hours,<sup><xref rid="zoi230569r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> and some societies began to recommend uptake of multimodal pain regimens, including consideration of gabapentinoids, to decrease pain for patients undergoing surgery. Unfortunately, gabapentinoids increase postoperative sedation, dizziness, and delirium in both the short and long term,<sup><xref rid="zoi230569r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230569r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230569r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> and a more recent meta-analysis<sup><xref rid="zoi230569r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> suggests that perioperative gabapentinoids may not in fact decrease pain as was hoped.</p><p>Older adults (aged &#8805;65 years) account for almost half of all patients undergoing surgery each year in the US.<sup><xref rid="zoi230569r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> In this growing patient population, gabapentinoids are often poorly tolerated because of pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic changes associated with aging, comorbidities, and interactions with other medications.<sup><xref rid="zoi230569r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> In addition, gabapentinoids are listed in the American Geriatrics Society Beers Criteria, which explicitly detail potentially inappropriate medications for older adults, including strong recommendations to avoid using gabapentinoids with opioids except when transitioning from one to the other, and include a caution to dose renally when necessary. Concomitant use has been shown to increase risk of overdose, respiratory depression, and death, except when transitioning from one to the other.<sup><xref rid="zoi230569r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230569r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> Additionally, postoperative prescribing of gabapentin is known to lead to prolonged use,<sup><xref rid="zoi230569r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> with its own inherent risks of altered mental status and polypharmacy. Nevertheless, older age is one of several risk factors for receiving more opioids and multimodal pain medication in the postoperative period.<sup><xref rid="zoi230569r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230569r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup></p><p>The prevalence and especially the acceleration of postoperative gabapentinoid prescribing among older adults is unknown. Similarly, it is uncertain whether this shift to multimodal medications has in fact moved the needle toward its intended outcome: decreased opioid prescribing. Further, the shift toward gabapentinoid use has taken place without attention to concomitant use of opioids, a potentially dangerous combination found to lead to serious adverse events, including overdose and death.<sup><xref rid="zoi230569r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230569r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> Therefore, we sought to describe trends in prescribing of both postoperative gabapentinoids and concomitant opioids over a recent period by examining nationally representative Medicare data for multiple surgical procedures. We further sought to understand prescribing variation by procedure type.</p></sec><sec id="H1-2-ZOI230569"><title>Methods</title><p>This cross-sectional study followed the Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.equator-network.org/reporting-guidelines/strobe/" ext-link-type="uri">STROBE</ext-link>) reporting guideline for cross-sectional studies (guideline responses are found in eMethods 1 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230569-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>). The study was approved by the University of California, San Francisco, Institutional Review Board, which waived the need for informed consent based on the use of publicly available deidentified data.</p><sec id="H2-1-ZOI230569"><title>Data Source</title><p>We conducted a retrospective cross-sectional analysis of gabapentinoid prescribing by merging patient data from Medicare Carrier, Medicare Provider Analysis and Review (MedPAR), and Outpatient Files with Medicare Part D for January 1, 2013, through December 31, 2018, using a 20% Medicare sample. Medicare is a federal health insurance program that covers approximately 96% of all US citizens 65 years or older, and this data set is a representative sample of 20% of the total population. We merged Medicare Carrier, MedPAR, and Outpatient Files with Part D files and used the Master Beneficiary Summary File base file, the Chronic Condition Segment, the Other Chronic or Potentially Disabling Conditions segment, and the National Death Index segment to determine cohort composition regarding age, sex, race and ethnicity, comorbidity score, and socioeconomic disadvantage based on zip code<sup><xref rid="zoi230569r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> and identify hospitalizations and fee-for-service claims at free-standing ambulatory surgical centers for specifically identified procedures, discharge location, and prescription fills. We tracked both gabapentinoid (gabapentin and pregabalin) and postoperative opioid prescribing.</p></sec><sec id="H2-2-ZOI230569"><title>Study Population</title><p>We included patients undergoing 1 of the 14 most common noncataract surgical procedures performed in older adults<sup><xref rid="zoi230569r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230569r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> who were 66 years or older at the time of the procedure (eTable 1 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230569-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>) and had at least 1 prescription filled in Medicare Part D 3 months prior to surgery. To ensure we had patients who were using their Part D benefit, we only included patients with continuous Part D coverage for 3 months before and 6 months after the procedure date. For patients who had multiple procedures that met inclusion criteria over the time period, we included only their most recent procedure. We excluded patients whose discharge disposition was death or hospice,<sup><xref rid="zoi230569r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> who died within 30 days after discharge, and who had 3 or more procedures on the same day. To exclude current users of gabapentinoids, we excluded patients who had any prior fill of a gabapentinoid within the 3 months prior to surgery.</p><p>We included patients 66 years or older to allow for 1 year prior to the procedure to compile comorbidities to calculate a Charlson Comorbidity Index<sup><xref rid="zoi230569r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> using an updated 17-disease version more appropriate for administrative databases.<sup><xref rid="zoi230569r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> The 14 surgical procedures included represent a wide range of surgical risk, anatomical regions, and specialties. We defined outpatient procedures using codes from the <italic toggle="yes">Healthcare Common Procedural Coding System</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Current Procedural Terminology</italic> and inpatient procedures using codes from the <italic toggle="yes">International Classification of Diseases, Ninth Revision, Clinical Modification</italic>, or <italic toggle="yes">ICD-10 Procedure Coding System</italic> (eTable 2 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230569-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>). We included specific groups of patients who had 2 different procedures on the same day if those procedures both fell into our inclusion criteria (specifically total shoulder arthroplasty with knee arthroplasty and total shoulder arthroplasty with total hip arthroplasty), and we combined the spinal procedures (laminectomy and laminotomy) into 1 category for analysis, given their extensive overlap in our data set. We defined race and ethnicity using the Research Triangle Institute race code, which is an algorithm providing an expanded definition of race and ethnicity to the Medicare data.<sup><xref rid="zoi230569r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> We included race and ethnicity data to show the demographics of the cohort for generalizability to practice.</p><p>From this cohort (eFigure in <xref rid="note-ZOI230569-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>), we analyzed patients who had a new postoperative prescription for a gabapentinoid at the time of surgery, defined as a gabapentinoid that had not been prescribed in the 3 months prior to surgery (excluding the 7 days prior to surgery).<sup><xref rid="zoi230569r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> We considered a postoperative prescription as any fill between 7 days before and 7 days after the surgery (or discharge for inpatients),<sup><xref rid="zoi230569r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230569r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> as some surgical practices prescribe medications preoperatively so that patients can have the medication ready at home. We excluded patients discharged to skilled nursing facilities (SNFs), as medication prescribing during an SNF stay cannot be ascertained with Medicare data. This excluded 17% of the entire population. We pulled the National Drug Code codes from Part D claims and then linked them with Medi-Span crosswalk files (Wolters Kluwer Health) to identify generic drug names and prescription information.</p></sec><sec id="H2-3-ZOI230569"><title>Outcomes</title><p>The primary outcome was the rate of postoperative prescribing of gabapentinoids after surgery, defined as a prescription filled between 7 days before the procedure to 7 days after discharge from surgery, as some surgeons prescribe pain medication before the procedure so that it is already on hand when the patient is discharged, especially for outpatient procedures, as described elsewhere.<sup><xref rid="zoi230569r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> We then calculated the days&#8217; supply by using the days&#8217; supply variable in Part D and summed all prescribing in this period. We defined which procedures most commonly had gabapentin prescribed postoperatively. We also assessed opioid prescribing (eMethods 3 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230569-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>), as the premise of postoperative gabapentinoid use is to decrease the need for opioids. We measured opioid prescribing using the same methods we used for gabapentinoid prescribing. Additionally, we evaluated concomitant prescribing of opioids in the postoperative period, as well as oral morphine equivalents (OME) of the prescription, since concomitant use can increase the risk of adverse drug events. Oral morphine equivalents are used as a tool to compare the amount of different opioids using an equianalgesic dose chart to calculate opioid dose in a consistent and systematic way.<sup><xref rid="zoi230569r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> We did not limit our population to opioid-naive patients prior to surgery, as our main focus was gabapentinoids.</p></sec><sec id="H2-4-ZOI230569"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>Data were analyzed from April 2022 to April 2023. We used unpaired 2-sample <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> tests for continuous variables and &#967;<sup>2</sup> tests for categorical variables. Statistical significance was set to 2-sided <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.05. To identify associations with the trends in prescribing, we constructed multivariable logistic regression models, adjusted for age, sex, race and ethnicity, and procedure type. We then constructed trends over time by analyzing the proportion of postoperative prescribing of new gabapentinoids, opioids, and mean OME across each year from 2014 to 2018, as 2013 was used to calculate comorbidities for people in the first cohort year. Trends of both gabapentinoid (gabapentin and pregabalin) and opioid prescribing during the period were analyzed using a test of linear trend in the log odds of prescribing for each year after multivariable logistic regression adjusting for procedure year, age, sex, race and ethnicity, and procedure types. Rates of gabapentinoid prescribing across years were identified using the mean estimated probability of prescription in the entire cohort for each year using the method of recycled predictions<sup><xref rid="zoi230569r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup>; from the fitted multivariable regression model adjusting for procedure year, age, sex, race and ethnicity, and procedure types, a set of estimated probabilities were generated and then the mean calculated for each possible combination of year between 2014 and 2018 and race and ethnicity, in the full data set case mix of age, sex, and procedure type.</p><p>For trends over year by procedure groups, we ran the multivariable logistic regression with an interaction term of procedure year and procedure groups, adjusting for age, sex, and race and ethnicity. Linear trends of OME over year were analyzed by using multivariable linear regression adjusting for procedure year, age, sex, race and ethnicity, and procedure types. To analyze trends over time for procedure, we collapsed procedures into similar groups including laparoscopic, open, orthopedic, spine, and vascular (eTable 1 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230569-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>). We conducted analyses using SAS, version 9.4 (SAS Institute Inc), Stata, version 17 (StataCorp LLC), and plots were generated with R, version 4.2.1 (R Project for Statistical Computing).</p></sec></sec><sec id="H1-3-ZOI230569"><title>Results</title><p>The total study cohort included 494&#8201;922 patients with a mean (SD) age of 73.7 (5.9) years; 53.9% were women and 46.1% were men. In terms of race and ethnicity, 4.9% of the patients were Black, 5.1% were Hispanic, 86.0% were White, and 4.0% were of other race or ethnicity (including American Indian or Alaska Native, Asian American or Pacific Islander, unknown, and other). A total of 18&#8201;095 patients (3.7%) received a new gabapentinoid prescription in the postoperative period (<xref rid="zoi230569t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Of those who received a new gabapentinoid prescription, 10&#8201;956 (60.5%) were women and 15&#8201;529 (85.8%) were White. There was minimal variation in the proportion of the total cohort who received a new gabapentinoid prescription by race and ethnicity (4.0% of Black patients, 3.3% of Hispanic patients, 3.6% of White patients, and 3.9% of all other groups). However, there was significant variation in prescribing by procedure type, with the most common procedure overall and the most common procedure in the new gabapentinoid prescription cohort being a total knee arthroplasty, followed by total hip arthroplasty and joint total shoulder and total knee arthroplasty (<xref rid="zoi230569t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Of the total cohort, 282 145 patients (57.0%) received a postoperative opioid prescription. Patients with a new gabapentinoid prescription received a median supply of 30 (IQR, 14-30) days.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="zoi230569t1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1. </label><caption><title>Overall Cohort for New Gabapentinoid Prescription</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="31.26%" span="1"/><col width="19.17%" span="1"/><col width="19.17%" span="1"/><col width="19.18%" span="1"/><col width="11.22%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristic</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Entire cohort (N&#8201;=&#8201;494&#8201;922)<xref rid="zoi230569t1n1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">New gabapentinoid prescription (n&#8201;=&#8201;18&#8201;095)<xref rid="zoi230569t1n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No gabapentinoid prescription (n&#8201;=&#8201;476&#8201;827)<xref rid="zoi230569t1n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value<xref rid="zoi230569t1n3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, mean (SD), y</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.7 (5.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.7 (5.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.8 (6.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="3" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Women</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">266&#8201;959 (53.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10&#8201;956 (4.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">256&#8201;003 (95.9)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Men</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">227 963 (46.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7139 (3.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220&#8201;824 (96.9)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Race and ethnicity</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="5" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">&lt;.01</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Black</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24&#8201;099 (4.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">969 (4.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23&#8201;130 (96.0)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hispanic</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25&#8201;359 (5.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">833 (3.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24&#8201;526 (96.7)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> White</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">425 753 (86.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15&#8201;529 (3.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">410&#8201;224 (96.4)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> All other<xref rid="zoi230569t1n4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19&#8201;711 (4.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">764 (3.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18&#8201;947 (96.1)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Charlson Comorbidity Index</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="5" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">200&#8201;734 (40.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8374 (4.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">192&#8201;360 (95.8)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1-2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">152&#8201;011 (30.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5406 (3.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">146&#8201;605 (96.4)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 3-4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78&#8201;246 (15.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2463 (3.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75&#8201;783 (96.9)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &#8805;5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63&#8201;931 (12.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1852 (2.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62&#8201;079 (97.1)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gabapentinoid supply, median (IQR), d</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (14-30)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (14-30)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Facility type</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="3" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Inpatient</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">301&#8201;676 (61.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14&#8201;516 (4.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">287&#8201;160 (95.2)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Outpatient</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">193&#8201;246 (39.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3579 (1.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">189&#8201;667 (98.1)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inpatient LOS, median (IQR), d</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1-3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1-3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1-3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Surgery planned</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="3" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">465&#8201;547 (94.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#8201;568 (3.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">447&#8201;979 (96.2)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29&#8201;375 (5.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">527 (1.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28&#8201;848 (98.2)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Care complexity (No. of physicians seen in prior 6 mo)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="5" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Quartile 1 (1-2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">125&#8201;520 (25.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5121 (4.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120&#8201;399 (95.9)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Quartile 2 (3-11)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">149&#8201;557 (30.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4430 (3.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">145&#8201;127 (97.0)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Quartile 3 (12-16)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97&#8201;058 (19.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3851 (4.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93&#8201;207 (96.0)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Quartile 4 (17-161)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">122&#8201;787 (24.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4693 (3.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">118&#8201;094 (96.2)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Abbreviations: LOS, length of stay; NA, not applicable.</p><fn id="zoi230569t1n1"><label>
<sup>a</sup>
</label><p>Unless otherwise indicated, data are expressed as No. (% of column total). Percentages have been rounded and may not total 100.</p></fn><fn id="zoi230569t1n2"><label>
<sup>b</sup>
</label><p>Unless otherwise indicated, data are expressed as No. (% of row total). Percentages have been rounded and may not total 100.</p></fn><fn id="zoi230569t1n3"><label>
<sup>c</sup>
</label><p>Calculated using <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> tests for continuous variables and &#967;<sup>2</sup> tests for categorical variables.</p></fn><fn id="zoi230569t1n4"><label>
<sup>d</sup>
</label><p>According to the Research Triangle Institute, this variable includes American Indian or Alaska Native, Asian or Pacific Islander, unknown, and other.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="zoi230569t2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2. </label><caption><title>Cohort by Procedure Type for New Gabapentinoid Prescription</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="49.39%" span="1"/><col width="18.94%" span="1"/><col width="19.48%" span="1"/><col width="12.19%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type of procedure</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Entire cohort, No. (%)</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">New gabapentinoid prescription, No. (%) undergoing procedure</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value<xref rid="zoi230569t2n1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Knee arthroplasty</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">129&#8201;056 (26.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7730 (6.0)</td><td rowspan="14" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total hip arthroplasty</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59&#8201;635 (12.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3513 (5.9)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total shoulder arthroplasty and total knee arthroplasty</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49&#8201;604 (10.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">366 (0.7)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lumbar laminotomy or lumbar laminectomy</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49&#8201;132 (9.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2269 (4.6)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cholecystectomy, laparoscopic</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40&#8201;199 (8.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1709 (4.3)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total shoulder arthroplasty and total hip arthroplasty</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31&#8201;722 (6.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">165 (0.5)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Initial inguinal hernia repair, open</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24&#8201;371 (4.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213 (0.9)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carotid endarterectomy</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#8201;928 (4.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">606 (2.8)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ventral hernia repair, open</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#8201;241 (4.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">283 (1.3)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total shoulder arthroplasty</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20&#8201;094 (4.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">838 (4.2)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Initial inguinal hernia repair, laparoscopic</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14&#8201;803 (3.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79 (0.5)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hysterectomy</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14&#8201;357 (2.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">109 (0.8)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prostatectomy, laparoscopic</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12&#8201;436 (2.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (0.5)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low anterior resection, laparoscopic</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6344 (1.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">148 (2.3)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="zoi230569t2n1"><label>
<sup>a</sup>
</label><p>Calculated using <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> tests for continuous variables and &#967;<sup>2</sup> tests for categorical variables.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><sec id="H2-5-ZOI230569"><title>Overall Trends</title><p>After adjusting for age, sex, race and ethnicity, and procedure type in each year, the rate of new postoperative gabapentinoid prescribing increased from 2.3% (95% CI, 2.2%-2.4%) in 2014 to 5.2% (95% CI, 5.0%-5.4%) in 2018 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001) (<xref rid="zoi230569f1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). The median supply of gabapentinoid decreased from 34 to 27 days over the entire period (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001). The rate of postoperative opioid prescribing among the total patient cohort increased from 56% (95% CI, 55%-56%) in 2014 to 59% (95% CI, 58%-60%) in 2018 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001) (<xref rid="zoi230569f2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). The rate of concomitant postoperative gabapentinoid and opioid prescribing increased from 1.6% (95% CI, 1.5%-1.7%) in 2014 to 4.1% (95% CI, 4.0%-4.3%) in 2018 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001). The OME was more variable, starting at a mean of 436 (IQR, 431-441) in 2014, increasing in 2015 to 471 (IQR, 466-476), then trending back down to 379 (IQR, 372-384) in 2018 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.01). An OME of 436 is equivalent to fifty-eight 5-mg tablets of oxycodone and an OME of 379 is equivalent to fifty-one 5-mg tablets of oxycodone.</p><fig position="float" id="zoi230569f1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1. </label><caption><title>Rate of New Postoperative Gabapentinoid Prescribing Over Time</title><p>Error bars indicate 95% CIs. </p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2318626-g001.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="zoi230569f2" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2. </label><caption><title>Rate of Postoperative Opioid Prescribing Over Time</title><p>Error bars indicate 95% CIs. OME indicates oral morphine equivalents.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2318626-g002.jpg"/></fig><p>Trends by medication groups included increases in both opioid and gabapentinoid prescribing during the study period. There was an increase in gabapentinoid-only prescribing from 0.7% (95% CI, 0.6%-0.7%) in 2014 to 1.1% (95% CI 1.0%-1.2%) in 2018 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001), a slight increase in opioid-only prescribing from 53.7% (95% CI, 53.3%-54%) in 2014 to 55.1% (95% CI, 54.7%-55.5%) in 2018 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001), and an increase in concomitant opioid and gabapentinoid prescribing from 1.6% (95% CI, 1.5%-1.7%) in 2014 to 4.1% (95% CI, 4.0%-4.3%) in 2018 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001). During the study period, patients undergoing surgery without a postoperative medication fill for an opioid and/or a gabapentinoid decreased from 43.6% (95% CI, 43.3%-43.9%) to 39.8% (95% CI, 39.4%-40.2%) in 2018 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001).</p></sec><sec id="H2-6-ZOI230569"><title>Trends by Procedure</title><p>After adjusting for age, sex, and race and ethnicity, the rates of new postoperative gabapentinoid prescribing increased in all procedure types over time (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001) except vascular (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;.65) from 2014 to 2018. Spine procedures started with the highest prescription rate of 4.4% in 2014, and in 2018 the procedure group with the highest rate was orthopedic at 7.3%. The orthopedic surgery group also represented the largest change both in absolute numbers and proportionally, going from 3.2% in 2014 to 7.3% in 2018. All procedure groups except vascular also had an increase in both opioid prescribing and concomitant opioid and gabapentinoid prescribing over time (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001). There was a statistically significant decrease over time (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001) of mean OME in all groups with the exception of vascular surgery, in which mean OME decrease was not significant over time (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;.05) (<xref rid="zoi230569f3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="zoi230569f3" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3. </label><caption><title>Estimated Gabapentinoid and Opioid Prescriptions by Procedure Over Time</title><p>Error bars indicate 95% CIs. OME indicates oral morphine equivalents.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2318626-g003.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="H1-4-ZOI230569"><title>Discussion</title><p>In this cross-sectional study of postoperative prescribing of gabapentinoids and opioids over time, we sought to describe trends in prescribing of these 2 medication groups as well as prescribing of concomitant opioids by examining nationally representative Medicare data. Overall, those who did and did not receive a new gabapentinoid prescription in the postoperative period were very similar across demographic characteristics. While many of the comparisons between the 2 cohorts were statistically significant, this likely reflects the large sample size and not necessarily a clinically meaningful difference between the groups.</p><p>Our results demonstrated a persistent increase in the prescribing of postoperative gabapentinoids over a 5-year period. Importantly, our results also reveal an increase in prescribing of postoperative opioids despite national attention to the opioid crisis and numerous studies that link opioid prescribing in the postoperative period with opioid use disorder. Finally, we also find a near tripling of concomitant gabapentinoid and opioid prescribing, all of which are statistically significant over time. The increase in the proportion of opioid prescribing over the same period persisted despite the increased use of gabapentinoids, medication meant to be opioid sparing. The increase in opioid prescribing may be balanced by the fact that OME per patient decreased; however, that decrease was only the equivalent of seven 5-mg tablets of oxycodone. These trends were reflected among patients from all racial and ethnic groups and almost all procedures.</p><p>The increase in gabapentinoid prescribing was especially notable in orthopedic procedures, while prescribing for spinal procedures started relatively high but did not increase as rapidly. Among various procedure types, the rate of change of gabapentinoid prescribing was only stable in vascular cases (carotid endarterectomy). The proportion of patients who had concomitant prescribing of gabapentinoids and opioids also rose in all procedural groups except vascular. Especially concerning is that a 2020 systematic review and meta-analysis<sup><xref rid="zoi230569r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> suggests that gabapentinoids do not in fact improve postoperative pain, though 68% of the included trials studied a single dose of gabapentinoid and 71% evaluated its use in the preoperative period, not the postoperative setting.</p><p>These findings are concerning given that the prescribing of opioids in the postoperative period has been found to increase the risk of prolonged use,<sup><xref rid="zoi230569r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> and the same has been described for gabapentinoid.<sup><xref rid="zoi230569r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> Further, the risk of prolonged opioid use has also been found with the use of any perioperative gabapentinoid.<sup><xref rid="zoi230569r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> We found that more older adults are being prescribed both of these medication types, either of which alone can be harmful, and together pose increased risks of respiratory depression and other adverse effects. Adverse events can occur for these medications, even in the setting of robust interventions to avoid them.<sup><xref rid="zoi230569r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> The findings are similar to others that show increasing rates of prescribing of nonopioid medications, including muscle relaxants.<sup><xref rid="zoi230569r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> Our findings suggest that the mean OME is decreasing, which may mitigate some of the danger of an increased number of patients being prescribed opioids, though that decrease may not be clinically meaningful. The proportion of opioid and OME prescribing is higher in the new gabapentinoid prescription group, suggesting that these patients are either in more pain or are receiving more pain medication than they need. In this cohort, gabapentinoid prescriptions do not appear to be reducing the proportion of patients who receive a postoperative prescription for an opioid. As has been described in prior studies,<sup><xref rid="zoi230569r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> given that the risks of gabapentinoids include prolonged use, greater attention is needed to ensure they are prescribed appropriately and that concomitant use is avoided.</p><sec id="H2-7-ZOI230569"><title>Limitations</title><p>Our study has several limitations. We may have missed patients who received their supply of medications from the hospital pharmacy, which is not captured in Part D data. We excluded patients with Medicare Advantage, as diagnosis data from outpatient visits can be harder to obtain, which may limit our generalizability to fee-for-service beneficiaries. Importantly, it can be difficult to capture outpatient and diagnosis data on these patients. However, our sample size remains large despite this exclusion to allow robust assessments of the non&#8211;Medicare Advantage population. The geographic region does not necessarily represent the prescriber&#8217;s geographic location but only that of the patients. However, as these regions are quite large, they may remain a useful framework for evaluating use in larger geographic distributions. Finally, our ability to detect differences between racial and ethnic groups is limited by the manner in which Medicare traditionally categorized patients and has low validity in some groups.<sup><xref rid="zoi230569r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> Because of this, certain racial and ethnic groups represented too small of a subgroup to meaningfully interpret the results and were therefore removed from the analysis by race and ethnicity. Due to availability of Medicare data, our analysis ended in 2018, so we were unable to assess whether there had been further changes in more recent years, especially given newer data on the lack of efficacy of gabapentinoids.<sup><xref rid="zoi230569r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> It is possible that although gabapentinoid prescribing was rising, it is now decreasing. Additionally, we did not study single-dose preoperative or inpatient use. We did not include patients from SNFs in our analysis, therefore our results cannot be generalized to this population. Of note, while our methods of assessing medication prescribing are based on established practice, it may not perfectly capture actual medication use, as this data set was not designed to do so.</p></sec></sec><sec id="H1-5-ZOI230569"><title>Conclusions</title><p>The findings of this cross-sectional study suggest that new postoperative gabapentinoid prescribing is rising, without a downward trend in the proportion of patients receiving postoperative opioid prescribing. In fact, there may be an increase in postoperative opioid prescribing despite national attention on the opioid crisis. Although we found a downward trend in the OME prescribed per patient, this decrease is small. The use of gabapentinoid as opioid sparing does not appear to spare the proportion of patients receiving postoperative prescriptions for opioids from a surgical procedure, which is concerning for a medication that has its own inherent risks, especially when used concomitantly with opioids. Finally, closer attention needs to be paid to postoperative prescribing for older adults, especially when using multiple types of medications that can have adverse effects and adverse drug events.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="REF-ZOI230569"><title>References</title><ref id="zoi230569r1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lubarsky</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Flood</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Patient preferences for acute pain treatment</article-title>. <source>Br J Anaesth</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>92</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>681</fpage>-<lpage>688</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bja/aeh123</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15003986</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230569r2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bongiovanni</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Marcum</surname><given-names>ZA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Perioperative gabapentin use in older adults: revisiting multimodal pain management</article-title>. <source>JAMA Intern Med</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>182</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1127</fpage>-<lpage>1128</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamainternmed.2022.3757</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36121647</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230569r3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Grover</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mathew</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yaddanapudi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sehgal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>A single dose of preoperative gabapentin for pain reduction and requirement of morphine after total mastectomy and axillary dissection: randomized placebo-controlled double-blind trial</article-title>. <source>J Postgrad Med</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>55</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>257</fpage>-<lpage>260</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0022-3859.58928</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20083871</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230569r4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hurley</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rowlingson</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The analgesic effects of perioperative gabapentin on postoperative pain: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Reg Anesth Pain Med</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>237</fpage>-<lpage>247</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00115550-200605000-00011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16701190</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230569r5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mishriky</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Waldron</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Habib</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Impact of pregabalin on acute and persistent postoperative pain: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Br J Anaesth</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>114</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>10</fpage>-<lpage>31</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bja/aeu293</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25209095</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230569r6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Inouye</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Marcantonio</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Perioperative gabapentin use and in-hospital adverse clinical events among older adults after major surgery</article-title>. <source>JAMA Intern Med</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>182</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1117</fpage>-<lpage>1127</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamainternmed.2022.3680</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36121671</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9486639</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230569r7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Verret</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lauzier</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zarychanski</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>; <collab>Canadian Perioperative Anesthesia Clinical Trials (PACT) Group</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Perioperative use of gabapentinoids for the management of postoperative acute pain: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Anesthesiology</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>133</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>265</fpage>-<lpage>279</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/ALN.0000000000003428</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32667154</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230569r8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Berian</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenthal</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Hospital standards to promote optimal surgical care of the older adult: a report from the Coalition for Quality in Geriatric Surgery</article-title>. <source>Ann Surg</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>267</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>280</fpage>-<lpage>290</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/SLA.0000000000002185</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28277408</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230569r9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>McKeown</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Pain management issues for the geriatric surgical patient</article-title>. <source>Anesthesiol Clin</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>563</fpage>-<lpage>576</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anclin.2015.05.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26315638</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230569r10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><collab>2019 American Geriatrics Society Beers Criteria Update Expert Panel</collab></person-group>. <article-title>American Geriatrics Society 2019 Updated AGS Beers Criteria for potentially inappropriate medication use in older adults</article-title>. <source>J Am Geriatr Soc</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>67</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>674</fpage>-<lpage>694</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30693946</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/jgs.15767</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230569r11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bykov</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bateman</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Franklin</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vine</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Patorno</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Association of gabapentinoids with the risk of opioid-related adverse events in surgical patients in the United States</article-title>. <source>JAMA Netw Open</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<elocation-id>e2031647</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.31647</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33372975</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7772715</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230569r12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bongiovanni</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Finlayson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Prolonged use of newly prescribed gabapentin after surgery</article-title>. <source>J Am Geriatr Soc</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>70</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>3560</fpage>-<lpage>3569</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jgs.18005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36000860</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9771946</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230569r13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Soprano</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hennessy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bilker</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Leonard</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Assessment of physician prescribing of muscle relaxants in the United States, 2005-2016</article-title>. <source>JAMA Netw Open</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<elocation-id>e207664</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.7664</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32579193</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7315288</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230569r14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Johansen</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Gabapentinoid use in the United States 2002 through 2015</article-title>. <source>JAMA Intern Med</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>178</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>292</fpage>-<lpage>294</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamainternmed.2017.7856</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29297045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5838608</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230569r15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kind</surname><given-names>AJH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Buckingham</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Making neighborhood-disadvantage metrics accessible&#8212;the Neighborhood Atlas</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>378</volume>(<issue>26</issue>):<fpage>2456</fpage>-<lpage>2458</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMp1802313</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29949490</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6051533</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230569r16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Thiels</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Habermann</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hooten</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jeffery</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Chronic use of tramadol after acute pain episode: cohort study</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>365</volume>:<fpage>l1849</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.l1849</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31088782</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6514531</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230569r17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Deiner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Westlake</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dutton</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Patterns of surgical care and complications in elderly adults</article-title>. <source>J Am Geriatr Soc</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>62</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>829</fpage>-<lpage>835</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jgs.12794</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24731176</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4024102</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230569r18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stearns</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Post-acute care locations: hospital discharge destination reports vs Medicare claims</article-title>. <source>J Am Geriatr Soc</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>68</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>847</fpage>-<lpage>851</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jgs.16308</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31880309</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230569r19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Charlson</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pompei</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ales</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>MacKenzie</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>A new method of classifying prognostic comorbidity in longitudinal studies: development and validation</article-title>. <source>J Chronic Dis</source>. <year>1987</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>373</fpage>-<lpage>383</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0021-9681(87)90171-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3558716</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230569r20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Deyo</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cherkin</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ciol</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Adapting a clinical comorbidity index for use with <italic toggle="yes">ICD-9-CM</italic> administrative databases</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>613</fpage>-<lpage>619</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0895-4356(92)90133-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1607900</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230569r21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">Research Data Assistance Center. Research Triangle Institute (RTI) Race Code. Accessed September 20, 2022. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://resdac.org/cms-data/variables/research-triangle-institute-rti-race-code" ext-link-type="uri">https://resdac.org/cms-data/variables/research-triangle-institute-rti-race-code</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230569r22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tighe</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lo-Ciganic</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Winterstein</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Perioperative use of gabapentinoids and risk for postoperative long-term opioid use in older adults undergoing total knee or hip arthroplasty</article-title>. <source>J Arthroplasty</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>2149</fpage>-<lpage>2157.e3</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arth.2022.05.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35577053</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9588599</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230569r23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">Oregon Pain Guidance. Opioid conversion calculator for morphine equivalents. <year>2023</year>. Accessed March 1, 2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.oregonpainguidance.org/opioidmedcalculator/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.oregonpainguidance.org/opioidmedcalculator/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230569r24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Graubard</surname><given-names>BI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Korn</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Predictive margins with survey data</article-title>. <source>Biometrics</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>55</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>652</fpage>-<lpage>659</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.0006-341X.1999.00652.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11318229</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230569r25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Brummett</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Waljee</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Goesling</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>New Persistent opioid use after minor and major surgical procedures in US adults</article-title>. <source>JAMA Surg</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>152</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<elocation-id>e170504</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamasurg.2017.0504</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28403427</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7050825</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230569r26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bongiovanni</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Steinman</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Adverse drug events after hospitalization&#8212;are we missing the mark?</article-title><source>JAMA Intern Med</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>181</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>618</fpage>-<lpage>619</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamainternmed.2020.9282</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33646266</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9258471</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230569r27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Billig</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sears</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gunaseelan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Inappropriate preoperative gabapentinoid use among patients with carpal tunnel syndrome</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Am</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>677</fpage>-<lpage>689.e5</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhsa.2020.04.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32487365</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7453721</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230569r28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jarr&#237;n</surname><given-names>OF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nyandege</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Grafova</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Validity of race and ethnicity codes in Medicare administrative data compared with gold-standard self-reported race collected during routine home health care visits</article-title>. <source>Med Care</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>58</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e1</fpage>-<lpage>e8</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MLR.0000000000001216</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31688554</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6904433</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><notes notes-type="supplementary-material" id="note-ZOI230569-1"><supplementary-material id="note-ZOI230569-1-s" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplement 1.</label><caption><p><bold>eTable 1.</bold> Included Surgical Procedures and Groupings</p><p><bold>eTable 2.</bold> List of Outpatient Procedures Using <italic toggle="yes">HCPCS</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">CPT</italic> codes and Inpatient Procedures Using <italic toggle="yes">ICD-9-CM</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">ICD-10-PCS</italic> Codes</p><p><bold>eFigure.</bold> Flowchart Inclusion Criteria</p><p><bold>eMethods 1.</bold> STROBE and RECORD Guideline Responses</p><p><bold>eMethods 2.</bold> Surgical Procedures Explanation</p><p><bold>eMethods 3.</bold> List of Opioids Used in Analysis</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2318626-s001.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplement 2.</label><caption><p>
Data Sharing Statement
</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2318626-s002.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></notes></back></article></pmc-articleset>