<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Contemp Clin Trials Commun</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Contemp Clin Trials Commun</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3365</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">cctc</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Contemporary Clinical Trials Communications</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2451-8654</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5898521</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC5898521.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">5898521</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">5898521</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29696224</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.conctc.2017.11.010</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2451-8654(17)30118-7</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Barriers to non-small cell lung cancer trial eligibility</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hardesty</surname><given-names initials="JJ">Jeffrey J.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kanarek</surname><given-names initials="NF">Norma F.</given-names></name><email>nkanarek@jhsph.edu</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#8727;</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Johns Hopkins University Bloomberg School of Public Health, USA</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, Geriatrics Department, USA</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, Sidney Kimmel Comprehensive Cancer Center, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#8727;</label>Corresponding author. Department of Environmental Health Sciences, Johns Hopkins University Bloomberg School of Public Health, 615 North Wolfe Street, Room E7541, Baltimore, MD 21205, USA. <email>nkanarek@jhsph.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>3</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>11</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">310423</issue-id><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>6</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>19</day><month>11</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>11</month><year>2017</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>24</day><month>11</month><year>2017</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>25</day><month>04</month><year>2018</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2018-04-28 05:15:29.320"><day>28</day><month>04</month><year>2018</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2017 Published by Elsevier Inc.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><copyright-holder/><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><abstract id="abs0010"><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Cancer clinical trial (CCT) enrollment is low potentially threatening the generalizability of trial results and expedited regulatory approvals. We assessed whether type of initial patient appointment for non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) is associated with CCT eligibility.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>Using a patient-to-accrual framework, we conducted a quasi-retrospective cohort pilot study at Sidney Kimmel Comprehensive Cancer Center (SKCCC), Baltimore, Maryland. 153 NSCLC patients new to SKCCC were categorized based on type of initial appointment: patients diagnosed or treated and patients seen for a consultation. CCT eligibility was determined by comparing eligibility criteria for each open trial to the electronic medical record (EMR) of each patient at every office visit occurring within 6-months of initial visit.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>We found no association between type of initial appointment and CCT eligibility (OR, 1.15; 95% CI, 0.49&#8211;2.73). Analyses did suggest current smokers were less likely to be eligible for trials compared to never smokers (OR, 0.15; 95% CI, 0.03&#8211;0.64), and stage 4 patients with second line therapy or greater were more likely to be eligible than stage 1 or 2 patients (OR, 5.18; 95% CI, 1.08&#8211;24.75). Additional analyses suggested most current smokers and stage 1 or 2 patients had trials available but were still ineligible.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>SKCCC has a diverse portfolio of trials available for NSCLC patients and should consider research strategies to re-examine eligibility criteria for future trials to ensure increased enrollment of current smokers and stage 1 or 2 patients. We could not confirm whether type of initial visit was related to eligibility.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Lung cancer</kwd><kwd>Trials</kwd><kwd>Eligibility</kwd><kwd>Barriers</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0010">Cancer clinical trial (CCT) enrollment has been low for decades and is a central issue in oncology because the profile of trial participants does not match the diversity found in treatment populations. CCTs differentially exclude minorities, female, and older patients threatening the generalizability of trial results and expedited regulatory approvals <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>.</p><p id="p0015">Patient-, physician-, and protocol-centered factors are known to affect CCT enrollment <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. A patient's willingness to enroll may depend on travel distance, treatment options, internet access, income, trust, and patient preferences <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. Known physician-centered factors include incompatibility of protocols with normal practice, lack of compliance with protocols, consent procedures, discussion of trials, timing of trial information presentation, and time constraints <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. Protocol-centered factors include limited trial availability and potentially overly restrictive eligibility criteria (e.g., prior cancer in early-stage or stage 4 lung cancer patients) <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>.</p><p id="p0020">Previous interventions to remove barriers to CCT enrollment have focused on physician- and patient-centered factors, like trial education and navigation systems <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. In practice, intervention benefits have been limited suggesting protocol-centered or more comprehensive interventions should be considered <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. For example, Ohio State University Comprehensive Cancer Center (OSUCCC) increased CCT enrollment 40% within two years by increasing oversight of the CCT process; educating stakeholders (e.g., patients, physicians, staff, leadership, etc.); ensuring CCTs are available irrespective of cancer type and stage of disease; and improving trial enrollment operations and infrastructure <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>.</p><p id="p0025">Building on the OSUCCC campaign, patient-to-accrual frameworks that address patient-, physician-, and protocol-centered factors have the potential to identify barriers and increase enrollment through subsequent interventions <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. According to one established framework, there are seven steps to enrollment <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>: trials must be available for a patient's cancer type, stage, and line of therapy <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, patient must be eligible for the trial(s) <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, physician must not triage the patient <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, physician must discuss the trial with the patient <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, patient must be interested <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, patient must sign a consent form, and <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref> patient must pass the final screen and enroll in the trial. Each step is conditional on the previous step <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. Therefore trial availability and eligibility are upstream steps and potential barriers to enrollment that would require institution- or protocol-specific interventions.</p><p id="p0030">Lung cancer is the number one cause of cancer-related death in the U.S. making it a research priority across the country, and, like other CCTs, enrollment is low <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. Given that National Cancer Institute (NCI) sponsored CCTs are listed online to help cancer patients determine their eligibility prior to seeking care, our primary goal was to assess whether type of initial appointment was related to CCT eligibility among a sample of non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) patients seen at Sidney Kimmel Comprehensive Cancer Center (SKCCC) <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. We hypothesized consult patients would have higher odds of eligibility compared to patients seen for a diagnosis or treatment because savvy patients may self-navigate to trials they believe they are eligible for <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. Secondary goals included assessing whether type of initial appointment or other factors were related to trial availability or eligibility conditional upon an available trial.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec2.1"><label>2.1</label><title>Study design</title><p id="p0035">A quasi-retrospective cohort design was used to investigate whether the type of initial appointment was related to trial eligibility at SKCCC. We examined each patient's electronic medical record (EMR) longitudinally for six months to determine trial availability and eligibility for each trial at every appointment. The date that eligibility screenings occurred in clinic was not recorded due to an assumption that each appointment was an opportunity to screen patients for eligibility.</p><p id="p0040">The Johns Hopkins School of Medicine Institutional Review Board approved this study.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><label>2.2</label><title>Study population</title><p id="p0045">NSCLC patients seen for their first appointment at a Baltimore-area NCI comprehensive cancer center from July 2012 through January 2013 were identified in the EMR as new patients (n&#160;=&#160;153). Each patient was followed in the EMR until they became eligible for a trial or they were administratively censored 6 months after their initial visit.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><label>2.3</label><title>Independent variables</title><p id="p0050">The independent variable was type of initial appointment, which was dichotomized: those seeking diagnosis or treatment at the initial appointment and those seeking a consult but no diagnosis or treatment at the initial appointment. The Johns Hopkins Hospital cancer registry categorized each study patient.</p><p id="p0055">Administrative staff at SKCCC recorded patients' smoking status (never, former, or current) and demographic data before the patients' initial visit. Patient demographics included: age at time of initial visit, sex (male or female), and race (white, black, or other races). It is presumed the patients self-reported their race. Each variable was abstracted from the EMR by one of the investigators (JH).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><label>2.4</label><title>Outcomes</title><p id="p0060">The primary outcome was clinical trial eligibility. Eligibility was determined by comparing eligibility criteria for each open trial with the EMR of each patient at each appointment until they were eligible for a trial or 6 months from their initial visit had passed.</p><p id="p0065">Secondary outcomes were trial availability and trial eligibility conditional on trial availability. Both were ascertained using the seven-step framework for CCT enrollment <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. More specifically, trial availability was determined by crosschecking each patient's NSCLC stage-and-line of therapy with a list of available trials at each appointment. Lists of available trials were provided for two time points (June 2012 and June 2013). Only patients with available trials were examined further for trial eligibility per the same abstraction protocol as the primary outcome.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><label>2.5</label><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="p0070">One NSCLC patient new to SKCCC had missing demographic values and was dropped from the data set after substantial efforts to locate the missing values were unsuccessful. Dropping one patient was not expected to influence the results. One hundred fifty-three NSCLC patients were included in the analyses.</p><p id="p0075">Before testing our primary hypothesis, we identified covariates and potential confounders. The literature suggested age, sex, and race were related to enrollment but was less conclusive regarding smoking status and cancer stage-and-line of therapy <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. Thus smoking status and stage-and-line of therapy were considered two potential confounders. Chi-square analyses were conducted to help identify relationships between these variables and our main exposure, appointment type, and our primary outcome, eligibility (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, respectively).<table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Baseline characteristics of NSCLC patients new to SKCCC.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Characteristic</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Diagnosis or treatment (n&#160;=&#160;67)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Consult only (n&#160;=&#160;86)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total (n&#160;=&#160;153)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">P value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age, y<break/>&lt;60<break/>60&#8211;69<break/>&gt;&#160;=&#160;70</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26 (38.8)<break/>21 (31.3)<break/>20 (29.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30 (34.9)<break/>35 (40.7)<break/>21 (24.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56 (36.6)<break/>56 (36.6)<break/>41 (26.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.48</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex, %<break/>Male<break/>Female</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32 (47.8)<break/>35 (52.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44 (51.2)<break/>42 (48.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">76 (49.7)<break/>77 (50.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.68</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Race<break/>White<break/>Black<break/>Other</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46 (68.7)<break/>16 (23.9)<break/>5 (7.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63 (73.3)<break/>11 (12.8)<break/>12 (14.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">109 (71.2)<break/>27 (17.6)<break/>17 (11.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Smoking status<break/>Never<break/>Former<break/>Current</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 (23.9)<break/>33 (49.3)<break/>18 (26.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 (27.9)<break/>52 (60.5)<break/>10 (11.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40 (26.1)<break/>85 (55.6)<break/>28 (18.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Stage and line of treatment<break/>Stage 1 or 2<break/>Stage 3<break/>Stage 4: first line therapy<break/>Stage 4: second line therapy or greater</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (16.4)<break/>16 (23.9)<break/>30 (44.8)<break/>10 (14.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (4.7)<break/>11 (12.8)<break/>25 (29.1)<break/>46 (53.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 (9.8)<break/>27 (17.6)<break/>55 (35.9)<break/>56 (36.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Eligibility<break/>Ineligible<break/>Eligible</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41 (61.2)<break/>26 (38.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36 (41.9)<break/>50 (58.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">77 (50.3)<break/>76 (49.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.18</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Baseline characteristics of NSCLC patients new to SKCCC.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0020">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Characteristic</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ineligible for trials (n&#160;=&#160;77)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Eligible for trials (n&#160;=&#160;76)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total (n&#160;=&#160;153)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">P value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age, y<break/>&lt;60<break/>60&#8211;69<break/>&gt;&#160;=&#160;70</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25 (32.5)<break/>28 (36.4)<break/>24 (31.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31 (40.8)<break/>28 (36.8)<break/>17 (22.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56 (36.6)<break/>56 (36.6)<break/>41 (26.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.40</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex, %<break/>Male<break/>Female</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43 (55.8)<break/>34 (44.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33 (43.4)<break/>43 (56.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">76 (49.7)<break/>77 (50.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.12</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Race<break/>White<break/>Black<break/>Other</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50 (64.9)<break/>18 (23.4)<break/>9 (11.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">59 (77.6)<break/>9 (11.8)<break/>8 (10.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">109 (71.2)<break/>27 (17.6)<break/>17 (11.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.15</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Smoking status<break/>Never<break/>Former<break/>Current</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17 (22.1)<break/>36 (46.8)<break/>24 (31.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23 (30.3)<break/>49 (64.5)<break/>4 (5.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40 (26.1)<break/>85 (55.6)<break/>28 (18.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Stage and line of treatment<break/>Stage 1 or 2<break/>Stage 3<break/>Stage 4: first line therapy<break/>Stage 4: second line therapy or greater</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 (15.6)<break/>24 (31.2)<break/>23 (29.9)<break/>18 (23.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (4.0)<break/>3 (4.0)<break/>32 (42.1)<break/>38 (50.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 (9.8)<break/>27 (17.6)<break/>55 (35.9)<break/>56 (36.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Type of initial appointment<break/>Diagnosis or treatment<break/>Consult only</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41 (53.3)<break/>36 (46.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26 (34.2)<break/>50 (65.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67 (43.8)<break/>86 (56.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0080">To test our primary hypothesis we created a multiple logistic regression model using the backwards selection method. Three separate models derived from the backwards selection were also compared using Akaike information criterion (AIC). The final model included the independent variable and all covariates and confounders: type of initial appointment, age, sex, race, smoking status, and cancer stage-and-line of therapy. A scatterplot of residuals versus fitted values was used to check model fit. Given that SKCCC has a smaller catchment area for African Americans, we also evaluated whether race modified the association between appointment type and eligibility using a likelihood ratio test <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>.</p><p id="p0085">To further examine the upstream steps or barriers to enrollment, we tested the relationships between type of initial appointment and trial availability and eligibility conditional on trial availability using chi-square analyses. Associations between significant confounders and secondary outcomes were also analyzed by chi-square analyses.</p><p id="p0090">Stata software, version 13 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.stata.com/" id="intref0010">http://www.stata.com</ext-link>) was used for all statistical analyses.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="sec3.1"><label>3.1</label><title>Study participants and baseline characteristics</title><p id="p0095">There were 834 oncology patients screened for inclusion into our study. 681 of which were excluded because they did not have NSCLC, had an appointment prior to our study start date, or were missing demographic data. The primary analysis was conducted on 153 NSCLC patients new to the SKCCC with an average age of 64.0 years (SD, 10.3 years).</p><p id="p0100">Of the 153 patients, 67 (43.8%) were diagnosed or scheduled for treatment at their first visit and 86 (56.2%) were not diagnosed or scheduled for treatment at their first visit because they were at the clinic for a consult only. Patients categorized by type of initial appointment differed significantly by smoking status and cancer stage-and-line of therapy (p&#160;=&#160;0.05 and p&#160;&lt;&#160;0.001, respectively) (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><label>3.2</label><title>Covariates and potential confounders</title><p id="p0105">Previous studies have found that age, sex, and race are related to patient comorbidities and clinical trial enrollment <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. Therefore we adjusted for these covariates in our examination of the hypothesis. According to the chi-square analyses, smoking status and stage-and-line of therapy were related to the independent variable and the primary outcome supporting the notion they confound the relationship between initial appointment type and eligibility (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Further investigation of these relationships were carried out in the model-building portion of our analysis.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><label>3.3</label><title>Logistic regression</title><p id="p0110">Multiple logistic regression was used to assess the relationship between type of initial appointment and eligibility, and the final model was built using the backwards selection method. The final logistic regression model examined eligibility as function of type of initial appointment, age, sex, race, smoking status, and stage-and-line of therapy and suggested both smoking status and stage-and-line of therapy were confounders.</p><p id="p0115">Three models were derived from the backwards selection. The full model contained six variables; another contained all variables except for smoking status; and the last model contained all variables except for stage-and-line of therapy. The AIC results confirmed that the full model contained the least variation attributed to error and was the best overall fit.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.4"><label>3.4</label><title>Types of initial appointment and eligibility</title><p id="p0120">After adjusting for the covariates and confounders, there was no statistically significant relationship between type of initial appointment and trial eligibility (Odds Ratio [OR], 1.32; 95% Confidence Interval [CI], 0.57&#8211;3.07) (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).<table-wrap id="tbl3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Results of multiple logistic regression analyses: Eligibility for NSCLC clinical trials.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0025">Table 3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Covariates</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">P value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age, y<break/>&lt;60<break/>60&#8211;69<break/>&gt;&#160;=&#160;70</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ref<break/>0.66 (0.26&#8211;1.63)<break/>0.56 (0.20&#8211;1.51)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ref<break/>0.36<break/>0.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex, %<break/>Male<break/>Female</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ref<break/>1.44 (0.63&#8211;3.32)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ref<break/>0.39</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Race<break/>White<break/>Black<break/>Other</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ref<break/>0.67 (0.22&#8211;2.06)<break/>0.48 (0.13&#8211;1.79)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ref<break/>0.49<break/>0.27</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Smoking status<break/>Never<break/>Former<break/>Current</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ref<break/>0.85 (0.29&#8211;2.48)<break/>0.15 (0.03&#8211;0.64)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ref<break/>0.77<break/>0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Stage and line of treatment<break/>Stage 1 or 2<break/>Stage 3<break/>Stage 4: first line therapy<break/>Stage 4: second line therapy or greater</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ref<break/>0.36 (0.06&#8211;2.30)<break/>4.43 (0.99&#8211;19.94)<break/>5.18 (1.08&#8211;24.75)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ref<break/>0.28<break/>0.05<break/>0.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Type of initial appointment<break/>Diagnosis or treatment<break/>Consult only</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ref<break/>1.32 (0.57&#8211;3.07)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ref<break/>0.51</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Wald Test: Age (p&#160;=&#160;0.47), Race (p&#160;=&#160;0.44), Smoking status (p&#160;=&#160;0.02), and Stage-and-line of treatment (p&#160;&lt;&#160;0.0001).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0125">While race may be an important modifier of the association between appointment type and eligibility, the likelihood ratio test comparing the null versus extended model did not suggest it influenced the relationship (p&#160;=&#160;0.63).</p></sec><sec id="sec3.5"><label>3.5</label><title>Other variables and eligibility</title><p id="p0130">Despite failing to reject the null hypothesis, we discovered other potentially important associations that merit attention. Current smokers, for instance, appear to be far less likely to be eligible for trials than never smokers after adjustment (OR, 0.15; 95% CI, 0.03&#8211;0.64) (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Stage 4 NSCLC patients receiving 1st line therapy appear 4.43 times more likely than stage 1 or 2 patients to be eligible for trials (OR, 4.43; 95% CI, 0.99 to 19.94). Stage 4 patients receiving 2nd line therapy or greater were 5.18 times more likely than stage 1 or 2 patients to be eligible for trials (OR, 5.18; 95% CI, 1.08 to 24.75).</p></sec><sec id="sec3.6"><label>3.6</label><title>Upstream associations examined further</title><p id="p0135">To this point, we have focused on trial eligibility. In the following analyses, we examined the relationship between our independent variables and trial availability and the relationship between independent variables and trial eligibility conditional on trial availability <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. Relationships between the variables, smoking status and stage-and-line of therapy, and the secondary outcomes were also assessed. The main purpose for conducting these analyses was to better understand the upstream effects preventing certain patients from moving past the eligibility phase of the enrollment process.</p><p id="p0140">Our study population contained 28 current smokers. Of these, 25 (89%) had an available trial. Only 4 (16%) with an available trial were eligible for a CCT (<xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). Out of the 15 stage 1 or 2 patients, 15 (100%) had an available trial, but only 3 (20%) with an available trial were eligible for a trial.<table-wrap id="tbl4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Additional analyses of NSCLC patients using patient-to-Accrual framework.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0030">Table 4</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Characteristic</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Not available (n&#160;=&#160;13)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Available (n&#160;=&#160;140)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">P value</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Available but not eligible (n&#160;=&#160;64)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Available and eligible (n&#160;=&#160;76)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">P value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Smoking status<break/>Never<break/>Former<break/>Current</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0)<break/>10 (76.9)<break/>3 (23.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40 (28.6)<break/>75 (53.6)<break/>25 (17.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.08</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17 (26.6)<break/>26 (40.6)<break/>21 (32.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23 (30.3)<break/>49 (64.5)<break/>4 (5.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Stage and line of treatment<break/>Stage 1 or 2<break/>Stage 3<break/>Stage 4: First line therapy<break/>Stage 4: Second line therapy or greater</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0)<break/>12 (92.3)<break/>1 (7.7)<break/>0 (0.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 (10.7)<break/>15 (10.7)<break/>54 (38.6)<break/>56 (40.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 (18.8)<break/>12 (18.8)<break/>22 (34.4)<break/>18 (28.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (4.0)<break/>3 (4.0)<break/>32 (42.1)<break/>38 (50.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Type of initial appointment<break/>Diagnosis or treatment<break/>Consult only</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (76.9)<break/>3 (23.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57 (40.7)<break/>83 (59.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.012</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31 (48.4)<break/>33 (51.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26 (34.2)<break/>50 (65.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.09</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0145">The chi-square analyses suggested unadjusted relationships between the variables, stage-and-line of therapy and type of initial appointment, and trial availability (p&#160;&lt;&#160;0.0001 and p&#160;=&#160;0.01, respectively). It also suggested significant unadjusted relationships between the variables, smoking status and stage-and-line of therapy, and eligibility (p&#160;&lt;&#160;0.0001 and p&#160;&lt;&#160;0.0001, respectively).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0150">We found no evidence of an association between type of initial appointment and eligibility for NSCLC clinical trials after adjustment. However we did find the odds of eligibility were 85% lower for current smokers compared to never smokers, and the odds of eligibility were 343% greater for patients with stage 4&#8211;1st line therapy and 418% greater for patients with stage 4&#8211;2nd line therapy or greater compared to stage 1 or 2 patients.</p><p id="p0155">Upstream steps to trial enrollment, like eligibility, have the potential to limit the overall number of patients and to protect research subjects from unnecessary harm. The key is maintaining an ethical balance that translates to generalizable and safe NSCLC research <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. In addition, Beaver et al., 2017 correctly states, &#8220;the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) regulations state that a &#8216;protocol is required to contain &#8230; the criteria for patient selection and for exclusion of patients&#8217; but do not contain detailed language regarding clinical trial eligibility criteria. Regulatory approval, however, must be predicated on data pertinent to the enrolled patients and relevant to the U.S. population and U.S. medical practice.&#8221; Ethically conducted interventions based on eligibility criteria have the potential to increase CCT enrollment, address generalizability issues, and safely expedite FDA approval of prescribing information <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. It is therefore important to carefully describe the ineligible CCT populations; investigate the reason(s) they are not eligible; conduct studies to determine whether the criteria can be eased in future clinical trials without harming participants; and disseminate the results to principal investigators and Institutional Review Boards <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>.</p><p id="p0160">In this particular pilot study, current smokers and stage 1 or 2 patients had trials available but were disproportionately ineligible for trials. Current smokers may have been disproportionately ineligible due to poorer performance status, more severe comorbidities, previous therapies, recent NSCLC diagnosis, or a number of other trial-specific reasons. Stage 1 or 2 patients were likely disproportionately ineligible due to past medical history (i.e., previous case of cancer), previous treatment, or tumor size-based inclusion criteria. A more thorough investigation at SKCCC is needed, but it is possible that criteria, such as prior cases of cancer, may be unnecessarily restricting clinical trial enrollment at SKCCC. For instance, previous studies have found that patients with prior cases of cancer represent a sizeable proportion of cancer patients yet prior cases of cancer do not increase risks for clinical trial participants. Therefore we believe that future studies should aim to: prospectively identify criteria causing current smokers and stage 1 or 2 to be excluded at the eligibility step of enrollment; identify potentially modifiable eligibility criteria; test whether it is safe to modify the criteria; and monitor future enrollment after implementation of the modified criteria <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>.</p><p id="p0165">To our knowledge, this is the only study that has examined the relationship between type of initial appointment and NSCLC-specific trial eligibility. All variables were abstracted twice to verify accuracy. The primary outcome was abstracted by crosschecking all verifiable eligibility criteria for each open trial to each patient's EMR. The outcome abstraction was repeated at every office visit during the study period to more accurately reflect the enrollment process and avoid visit-related biases.</p><p id="p0170">We acknowledge several important limitations. This was a pilot study with a small sample size, which increased the probability of finding significant associations by chance alone. The chart review was conducted at a single comprehensive cancer center limiting the external validity. For practical reasons, the study was retrospective preventing us from controlling the study conditions. The list of available trials may not have been comprehensive because it was not possible to know exactly when new trials were added and old trials removed. Finally, residual confounding cannot be ruled out because variables, such as distance to SKCCC and phase of clinical trials, were not abstracted.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><label>5</label><title>Conclusions</title><p id="p0175">The SKCCC has a diverse portfolio of trials available for NSCLC patients but should consider using research strategies to re-examine eligibility criteria for future trials to ensure more inclusive enrollment of current smokers and stage 1 or 2 patients. Future research should prospectively identify criteria causing current smokers and stage 1 or 2 to be excluded at the eligibility step of enrollment; identify potentially modifiable eligibility criteria; test whether it is safe to modify the criteria; and monitor future enrollment after implementation of the modified criteria.</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><label>6</label><title>Conflicts of interest and source of funding</title><p id="p0180">This work was supported in part by the <funding-source id="gs4">Maryland Cigarette Restitution</funding-source> Fund at <funding-source id="gs5">Johns Hopkins Sidney Kimmel Comprehensive Cancer Center</funding-source> Support Grant from the <funding-source id="gs6">National Cancer Institute</funding-source> (P30 CA006973), and the <funding-source id="gs7">Medical Students Training in Aging Research Program</funding-source> (T35AG026758). Funders did not influence study design, data collection, analysis, interpretation of data, writing of the manuscript, or the decision to submit for publication.</p></sec><sec id="sec7"><title>Disclaimers</title><p id="p0185">The views expressed in the article are those of the authors only and are not an official position of the institutions or funders.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murthy</surname><given-names>V.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krumholz</surname><given-names>H.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>G.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Participation in cancer clinical trials: race-, sex-, and age-based disparities</article-title><source>JAMA J. Am. Med. Assoc.</source><volume>291</volume><issue>22</issue><year>2004</year><fpage>2720</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.291.22.2720</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15187053</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beaver</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ison</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pazdur</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reevaluating eligibility criteria - balancing patient protection and participation in oncology trials</article-title><source>N. Engl. J. Med.</source><volume>376</volume><issue>16</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>1504</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28423289</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMp1615879</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seely</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rachlis</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Barriers to participation in clinical trials of cancer: a meta-analysis and systematic review of patient-reported factors</article-title><source>Lancet Oncol.</source><volume>7</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2006</year><fpage>141</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16455478</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S1470-2045(06)70576-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kanarek</surname><given-names>N.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>H.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Metzger-Gaud</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Geographic proximity and racial disparities in cancer clinical trial participation</article-title><source>J. Natl. Compr. Cancer Netw.</source><volume>8</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>1343</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.6004/jnccn.2010.0102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3201828</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21147901</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sateren</surname><given-names>W.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trimble</surname><given-names>E.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abrams</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How sociodemographics, presence of oncology specialists, and hospital cancer programs affect accrual to cancer treatment trials</article-title><source>J. Clin. Oncol.</source><volume>20</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2002</year><fpage>2109</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11956272</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1200/JCO.2002.08.056</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shavers</surname><given-names>V.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>C.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burmeister</surname><given-names>L.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Racial differences in factors that influence the willingness to participate in medical research studies</article-title><source>Ann. Epidemiol.</source><volume>12</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2002</year><fpage>248</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11988413</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s1047-2797(01)00265-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schramm</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hillis</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Patient internet use surrounding cancer clinical trials: clinician perceptions and responses</article-title><source>Contemp. Clin. Trials</source><volume>31</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>229</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20227523</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cct.2010.03.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2858243</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Unger</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gralow</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Albain</surname><given-names>K.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramsey</surname><given-names>S.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hershman</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Patient income level and cancer clinical trial participation: a prospective survey study</article-title><source>JAMA Oncol.</source><volume>2</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>137</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26468994</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamaoncol.2015.3924</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4824189</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mc Grath-Lone</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Day</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schoenborn</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exploring research participation among cancer patients: analysis of a national survey and an in-depth interview study</article-title><source>BMC Cancer</source><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26341736</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12885-015-1628-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4560870</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tannenbaum</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gl&#252;ck</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hurley</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Antoni</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Participation in cancer clinical trials: why are patients not participating?</article-title><source>Med. Decis. Mak.</source><volume>34</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>116</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/0272989X13497264</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23897588</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tournoux</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Katsahian</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chevret</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factors influencing inclusion of patients with malignancies in clinical trials</article-title><source>Cancer</source><volume>106</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2006</year><fpage>258</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16397866</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/cncr.21613</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Logan</surname><given-names>J.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of factors affecting successful clinical trial enrollment in the context of three prospective, randomized, controlled trials</article-title><source>Int. J. Radiat. Oncol. Biol. Phys.</source><volume>97</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>770</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28244413</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ijrobp.2016.11.035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5901977</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pruitt</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laccetti</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xuan</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Halm</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gerber</surname><given-names>D.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Revisiting a longstanding clinical trial exclusion criterion: impact of prior cancer in early-stage lung cancer</article-title><source>Br. J. Cancer</source><volume>116</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>717</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28196065</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/bjc.2017.27</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5355931</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laccetti</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pruitt</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xuan</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Halm</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gerber</surname><given-names>D.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of prior cancer on outcomes in advanced lung cancer: implications for clinical trial eligibility and accrual</article-title><source>J. Natl. Cancer Inst.</source><issue>4</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>107</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/jnci/djv002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4402360</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25667420</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rearden</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanlon</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ulrich</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brooks-Carthon</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sommers</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Examining differences in opportunity and eligibility for cancer clinical trial participation based on sociodemographic and disease characteristics</article-title><source>Oncol. Nurs. Forum</source><volume>43</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>57</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26679445</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1188/16.ONF.57-66</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5934287</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kimmick</surname><given-names>G.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>B.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kornblith</surname><given-names>A.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improving accrual of older persons to cancer treatment trials: a randomized trial comparing an educational intervention with standard information: CALGB 360001</article-title><source>J. Clin. Oncol.</source><volume>23</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2005</year><fpage>2201</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15800312</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1200/JCO.2005.01.222</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moffitt</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brogan</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Statewide cancer clinical trial navigation service</article-title><source>J. Oncol. Pract.</source><volume>6</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20808555</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1200/JOP.200006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2868637</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Denicoff</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCaskill-Stevens</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grubbs</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The national cancer institute-american society of clinical oncology cancer trial accrual symposium: summary and recommendations</article-title><source>J. Oncol. Pract.</source><volume>9</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>267</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24130252</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1200/JOP.2013.001119</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3825288</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paskett</surname><given-names>E.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reeves</surname><given-names>K.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McLaughlin</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recruitment of minority and underserved populations in the United States: the centers for population health and health disparities experience</article-title><source>Contemp. Clin. Trials</source><volume>29</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>847</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18721901</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cct.2008.07.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2642621</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramaswamy</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beisler</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A comprehensive program for the enhancement of accrual to clinical trials</article-title><source>Ann. Surg. Oncol.</source><volume>23</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>2146</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26790668</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1245/s10434-016-5091-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>D.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Major</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lyonga</surname><given-names>D.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alleyne</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clayton</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increasing minority patient participation in cancer clinical trials using oncology nurse navigation</article-title><source>Am. J. Surg.</source><volume>203</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>415</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21996347</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.amjsurg.2011.02.005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kanarek</surname><given-names>N.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kanarek</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olatoye</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carducci</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Removing barriers to participation in clinical trials, a conceptual framework and retrospective chart review study</article-title><source>Trials</source><volume>13</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>237</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23227880</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1745-6215-13-237</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3551829</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Center for Disease Control and Prevention</surname></name></person-group><chapter-title>Lung Cancer. Lung Cancer Web Site</chapter-title><year>2014</year><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/cancer/lung/" id="intref0020">http://www.cdc.gov/cancer/lung/</ext-link><comment>Updated</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>National Institutes of Health</surname></name></person-group><chapter-title>National Cancer Institute, Office of Communications. Cancer Clinical Treatment Trials: Informational Preferences of Patients and Their Families002E</chapter-title><year>1996</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref25"><source>Find NCI-supported Clinical Trials - National Cancer Institute</source><year>2017</year><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/clinical-trials/search" id="intref0025">https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/clinical-trials/search</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref26"><source>National Cancer Institute. Clinical Trials</source><year>2015</year><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cancer.gov/clinicaltrials" id="intref0030">http://www.cancer.gov/clinicaltrials</ext-link><comment>Updated</comment></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="appsec1" sec-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><title>Supplementary data</title><p id="p0195">The following is the supplementary data related to this article:<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>mmc1</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc1.xml" position="float" orientation="portrait"><alt-text>mmc1</alt-text></media></supplementary-material></p></sec><ack id="ack0010"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Dina Lansey, MSN, RN, OCN and Dr. Michael Carducci, MD, Johns Hopkins School of Medicine, for their helpful advice on the study concept and design. Additionally, we thank <funding-source id="gs1">Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health</funding-source>, <funding-source id="gs2">Johns Hopkins School of Medicine</funding-source>, and <funding-source id="gs3">Sidney Kimmel Comprehensive Cancer Center</funding-source> for their support of this research.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="appsec2" fn-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><p id="p0200">Supplementary data related to this article can be found at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.conctc.2017.11.010" id="intref0015">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.conctc.2017.11.010</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article></pmc-articleset>