<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Biosci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Biosci. Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1915</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bsr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">BSR</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Bioscience Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0144-8463</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1573-4935</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Portland Press Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6239252</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC6239252.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">6239252</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">6239252</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30341251</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BSR20180702</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Articles</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>42</subject><subject>39</subject><subject>15</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The association between rs16917496 T/C polymorphism of <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> gene and cancer risk in Asian populations: a meta-analysis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names initials="HX">Hui-Xia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="afn1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names initials="GX">Guo-Xiang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="afn1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names initials="JK">Ju-Kun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="afn1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names initials="LJ">Lian-Jie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2799-5901</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="YP">Yu-Pei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1"/></contrib><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Anesthesiology and Stomatology, Taihe Hospital, Hubei University of Medicine, Shiyan 442000, China</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of 4th Cadres Ward, PLA Army General Hospital, Beijing100700, China</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Department of Oral and Maxillary Surgery, Guizhou Provincial People&#8217;s Hospital, Guiyang 550002, China</aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Trade union, Taihe Hospital, Hubei University of Medicine, Shiyan 442000, China</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="COR1"><bold>Correspondence:</bold> Yu-Pei Wang (<email>2862204732@qq.com</email>)</corresp><fn id="afn1" fn-type="equal"><label>*</label><p>These authors contributed equally to the present work.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epreprint"><day>19</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>21</day><month>12</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>38</volume><issue>6</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">324163</issue-id><elocation-id>BSR20180702</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>07</day><month>5</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>30</day><month>9</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>14</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>28</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-11-05 17:25:33.103"><day>05</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2018 The Author(s).</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><ali:license_ref>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article published by Portland Press Limited on behalf of the Biochemical Society and distributed under the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License 4.0 (CC BY)</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="bsr-38-bsr20180702.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="bsr-38-bsr20180702.pdf"/><abstract><p>Epidemiological studies have demonstrated close associations between <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> rs16917496 T/C polymorphism and cancer risk, but the results of published studies were not consistent. We therefore performed this meta-analysis to explore the associations between rs16917496 T/C polymorphism and cancer risk. Five online databases were searched. Odds ratios (ORs) with a 95% confidence interval (CI) were calculated to assess the association between rs16917496 T/C polymorphism and cancer risk. In addition, heterogeneity, accumulative, sensitivity analysis, and publication bias were conducted to check the statistical power. Overall, 13 publications involving 5878 subjects were identified according to included criteria. No significant cancer risk was observed in genetic model of <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> rs16917496 T/C polymorphism in Asian populations (C vs. T: OR = 1.04, 95%CI = 0.88&#8211;1.23, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.63%; TC vs. TT: OR = 1.17, 95%CI = 0.96&#8211;1.24, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.11%; CC vs. TT: OR = 0.90, 95%CI = 0.60&#8211;1.37, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.63; TC+CC vs. TT: OR = 1.11, 95%CI = 0.90&#8211;1.38, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.33; CC vs. TT+TC: OR = 0.92, 95%CI = 0.65&#8211;1.30, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.63). Furthermore, similar associations were found in the subgroup analysis of race diversity, control design, genotyping methods, and different cancer types. In summary, our meta-analysis indicated that the <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> rs16917496 T/C polymorphism may not play a critical role in cancer development in Asian populations.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>cancer</kwd><kwd>miR-502</kwd><kwd>polymorphism</kwd><kwd>rs16917496</kwd><kwd>SET8</kwd></kwd-group><counts><page-count count="10"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Cancer is one of the most common causes of death, second only to cardiovascular disease [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. In 2012, more than 14.1 million people suffered from cancer and 8.2 million people died from the disease worldwide. In China, approximately 4,292,000 new cancer cases and 2,814,000 cancer deaths were recorded in 2015 [<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Surgery, radiotherapy, and chemotherapy are the most important cancer treatments [<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3&#8211;5</xref>]. However, these methods induce harmful side effects in patients, and the resulting damage to the treated tissues and organs causes considerable physical dysfunction as well as a reduction in quality of life. As a result, cancer and its complications are major mental and economic burdens for patients and their families. To date, the etiology and pathogenesis of cancer have been extensively explored, but the underlying mechanisms remain unclear [<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Prior studies indicate that environmental pollution [<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], unhealthy living habits [<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], viral infection [<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], and radioactive exposure [<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] may contribute to tumorigenesis.</p><p>The diversity in cancer susceptibility within different populations has also not yet been explained. Molecular studies have proposed that genetic factors may play an important role in tumorigenesis [<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. One potential genetic factor, SET domain-containing protein 8 (<italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic>), encodes H4 lysine 20 monomethyltransferase, which is present in mitotic cell chromosomes and belongs to the family of methyltransferases contained in the SET domain. <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> could be involved in multiple biological processes, such as gene transcriptional regulation, genome replication genomic stability, and cell cycle management [<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Many studies have indicated that increased expression of <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> can suppress the transcriptional activation of the p53 protein and inhibit cell apoptosis. It also promotes tumor invasion and migration by enhancing the epithelial&#8211;mesenchymal transition (EMT) [<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. The aberrant expression or dysfunction of <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> may affect cell cycle progression and alter an individual&#8217;s cancer risk, resulting in a close association between <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> and the risks of various cancers [<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. In addition, some studies have reported that <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> is a target gene of many miRNAs during the development of cancer, including miR-502, miR-382, miR-335, miR-127-3p, and miR-7. Ma found that <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> expression was upregulated in glioma cells and that there is a significant inverse correlation between SET8 expression and miR-382 [<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Zhang et al. reported that <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> was directly regulated by miR-127-3p, with miR-127-3p overexpression resulting in decreased expression of <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> and reduced migration and invasion of osteosarcoma cells [<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Yu et al. also observed that miRNA-7 is a negative regulator of <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> and further inhibits H4K20 monomethylation to suppress EMT and the invasive potential of breast cancer cells [<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. This evidence suggests that <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> may be a potential molecular target for the prevention and treatment of cancers.</p><p>Single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) are the most common genetic variations in the human genome. The rs16917496 T/C polymorphism is the most important variant locus located in sequences of the 3&#8217;-untranslated region (UTR) of the <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> mRNA, which influences reorganization and binding to miR-502. In 2009, Song et al. reported the first case&#8211;control study in a Chinese population with breast cancer; results suggest that the miR-502 binding site (rs16917496 T/C polymorphism) of <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> contributes to an increased breast cancer risk at an early age [<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Since then, a series of epidemiological studies have been conducted to investigate the association between the rs16917496 T/C polymorphism and cancer risk; however, the results are inconsistent. Therefore, we conducted this meta-analysis to more precisely and comprehensively assess the association between the <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> rs16917496 T/C polymorphism and cancer risk.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><p>This meta-analysis was designed and performed according to the guidelines of the preferred reporting items for systematic reviews and meta-analyses compliant statement [<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. All included data were collected from published studies and no ethical issues were involved.</p><sec id="sec2-1"><title>Search strategy</title><p>We searched three English databases (PubMed, Embase, and Science Citation Index) and two Chinese databases (CNKI and Wanfang) for relevant studies that were conducted prior to December 1, 2017 and investigated the association between <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> rs16917496 T/C polymorphism and cancer risk. The bibliographies of the included studies were reviewed to identify additional studies. The following search terms and strategy were used (e.g. in PubMed):</p><p>#1 SET8</p><p>#2 SETD8</p><p>#3 microRNA-502</p><p>#4 miR-502</p><p>#5 rs16917496</p><p>#6 #1 OR #2 OR #3 OR #4 OR #5</p><p>#7 polymorphism</p><p>#8 variant</p><p>#9 mutation</p><p>#10 #7 OR #8 OR #9</p><p>#11 cancer</p><p>#12 tumor</p><p>#13 neoplasm</p><p>#14 #11 OR #12 OR #13</p><p>#15 #6 AND #10 AND #14</p></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title>Eligibility criteria</title><p>Studies were selected according to the following criteria: (1) they should be case&#8211;control studies that investigated the association between <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> rs16917496 T/C polymorphism and cancer risk; (2) studies should provide sufficient data on genotype distribution which could be used to evaluate odds ratios (ORs) and 95% confidence intervals (CIs); (3) studies were published either in English or Chinese; and (4) publications included the largest or most recent sample data available when overlapping or duplicate data were published on the same item.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-3"><title>Data extraction</title><p>Two authors (Wei and Wang) reviewed the qualified studies and extracted the following information: the name of the first author, publishing date, country or region of the subjects, race of the subjects, control design, sample sizes, genotype distribution of cases and controls, genotyping method, and cancer type. Modified Newcastle&#8211;Ottawa scale (NOS) was employed by the first two authors in order to evaluate the quality of the included studies according to the publication of Niu et al. [<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. The scores ranged from 0 (worst) to 10 points (best). Studies with a score of 7 or higher were classified as high quality (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec2-4"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Crude ORs and 95% CIs were calculated to evaluate the association between <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> rs16917496 T/C polymorphism and cancer risk. Hardy&#8211;Weinberg equilibrium (HWE) was assessed in the controls by using genotype frequencies of the <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> rs16917496 T/C polymorphism with the &#967;<sup>2</sup> test. Five genetic models, namely allele contrast (C vs. T), co-dominant (TC vs. TT and CC vs. TT), dominant (TC+CC vs. TT), and recessive models (CC vs. TT+TC) were used. Heterogeneity was assessed among the included studies by using Cochran&#8217;s Q test and <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> statistical method [<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. The random-effect model (DerSimonian and Laird method) was adopted when the <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> value was greater than 40%; otherwise, the fixed-effect model (Mantel&#8211;Haenszel method) was applied [<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Subgroup analysis was conducted on HWE status, race, control design, sex, genotyping method, and cancer type. Meta-regression analysis was performed using the genetic modes to determine between-group heterogeneity. Cumulative and sensitivity analyses were conducted to examine possible changes when single studies were omitted. Potential publication bias was assessed with Egger&#8217;s linear regression and Begg&#8217;s funnel plots [<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. All statistical analyses were conducted with STATA version 14.0 (Stata Corporation, College Station, TX, U.S.A.). A two-sided <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec3"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec3-1"><title>Study characteristics</title><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref> provides a schematic representation of the selection process. A total of 147 articles were identified through online search; of these, 76 studies were excluded due to article duplication, and 48 studies were excluded after the abstracts and full texts were reviewed. Finally, 13 studies involving 2866 patients and 3012 controls were included in our meta-analysis [<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31&#8211;42</xref>]. All of the subjects in these thirteen studies were from Asian countries, including nine case&#8211;control studies involving 2212 cases and 2314 controls conducted in Chinese populations [<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31&#8211;35</xref>,<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>], and four case&#8211;control studies involving 654 cases and 698 controls conducted in Iranian populations [<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Population-based controls were used in seven studies [<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31&#8211;33</xref>,<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35&#8211;37</xref>] and hospital-based controls were used in six studies [<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38&#8211;42</xref>]. Seven studies used the polymerase chain reaction-restriction fragment length polymorphism method [<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35&#8211;37</xref>,<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], five studies used the polymerase chain reaction-restriction sequencing method [<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>], and one study used the polymerase chain reaction-ligase detection method [<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Furthermore, three studies focused on digestive system cancer [<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], two studies on lung cancer [<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], and two studies on ovarian cancer [<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Only seven studies satisfied the HWE of the genotype distributions in the control groups. All characteristics of the included studies are presented in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Flow diagram of the study selection process</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bsr-38-bsr20180702-g1.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Characteristics of included studies on <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> rs16917496 T/C polymorphism and cancer risk</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">First author</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Year</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Country /Region</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Race</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source of controls</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</th><th colspan="6" align="center" rowspan="1">Genotype distribution</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genotyping methods</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for HWE<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T1TFN1"><sup>*</sup></xref></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAF in control</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NOS</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">Case</th><th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">Control</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TT</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TC</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TT</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TC</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Song [<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2009</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">East Asia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1079</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">504</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">491</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">115</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">518</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">475</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">104</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR-RFLP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Guo [<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">East Asia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">133</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">142</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR-sequencing</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wang [<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">East Asia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">342</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">344</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">160</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">155</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">167</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">132</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR-sequencing</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ding [<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">East Asia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR-LDR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zhao [<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">East Asia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR-sequencing</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yang [<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2014</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">East Asia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">164</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">199</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">102</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR-RFLP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hashemi [<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2014</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Western Asia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">115</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">108</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR-RFLP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yang [<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2014</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">East Asia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">114</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">200</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">111</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR-RFLP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zhang [<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2017</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">East Asia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">140</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">130</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR-sequencing</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RCC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Narouie [<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2017</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Western Asia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">169</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">182</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR-RFLP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mosallayi [<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2017</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Western Asia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">170</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">170</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR-RFLP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Li [<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2017</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">East Asia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR-sequencing</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parchami Barjui [<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2017</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Western Asia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">240</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">231</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">183</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">172</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR-RFLP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T1TFN1"><label>*</label><p>HWE in control</p></fn><fn><p>Abbreviations: ALL, acute lymphoblastic leukemia; BC, breast cancer; CC, cervical cancer; CRC, colorectal cancer; ESC, esophageal cancer; HB, hospital-based; HC, hepatocellular cancer; LC, lung cancer; MAF, minor allele frequency in control group; OC, ovarian cancer; PB, population-based; PC, prostate cancer; PCR-LDR, polymerase chain reaction-ligase detection reaction; PCR-RFLP, created restriction site-restriction fragment length polymorphism; PCR-sequencing, polymerase chain reaction-sequencing; RCC, renal cell carcinoma.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec3-2"><title>Quantitative and subgroup analyses</title><p>Overall, no significant association was observed between the <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> rs16917496 T/C polymorphism and cancer risk in all five genetic models in Asian populations (C vs. T: OR = 1.04, 95%CI = 0.88&#8211;1.23, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.63, <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 72.3%; TC vs. TT: OR = 1.17, 95%CI = 0.96&#8211;1.24, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.11, <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 50.0%; CC vs. TT: OR = 0.90, 95%CI = 0.60&#8211;1.37, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.63, <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 76.9%; TC+CC vs. TT: OR = 1.11, 95%CI = 0.90&#8211;1.38, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.33, I<sup>2</sup> = 64.0%, (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>); CC vs. TT+TC: OR = 0.92, 95%CI = 0.65&#8211;1.30, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.63, <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 73.9%) (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> and Supplementary Figure S1). Furthermore, no significant association was found between the <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> rs16917496 T/C polymorphism and cancer risk in the subgroup analysis of HWE status, race diversity, control design, and sex. Few protective effects of the <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> rs16917496 T/C polymorphism against cancer development were found in the PCR-sequencing subgroup (CC vs. TT: OR = 0.61, 95%CI = 0.44&#8211;0.86, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.01, <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 18.6%; CC vs. TT+TC: OR = 0.59, 95%CI = 0.37&#8211;0.94, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.03, <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 41.0%) and ovarian cancer subgroup (CC vs. TT: OR = 0.59, 95%CI = 0.37&#8211;0.94, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.03, <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0%; CC vs. TT+TC: OR = 0.52, 95%CI = 0.33&#8211;0.82, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.01, <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0%). Heterogeneity was observed in all five genotype models. Meta-regression analysis was conducted with all stratified factors, but no critical factors were found to contribute to heterogeneity (e.g. TC+CC vs. TT model: <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.23 for HWE status, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.78 for race diversity, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.82 for control design, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.60 for sex, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.81 for genotyping methods and <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.98 for cancer type).</p><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>OR and 95% CIs of the associations between <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> rs16917496 T/C polymorphism and cancer risk in TC+CC vs. TT model</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bsr-38-bsr20180702-g2.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Summary ORs and 95% CI of <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> rs16917496 T/C polymorphism and cancer risk</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="5" align="center" rowspan="1">C vs. T</th><th colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1">TC vs. TT</th><th colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1">CC vs. TT</th><th colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1">TC+CC vs. TT</th><th colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1">CC vs. TT+TC</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">N</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T2TFN1">*</xref></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> (%)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> (%)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> (%)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> (%)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Total</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88&#8211;1.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96&#8211;1.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60&#8211;1.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90&#8211;1.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65&#8211;1.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>HWE status</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98&#8211;1.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98&#8211;1.66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85&#8211;1.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86&#8211;1.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92&#8211;1.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70&#8211;1.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74&#8211;1.47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29&#8211;1.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62&#8211;1.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41&#8211;1.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Race</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83&#8211;1.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99&#8211;1.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57&#8211;1.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95&#8211;1.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54&#8211;1.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77&#8211;1.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47&#8211;2.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27&#8211;2.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44&#8211;2.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57&#8211;2.47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Design</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87&#8211;1.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95&#8211;1.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60&#8211;1.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85&#8211;1.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68&#8211;1.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74&#8211;1.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84&#8211;1.87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37&#8211;1.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44&#8211;1.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42&#8211;1.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sex</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81&#8211;1.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88&#8211;1.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41&#8211;1.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83&#8211;1.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44&#8211;1.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Genotyping</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR-RFLP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88&#8211;1.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83&#8211;1.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57&#8211;1.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79&#8211;1.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73&#8211;1.74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR sequencing</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76&#8211;1.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95&#8211;1.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44&#8211;0.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83&#8211;1.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37&#8211;0.94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Type</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DSC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86&#8211;1.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79&#8211;1.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73&#8211;1.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81&#8211;1.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70&#8211;1.66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63&#8211;1.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48&#8211;1.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15&#8211;2.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40&#8211;1.58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29&#8211;1.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51&#8211;1.58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63&#8211;1.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24&#8211;2.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55&#8211;1.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27&#8211;1.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76&#8211;1.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98&#8211;1.71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37&#8211;0.94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86&#8211;1.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33&#8211;0.82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Abbreviations: DSC, digestive system cancer; HB, hospital-based; LC, lung cancer; OC, ovarian cancer; PB, population-based; PCR-RFLP, created restriction site-restriction fragment length polymorphism.</p></fn><fn id="T2TFN1"><label>*</label><p>Numbers of comparisons</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Scale for quality evaluation</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Criteria</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Score</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Representativeness of cases</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Consecutive/randomly selected cases with clearly defined sampling frame</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Not consecutive/randomly selected case or without clearly defined sampling frame</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Not described</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Source of controls</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Population- or Healthy-based</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Hospital-based</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Not described</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>HWE in controls</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;HWE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Hardy&#8211;Weinberg disequilibrium</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Not available</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Genotyping examination</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Genotyping done under &#8216;blinded&#8217; condition and repeated again</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Genotyping done under &#8216;blinded&#8217; condition or repeated again</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Unblinded done or not mentioned and unrepeated</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Association assessment</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Assess association between genotypes and cancer with appropriate statistics and adjustment for confounders</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Assess association between genotypes and cancer with appropriate statistics and without adjustment for confounders</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Inappropriate statistics used</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec3-3"><title>Cumulative and sensitivity analyses</title><p>Cumulative analysis indicated a consistent and negative tendency accompanied by the continuously published studies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref> for TC+CC vs. TT model) (Supplementary Figure S2). Sensitivity analysis was performed by omitting each study one at a time, and the results did not indicate significant changes in the statistical analysis results (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref> for TC+CC vs. TT model) (Supplementary Figure S3).</p><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Cumulative meta-analyses according to publication year in TC+CC vs. TT model of <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> rs16917496 T/C polymorphism</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bsr-38-bsr20180702-g3.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Sensitivity analysis through deleting each study to reflect the influence of the individual dataset to the pooled ORs in TC+CC vs. TT model of <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> rs16917496 T/C polymorphism</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bsr-38-bsr20180702-g4.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec3-4"><title>Publication bias</title><p>Publication bias was examined using the Begg&#8217;s test and no apparent asymmetry of the funnel plot was found (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref> for TC+CC vs. TT model) (Supplementary Figure S4). These results were confirmed using Egger&#8217;s test (C vs. T: <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.90; TC vs. TT: <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.95; CC vs. TT: <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.48; TC+CC vs. TT: <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.83; CC vs. TT+TC: <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.77).</p><fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Funnel plot analysis to detect publication bias for TC+CC vs. TT model of <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> rs16917496 T/C polymorphism</title><p>Circles represent the weight of the studies.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bsr-38-bsr20180702-g5.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec4"><title>Discussion</title><p>To date, cancer is still one of the most dangerous diseases worldwide. The improvement in cancer detection and treatments has resulted in decreased incidence and mortality rates of several cancer types. However, the etiology of cancer development, including both the molecular mechanisms and individual susceptibility, remains unclear.</p><p>MicroRNA (miRNA) is a highly conservative small non-coding RNA. It facilitates post-transcriptional mRNA expression and results in targeted mRNA degradation by base-paired binding to complementary sequences of the 3&#8217;-UTR of the target mRNA. SNPs, important variations in single-nucleotide sequences in a genome, contribute to genetic variations and influence the cancer susceptibility of individuals. SNPs in miRNA binding sites have been associated with cancer risk and outcomes. Alterations in these sites could modify the binding sites or change the binding affinity, leading to escape from miRNA regulation [<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>].</p><p><italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> (also known as <italic toggle="yes">SETD8</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">PR-SET7</italic>), located in chromosome 12q24.31, has various functions in multiple biological processes [<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45&#8211;47</xref>]. Rs16917496 T/C is the most common SNP locus located in the 3&#8242;-UTR of the <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> gene. Since 2009, several studies on SNPs and cancer risk have been published. Song et al. reported an increased risk in CC genotype that contributed to the early development of breast cancer (OR = 1.66, 95%CI = 106&#8211;2.61) [<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Yang et al. [<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] and Narouie et al. [<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] reported that the C allele may increase the risk of cervical and prostate cancers in Chinese and Indian populations. In contrast, Yang et al. indicated that the TT genotype presents an increased lung cancer risk compared with the CC genotype in a Chinese population (OR = 2.17, 95%CI = 1.05&#8211;4.52) [<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Moreover, Mosallayi et al. demonstrated the apparent association of increased colorectal cancer risk with the TT+TC genotypes based on smoking status among Turkish subjects (OR = 5.8, 95%CI = 1.37&#8211;24.34) [<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. However, several studies also reported a negative association between the rs16917496 T/C polymorphism and cancer risk [<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. All these results suggest that rs16917496 T/C may have an apparent linkage with carcinogenesis.</p><p>The contradictory results in the association of rs16917496 T/C polymorphism and cancer risk could be due to the following: (1) studied populations were from different countries and of different ethnicities; (2) different genotyping methods were used; (3) the genotype distributions in the controls in some studies deviate from HWE; and (4) control groups were not consistent. Therefore, we conducted this meta-analysis using the current 13 case&#8211;control studies involving 5878 subjects to assess the association between <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> rs16917496 T/C polymorphism and cancer susceptibility. To the best of our knowledge, the present study is the first meta-analysis that focused on <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> rs16917496 T/C polymorphism and cancer risk. The results showed no significant association between <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> rs16917496 T/C polymorphism and cancer susceptibility in Asian populations. A negative association was also found through analysis in the stratified groups. This meta-analysis utilized scientific retrieval strategy and rigorous statistic methodologies, such as cumulative, sensitivity, and meta-regression analyses.</p><p>The present study presents the following advantages: (1) it was the first and latest analysis that focused on the relationship between <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> rs16917496 T/C polymorphism and cancer risk and included comprehensive stratified analysis; (2) systematic and comprehensive retrieval strategies were conducted to collect all published studies carefully and avoid the omission of related research; (3) sensitivity, accumulation, and meta-regression analyses were conducted to identify factors affecting inconsistencies in the results; (4) Egger&#8217;s test and Begg&#8217;s funnel plots were conducted and did not detect any publication bias. However, the present work also presents several limitations that should be addressed in future studies: (1) only one SNP locus of rs16917496 T/C was investigated in this meta-analysis, and the interactions between relative polymorphism loci and gene-environment were not conducted with the current data; (2) the included sample size was small and widely distributed, which could influence the results and lead to incorrect conclusions; (3) subjects in the included studies were all Asian (from East Asia and West Asia), so ethnicity bias was inevitable and affected the results; (4) heterogeneity existed in some genetic models, and the subsequent meta-regression analysis could not identify interfering factors.</p><p>In summary, our analyses suggest that <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> rs16917496 T/C polymorphism is not a candidate genetic factor for cancer susceptibility. Considering the current limitations of this meta-analysis, further studies with larger sample sizes and participants of multiple ethnicities should be conducted to clarify the association between <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> rs16917496 T/C polymorphism and cancer risk.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec5"><title>Supporting information</title><fig id="F6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Supplementary Figure S1</label><caption><p>OR and 95% CIs of the associations between <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> rs16917496 T/C polymorphism and cancer risk (A for C vs. T model; B for TC vs. TT model; C for CC vs. TT model; D for CC vs. TT+TC model).</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="pdf" xlink:href="bsr20180702_Supp1.pdf" orientation="portrait" id="d35e2526" position="anchor"/></fig><fig id="F7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Supplementary Figure S2</label><caption><p>Cumulative meta-analyses according to publication year in <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> rs16917496 T/C polymorphism and cancer risk (A for A vs. G model; B for GA vs. GG model; C for AA vs. GG model; D for AA vs. GG+GA model).</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="pdf" xlink:href="bsr20180702_Supp1.pdf" orientation="portrait" id="d35e2536" position="anchor"/></fig><fig id="F8" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Supplementary Figure S3</label><caption><p>Sensitivity analysis through deleting each study to reflect the influence of the individual dataset to the pooled ORs in <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> rs16917496 T/C polymorphism and cancer risk (A for C vs. T model; B for TC vs. TT model; C for CC vs. TT model; D for CC vs. TT+TC model).</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="pdf" xlink:href="bsr20180702_Supp1.pdf" orientation="portrait" id="d35e2546" position="anchor"/></fig><fig id="F9" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Supplementary Figure S4</label><caption><p>Funnel plot analysis to detect publication bias in <italic toggle="yes">SET8</italic> rs16917496 T/C polymorphism and cancer risk (A for C vs. T model; B for TC vs. TT model; C for CC vs. TT model; D for CC vs. TT+TC model).</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="pdf" xlink:href="bsr20180702_Supp1.pdf" orientation="portrait" id="d35e2556" position="anchor"/></fig></sec></body><back><sec id="sec6" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work.</p></sec><sec id="sec7" sec-type="author-contrib"><title>Author contribution</title><p>W.H.X. and W.Y.P. conceived the study. W.H.X. and S.J.K. searched the databases and extracted the data. T.G.X. and W.Y.P. analysed the data. W.H.X., T.G.X., and S.J.K. wrote the draft of the paper. Y.L.J. and W.Y.P. reviewed the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="sec8" sec-type="funding"><title>Funding</title><p>The authors declare that there are no sources of funding to be acknowledged.</p></sec><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list list-content="abbreviations"><def-item><term>CI</term><def><p>confidence interval</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EMT</term><def><p>epithelial&#8211;mesenchymal transition</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HWE</term><def><p>Hardy&#8211;Weinberg equilibrium</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NOS</term><def><p>Newcastle&#8211;Ottawa scale</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OR</term><def><p>odds ratio</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SNP</term><def><p>single-nucleotide polymorphism</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>UTR</term><def><p>untranslated region</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Torre</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferlay</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lortet-Tieulent</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Jemal</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Global cancer statistics, 2012</article-title>. <source>CA Cancer J. Clin.</source><volume>65</volume>, <fpage>87</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3322/caac.21262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25651787</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baade</surname><given-names>P.D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Cancer statistics in China, 2015</article-title>. <source>CA Cancer J. Clin.</source><volume>66</volume>, <fpage>115</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3322/caac.21338</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26808342</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>K.D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Panjwani</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Elmously</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Afaneh</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fahey</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Predicting survival and response to treatment in gastroesophageal neuroendocrine tumors: an analysis of the National Cancer Database</article-title>. <source>Ann. Surg. Oncol.</source><volume>25</volume>, <fpage>1418</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1424</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1245/s10434-018-6389-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29476295</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirke</surname><given-names>D.N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qureshi</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kamran</surname><given-names>S.C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ezzat</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jalisi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Salama</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Role of adjuvant chemoradiotherapy in T4N0 stage IV head and neck cancer: a National Cancer Database analysis</article-title>. <source>Head Neck</source><volume>40</volume>, <fpage>1174</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hed.25087</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29417687</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Amsbaugh</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yusuf</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cash</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Silverman</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Potts</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Dunlap</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Effect of time to simulation and treatment for patients with oropharyngeal cancer receiving definitive radiotherapy in the era of risk stratification using smoking and human papillomavirus status</article-title>. <source>Head Neck</source><volume>40</volume>, <fpage>687</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>695</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hed.24963</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29356189</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Renaud</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seitlinger</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guerrera</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reeb</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beau-Faller</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Voegeli</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Prognostic value of Exon 19 versus 21 <italic toggle="yes">EGFR</italic> mutations varies according to disease stage in surgically resected non-small cell lung cancer adenocarcinoma</article-title>. <source>Ann. Surg. Oncol.</source><volume>25</volume>, <fpage>1069</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1078</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1245/s10434-018-6347-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29362963</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Functional role of lncRNA LOC101927497 in N-methyl-N&#8217;-nitro-N-nitrosoguanidine-induced malignantly transformed human gastric epithelial cells</article-title>. <source>Life Sci.</source><volume>193</volume>, <fpage>93</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lfs.2017.12.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29223541</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nkanga</surname><given-names>M.S.N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Longo-Mbenza</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adeniyi</surname><given-names>O.V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ngwidiwo</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Katawandja</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kazadi</surname><given-names>P.R.B.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Ageing, exposure to pollution, and interactions between climate change and local seasons as oxidant conditions predicting incident hematologic malignancy at KINSHASA University clinics, Democratic Republic of CONGO (DRC)</article-title>. <source>BMC Cancer</source><volume>17</volume>, <fpage>559</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12885-017-3547-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28835214</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5569529</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Q.C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>C.Z.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.Q.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Attributable causes of colorectal cancer in China</article-title>. <source>BMC Cancer</source><volume>18</volume>, <fpage>38</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12885-017-3968-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29304763</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5756355</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gessner</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Borkowetz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baier</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gohlert</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilhelm</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thumbs</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Detection of HPV16 in esophageal cancer in a high-incidence region of Malawi</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Mol. Sci.</source><volume>19</volume>, <fpage>E557</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms19020557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29439548</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5855779</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>W.H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>I.F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>P.W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>30 years follow-up and increased risks of breast cancer and leukaemia after long-term low-dose-rate radiation exposure</article-title>. <source>Br. J. Cancer</source><volume>117</volume>, <fpage>1883</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1887</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/bjc.2017.350</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28972968</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5729469</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bignell</surname><given-names>G.R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Edkins</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clegg</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Mutations of the <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> gene in human cancer</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>417</volume>, <fpage>949</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>954</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature00766</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12068308</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>L.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ostermeyer</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Szabo</surname><given-names>C.I.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dowd</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>E.D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rowell</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Confirmation of <italic toggle="yes">BRCA1</italic> by analysis of germline mutations linked to breast and ovarian cancer in ten families</article-title>. <source>Nat. Genet.</source><volume>8</volume>, <fpage>399</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>404</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng1294-399</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7894493</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jorgensen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schotta</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Sorensen</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Histone H4 lysine 20 methylation: key player in epigenetic regulation of genomic integrity</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>41</volume>, <fpage>2797</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2806</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkt012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23345616</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3597678</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nikolaou</surname><given-names>K.C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moulos</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chalepakis</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hatzis</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oda</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reinberg</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Spontaneous development of hepatocellular carcinoma with cancer stem cell properties in PR-SET7-deficient livers</article-title>. <source>EMBO J.</source><volume>34</volume>, <fpage>430</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>447</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15252/embj.201489279</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25515659</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4330999</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Veschi</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Voss</surname><given-names>T.C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ozbun</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gryder</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Epigenetic siRNA and chemical screens identify SETD8 inhibition as a therapeutic strategy for p53 activation in high-risk neuroblastoma</article-title>. <source>Cancer Cell</source><volume>31</volume>, <fpage>50</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ccell.2016.12.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28073004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5233415</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nourbakhsh</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Emadi-Baygi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Salehi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Nikpour</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Gene expression analysis of two epithelial&#8211;mesenchymal transition-related genes: long noncoding RNA-ATB and SETD8 in gastric cancer tissues</article-title>. <source>Adv. Biomed. Res.</source><volume>7</volume>, <fpage>42</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/abr.abr_252_16</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29657927</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5887690</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>MiR-502/SET8 regulatory circuit in pathobiology of breast cancer</article-title>. <source>Cancer Lett.</source><volume>376</volume>, <fpage>259</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>267</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.canlet.2016.04.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27080302</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>X.L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Z.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X.L.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>G.F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>SET8 expression is associated with overall survival in gastric cancer</article-title>. <source>Genet. Mol. Res.</source><volume>14</volume>, <fpage>15609</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>15615</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4238/2015.December.1.12</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26634528</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Downregulation of SETD8 by miR-382 is involved in glioma progression</article-title>. <source>Pathol. Res. Pract.</source><volume>214</volume>, <fpage>356</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>360</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.prp.2018.01.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29487005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chai</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>MicroRNA-127-3p inhibits proliferation and invasion by targeting SETD8 in human osteosarcoma cells</article-title>. <source>Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun.</source><volume>469</volume>, <fpage>1006</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1011</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbrc.2015.12.067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26707641</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huangyang</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>microRNA-7 suppresses the invasive potential of breast cancer cells and sensitizes cells to DNA damages by targeting histone methyltransferase SET8</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><volume>288</volume>, <fpage>19633</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>19642</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M113.475657</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23720754</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3707664</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>An miR-502-binding site single-nucleotide polymorphism in the 3&#8217;-untranslated region of the SET8 gene is associated with early age of breast cancer onset</article-title>. <source>Clin. Cancer Res.</source><volume>15</volume>, <fpage>6292</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6300</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-09-0826</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19789321</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moher</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liberati</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tetzlaff</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>D.G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Preferred reporting items for systematic reviews and meta-analyses: the PRISMA statement</article-title>. <source>J. Clin. Epidemiol.</source><volume>62</volume>, <fpage>1006</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1012</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2009.06.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19631508</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>Y.M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>R.X.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>J.Z.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>X.Y.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Systematic review by multivariate meta-analyses on the possible role of tumor necrosis factor-alpha gene polymorphisms in association with ischemic stroke</article-title>. <source>Neuromolecular Med.</source><volume>17</volume>, <fpage>373</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>384</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12017-015-8365-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26231680</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huedo-Medina</surname><given-names>T.B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez-Meca</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marin-Martinez</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Botella</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Assessing heterogeneity in meta-analysis: Q statistic or I2 index?</article-title><source>Psychol. Methods</source><volume>11</volume>, <fpage>193</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>206</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/1082-989X.11.2.193</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16784338</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>DerSimonian</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Laird</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Meta-analysis in clinical trials</article-title>. <source>Control. Clin. Trials</source><volume>7</volume>, <fpage>177</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0197-2456(86)90046-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3802833</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mantel</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Haenszel</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1959</year>) <article-title>Statistical aspects of the analysis of data from retrospective studies of disease</article-title>. <source>J. Natl. Cancer Inst.</source><volume>22</volume>, <fpage>719</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>748</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13655060</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Egger</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davey Smith</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Minder</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Bias in meta-analysis detected by a simple, graphical test</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source><volume>315</volume>, <fpage>629</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>634</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.315.7109.629</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9310563</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2127453</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Begg</surname><given-names>C.B.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Mazumdar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Operating characteristics of a rank correlation test for publication bias</article-title>. <source>Biometrics</source><volume>50</volume>, <fpage>1088</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2533446</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7786990</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>A polymorphism at the miR-502 binding site in the 3&#8217;-untranslated region of the histone methyltransferase SET8 is associated with hepatocellular carcinoma outcome</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Cancer</source><volume>131</volume>, <fpage>1318</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1322</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ijc.27352</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22095217</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>A polymorphism at the miR-502 binding site in the 3&#8217; untranslated region of the SET8 gene is associated with the risk of epithelial ovarian cancer</article-title>. <source>Cancer Genet.</source><volume>205</volume>, <fpage>373</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>376</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cancergen.2012.04.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22867998</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>A polymorphism at the miR-502 binding site in the 3&#8217; untranslated region of the SET8 gene is associated with the outcome of small-cell lung cancer</article-title>. <source>Exp. Ther. Med.</source><volume>3</volume>, <fpage>689</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>692</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3892/etm.2012.469</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22969952</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3438626</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <comment>A polymorphism at the miR-502 binding site in the 3&#8217;-untranslated region of the SET8 gene is associated with clinical characteristics and the prognosis of esophageal cancer [M]. Hebei Medical University, 2013</comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Association of miR-502-binding site single nucleotide polymorphism in the 3&#8217;-untranslated region of SET8 and TP53 codon 72 polymorphism with non-small cell lung cancer in Chinese population</article-title>. <source>Acta Biochim. Biophys. Sin. (Shanghai)</source><volume>46</volume>, <fpage>149</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>154</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/abbs/gmt138</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24374662</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hashemi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sheybani-Nasab</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Naderi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roodbari</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Taheri</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Association of functional polymorphism at the miR-502-binding site in the 3&#8217; untranslated region of the SETD8 gene with risk of childhood acute lymphoblastic leukemia, a preliminary report</article-title>. <source>Tumour Biol.</source><volume>35</volume>, <fpage>10375</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>10379</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13277-014-2359-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25048968</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>S.D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Y.L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>J.X.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Association of a miR-502-binding site single nucleotide polymorphism in the 3&#8217;-untranslated region of SET8 and the TP53 codon 72 polymorphism with cervical cancer in the Chinese population</article-title>. <source>Asian Pac. J. Cancer Prev.</source><volume>15</volume>, <fpage>6505</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6510</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7314/APJCP.2014.15.16.6505</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25169478</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>miR-502-mediated histone methyltransferase SET8 expression is associated with clear cell renal cell carcinoma risk</article-title>. <source>Oncol. Lett.</source><volume>14</volume>, <fpage>7131</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29250163</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3892/ol.2017.7115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5727589</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Narouie</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ziaee</surname><given-names>S.A.M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Basiri</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Hashemi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Functional polymorphism at the miR-502-binding site in the 3&#8217; untranslated region of the SETD8 gene increased the risk of prostate cancer in a sample of Iranian population</article-title>. <source>Gene</source><volume>626</volume>, <fpage>354</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gene.2017.05.060</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28578017</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mosallayi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simonian</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khosravi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Salehi</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khodadoostan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sebghatollahi</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Polymorphism (rs16917496) at the miR-502 Binding Site of the Lysine Methyltransferase 5A (SET8) and Its Correlation with Colorectal Cancer in Iranians</article-title>. <source>Adv. Biomed. Res.</source><volume>6</volume>, <fpage>77</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28808643</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4103/2277-9175.210656</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5539672</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>T.H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>An observational study between the single nucleotide polymorphisms of SET8 gene rs16917496 loci and epithelial ovarian cancer risk (Chinses)</article-title>. <source>J. Shandong Med.</source><volume>59</volume>, <fpage>51</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>53</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parchami Barjui</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reiisi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ebrahimi</surname><given-names>S.O.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Shekari</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Study of correlation between genetic variants in three microRNA genes (hsa-miR-146a, hsa-miR-502 binding site, hsa-miR-27a) and breast cancer risk</article-title>. <source>Curr. Res. Transl. Med.</source><volume>65</volume>, <fpage>141</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>147</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.retram.2017.10.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29128203</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pirooz</surname><given-names>H.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jafari</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rastegari</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fathi-Roudsari</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tasharrofi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shokri</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Functional SNP in microRNA-491-5p binding site of MMP9 3&#8217;-UTR affects cancer susceptibility</article-title>. <source>J. Cell Biochem.</source><volume>119</volume>, <fpage>5126</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5134</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/jcb.26471</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29091292</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schneiderova</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Naccarati</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pardini</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rosa</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gaetano</surname><given-names>C.D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jiraskova</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>MicroRNA-binding site polymorphisms in genes involved in colorectal cancer etiopathogenesis and their impact on disease prognosis</article-title>. <source>Mutagenesis</source><volume>32</volume>, <fpage>533</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>542</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/mutage/gex026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29048575</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duronio</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>MacAlpine</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Methylation of histone H4 lysine 20 by PR-Set7 ensures the integrity of late replicating sequence domains in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>44</volume>, <fpage>7204</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27131378</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkw333</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5009726</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Houston</surname><given-names>S.I.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McManus</surname><given-names>K.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sims</surname><given-names>J.K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>P.B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hendzel</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Catalytic function of the PR-Set7 histone H4 lysine 20 monomethyltransferase is essential for mitotic entry and genomic stability</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><volume>283</volume>, <fpage>19478</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>19488</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M710579200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18480059</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2443654</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kapoor-Vazirani</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Vertino</surname><given-names>P.M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>A dual role for the histone methyltransferase PR-SET7/SETD8 and histone H4 lysine 20 monomethylation in the local regulation of RNA polymerase II pausing</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><volume>289</volume>, <fpage>7425</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7437</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M113.520783</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24459145</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3953257</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>