<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Rheumatol Ther</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Rheumatol Ther</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3008</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">rheuther</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Rheumatology and Therapy</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2198-6576</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2198-6584</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7211223</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC7211223.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">7211223</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">7211223</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">32227284</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40744-020-00201-y</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">201</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Real-World Persistence with Tocilizumab Compared to Other Subcutaneous Biologic Disease-Modifying Antirheumatic Drugs Among Patients with Rheumatoid Arthritis Switching from Another Biologic</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Best</surname><given-names initials="JH">Jennie H.</given-names></name><address><email>best.jennie@gene.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vlad</surname><given-names initials="SC">Steven C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tominna</surname><given-names initials="L">Lenore</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbass</surname><given-names initials="I">Ibrahim</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/04gndp242</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 5899 3818</institution-id><institution>Genentech, Inc., </institution></institution-wrap>South San Francisco, CA USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/002hsbm82</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.67033.31</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 8934 4045</institution-id><institution>Department of Rheumatology, </institution><institution>Tufts Medical Center, </institution></institution-wrap>Boston, MA USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>6</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>2</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">357391</issue-id><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>355</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>7</day><month>2</month><year>2020</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>29</day><month>03</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>13</day><month>05</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-05-03 18:25:13.263"><day>03</day><month>05</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="40744_2020_Article_201.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par1">In patients with rheumatoid arthritis (RA) who have an inadequate response to or intolerance of their first biologic disease-modifying antirheumatic drug (bDMARD), guidelines recommend switching to a different biologic class. The objective of this study was to compare persistence with subcutaneous (SC) tocilizumab to persistence with other SC bDMARDs when these drugs are used as subsequent-line therapy in RA patients who previously received&#8201;&#8805;&#8201;1 bDMARD.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">RA patients in a US administrative claims database who initiated a second- or subsequent-line SC bDMARD between January 1, 2012 and June 30, 2017 (initiation date&#8201;=&#8201;index date) were included. Persistence was defined as the number of days between the bDMARD initiation date and (1) the last supplied day of medication fill (primary) or (2) the day on which the patient switched or there was a gap in treatment of&#8201;&gt;&#8201;90&#160;days (secondary). Parametric survival models utilizing an exponential distribution with a robust variance estimator were used to compare persistence with tocilizumab to persistence with other bDMARDs.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">A total of 10,301 patients with 12,704 bDMARD episodes were included. Patients receiving tocilizumab had a significantly higher adjusted median (95% CI) number of days of primary persistence [333 (311&#8211;356)] than those receiving adalimumab [280 (268&#8211;293); <italic toggle="yes">P&#8201;</italic> &lt;&#8201;0.001], certolizumab [262 (241&#8211;284); <italic toggle="yes">P &#8201;</italic>&lt;&#8201;0.001], and etanercept [289 (274&#8211;304); <italic toggle="yes">P &#8201;</italic>=&#8201;0.001], and a similar persistence to those receiving abatacept [320 (305&#8211;335); <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.327] and golimumab [304 (274&#8211;333); <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.122].</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">Among patients with RA who had previously received&#8201;&#8805;&#8201;1 bDMARD, tocilizumab-treated patients exhibited a similar or significantly better biologic persistence than those receiving other bDMARDs.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Biologic</kwd><kwd>Persistence</kwd><kwd>Real-world</kwd><kwd>Rheumatoid arthritis</kwd><kwd>Tocilizumab</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100004328</institution-id><institution>Genentech</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#169; Springer Healthcare Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="FPar1"><title>Key Summary Points</title><p id="Par5">
<table-wrap id="Taba" position="float" orientation="portrait"><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Why carry out this study?</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">In patients with rheumatoid arthritis (RA) who have an inadequate response to or intolerance of their first biologic disease-modifying antirheumatic drug (bDMARD), current guidelines recommend switching to a different biologic class.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">The objective of this study was to compare persistence with subcutaneous (SC) tocilizumab to persistence with other SC bDMARDs when these drugs are used as subsequent-line therapy in RA patients who previously received first-line bDMARD(s).</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>What was learned from this study?</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Among patients with RA who previously received&#8201;&#8805;&#8201;1 bDMARD, tocilizumab-treated patients exhibited similar or significantly better biologic persistence than those receiving other bDMARDs.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study, which involved a large number of second- or subsequent-line SC bDMARD episodes in patients with RA across the United States, provides valuable real-world information and adds to existing data on persistence with bDMARDs.</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par6">Rheumatoid arthritis (RA) is a chronic, progressive autoimmune disease characterized by joint swelling, stiffness, and pain and synovial inflammation, which can lead to permanent joint damage and disability if left untreated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. The goal of RA treatment is to achieve sustained remission or low disease activity based on shared decision-making between the patient and rheumatologist taking into account disease activity, prognostic factors, and comorbidities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. The American College of Rheumatology (ACR) and European League Against Rheumatism (EULAR) guidelines recommend that RA should initially be treated with conventional synthetic disease-modifying antirheumatic drugs (csDMARDs), such as methotrexate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. If patients have an inadequate response to csDMARDs, the addition of either a second csDMARD, a biologic DMARD (bDMARD), or a targeted synthetic DMARD is recommended [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>].</p><p id="Par7">Although bDMARDs are effective for many patients with RA, switching to another biologic may sometimes be necessary because of treatment-related adverse events or a failure to achieve adequate disease control [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Approximately 30&#8211;40% of patients have an inadequate response to csDMARDs and first-line bDMARDs, most commonly tumor necrosis factor inhibitors (TNFis) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. In addition, patients receiving bDMARDs may experience a loss of response to treatment over time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. In patients with RA who have an inadequate response to or are intolerant of their first bDMARD, guidelines recommend switching to a different biologic class or a targeted synthetic DMARD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Understanding persistence with subsequent-line biologic therapies is important, as it can help to guide rheumatologists and patients in choosing an appropriate therapy after an inadequate response to or intolerance of first-line biologics.</p><p id="Par8">Approved biologics for use in patients with RA have different mechanisms of action, and although there is evidence that supports switching to a biologic with a different mechanism of action, switching to another TNFi is more common in clinical practice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. However, the ACR guidelines recommend switching to a non-TNFi after a first-line TNFi failure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]; additionally, treatment patterns of switching to a bDMARD with a different mechanism of action in patients in whom a first-line bDMARD has failed are increasing. If a patient has an inadequate response to a second bDMARD, multiple guidelines recommend that they should be switched to a biologic with a different mechanism of action [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>].</p><p id="Par9">Currently available subcutaneous (SC) bDMARDs include TNFis (adalimumab, certolizumab, etanercept, and golimumab), abatacept (a T-cell costimulation inhibitor), interleukin (IL)-6 receptor blockers (tocilizumab and sarilumab), and the IL-1 receptor antagonist (anakinra). Treatment persistence has been associated with improved outcomes in patients with RA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. However, real-world studies of persistence with SC bDMARDs and comparative information on persistence with SC bDMARDs among patients with RA who are not biologic na&#239;ve are limited. The objective of this study was to compare persistence with SC-administered tocilizumab to persistence with other SC bDMARDs when these drugs were used as subsequent-line therapy in RA patients who previously responded inadequately to or were intolerant of first-line bDMARDs.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Data Source and Patient Population</title><p id="Par10">This US-based retrospective observational study used medical claims data from the IBM<sup>&#174;</sup> MarketScan<sup>&#174;</sup> Commercial and Medicare Supplemental Databases, which provide detailed costs, use, and outcomes data for healthcare services performed in both inpatient and outpatient settings. Adult patients (aged 18&#8211;89&#160;years) with an International Classification of Diseases, Ninth Revision, Clinical Modification (ICD-9-CM) or ICD-10-CM diagnosis of RA who initiated a SC bDMARD between January 2, 2012 and June 30, 2017 were identified. The index date was defined as the date of SC bDMARD initiation.</p><p id="Par11">Patients were included if they were continuously enrolled in a commercial or Medicare plan for&#8201;&#8805;&#8201;6&#160;months before and&#8201;&#8805;&#8201;3&#160;months after the index date; had received any prior bDMARD, including those not evaluated in this analysis; and did not have other autoimmune conditions during the study period, including ankylosing spondylitis, Crohn&#8217;s disease, ulcerative colitis, polyarteritis nodosa, granulomatosis with polyangiitis, systemic lupus erythematosus, non-Hodgkin&#8217;s lymphoma, plaque psoriasis, psoriatic arthritis, and juvenile idiopathic arthritis.</p><p id="Par12">This retrospective, observational analysis used only de-identified patient records and did not include the collection, use, or transmittal of individually identifiable data; therefore, institutional review board approval to conduct this study was not necessary.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Covariates</title><p id="Par13">Factors evaluated for persistence included age, sex, geographic region, health plan type, Elixhauser Comorbidity Index (ECI) score [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>], initial bDMARD, line of biologic therapy (e.g., second, third, etc.), and year of starting the bDMARD. Patients&#8217; comorbidities, as identified by ECI, were carried forward from prior treatment episodes if the patients had&#8201;&#8805;&#8201;1 episode.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Outcomes</title><p id="Par14">Primary bDMARD persistence was defined as the number of days between the initiation date and the last supplied day of medication fill. Patients who had a gap in therapy (e.g., during a period of remission) and then restarted on the same bDMARD were considered to be persistent; patients who switched therapy were considered nonpersistent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Secondary persistence was defined as the period of time that patients received bDMARDs until they switched or had a gap in treatment of&#8201;&gt;&#8201;90&#160;days [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Patients who switched to a different bDMARD were included as a separate episode (i.e., patients could have multiple episodes due to switching to a different biologic as a third- or subsequent-line therapy). For patients who had a gap in treatment of&#8201;&gt;&#8201;90&#160;days and then restarted the same bDMARD, only the episode prior to the 90-day gap was included in the analysis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p id="Par15">Analysis of variance and <italic toggle="yes">&#967;</italic><sup>2</sup> tests were used to compare demographic and clinical characteristics between bDMARD episodes. Parametric survival models utilizing an exponential distribution with a robust variance estimator were used to compare outcomes with tocilizumab to those with other bDMARDs, adjusting for differences in baseline characteristics and comorbidities over time prior to initiating subsequent bDMARDs and accounting for correlation among different bDMARD episodes. Hazard ratios for discontinuation were derived from the survival models after adjusting for patients&#8217; baseline demographics, lines of therapy, and episode-specific comorbidities. Patients who left the database (e.g., patients who died or switched to a health plan outside of the database) were censored.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec8"><title>Demographics and Baseline Characteristics</title><p id="Par16">Overall, 10,301 patients with 12,704 bDMARD episodes were included (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). The most common bDMARD episode was adalimumab (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;3599), followed by abatacept (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;2988), etanercept (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;2760), tocilizumab (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;1630), golimumab (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;745), and certolizumab pegol (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;982). Most patients were female (78.9&#8211;82.2%), and mean age ranged from 51.0 to 53.2&#160;years (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Mean [SD] ECI scores were significantly higher (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001) in patients initiating tocilizumab (2.8 [2.3]) than in those receiving abatacept (2.5 [2.2]), adalimumab (2.5 [2.1]), certolizumab pegol (2.4 [2.0]), etanercept (2.4 [2.0]), or golimumab (2.4 [2.2]) (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig.&#160;1</label><caption><p>Patient attrition</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO1" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="40744_2020_201_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table&#160;1</label><caption><p>Demographics and characteristics</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Variable</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Abatacept<break/><italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;2988</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Adalimumab<break/><italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;3599</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Certolizumab pegol<break/><italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;982</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Etanercept<break/><italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;2760</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Golimumab<break/><italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;745</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tocilizumab<break/><italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;1630</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value<sup>a</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age, mean (SD)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53.2 (11.0)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52.7 (11.3)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">51.0 (11.0)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52.5 (10.9)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52.1 (11.2)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52.7 (10.6)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Female, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2446 (81.9)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2838 (78.9)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">807 (82.2)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2206 (79.9)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">610 (81.9)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1325 (81.3)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.018</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1">Health plan type, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;HMO</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">269 (9.00)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">338 (9.39)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">81 (8.25)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">252 (9.13)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67 (8.99)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">117 (7.18)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.169</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;PPO</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2017 (67.5)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2391 (66.4)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">692 (70.5)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1878 (68.0)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">500 (67.1)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1122 (68.8)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.196</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Other</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">702 (23.5)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">870 (24.2)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">209 (21.3)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">630 (22.8)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">178 (23.9)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">391 (24.0)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.472</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1">US region, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Northeast</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">539 (18.0)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">620 (17.2)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">131 (13.3)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">443 (16.1)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">136 (18.3)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">271 (16.6)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.013</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;South</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1271 (42.5)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1564 (43.5)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">519 (52.9)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1327 (48.1)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">292 (39.2)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">735 (45.1)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;North Central</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">616 (20.6)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">737 (20.5)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">157 (16.0)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">496 (18.0)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">146 (19.6)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">307 (18.8)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.005</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;West</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">535 (17.9)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">631 (17.5)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">170 (17.3)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">467 (16.9)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">152 (20.4)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">292 (17.9)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.392</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Unknown</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 (0.9)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47 (1.3)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (0.5)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 (1.0)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19 (2.6)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25 (1.5)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ECI score, mean (SD)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.5 (2.2)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.5 (2.1)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.4 (2.0)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.4 (2.0)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.4 (2.2)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.8 (2.3)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1">Comorbidities, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Chronic pulmonary disease</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">486 (16.3)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">503 (14.0)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">126 (12.8)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">386 (14.0)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">118 (15.8)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">284 (17.4)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Deficiency anemias</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">426 (14.3)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">448 (12.4)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">131 (13.3)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">369 (13.4)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98 (13.2)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">251 (15.4)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.077</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Depression</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">279 (9.34)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">371 (10.3)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">80 (8.1)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">265 (9.6)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65 (8.7)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">175 (10.7)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.185</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Diabetes without chronic complications</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">379 (12.7)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">446 (12.4)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94 (9.6)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">304 (11.0)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">87 (11.7)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">202 (12.4)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.072</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Fluid and electrolyte disorders</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">233 (7.8)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">232 (6.4)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">74 (7.5)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">187 (6.8)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">51 (6.8)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">130 (8.0)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.211</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Hypothyroidism</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">513 (17.2)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">575 (16.0)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">161 (16.4)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">458 (16.6)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">117 (15.7)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">327 (20.1)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.010</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Liver disease</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">149 (5.0)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">154 (4.3)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50 (5.1)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">125 (4.5)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30 (4.0)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">82 (5.0)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.613</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Obesity</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">487 (16.3)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">613 (17.0)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">180 (18.3)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">470 (17.0)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">116 (15.6)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">332 (20.4)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.009</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Hypertension</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1070 (35.8)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1316 (36.6)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">346 (35.2)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">978 (35.4)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">269 (36.1)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">638 (39.1)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.184</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;RA/collagen vascular disease</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2273 (76.1)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2731 (75.9)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">765 (77.9)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2071 (75.0)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">570 (76.5)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1342 (82.3)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Valvular disease</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">130 (4.4)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">131 (3.6)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40 (4.1)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93 (3.4)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28 (3.8)</td><td char="(" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">81 (5.0)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.103</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">ECI</italic> Elixhauser Comorbidity Index, <italic toggle="yes">HMO</italic> health maintenance organization, <italic toggle="yes">PPO</italic> preferred provider organization, <italic toggle="yes">RA</italic> rheumatoid arthritis</p><p><sup>a</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05 indicates a statistically significant difference among therapies</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Outcomes</title><p id="Par17">Tocilizumab was the least frequently used second-line bDMARD and the most frequently used third-, fourth-, and fifth-line bDMARD (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The adjusted median (95% CI) number of days of primary persistence for tocilizumab [333 (311&#8211;356)] was significantly higher than those for adalimumab [280 (268&#8211;293); <italic toggle="yes">P&#8201;</italic> &lt;&#8201;0.001], certolizumab [262 (241&#8211;284); <italic toggle="yes">P&#8201;</italic> &lt;&#8201;0.001], and etanercept [289 (274&#8211;304); <italic toggle="yes">P&#8201;</italic> =&#8201;0.001], and similar to those for abatacept [320 (305&#8211;335); <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.327] and golimumab [304 (274&#8211;333); <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.122] (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). The adjusted median (95% CI) number of days of secondary persistence for tocilizumab [315 (292&#8211;337)] was significantly higher than those for adalimumab [265 (253&#8211;276); <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001], certolizumab pegol [253 (231&#8211;275); <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001], and etanercept [272 (257&#8211;286); <italic toggle="yes">P </italic>=&#8201;0.001], and similar to those for abatacept [306 (291&#8211;321); <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.545] and golimumab [284 (257&#8211;311); <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.092] (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). After adjusting for patients&#8217; baseline demographics, lines of therapy, and episode-specific comorbidities, adalimumab, certolizumab pegol, and etanercept had significantly higher likelihoods of discontinuation than tocilizumab (Tables&#160;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).<fig id="Fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig.&#160;2</label><caption><p>Lines of bDMARD therapy by biologic</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO2" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="40744_2020_201_Fig2_HTML.jpg"/></fig><fig id="Fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig.&#160;3</label><caption><p>Adjusted mean primary persistence with bDMARDs among patients with RA<sup>a</sup></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO3" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="40744_2020_201_Fig3_HTML.jpg"/></fig><fig id="Fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig.&#160;4</label><caption><p>Adjusted mean secondary persistence with bDMARDs among patients with RA<sup>a</sup></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO4" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="40744_2020_201_Fig4_HTML.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table&#160;2</label><caption><p>Risk of discontinuing bDMARDs vs. tocilizumab for primary persistence</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Abatacept<break/><italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;2988</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Adalimumab<break/><italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;3599</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Certolizumab pegol<break/><italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;982</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Etanercept<break/><italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;2760</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Golimumab<break/><italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;745</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tocilizumab<break/><italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;1630</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Hazard ratio</p><p>(95% CI)<sup>a</sup></p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.04</p><p>(0.96&#8211;1.13)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.19</p><p>(1.10&#8211;1.29)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.27</p><p>(1.14&#8211;1.41)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.15</p><p>(1.06&#8211;1.26)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.10</p><p>(0.98&#8211;1.24)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">bDMARD</italic> biologic disease-modifying antirheumatic drug</p><p><sup>a</sup>Hazard ratios were derived from the survival models after adjusting for patients&#8217; baseline demographics, lines of therapy, and episode-specific comorbidities</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table&#160;3</label><caption><p>Risk of discontinuing bDMARDs vs. tocilizumab for secondary persistence</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Abatacept<break/><italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;2988</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Adalimumab<break/><italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;3599</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Certolizumab pegol<break/><italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;982</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Etanercept<break/><italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;2760</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Golimumab<break/><italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;745</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tocilizumab<break/><italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;1630</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Hazard ratio</p><p>(95% CI)<sup>a</sup></p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.03</p><p>(0.94&#8211;1.12)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.19</p><p>(1.09&#8211;1.29)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.24</p><p>(1.12&#8211;1.39)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.16</p><p>(1.06&#8211;1.27)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.11</p><p>(0.98&#8211;1.25)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">bDMARD</italic> biologic disease-modifying antirheumatic drug</p><p><sup>a</sup>Hazard ratios were derived from the survival models after adjusting for patients&#8217; baseline demographics, lines of therapy, and episode-specific comorbidities</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par18">Among the patients who received tocilizumab for&#8201;&#8805;&#8201;12&#160;months, 45% initiated tocilizumab administered every other week (q2w) and 55% initiated tocilizumab weekly (qw). Of the 347 patients who initiated q2w tocilizumab, 32.8% switched to qw dosing over the 12-month follow-up; the mean time to switch was 177&#160;days. After 12&#160;months of follow-up, approximately 68.3% of patients were receiving qw dosing and 31.7% were receiving q2w dosing.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par19">In this large US claims-based analysis, persistence with tocilizumab as a second- or subsequent-line bDMARD in patients with RA was found to be similar to or significantly longer than persistence with other bDMARDs. These results are consistent with registry studies showing increased persistence with tocilizumab compared to persistence with TNFis in patients who had an inadequate response to a first-line TNFi [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Although the present study did not evaluate the reasons for patients switching or discontinuing bDMARD therapy, previous studies have shown that multiple factors are both positively and negatively associated with persistence, including age, sex, and race, as well as disease activity, comorbidities, concurrent use of methotrexate, and therapy-management programs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>].</p><p id="Par20">The intravenous and SC formulations of tocilizumab have been shown to be safe and effective treatments for patients with RA who are bDMARD na&#239;ve and for those with prior exposure to bDMARDs, either as a monotherapy or in combination with csDMARDs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. As shown in the present study, patients (particularly those treated with tocilizumab) may receive third, fourth, or greater lines of biologic therapy. Frequent switching of biologic therapy can make longer-term management of RA more challenging (e.g., management by payers requiring step therapy) and result in greater costs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Studies have shown that switching from a TNFi to a biologic with a different mechanism of action can be more effective (e.g., higher persistence, improved clinical outcomes) than switching to another TNFi [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Results from the present study also suggest that for patients who have an inadequate response to their first biologic, switching to one with a different mechanism of action may be more effective than switching to another biologic with the same mechanism of action.</p><p id="Par21">Lower costs have been reported in patients who switched to a bDMARD with a different mechanism of action [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Another study reported higher direct costs but lower indirect costs in patients who switched from a first-line TNFi to a bDMARD with a different mechanism of action than in those who switched to another TNFi [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. For patients weighing&#8201;&lt;&#8201;100&#160;kg, tocilizumab SC is initiated q2w, followed by an increase to qw based on clinical response; for patients weighing&#8201;&gt;&#8201;100&#160;kg, SC tocilizumab is initiated qw [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. In the present study, 33% of patients increased tocilizumab dosing from q2w to qw. These results are consistent with a long-term study of SC tocilizumab which showed that 23% of patients who initiated SC TCZ q2w injections switched to qw within 2&#160;years; in the patients who switched to qw dosing, improvements in ACR response and DAS28 remission were achieved [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. The flexibility to increase dosing based on clinical response may contribute to the longer persistence observed with tocilizumab.</p><sec id="Sec11"><title>Limitations</title><p id="Par22">The results of this analysis may not be generalizable to all patients with RA, including those who do not have health insurance. Drug samples provided to the patient by their doctor and prescriptions filled in situations where the patient does not use their prescription drug coverage are not captured in the pharmacy claims data in the MarketScan databases. Finally, a substantial proportion of tocilizumab use (45.8%) was as a second-line bDMARD, but some patients also received tocilizumab as a third-line (33.3%) or subsequent-line bDMARD. Thus, one should also consider the possibility that persistence was longer in this group of patients because fewer options for subsequent therapies were available to them. However, the analysis was adjusted for line of therapy, and an increasing number of biologic therapies are available for patients, so we do not believe that this had an effect on persistence.</p><p id="Par23">Despite the abovementioned limitations, this study involving a large number of second- or subsequent-line SC bDMARD episodes in patients with RA across the United States provides valuable real-world information and adds to the existing data on persistence with bDMARDs.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par24">Among patients with RA who previously received&#8201;&#8805;&#8201;1 other bDMARD, those who received tocilizumab exhibited similar or significantly better persistence than those receiving other bDMARDs.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Digital Features</bold></p><p>To view digital features for this article go to: 10.6084/m9.figshare.11974503.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><sec id="FPar2"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par25">This work was funded by Genentech, Inc. All authors had full access to all data in this study and take complete responsibility for the integrity of the data and accuracy of the data analysis. The Rapid Service Fee was funded by Genentech, Inc.</p></sec><sec id="FPar3"><title>Medical Writing Assistance</title><p id="Par26">Support for third-party writing assistance, furnished by Nicola Gillespie, DVM, of Health Interactions, Inc., was provided by Genentech, Inc.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Authorship</title><p id="Par27">All named authors meet the International Committee of Medical Journal Editors (ICMJE) criteria for authorship for this article, take responsibility for the integrity of the work as a whole, and have given their approval for this version to be published.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Authorship Contributions</title><p id="Par28">All authors were involved in drafting the manuscript, reviewing, and revising it critically for important intellectual content, and all authors read and approved the final version. All authors also contributed to the study design, analysis, and interpretation of data.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Prior Presentation</title><p id="Par29">A portion of these data was presented at the 2019 EULAR Annual European Congress of Rheumatology, June 12&#8211;15, Madrid, Spain, and at the 2019 ACR Annual Meeting, November 8&#8211;13, Atlanta, GA, USA.</p></sec><sec id="FPar7" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Disclosures</title><p id="Par30">Jennie H. Best, Lenore Tominna, and Ibrahim Abbass are employees of Genentech, Inc. Steven C. Vlad has received speakers bureau fees from AbbVie (&lt;&#8201;$10,000), consulting fees from Kiniksa, Horizon Therapeutics, AbbVie, and UCB (&lt;&#8201;$10,000), and research funding from Regeneron, Centrexion, AbbVie, UCB, GSK, Samumed, Galapagos NV, Eli Lilly, and Novartis.</p></sec><sec id="FPar8"><title>Compliance with Ethics Guidelines</title><p id="Par31">This retrospective, observational analysis used only de-identified patient records and did not include the collection, use, or transmittal of individually identifiable data; therefore, institutional review board approval to conduct this study was not necessary.</p></sec><sec id="FPar9" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data Availability</title><p id="Par32">The database used for the analyses in this paper is commercially available from IBM Watson at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ibm.com/watson-health/learn/truven-health-analytics">https://www.ibm.com/watson-health/learn/truven-health-analytics</ext-link>. The license agreement to access these data does not give the authors permission to share this database.</p></sec></ack><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smolen</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aletaha</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McInnes</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rheumatoid arthritis</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2016</year><volume>388</volume><issue>10055</issue><fpage>2023</fpage><lpage>2038</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(16)30173-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27156434</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saag</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bridges</surname><given-names>SL</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>2015 American College of Rheumatology guideline for the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis</article-title><source>Arthritis Care Res (Hoboken).</source><year>2016</year><volume>68</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/acr.22783</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26545825</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smolen</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Landew&#233;</surname><given-names>RBM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bijlsma</surname><given-names>JWJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>EULAR recommendations for the management of rheumatoid arthritis with synthetic and biological disease-modifying antirheumatic drugs: 2019 update</article-title><source>Ann Rheum Dis</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/annrheumdis-2019-216655</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31969328</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smolen</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Breedveld</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burmester</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Treating rheumatoid arthritis to target: 2014 update of the recommendations of an international task force</article-title><source>Ann Rheum Dis</source><year>2016</year><volume>75</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/annrheumdis-2015-207524</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25969430</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4717393</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Souto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maneiro</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomez-Reino</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rate of discontinuation and drug survival of biologic therapies in rheumatoid arthritis: a systematic review and meta-analysis of drug registries and health care databases</article-title><source>Rheumatology (Oxford)</source><year>2016</year><volume>55</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>523</fpage><lpage>534</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26490106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/rheumatology/kev374</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bathon</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fleischmann</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A comparison of etanercept and methotrexate in patients with early rheumatoid arthritis</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2000</year><volume>343</volume><issue>22</issue><fpage>1586</fpage><lpage>1593</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJM200011303432201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11096165</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weinblatt</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keystone</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Furst</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Adalimumab, a fully human anti-tumor necrosis factor alpha monoclonal antibody, for the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis in patients taking concomitant methotrexate: the ARMADA trial</article-title><source>Arthritis Rheum</source><year>2003</year><volume>48</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/art.10697</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12528101</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>St Clair</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Breedveld</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Infliximab (chimeric anti-tumour necrosis factor alpha monoclonal antibody) versus placebo in rheumatoid arthritis patients receiving concomitant methotrexate: a randomised phase III trial. ATTRACT Study Group</article-title><source>Lancet.</source><year>1999</year><volume>354</volume><issue>9194</issue><fpage>1932</fpage><lpage>1939</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(99)05246-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10622295</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rubbert-Roth</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Finckh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Treatment options in patients with rheumatoid arthritis failing initial TNF inhibitor therapy: a critical review</article-title><source>Arthritis Res Ther</source><year>2009</year><volume>11</volume><issue>suppl 1</issue><fpage>S1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/ar2666</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19368701</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2669237</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chastek</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahajan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Outcomes of tumor necrosis factor inhibitor cycling versus switching to a disease-modifying anti-rheumatic drug with a new mechanism of action among patients with rheumatoid arthritis</article-title><source>J Med Econ.</source><year>2017</year><volume>20</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>464</fpage><lpage>473</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13696998.2016.1275653</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28010149</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knapp</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Treatment persistence and clinical outcomes of tumor necrosis factor inhibitor cycling or switching to a new mechanism of action therapy: real-world observational study of rheumatoid arthritis patients in the United States with prior tumor necrosis factor inhibitor therapy</article-title><source>Adv Ther.</source><year>2017</year><volume>34</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1936</fpage><lpage>1952</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12325-017-0578-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28674959</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5565674</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Contreras-Yanez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pascual-Ramos</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Window of opportunity to achieve major outcomes in early rheumatoid arthritis patients: how persistence with therapy matters</article-title><source>Arthritis Res Ther.</source><year>2015</year><volume>17</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>177</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13075-015-0697-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26162892</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4499189</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elixhauser</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steiner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coffey</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comorbidity measures for use with administrative data</article-title><source>Med Care</source><year>1998</year><volume>36</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00005650-199801000-00004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9431328</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Walraven</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Austin</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jennings</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forster</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A modification of the Elixhauser comorbidity measures into a point system for hospital death using administrative data</article-title><source>Med Care</source><year>2009</year><volume>47</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>626</fpage><lpage>633</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MLR.0b013e31819432e5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19433995</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Quan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sundararajan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Halfon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fong</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burnand</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luthi</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Coding algorithms for defining comorbidities in ICD-9-CM and ICD-10 administrative data</article-title><source>Med Care</source><year>2005</year><volume>43</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1130</fpage><lpage>1139</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.mlr.0000182534.19832.83</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16224307</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Leslie RS. Calculating medication compliance, adherence, and persistence in administrative pharmacy claims databases. San Diego: MedImpact Healthcare Systems, Inc.; 2008.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Santos-Faria</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tavares-Costa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eusebio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tocilizumab and rituximab have similar effectiveness and are both superior to a second tumour necrosis factor inhibitor in rheumatoid arthritis patients who discontinued a first TNF inhibitor</article-title><source>Acta Rheumatol Port</source><year>2019</year><volume>44</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31243259</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ebina</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Drug retention and discontinuation reasons between seven biologics in patients with rheumatoid arthritis&#8212;the ANSWER cohort study</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2018</year><volume>13</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>e0194130</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0194130</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29543846</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5854351</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hishitani</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogata</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shima</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Retention of tocilizumab and anti-tumour necrosis factor drugs in the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis</article-title><source>Scand J Rheumatol</source><year>2013</year><volume>42</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>253</fpage><lpage>259</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/03009742.2012.762037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23470089</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murage</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tongbram</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Medication adherence and persistence in patients with rheumatoid arthritis, psoriasis, and psoriatic arthritis: a systematic literature review</article-title><source>Patient Prefer Adherence.</source><year>2018</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1483</fpage><lpage>1503</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/PPA.S167508</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30174415</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6110273</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kremer</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rigby</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sustained response following discontinuation of methotrexate in patients with rheumatoid arthritis treated with subcutaneous tocilizumab: results from a randomized, controlled trial</article-title><source>Arthritis Rheumatol (Hoboken).</source><year>2018</year><volume>70</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1200</fpage><lpage>1208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/art.40493</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29575803</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kivitz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olech</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borofsky</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Two-year efficacy and safety of subcutaneous tocilizumab in combination with disease-modifying antirheumatic drugs including escalation to weekly dosing in rheumatoid arthritis</article-title><source>J Rheum.</source><year>2018</year><volume>45</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>456</fpage><lpage>464</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3899/jrheum.161539</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29247149</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kremer</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blanco</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Halland</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical efficacy and safety maintained up to 5&#160;years in patients with rheumatoid arthritis treated with tocilizumab in a randomised trial</article-title><source>Clin Exp Rheumatol</source><year>2016</year><volume>34</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>625</fpage><lpage>633</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27087059</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burmester</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rigby</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Vollenhoven</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tocilizumab combination therapy or monotherapy or methotrexate monotherapy in methotrexate-naive patients with early rheumatoid arthritis: 2-year clinical and radiographic results from the randomised, placebo-controlled FUNCTION trial</article-title><source>Ann Rheum Dis</source><year>2017</year><volume>76</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1279</fpage><lpage>1284</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/annrheumdis-2016-210561</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28389552</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5530348</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Emery</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keystone</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tony</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>IL-6 receptor inhibition with tocilizumab improves treatment outcomes in patients with rheumatoid arthritis refractory to anti-tumour necrosis factor biologicals: results from a 24-week multicentre randomised placebo-controlled trial</article-title><source>Ann Rheum Dis</source><year>2008</year><volume>67</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1516</fpage><lpage>1523</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/ard.2008.092932</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18625622</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3811149</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alfonso-Cristancho</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mallya</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ringold</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Economic consequences of sequencing biologics in rheumatoid arthritis: a systematic review</article-title><source>J Med Econ.</source><year>2013</year><volume>16</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>391</fpage><lpage>396</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3111/13696998.2013.763812</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23298329</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonafede</surname><given-names>MMK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McMorrow</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Proudfoot</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shinde</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuznik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Treatment persistence and healthcare costs among patients with rheumatoid arthritis after a change in targeted therapy</article-title><source>Am Health Drug Benefits.</source><year>2018</year><volume>11</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>192</fpage><lpage>202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30464787</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6207310</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chastek</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Proudfoot</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shinde</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuznik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Treatment persistence and healthcare costs among patients with rheumatoid arthritis changing biologics in the USA</article-title><source>Adv Ther.</source><year>2017</year><volume>34</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>2422</fpage><lpage>2435</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12325-017-0617-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29039054</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5702369</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cantini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niccoli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nannini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Second-line biologic therapy optimization in rheumatoid arthritis, psoriatic arthritis, and ankylosing spondylitis</article-title><source>Semin Arthritis Rheum</source><year>2017</year><volume>47</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>192</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.semarthrit.2017.03.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28413099</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Emery</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gottenberg</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rubbert-Roth</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarzi-Puttini</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choquette</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taboada</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Rituximab versus an alternative TNF inhibitor in patients with rheumatoid arthritis who failed to respond to a single previous TNF inhibitor: SWITCH-RA, a global, observational, comparative effectiveness study</article-title><source>Ann Rheum Dis</source><year>2015</year><volume>74</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>979</fpage><lpage>984</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/annrheumdis-2013-203993</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24442884</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4431330</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Favalli</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Biggioggero</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marchesoni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meroni</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Survival on treatment with second-line biologic therapy: a cohort study comparing cycling and swap strategies</article-title><source>Rheumatology (Oxford)</source><year>2014</year><volume>53</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1664</fpage><lpage>1668</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/rheumatology/keu158</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24729445</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rotar</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hocevar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rebolj Kodre</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Praprotnik</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomsic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Retention of the second-line biologic disease-modifying antirheumatic drugs in patients with rheumatoid arthritis failing one tumor necrosis factor alpha inhibitor: data from the BioRx.si registry</article-title><source>Clin Rheumatol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>34</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1787</fpage><lpage>1793</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10067-015-3066-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26345633</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harnett</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiederkehr</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gerber</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gruben</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koenig</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bourret</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Real-world evaluation of TNF-inhibitor utilization in rheumatoid arthritis</article-title><source>J Med Econ.</source><year>2016</year><volume>19</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3111/13696998.2015.1099538</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26401963</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"> Genentech, Inc. ACTEMRA prescribing information. South San Francisco: Genentech, Inc.; 2019.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>