<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="review-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Oral Oncol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Oral Oncol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3815</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">pheelsevier</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Oral Oncology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1368-8375</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1879-0593</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>Elsevier - PMC COVID-19 Collection</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7284253</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC7284253.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">7284253</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">7284253</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">32599499</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.oraloncology.2020.104849</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S1368-8375(20)30285-2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">104849</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Nonsurgical management of resectable oral cavity cancer in the wake of COVID-19: A rapid review and meta-analysis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au005"><name name-style="western"><surname>Forner</surname><given-names initials="D">David</given-names></name><xref rid="af005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="af010" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au010"><name name-style="western"><surname>Noel</surname><given-names initials="CW">Christopher W.</given-names></name><xref rid="af010" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="af015" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au015"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names initials="V">Vincent</given-names></name><xref rid="af015" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au020"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parmar</surname><given-names initials="A">Ambica</given-names></name><xref rid="af010" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="af020" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au025"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names initials="KKW">Kelvin K.W.</given-names></name><xref rid="af010" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="af020" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au030"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Almeida</surname><given-names initials="JR">John R.</given-names></name><xref rid="af010" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="af015" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au035"><name name-style="western"><surname>Husain</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zain</given-names></name><xref rid="af025" ref-type="aff">e</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au040"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eskander</surname><given-names initials="A">Antoine</given-names></name><xref rid="af010" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="af015" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#8270;</xref></contrib><aff id="af005"><label>a</label>Division of Otolaryngology &#8211; Head and Neck Surgery, Dalhousie University, Halifax, Canada</aff><aff id="af010"><label>b</label>Institute of Health Policy, Management and Evaluation, University of Toronto, Toronto, Canada</aff><aff id="af015"><label>c</label>Department of Otolaryngology &#8211; Head and Neck Surgery, University of Toronto, Toronto, Canada</aff><aff id="af020"><label>d</label>Department of Medical Oncology, University of Toronto, Toronto, Canada</aff><aff id="af025"><label>e</label>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Toronto, Toronto, Canada</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#8270;</label>Corresponding author at: Sunnybrook Health Sciences Centre, 2075 Bayview Ave., Room M1 102, Toronto, Ontario M4N 3M5, Canada.</corresp><fn id="fn1"><label>1</label><p id="np045">Equal contribution.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>10</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>109</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">359289</issue-id><fpage>104849</fpage><lpage>104849</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>2</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>21</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>4</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>10</day><month>06</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>10</day><month>06</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-03-29 14:25:13.377"><day>29</day><month>03</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2020 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Elsevier Ltd</copyright-holder><license><license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><abstract abstract-type="graphical" id="ab005"><title>Graphical abstract</title><fig id="f0015" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ga1_lrg.jpg"/></fig></abstract><abstract abstract-type="author-highlights" id="ab010"><title>Highlights</title><p><list list-type="simple" id="l0055"><list-item id="o0190"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0190">COVID-19 resource constraints have resulted in treatment delays for oral cancer.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0195"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0195">Non-surgical treatment may be necessary to provide timely access to care.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0200"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0200">Definitive CCRT is associated with an increased rate of death in early oral cancer.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0205"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0205">Neoadjuvant regimens have not shown survival benefit in resectable oral cancer.</p></list-item></list></p></abstract><abstract id="ab015"><sec><title>Objective</title><p>Surgery is the preferred treatment modality for oral squamous cell carcinoma (OSCC). However, due to limited resources, re-assessment of treatment paradigms in the wake of the Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic is urgently required. In this rapid review, we described contemporary oncological outcomes for OSCC using non-surgical modalities.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>A systematic literature search was conducted for articles published between January 1, 2010 and April 1, 2020 on MEDLINE and Cochrane CENTRAL. Studies were included if they contained patients with OSCC treated with either neoadjuvant, induction, or definitive radiotherapy, chemotherapy, immunotherapy, or combination thereof, and an outcome of overall survival.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>In total, 36 articles were included. Definitive radiotherapy or chemoradiotherapy were the focus of 18 articles and neoadjuvant chemotherapy or chemoradiotherapy were the focus of the other 18 articles. In early stage OSCC, definitive radiotherapy, with or without concurrent chemotherapy, was associated with a significantly increased hazard of death compared to definitive surgery (HR: 2.39, 95% CI: 1.56&#8211;3.67, I<sup>2</sup>: 63%). The hazard of death was non-significantly increased with definitive chemoradiotherapy in studies excluding early disease (HR: 1.98, 95% CI: 0.85&#8211;4.64, I<sup>2</sup>: 84%). Two recent randomized control trials have been conducted, demonstrating no survival advantage to neoadjuvant chemotherapy.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>This review suggests that primary radiotherapy and chemoradiotherapy are inferior to surgical management for OSCC. Strategies for surgical delay warranting consideration are sparse, but may include several neoadjuvant regimens, recognizing these regimens may not offer a survival benefit over definitive surgery alone.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group id="kg005"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Oral cavity</kwd><kwd>Squamous cell carcinoma</kwd><kwd>Radiotherapy</kwd><kwd>Chemo-radiotherapy</kwd><kwd>Immunotherapy</kwd><kwd>Outcomes</kwd><kwd>COVID-19</kwd><kwd>Chemotherapy</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s0005"><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0210">The Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic has placed significant strain on healthcare systems across the world. To increase the capacity of these systems, surgical cases, including oncological surgery, have been either delayed or cancelled across various jurisdictions <xref rid="b0005" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="b0010" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. As COVID-19 pressures mount, head and neck surgeons must adapt to meet healthcare system needs during this unprecedented time. With resource constraints intensifying and surgical waitlists becoming longer, it may become increasingly difficult to meet established targets for treatment initiation. Head and neck oncologists may need to evaluate non-standard management options and weigh the best available evidence.</p><p id="p0215">In oral cavity squamous cell carcinoma (OSCC), surgery has remained first line therapy for decades, with the National Comprehensive Cancer Network (NCCN) recommending primary surgical management in both early and late stage disease <xref rid="b0015" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. Delays in cancer surgery may risk losing a window of opportunity for resection, potentially worsening both oncologic and functional outcomes <xref rid="b0020" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="b0025" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. As human resources, including nursing and critical care personnel, become less available during the pandemic, perioperative outcomes may worsen <xref rid="b0035" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. In the immediate postoperative period, nosocomial spread of COVID-19 is also a significant concern for OSCC patients, who are often elderly and medically complex, both of which correlate with increased COVID-19 related morbidity and mortality <xref rid="b0040" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, <xref rid="b0045" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="b0050" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="b0055" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, <xref rid="b0060" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>.</p><p id="p0220">Multiple societies, including the Canadian Association of Head &amp; Neck Surgical Oncology (CAHNSO), have released statements and guidelines for the management of patients with head and neck cancer during COVID-19 <xref rid="b0065" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="b0070" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, <xref rid="b0075" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, <xref rid="b0080" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. By necessity, these high-level guidelines do not provide specifics on disease management and patient-specific care, given the inherent complexity of such decision making and the variability in resource availability that may exist between institutions. As pandemic related health system changes accumulate, the need for non-surgical treatment of OSCC may become necessary. To better inform such decision making during both this initial surge and possible second wave surges, we have provided a review of contemporary oncological outcomes associated with non-surgical treatment modalities (primary radiation, chemoradiation, and immunotherapy) used for either definitive management or as potential bridging therapies in the management of surgically resectable OSCC.</p></sec><sec id="s0010"><title>Methods</title><sec id="s0015"><title>Search strategy</title><p id="p0225">This study was informed by the Cochrane COVID-19 Rapid Review templates <xref rid="b0085" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. A literature search was conducted for articles published between January 1, 2010 and April 1, 2020 on MEDLINE and Cochrane CENTRAL. The search strategy contained head and neck cancer terms and terms related to OSCC, non-surgical treatment modalities, and oncological outcomes. Snowballing and reference review techniques were used, including evaluation of previously published reviews <xref rid="b0090" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, <xref rid="b0095" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, <xref rid="b0100" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, <xref rid="b0105" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, <xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. The full search strategy is outlined in <bold>Supplemental</bold>
<xref rid="s0115" ref-type="sec">Figure S1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s0020"><title>Eligibility criteria</title><p id="p0230">Inclusion and exclusion criteria were defined <italic toggle="yes">a priori</italic> and applied to identified publications. Studies were included if they contained a population of patients (&#8805;18&#160;years of age) with potentially resectable OSCC, with a treatment intervention of either neoadjuvant, induction, or definitive radiotherapy, chemotherapy, immunotherapy, or combination thereof, and an outcome of overall survival. Studies involving non-OSCC head and neck cancer were considered eligible if OSCC-specific treatment and outcome details could be delineated. Induction therapy was considered to be treatment given before definitive non-surgical treatment, and neoadjuvant therapy was considered to be treatment given before definitive surgical treatment <xref rid="b0115" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. Publications were excluded if they contained populations of patients with salivary gland cancer or included an exclusive cohort of patients with lip cancer, basaloid squamous cell carcinoma (SCC) or verrucous SCC. Additionally, studies that described a cohort of patients with surgically unresectable disease, or those undergoing palliative therapy were also excluded. Treatments involving intra-arterial chemotherapy, brachytherapy, or photodynamic therapy were also excluded as these treatments would not be practical to administer in a pandemic setting, and would not eliminate the need for perioperative resources. Additionally, studies were excluded if they were non-English, abstract only, protocols, case-reports, case series of&#160;less than&#160;10 patients, or studies with no primary data.</p></sec><sec id="s0025"><title>Review process and data extraction</title><p id="p0235">Titles and abstracts were independently screened by three reviewers (CN, DF, VW) in duplicate to assess for initial relevance. Full articles were screened by two reviewers (CN, DF) to determine eligibility. All disagreements during the review process were resolved by consensus. Screening was facilitated using the Covidence systematic review software (Veritas Health Innovation, Australia).</p></sec><sec id="s0030"><title>Assessment of quality</title><p id="p0240">Risk of study bias was assessed using Version 2 of the Cochrane risk-of-bias tool (RoB 2) for randomized trials and the Newcastle-Ottawa Scale (NOS) for observational studies by a single reviewer (CN). For the RoB 2 tool, studies were categorized as: low risk of bias, some concerns, or high risk of bias across 5 domains and assigned an overall risk of bias judgement <xref rid="b0120" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, <xref rid="b0125" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. The NOS encompasses 3 subscales, each of which is scored separately and has a different maximum score (selection: 4 stars, comparability: 2 stars, outcome: 3 stars) <xref rid="b0125" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. Higher scores represent higher-quality studies, with decreased amounts of potential bias. Studies are considered good quality if they score 3&#8211;4 on selection, 1&#8211;2 on comparability, and 2&#8211;3 on outcome; fair quality if 2&#8211;3 on selection, 1&#8211;2 on comparability, and 2&#8211;3 on outcome; and poor quality if 0&#8211;1 on selection or 0 on comparability or 1 on outcome.</p></sec><sec id="s0035"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="p0245">Inter-rater agreement during title and abstract screening was assessed by percent agreement, and inter-rater agreement during full-text review was analyzed by Cohen&#8217;s kappa statistic <xref rid="b0130" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. In studies where overall survival was not directly reported in the body of the text, digitization of the Kaplan-Meier curves using the DigitizeIt software (version 2.3, Germany), allowed for generation of summary survival statistics.</p><p id="p0250">Pre-determined pooled analyses were performed. Meta-analysis was performed to examine pooled differences in the hazard of death between definitive radiotherapy, concurrent chemoradiotherapy (CCRT), and primary surgery. Studies which reported adjusted hazard ratios (HRs) underwent analysis. Standard errors were computed from the 95% confidence interval (CI) or p-value and log transformed HRs were used in the analysis <xref rid="b0135" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>. Meta-analysis was performed using a random effects model and the generic inverse variance method; HRs and 95% CIs were reported. Heterogeneity was quantified using the I<sup>2</sup> test statistic.<xref rid="b0060" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref> Meta-analysis was performed on observational studies with two separate analyses; studies that included only early stage disease were analysed separately from studies that included only advanced disease or that included all stages. Meta-analysis was also used to provide pooled proportions of osteoradionecrosis (ORN) following definitive CCRT through a DerSimonian-Laird binary random effects model. Meta-analysis was completed using Review Manager (version 5.3, Denmark).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0040"><title>Results</title><sec id="s0045"><title>Study selection</title><p id="p0255">The search strategy yielded 2,261 non-duplicate articles (<xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>
). An additional eight studies were identified through snowballing and reference review techniques. After title and abstract screening, 80 studies underwent full text review. Agreement between three independent reviewers during title and abstract screening was 95.9% (2,176 / 2,269). During full text review, 38 articles were excluded (<xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). Inter-rater agreement of two independent reviewers during the full text screen was high (Cohen&#8217;s kappa&#160;=&#160;0.713, percent agreement&#160;=&#160;86.8%). Six studies were excluded during the data extraction phase (total excluded, n&#160;=&#160;44) due to the inability to differentiate outcomes of unresectable disease (n&#160;=&#160;4) or inability to differentiate disease-specific from overall survival (n&#160;=&#160;2). Experts in the field ensured there were no missing studies (AP, KC, ZH, AE). Therefore, 36 studies were included in the review <xref rid="b0140" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, <xref rid="b0145" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, <xref rid="b0150" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>, <xref rid="b0155" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>, <xref rid="b0160" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>, <xref rid="b0165" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>, <xref rid="b0170" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, <xref rid="b0175" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>, <xref rid="b0180" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, <xref rid="b0185" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>, <xref rid="b0190" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>, <xref rid="b0195" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>, <xref rid="b0200" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>, <xref rid="b0205" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>, <xref rid="b0210" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>, <xref rid="b0215" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>, <xref rid="b0220" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>, <xref rid="b0225" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>, <xref rid="b0230" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>, <xref rid="b0235" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>, <xref rid="b0240" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>, <xref rid="b0245" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>, <xref rid="b0250" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>, <xref rid="b0255" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>, <xref rid="b0260" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>, <xref rid="b0265" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>, <xref rid="b0270" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>, <xref rid="b0275" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>, <xref rid="b0280" ref-type="bibr">[56]</xref>, <xref rid="b0285" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>, <xref rid="b0290" ref-type="bibr">[58]</xref>, <xref rid="b0295" ref-type="bibr">[59]</xref>, <xref rid="b0300" ref-type="bibr">[60]</xref>, <xref rid="b0305" ref-type="bibr">[61]</xref>.<fig id="f0005" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>PRISMA flow diagram.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr1_lrg.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0050"><title>Study characteristics</title><p id="p0260">Study characteristics are summarized in <xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>
. Definitive radiotherapy or CCRT was investigated in 18 studies, of which one was a randomized controlled trial and the remainder were observational studies. Comparatively, induction or neoadjuvant chemotherapy, radiotherapy, or CCRT was also the focus of 18 articles, of which 4 studies were randomized controlled trials reporting on 3 different trials. The majority of studies provided either a comparison against primary surgery, such as in studies where the primary exposure of interest was definitive CCRT, or a comparison against no neoadjuvant treatment, such as in studies where the primary exposure of interest was neoadjuvant treatment (n&#160;=&#160;24, 66.7%). Half of the studies presented multivariable adjusted analysis of overall survival (n&#160;=&#160;18, 50.0%).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0005" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Characteristics of Included Studies (n&#160;=&#160;36).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">First Author</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Year</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Journal</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Country</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Design</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Data Source</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Comparator</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Matched</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">N</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Adjusted Analysis</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Stages</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cannon</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2017</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Head &amp; Neck</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">USA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective Cohort</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">SEER</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5856</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">III-IV</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Crombie</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2012</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Oral Oncology</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Australia</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective Cohort</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chart Review</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">54</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">I-IV</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ellis</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2017</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Otolaryngology Head &amp; Neck Surgery</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">USA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective Cohort</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NCDB</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1912 (matched); 20779(unmatched)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">I-II</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fujiwara</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2017</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Oral Oncology</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">USA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective Cohort</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NCDB</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">23,459</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">I-IV</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gogarty</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2017</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">European Archives of Oto-Rhino-Laryngology</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ireland</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective Cohort</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">National Cancer Registry Ireland (NCRI)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">397</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">I-II</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gore</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2014</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Head &amp; Neck</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Australia</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective Cohort</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unspecified Cancer Database</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">104</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">I-IV</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hauswald</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2012</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Acta Oncologica</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Germany</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective Cohort</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chart Review</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">66</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">I-IV</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">lyer</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2015</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cancer</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Singapore</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Randomized Controlled Trial</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">119</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">III-IV</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Jenwitheesuk</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2010</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Journal of the Medical Association of Thailand</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Thailand</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective Cohort</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chart Review</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">107</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">I-IV</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kjems</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2015</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">International Journal Radiation Oncology, Biology, Physics</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Denmark</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective Cohort</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chart Review</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">942 (100 OSCC)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">I-IV</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">McDowell</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2014</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Oral Surgery, Oral Medicine, Oral Pathology, and Oral Radiology</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Australia</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective Cohort</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chart Review</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">31</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">T4</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pederson</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2011</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">American Journal of Clinical Oncology</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">USA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prospective Cohort</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chart Review</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">21</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">II-IV</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scher</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2015</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Oral Oncology</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">USA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective Cohort</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chart Review</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">73</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">I-IV</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sowder</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2017</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Head &amp; Neck</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">USA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective Cohort</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">SEER</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8274</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">I-II</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Spiotto</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2017</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">JAMA Otolaryngology</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">USA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective Cohort</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NCDB</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2286 (matched); 6900(unmatched)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">III-IV</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Stenson</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2010</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">The Laryngoscope</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">USA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective Cohort</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chart Review</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">138</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">III-IV</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Studer</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2012</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Radiation Oncology</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Switzerland</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective Cohort</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chart Review</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">160</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">I-IV</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Wang</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2010</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Oral Surgery, Oral Medicine, Oral Pathology, Oral Radiology, and Endodontology</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Taiwan</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective Cohort</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chart Review</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">88</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">I-IV</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bossi</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2014</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Annals of Oncology</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Italy</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Randomized Controlled Trial</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">198</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">T2-T4</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chinn</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2014</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">JAMA Otolaryngology</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">USA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prospective cohort</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chart Review</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">72</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">III-IV</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Harada</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2013</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cancer Chemotherapy and Pharmacology</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Japan</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Non-Randomized Trial</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">39</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">III-IV</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hauswald</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2012</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Acta Oncologica</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Germany</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective Cohort</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chart Review</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">66</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">I-IV</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hirakawa</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2017</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Japanese Journal of Clinical Oncology</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Japan</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective Cohort</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chart Review</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">164</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">I-IV</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inhestern</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2017</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Annals of Oncology</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Germany</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Non-Randomized Trial</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">59</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">I-IV</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Irjala</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2012</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">European Archives of Oto-Rhino-Laryngology</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Finland</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective Cohort</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chart Review</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">I-IV</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kies</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2012</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Head &amp; Neck</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">USA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Non-Randomized Trial</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">23</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">T2-3&#160;N0-2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kina</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2016</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cancer Chemotherapy and Pharmacology</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Japan</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective Cohort</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chart Review</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">117</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">I-II</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kirita</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2012</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">International Journal of Oral &amp; Maxillofacial Surgery</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Japan</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prospective cohort</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chart Review</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">154</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">II-IV</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kreppel</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2013</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Journal of Cranio-Maxillo-Facial Surgery</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Germany</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective Cohort</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chart Review</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">139</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">II-IV</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kreppel</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2012</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Oral Oncology</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Germany</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective Cohort</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chart Review</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">151</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IV</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lyu</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2014</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">China</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective Cohort</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chart Review</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">III-IV</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mucke</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2011</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Annals of Surgical Oncology</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Germany</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective Cohort</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chart Review</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">926</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">I-IV</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Myers</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2011</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Otolaryngology Head &amp; Neck Surgery</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">USA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective Cohort</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chart Review</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">70</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">III-IV</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sadighi</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2014</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Acta Medica Iranica</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Iran</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Randomized Controlled Trial</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">III-IVa</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Zhong</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2015</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Oncotarget</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">China</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Randomized Controlled Trial</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">I-IV</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Zhong</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2013</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Journal of Clinical Oncology</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">China</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Randomized Controlled Trial</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">I-IV</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>NCDB: National Cancer Database, SEER: Surveillance, Epidemiology, and End Results</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s0055"><title>Risk of bias assessment</title><p id="p0265">Observational cohort studies (<bold>Supplemental Table S1</bold>) and randomized controlled trials (<bold>Supplemental Table S2</bold>) underwent risk of bias assessment. Observational studies without a comparator arm were considered to be case series and thus no bias can exist. Overall, observational cohort studies were predominately low quality, primarily due to lack of adjusted analysis and insufficient detail on follow-up. Trials were generally of low risk of bias, except one <xref rid="b0300" ref-type="bibr">[60]</xref>, which was considered high risk due to insufficient information regarding the allocation concealment and randomization process, and some concern on how missing outcome data was handled.</p></sec><sec id="s0060"><title>Definitive radiotherapy/Concurrent chemoradiotherapy</title><p id="p0270">Definitive radiotherapy or CCRT for OSCC was examined in 18 studies. Specific chemotherapy regimens varied substantially (<xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>
). Among included studies there was only one randomized control trial, of which patients with OSCC (stage III-IV) were assigned to either upfront surgery or definitive CCRT <xref rid="b0175" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. The regimen used included cisplatin at a dose of 20&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> and 5-fluorouracil at a dose of 1000&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup>, as continuous intravenous infusions for 96&#160;h on days 1 and 28 of the radiotherapy course. The primary tumor and upper neck received a radiation dose total of 66&#160;Gy in 33 fractions over 6.5&#160;weeks, whereas involved lymph nodes received at least 60&#160;Gy. For the remaining observational studies, there was a wide variation in specific delivery and dosages of both chemotherapy and radiotherapy (<xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0010" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Survival Outcomes for Patients Undergoing Definitive Radiotherapy or Chemoradiotherapy for Oral Cavity Squamous Cell Carcinoma.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">First Author</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Stage<hr/></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">n<xref rid="tblfn3" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">T (%)<hr/></th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">N (%)<hr/></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Treatment Modality</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Radiation<hr/></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chemotherapy</th><th colspan="5" rowspan="1"><bold>Overall Survival (years, %)</bold></th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">I-II</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">III-IV</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">1&#8211;2</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">3&#8211;4</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">2&#8211;3</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Technique</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Dose (Gy)<hr/></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Median</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Range</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dose per fraction</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cannon</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5856</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">41</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">58</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">26</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">39</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">RT<xref rid="tblfn1" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11&#8211;16</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Crombie</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">54</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">46</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CCRT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3DC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">69.7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">44&#8211;73.6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Various:<list list-type="simple" id="l0005"><list-item id="o0005"><label>1.</label><p id="p0005">Cisplatin 100&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV q21 days;</p></list-item><list-item id="o0010"><label>2.</label><p id="p0010">Cisplatin 100&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV, 5-FU 1000&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV q21 days;</p></list-item><list-item id="o0015"><label>3.</label><p id="p0015">Cisplatin 75&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV, TPZ 290&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV q21 days;</p></list-item><list-item id="o0020"><label>4.</label><p id="p0020">Carbo 300&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV, 5-FU 1000&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV q28 days;</p></list-item><list-item id="o0025"><label>5.</label><p id="p0025">CTX 400&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV then 250&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV q7 days</p></list-item></list></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">29</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ellis</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20,779</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">100</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">100</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">RT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Various:<break/><list list-type="simple" id="l0010"><list-item id="o0031"><label>1.</label><p id="p0031">EBRT</p></list-item><list-item id="o0030"><label>2.</label><p id="p0030">3DC</p></list-item><list-item id="o0035"><label>3.</label><p id="p0035">IMRT</p></list-item><list-item id="o0040"><label>4.</label><p id="p0040">Other</p></list-item></list></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">58.7<xref rid="tblfn4" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.0<sup>a,c</sup></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fujiwara</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">23,459</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">68</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">74</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">15</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">RT/CCRT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">46.0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gogarty</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">397</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">100</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">100</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">RT/CCRT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">55.4<xref rid="tblfn6" ref-type="table-fn">c</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">lyer</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">119</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">19</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">82</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">30</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">51</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CCRT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">66</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">66</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cisplatin 20&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV&#160;&#215;&#160;4&#160;days, 5-FU 1000&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV x4 days, day 1 and 28 of RT course</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">35</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gore</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">104</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">35</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">36</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CCRT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3DC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Platinum-based, other</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">52.1<xref rid="tblfn6" ref-type="table-fn">c</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.9<xref rid="tblfn6" ref-type="table-fn">c</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hauswald</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">66</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">70</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">26</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">26</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">27</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">39</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">RT/CCRT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Various:<list list-type="simple" id="l0015"><list-item id="o0045"><label>1.</label><p id="p0045">3DC</p></list-item><list-item id="o0050"><label>2.</label><p id="p0050">IMRT</p></list-item></list></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">66</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Platinum-based, immunotherapy</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.5<xref rid="tblfn6" ref-type="table-fn">c</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Jenwitheesuk</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">117</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CT/RT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kjems</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">942</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">57</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">42</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">65</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">RT/CCRT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Various:<list list-type="simple" id="l0020"><list-item id="o0055"><label>1.</label><p id="p0055">2D</p></list-item><list-item id="o0060"><label>2.</label><p id="p0060">3DC</p></list-item><list-item id="o0065"><label>3.</label><p id="p0065">IMRT</p></list-item></list></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">66&#8211;68</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cisplatin 40&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV q7days</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">48<xref rid="tblfn6" ref-type="table-fn">c</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">McDowell</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">31</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">100</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">55</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CCRT, CCRT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">70</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">70</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Various:<list list-type="simple" id="l0025"><list-item id="o0070"><label>1.</label><p id="p0070">Cisplatin 100&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV on weeks 1,4, 7;</p></list-item><list-item id="o0075"><label>2.</label><p id="p0075">Carbo, 5-FU three times weekly;</p></list-item><list-item id="o0080"><label>3.</label><p id="p0080">Cisplatin, TPZ.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0085"><label>4.</label><p id="p0085">Chemoboost, Carbo, 5-FU</p></list-item></list></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">40</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pederson</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x<xref rid="tblfn2" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">21</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">76</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">29</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">19</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">52</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CCRT, CT&#160;+&#160;CCRT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IMRT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">72&#8211;75</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.5&#8211;2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Various:<list list-type="simple" id="l0030"><list-item id="o0090"><label>1.</label><p id="p0090">FHX (600&#8211;800&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup>&#160;&#215;&#160;5&#160;days, 500&#8211;1000&#160;mg PO BID&#160;&#215;&#160;14&#160;days) q14days, with one of:</p></list-item><list-item id="o0095"><label>2.</label><p id="p0095">Paclitaxel 100&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV q14days;</p></list-item><list-item id="o0100"><label>3.</label><p id="p0100">Bevacizumab 2.5&#8211;10&#160;mg/kg/m<sup>2</sup> q14days;</p></list-item><list-item id="o0105"><label>4.</label><p id="p0105">+/- Induction Carbo AUC 2, paclitaxel 135&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> q7days&#160;&#215;&#160;6 cycles</p></list-item></list></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">76</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scher</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">73</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">21</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">80</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">33</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">51</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">RT/CCRT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Various:<list list-type="simple" id="l0035"><list-item id="o0110"><label>1.</label><p id="p0110">2D</p></list-item><list-item id="o0115"><label>2.</label><p id="p0115">3DC</p></list-item><list-item id="o0120"><label>3.</label><p id="p0120">IMRT</p></list-item></list></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">70</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.24&#8211;73.1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Various:<list list-type="simple" id="l0040"><list-item id="o0125"><label>1.</label><p id="p0125">Cisplatin 100&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV q21days&#160;&#215;&#160;2&#8211;3 cycles;</p></list-item><list-item id="o0130"><label>2.</label><p id="p0130">Cisplatin 100&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV q21days x2-3 cycles, Other;</p></list-item><list-item id="o0135"><label>3.</label><p id="p0135">Carbo 70&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV&#160;&#215;&#160;4&#160;days</p></list-item><list-item id="o0140"><label>4.</label><p id="p0140">Carbo 70&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV, 5-FU 600&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV&#160;&#215;&#160;4&#160;days;</p></list-item><list-item id="o0145"><label>5.</label><p id="p0145">Carbo 70&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV, paclitaxel 50&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV&#160;&#215;&#160;4&#160;days;</p></list-item><list-item id="o0150"><label>6.</label><p id="p0150">CTX 400&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> then 250&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV q7days</p></list-item><list-item id="o0155"><label>7.</label><p id="p0155">CTX 400&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> then 250&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV, paclitaxel 50&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV qweeklyx7</p></list-item></list></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">15<xref rid="tblfn6" ref-type="table-fn">c</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sowder</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8274</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">100</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">RT<xref rid="tblfn1" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.3<xref rid="tblfn6" ref-type="table-fn">c</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Spiotto</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6900</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">29</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">70</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">44</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CCRT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">40</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Stenson</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">111</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">78</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CCRT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Various:<list list-type="simple" id="l0045"><list-item id="o0160"><label>1.</label><p id="p0160">2D</p></list-item><list-item id="o0165"><label>2.</label><p id="p0165">3DC</p></list-item><list-item id="o0170"><label>3.</label><p id="p0170">IMRT</p></list-item></list></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">60&#8211;75</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.5&#8211;2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Various: 5-FU NOS and hydroxyurea NOS with paclitaxel, docetaxol, carbo, cisplatin, or other NOS</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">65.9</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Studer</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">160</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">RT/CCRT/CT&#160;+&#160;CCRT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IMRT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">69.6&#8211;70</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Various:<list list-type="simple" id="l0050"><list-item id="o0175"><label>1.</label><p id="p0175">Cisplatin 40&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV q7days;</p></list-item><list-item id="o0180"><label>2.</label><p id="p0180">CTX 400&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV then 250&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV q7days</p></list-item><list-item id="o0185"><label>3.</label><p id="p0185">+/- Induction, taxotere, cisplatin, 5-FU</p></list-item></list></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">37</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Wang</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">88</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">41</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">59</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">78</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CCRT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3DC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">68&#8211;74</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.8&#8211;2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cisplatin 100&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV q21days then (cisplatin 100&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV&#160;&#215;&#160;1&#160;day and 5-FU 1000&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV&#160;&#215;&#160;4&#160;days)&#160;&#215;&#160;2 cycles</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">15</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="sp0060"><p><sup>a</sup> overall survival for matched cohort</p></fn><fn id="sp0065"><p><sup>b</sup> obtained from Licitra et al.</p></fn><fn id="sp0070"><p><sup>c</sup> obtained from digitization of Kaplan-Meier curves</p></fn><fn id="sp0075"><p>-&#8216; not reported</p></fn><fn id="sp0080"><p>2D&#160;=&#160;Conventional two-dimensional radiation; 3DC&#160;=&#160;Three-dimensional conformal radiation therapy; 5-FU&#160;=&#160;5-fluorouracil; AUC&#160;=&#160;Area Under the Curve; Carbo&#160;=&#160;Carboplatin; CT&#160;=&#160;Chemotherapy; CTX&#160;=&#160;Cetuximab; CRT&#160;=&#160;chemoradiotherapy; EBRT&#160;=&#160;External Beam Radiation Therapy; FHX: 5-Fluorouracil, hydroxyurea, radiation; IMRT&#160;=&#160;Intensity-modulated radiation therapy; NOS&#160;=&#160;Not Otherwise Stated, RT&#160;=&#160;Radiotherapy; TPZ: Tirapazamine</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn1"><label>*</label><p id="np005">obtained from SEER database which does not capture chemotherapy</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn2"><label>**</label><p id="np010">stage 2&#8211;4</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn3"><label>***</label><p id="np015">total study cohort, not just those receiving CRT/RT</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0275">All studies reported survival by year or provided Kaplan-Meier estimated survival curves (<xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The 5-year survival ranged from 0% to 76%. A subset of studies directly compared definitive radiotherapy or CCRT against primary surgery. Of these studies, eight performed adjusted analysis of the hazard of death. However, one study did not report the HR and therefore, seven studies were <italic toggle="yes">meta</italic>-analysed. Three studies restricted recruitment to early stage disease and were analysed separately from studies that included advanced disease or did not restrict participation. In early stage disease, definitive radiotherapy, with or without concurrent chemotherapy, was associated with a significantly increased hazard of death (<xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Figure&#160;2</xref>
<bold>A</bold>, HR: 2.39, 95% CI: 1.56&#8211;3.67, I<sup>2</sup>: 63%).<fig id="f0010" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Meta-analysis results for A) Early stage disease only and B) Late stage and all-stage disease. CI: confidence interval, SE: Standard error.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr2_lrg.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0280">In the four studies which excluded early disease, there was no statistically significant increased hazard of death associated with definitive CCRT (<xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Figure&#160;2</xref>
<bold>B</bold>, HR: 1.98, 95% CI: 0.85&#8211;4.64, I<sup>2</sup>: 84%). Only a single study showed a decreased hazard of death with definitive CCRT compared to primary surgery <xref rid="b0190" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>.</p><p id="p0285">Four studies, none of which had comparator arms, provided outcomes related to ORN. The proportion of patients experiencing ORN ranged between 6.8 and 18.4%, with a pooled proportion of 10.1% (95% CI: 5.5&#8211;14.7%, I<sup>2</sup>: 14.05%). Only a single study specifically reported the rate of neutropenia with definitive CCRT, in which the rate of febrile neutropenia was 19% and grade was not reported <xref rid="b0195" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s0065"><title>Neoadjuvant chemotherapy/Concurrent chemoradiotherapy</title><p id="p0290">Seventeen studies investigated neoadjuvant regimens. Nine of these studies explored neoadjuvant radiotherapy or CCRT and 8 evaluated chemotherapy alone (<xref rid="t0015" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>
). Among chemotherapy only studies, four reported on three different randomized control trials. Bossi et al. report the long-term results of individuals randomized to three cycles of cisplatin 100&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> and fluorouracil 1000&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> (120-h infusion administered every 21&#160;days) compared to upfront surgery in stage T2&#8211;T4, N0&#8211;N2 <xref rid="b0230" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>. Zhong et al. reported short- and long-term results of a phase III trial of patients receiving TPF (docetaxel, cisplatin, 5-flourouracil) induction in stage III/IVa OSCC <xref rid="b0305" ref-type="bibr">[61]</xref>, <xref rid="b0310" ref-type="bibr">[62]</xref>. Sadighi et al. also reported trial results of a TPF induction protocol in advanced OSCC <xref rid="b0300" ref-type="bibr">[60]</xref>.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0015" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Survival Outcomes for Patients Undergoing Either Neoadjuvant Chemotherapy or Neoadjuvant Chemoradiotherapy for Oral Cavity Squamous Cell Carcinoma.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">First Author</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Stage<hr/></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">n<xref rid="tblfn6" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">T (%)<hr/></th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">N (%)<hr/></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Neoadjuvant Modality</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Radiation<hr/></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chemotherapy</th><th colspan="5" rowspan="1"><bold>Overall Survival (years, %)</bold></th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">I-II</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">III-IV</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">1&#8211;2</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">3&#8211;4</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">2&#8211;3</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Technique</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Dose (Gy)<hr/></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Median</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Range</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dose per fraction</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bossi</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x<xref rid="tblfn5" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">198</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">41</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">59</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">57</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">27</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">None</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cisplatin 100&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV, 5-FU 1000&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV q21days&#160;&#215;&#160;3 cycles</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">55<xref rid="tblfn7" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chinn</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x<xref rid="tblfn5" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">72</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">76</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">26</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">51</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Various: Cisplatin NOS or Carboplatin, 5-FU NOS q21days&#160;&#215;&#160;1 cycle then CRT with:<break/>Cisplatin 100&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV q21days&#160;&#215;&#160;3 cycles;<break/>1. Carbo AUC 6 IV q21days&#160;&#215;&#160;3 cycles</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">47</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">42</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Harada</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">39</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">26</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">74</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">33</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">28</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">38</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CCRT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">40</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">40</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">S-1 50&#8211;100&#160;mg PO 5&#160;days/week&#160;&#215;&#160;4&#160;weeks</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">83.8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">78.9</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hauswald</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">66</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">70</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">26</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">26</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">27</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">39</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">RT/CCRT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IMRT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">40</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">40</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Platinum agent; immunotherapy (n&#160;=&#160;1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">56.1<xref rid="tblfn8" ref-type="table-fn">c</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hirakawa</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">164</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">80</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">34</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">21</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">45</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cisplatin 80&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV day 6, 5-FU 800&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV days 1&#8211;5, q21days&#160;&#215;&#160;1 cycle</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">63.8</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inhestern</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">54</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">43</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">57</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">87</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Docetaxel 30&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV , Cisplatin 40&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV, 5-FU 2000&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV days 1 and 8, q21days up to 3 cycles</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">97.3 responders73.7 non-responders</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Irjala</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">80</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">60</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">30</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">RT/CCRT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">63&#8211;65</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cisplatin 40&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV q7days&#160;&#215;&#160;4&#8211;6 cycles</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">60</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kies</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x<xref rid="tblfn5" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">23</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">57</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">43</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">43</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Paclitaxel 175&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV, Ifosfamide 1000&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV days 1&#8211;3, Carbo AUC 6 IV q21-28&#160;days&#160;&#215;&#160;3 cycles</td><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Crude overall survival: 48</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kina</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">117</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">100</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Met. Bleomycin 15&#160;mg IV twice weekly, S-1 100&#160;mg PO daily or UFT-E 450&#160;mg PO TID&#160;&#215;&#160;3&#160;weeks</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">90</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kirita</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x<xref rid="tblfn5" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">154</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CCRT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cisplatin 15&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> or Carbo 70&#8211;100&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> days 1&#8211;3 and peplomycin 5&#160;mg/day or 5-FU 500&#8211;750&#160;mg/day days 4&#8211;7, q28days&#160;&#215;&#160;2 cycles</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">83</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">79</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kreppel 2013</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x<xref rid="tblfn5" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">139</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">41</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">59</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">63</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CCRT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Carbo 60&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup>/day IV&#160;&#215;&#160;5&#160;days</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.5</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kreppel 2012</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x<xref rid="tblfn5" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">151</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">29</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">71</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CCRT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Carbo 70&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup>/day IV&#160;&#215;&#160;5&#160;days</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">46.3</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lyu</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">91</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">59</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">23</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CT&#160;+&#160;RT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Docetaxel 75&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV, cisplatin 75&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV, 5-FU 750&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV days 1&#8211;5, q21days&#160;&#215;&#160;2 cycles</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">67.2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mucke</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">926</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">68</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">60</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">23</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CCRT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">EBRT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cisplatin 12.5&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV&#160;&#215;&#160;5&#160;days during first week of RT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">85.3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">68.6</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Myers</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">70</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CT&#160;+&#160;RT/CCRT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">68</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">68</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Platinum agent/Taxane +/- 5-FU; CTX</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sadighi</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Docetaxel 70&#8211;80&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV Cisplatin 60&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV, 5-FU 750&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV&#160;&#215;&#160;5&#160;days&#160;&#215;&#160;2&#8211;3 cycles</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">46.5<xref rid="tblfn8" ref-type="table-fn">c</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">23<xref rid="tblfn8" ref-type="table-fn">c</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Zhong 2015</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">x</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">26</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">74</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">43</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">37</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Docetaxel 75&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV, Cisplatin 75&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV, 5-FU 750&#160;mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV on days1-5 q21days&#160;&#215;&#160;2 cycles</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.1<xref rid="tblfn8" ref-type="table-fn">c</xref></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="sp0090"><p>&#8216;-&#8216; not reported. 2D&#160;=&#160;Conventional two-dimensional radiation; 3DC&#160;=&#160;Three-dimensional conformational radiation therapy; 5-FU&#160;=&#160;5-fluorouracil, Carbo&#160;=&#160;Carboplatin, CT&#160;=&#160;Chemotherapy, CTX&#160;=&#160;Cetuximab, CRT&#160;=&#160;chemoradiotherapy; EBRT&#160;=&#160;External Beam Radiation Therapy, IMRT&#160;=&#160;Intensity-modulated radiation therapy, Met.&#160;=&#160;Metronomic, RT&#160;=&#160;Radiotherapy, S-1&#160;=&#160;oral 5-FU, UFT-E&#160;=&#160;oral 5-FU</p></fn><fn id="sp0095"><p><sup>a</sup>overall survival for matched cohort</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn4"><label>*</label><p id="np020">obtained from SEER database which does not capture chemotherapy</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn5"><label>**</label><p id="np025">stage 2&#8211;4</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn6"><label>***</label><p id="np030">total study cohort, not just those receiving CRT/RT</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn7"><label>b</label><p id="np035">obtained from Lictra et al.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn8"><label>c</label><p id="np040">obtained from digitization of Kaplan-Meier curves</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0295">One study investigated induction chemotherapy <xref rid="b0235" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>. Chinn and colleagues treated patients with induction cisplatin or carboplatin and fluorouracil. Tumor response was assessed at 3&#160;weeks, and patients with a response of greater than 50% were treated with definitive CCRT. Patients with responses less than 50% were treated with definitive surgical resection. Of the 53% of patients who responded to the initial induction therapy, 30% had complete response after CCRT. Of the 70% who did not have complete response after CCRT, 14% were successfully salvaged with surgery. Overall, patients undergoing induction chemotherapy had a 2.5 times increased hazard of death compared to those undergoing definitive surgery, regardless of initial response status to induction chemotherapy.</p><p id="p0300">For the 9 studies looking at neoadjuvant radiotherapy or CCRT the median radiation dose was 40 Gray. Typically, chemotherapy was administered concurrently, though induction protocols were also described.</p><p id="p0305">Among all studies reporting neoadjuvant or induction regimens, the median length of the neoadjuvant/induction treatment period was 5.0&#160;weeks (IQR 3.75 &#8211; 6.75&#160;weeks, range 2 &#8211; 12&#160;weeks). The length of time between conclusion of neoadjuvant or induction treatment to initiation of definitive treatment (either CCRT or surgery) was infrequently reported and varied between immediate and longer than 3&#160;weeks. Few studies specifically reported the proportion of patients receiving neoadjuvant treatment who did not undergo surgery. Only one study reported deaths in this interval, of which the death was unrelated to the neoadjuvant treatment or cancer <xref rid="b0310" ref-type="bibr">[62]</xref>. The majority of observational studies included only those patients who went on to have surgery.</p><p id="p0310">Five studies reported rates of neutropenia, which ranged from 3.7% to 26.1% of varying grades <xref rid="b0240" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>, <xref rid="b0245" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>, <xref rid="b0250" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>, <xref rid="b0260" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>, <xref rid="b0310" ref-type="bibr">[62]</xref>. Febrile neutropenia was specifically reported in three studies, ranging from 1.4% to 4.3% of varying grades <xref rid="b0245" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>, <xref rid="b0260" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>, <xref rid="b0310" ref-type="bibr">[62]</xref>.</p><p id="p0315">Among all included studies, one study reported 1-year overall survival (47.0%), five studies reported 2-year overall survival (46.5&#8211;86.7%), two reported 3-year (42.0%, 83.8%), and 12 reported 5-year overall survival (23.0&#8211;90.0%). One study reported crude overall survival (48.0%) and one study reported 10-year survival (46.5%). Meta-analysis of induction CCRT was not performed as insufficient information could be gathered from studies purporting to report adjusted analysis. Additionally, a recent <italic toggle="yes">meta</italic>-regression has already been published combining the results of the Zhong and Bossi trials <xref rid="b0105" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s0070"><title>Neoadjuvant immunotherapy</title><p id="p0320">No published studies were identified that reported final results of neoadjuvant immunotherapy trials. Published abstracts reporting preliminary results, as well as ongoing trials, were identified by reference review and snowballing techniques. One manuscript was retrieved as a non-peer reviewed pre-print. <xref rid="t0020" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>
summarizes ongoing immunotherapy trials that include the oral cavity, the majority of which include other sites within the head and neck. Therefore, this literature is not yet mature for review and the results of these trials are as of yet unknown.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0020" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Ongoing Neoadjuvant Immunotherapy Trials for Oral Cavity Squamous Cell Carcinoma.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Trial</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Neoadjuvant/Induction Regimen</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sites</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Recruitment Status</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Time From 1st Dose to Primary Treatment</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:clinical-trial" xlink:href="NCT02296684">NCT02296684</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pembrolizumab</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Any</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Recruiting</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2&#8211;3&#160;weeks</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:clinical-trial" xlink:href="NCT02641093">NCT02641093</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pembrolizumab</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Any</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Recruiting</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1&#160;week</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:clinical-trial" xlink:href="NCT02919683">NCT02919683</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nivolumab, Nivolumab&#160;+&#160;Ipilimumab</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">OSCC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Active, Not Recruiting</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2&#160;weeks</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:clinical-trial" xlink:href="NCT03021993">NCT03021993</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nivolumab</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">OSCC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Recruiting</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">36&#8211;50&#160;days</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:clinical-trial" xlink:href="NCT02827838">NCT02827838</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Durvalumab</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">OSCC, OPCC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Recruiting</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2&#160;weeks&#160;+&#160;3&#8211;17&#160;days</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:clinical-trial" xlink:href="NCT02488759">NCT02488759</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nivolumab</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Any</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Active, Not Recruiting</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:clinical-trial" xlink:href="NCT03174275">NCT03174275</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Carboplatin, Paclitaxel, Durvalumab</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Any</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Recruiting</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8&#8211;14&#160;weeks</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:clinical-trial" xlink:href="NCT03700905">NCT03700905</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nivolumab, Nivolumab&#160;+&#160;Ipilimumab</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Any</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Recruiting</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2&#160;weeks</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:clinical-trial" xlink:href="NCT03737968">NCT03737968</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Durvalumab, Durvalumab&#160;+&#160;Tremelimumab</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Any</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Not Yet Recruiting</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4&#160;weeks</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:clinical-trial" xlink:href="NCT02997332">NCT02997332</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Durvalumab, Docetaxel, Cisplatin, 5-FU</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Any</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Recruiting</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7&#160;weeks</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:clinical-trial" xlink:href="NCT02882308">NCT02882308</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Olarparib Vs. Cisplatin And Olaparib Vs. Olaparib&#160;+&#160;Durvalumab</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Any</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Recruitment Complete</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">23&#8211;29&#160;days</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:clinical-trial" xlink:href="NCT03708224">NCT03708224</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Atezolizumab, Atezolizumab&#160;+&#160;Emactuzumab</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Any</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Recruiting</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3&#8211;6&#160;weeks</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:clinical-trial" xlink:href="NCT03003637">NCT03003637</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nivolumab, Nivolumab&#160;+&#160;Ipilimumab</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Any</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Recruiting</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3&#160;weeks</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:clinical-trial" xlink:href="NCT03700905">NCT03700905</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nivolumab</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Any</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Recruiting</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2&#160;weeks</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:clinical-trial" xlink:href="NCT03721757">NCT03721757</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nivolumab</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Any</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Not Yet Recruiting</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2&#160;weeks</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:clinical-trial" xlink:href="NCT03247712">NCT03247712</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nivolumab, Radiation</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Any</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Recruiting</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2&#8211;6&#160;weeks</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:clinical-trial" xlink:href="NCT03342911">NCT03342911</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nivolumab, Carboplatin, Paclitaxel</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Any</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Recruiting</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6&#160;weeks</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:clinical-trial" xlink:href="NCT02777385">NCT02777385</ext-link></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pembrolizumab</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Any</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Recruiting</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>&#8216;-&#8216; not reported</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0325">To date, four trials have reported preliminary trial results through published abstracts. One trial was restricted to oral cavity cancer, while the remaining three included all head and neck sites. Preliminary results of the latter trials do not stratify results by site. Checkmate 358 is a larger trial that includes non-head and neck cancer. Patients receive 2 cycles of preoperative nivolumab. Twenty-nine patients with head and neck cancer were reported, with 48% experiencing a reduction in tumor size, with 10% of patients having reductions of 40% or more. Amongst a cohort of 28 head and neck cancer patients enrolled in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:clinical-trial" xlink:href="NCT02641093">NCT02641093</ext-link>, a trial in which patients receive neoadjuvant pembrolizumab, followed by surgery and adjuvant pembrolizumab and radiation therapy, 47% of patients experienced a pathologic response&#160;greater than&#160;10% of which 68% had a major response (greater than 70%) and one patient had a complete response. Lastly, in nine oral cavity cancer patients enrolled in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:clinical-trial" xlink:href="NCT03021993">NCT03021993</ext-link>, where patients receive 3&#8211;4 cycles of nivolumab, 44% of patients experienced a reduction in tumor size of more than 30%. Amongst preliminary reports, adverse effects appear infrequent.</p><p id="p0330">In a non-peer reviewed pre-print report, results of <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:clinical-trial" xlink:href="NCT02296684">NCT02296684</ext-link> are available <xref rid="b0315" ref-type="bibr">[63]</xref>. Thirty-six patients were enrolled to receive neoadjuvant pembrolizumab. Tumor response of more than 50% was shown in 22% of patients, and more than 10% in an additional 22% of patients. The one-year relapse rate was 16.7% amongst all-comers, and 0% in patients with low and intermediate risk pathology.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0075"><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0335">The COVID-19 pandemic has placed significant strains on healthcare systems world-wide. Within head and neck oncology, temporary alteration to treatment paradigms may be required given limitations of resources due to the ongoing spread of COVID-19. Our review confirms the accepted notion that surgery remains the preferred treatment modality for OSCC. However, in the context of a pandemic, current standard of care may not be achievable within a preferred time frames, generally accepted as within one month <xref rid="b0320" ref-type="bibr">[64]</xref>. Depending on regional variation in COVID-19 surge, some centres may be forced to use less than ideal treatments. It is therefore important both in terms of decision-making and patient counselling to have summarized data pertaining to these options.</p><p id="p0340">This review reports on a contemporary repository of observational studies and randomized controlled trials that document survival outcomes for patients with surgically resectable OSCC undergoing non-surgical treatment. In some settings, primary CCRT offers near comparable survival outcomes, albeit with significant toxicity, most commonly and more specifically, ORN.</p><sec id="s0080"><title>Definitive radiotherapy/Concurrent chemoradiotherapy</title><p id="p0345">Primary surgical management of OSCC has been a mainstay of therapy for decades. Indeed, one of the included studies using recent National Cancer Data Base data determined that of more than 20,000 early oral cancers, surgery was the modality of choice in 95% of cases <xref rid="b0150" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. There have been two randomized trials attempting to compare surgery with primary radiotherapy. In 1998, Robertson et al. randomized individuals with a planned sample size of 350 patients, though the study was aborted after the first 30 patients showed inferior survival with definitive radiation <xref rid="b0325" ref-type="bibr">[65]</xref>. Similarly, in 2015, Iyer et al. terminated their study early due to poor accrual <xref rid="b0175" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. However, this review does present evidence for primary radiation or CCRT through the assessment of observational studies of low to moderate risk of bias. The pooled hazard of death was assessed in those studies, which reported adjusted analysis, and revealed over a 100% increased instantaneous risk of death amongst early OSCC patients. In advanced disease, the increased hazard of death was non-significant, likely owing to individual studies within the pooled analysis being underpowered, and not a lack of true association.</p><p id="p0350">Although not a primary outcome of this review, definitive CCRT was found to have a high rate of ORN, with pooled analysis suggesting over 10% of patients experience this complication. Previous studies have shown the risk of ORN to be both dose- and target volume-dependent, and as such, the oral cavity has been shown to have a more than four times risk of developing ORN compared to other sites <xref rid="b0330" ref-type="bibr">[66]</xref>, <xref rid="b0335" ref-type="bibr">[67]</xref>. Clinicians must balance the increased risk of mortality and morbidity associated with definitive CCRT, in light of improving radiotherapy techniques, against pandemic associated threats.</p><p id="p0355">Additionally, while primary CCRT has the advantage of potentially facilitating primarily outpatient management, it poses unique challenges in the COVID-19 setting <xref rid="b0340" ref-type="bibr">[68]</xref>. Chemotherapy is immunosuppressive and radiotherapy requires visits to a radiation centre. Early reports have noted that patients with a history of cancer were more likely to acquire COVID-19, and that individuals who are immunocompromised or have medical comorbidities are at higher risks for intensive care unit admission, morbidity, and mortality secondary to COVID-19 <xref rid="b0060" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, <xref rid="b0345" ref-type="bibr">[69]</xref>. Moreover, patients undergoing non-surgical regimens may present with symptoms that mirror COVID-19, including cough and sore throat which may then interrupt treatment and impact survival outcomes <xref rid="b0350" ref-type="bibr">[70]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s0085"><title>Neoadjuvant chemotherapy/Concurrent chemoradiotherapy</title><p id="p0360">Neoadjuvant and induction chemotherapy have been studied in advanced head and neck cancers since the 1990&#160;s <xref rid="b0355" ref-type="bibr">[71]</xref>, <xref rid="b0360" ref-type="bibr">[72]</xref>. Over the past decade, two randomized control trials have examined the role of neoadjuvant chemotherapy in OSCC. Bossi, Licitra and colleagues reported on the early and long-term results of a randomized trial of 198 operable oral cancer patients (T2-T4) who were randomized to three cycles of cisplatin and 5-fluorouracil followed by surgery versus surgery alone <xref rid="b0230" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>, <xref rid="b0365" ref-type="bibr">[73]</xref>. The addition of chemotherapy failed to provide a survival benefit, though it resulted in reduced rates of adjuvant radiation (33% vs 46%) as well as a higher incidence of mandibular preservation (52% vs 31%). Zhong et al. conducted a similar trial, albeit with a different triple neoadjuvant chemotherapy regimen (docetaxel, cisplatin and 5-fluorouracil). This trial also failed to demonstrate an overall survival benefit, and was associated with grade 3 hematological toxicity in 6.6% of patients and grade 2 adverse events in over 70% of patients <xref rid="b0305" ref-type="bibr">[61]</xref>. Marta et al. recently combined these studies in a <italic toggle="yes">meta</italic>-analysis. The pooled data of 451 patients failed to show any difference in overall survival <xref rid="b0105" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. A second <italic toggle="yes">meta</italic>-analysis of 27 randomized trials over a 40&#160;year period also failed to identify any benefit <xref rid="b0100" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>.</p><p id="p0365">While neoadjuvant chemotherapy may not have a demonstrated role in routine management of primary OSCC, there is a potential for it to provide symptom relief and even delay the need for surgery for a finite period of time. Indeed, there is even some evidence of benefit for neoadjuvant approach amongst responders <xref rid="b0305" ref-type="bibr">[61]</xref>. In this systematic review, neoadjuvant regimens prior to surgery included both chemotherapy alone and CCRT. Specific treatment regimens were varied, resulting in an inability to adequately combine studies. Nevertheless, in the event where an institution has a clearly delineated target day to deliver surgical care, therapy delivered in the pre-surgical period could be considered as an option either for neoadjuvant intent, or simply as a bridging option until resource restrictions are loosened &#8211; the key difference being in specific dosing regimens delivered.</p><p id="p0370">The avoidance of triple modality therapy through the use of induction chemotherapy has importance in both resource-constrained and resource-abundant settings. In patients who respond to initial induction chemotherapy, definitive CCRT would avoid and preserve the use of surgical treatment. However, only a single contemporary study was included in this review <xref rid="b0235" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>, which did not demonstrate survival benefit with the use of induction chemoselection. While over half of patients receiving induction chemoselection had an initial response, this strategy was associated with worse survival than definitive surgery with risk informed adjuvant treatment.</p></sec><sec id="s0090"><title>Neoadjuvant immunotherapy</title><p id="p0375">Immunotherapy is governed by the principle that tumors can evade immune detection, and immunotherapies can activate immunologic effector mechanisms to kill cancer cells <xref rid="b0370" ref-type="bibr">[74]</xref>. Integrating immunotherapeutics into upfront therapies has gained significant traction within the head and neck oncology community. While immunotherapy has shown encouraging results in the salvage setting <xref rid="b0375" ref-type="bibr">[75]</xref>, <xref rid="b0380" ref-type="bibr">[76]</xref>, neoadjuvant and induction immunotherapy remains under investigation. Of the 18 identified studies, only a single trial has produced mature results, which remain to undergo formal peer-review. For the management of patients in extremely resource constrained settings, upfront immunotherapy may afford additional time for definitive treatment, though this is not directly supported by current literature. Despite the potential benefits, limitations must be considered. Immune-mediated toxicity is a concern, and the question of hyperprogression has been raised <xref rid="b0385" ref-type="bibr">[77]</xref>. In addition, immunomodulation could have implications with regards to post-operative wound healing, potentially necessitating, instead of protecting against, health system utilization <xref rid="b0100" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>. Lastly, neoadjuvant immunotherapy in head and neck oncology is in its early randomized trial years and is far from standard of care, and therefore may not be accessible at many centers. Many centers have closed non-essential randomized trials in the context of COVID-19. It should also be noted that the vast majority of these trials are industry sponsored due to the very expensive cost of these agents and therefore even if these agents prove efficacious, rigorous cost-effectiveness analyses will be required before uptake. Further, some of these trials are window of opportunity studies, and thus the immunotherapy administered is considered experimental and not necessarily considered a component of the planned treatment <xref rid="b0390" ref-type="bibr">[78]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s0095"><title>Risk of surgical therapy in the wake of COVID-19</title><p id="p0380">Although findings from our study suggest superiority of oncological outcomes for OSCC managed surgically, clinicians must balance the risk to both patients and healthcare providers, as well as limitations of available resources, that surgery would impose during COVID-19. Surgical management may involve increased duration and time spent inside hospitals, during the pre-operative, operative, and post-operative periods, potentially increasing the risk of nosocomial infections. Additionally, intubation, tracheostomy, surgical manipulation of the upper aerodigestive tract, and post-operative care with suctioning of the oral cavity, are all considered aerosol generating medical procedures and known transmission routes for SARS-COV-2 <xref rid="b0010" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="b0395" ref-type="bibr">[79]</xref>, <xref rid="b0400" ref-type="bibr">[80]</xref>, <xref rid="b0405" ref-type="bibr">[81]</xref>. However, for many OSCCs, particularly early stage cancers, the short-term risks of surgery may be outweighed by the collective risk of daily presentation to a radiation centre over the course of 7&#160;weeks and the increased susceptibility to infection that is associated with CCRT. Furthermore, there has been rapid progression in protocols to allow for safer surgical care of the OSCC patient during COVID-19 including, appropriate use of personal protective equipment, self-isolation prior to surgery, and COVID-19 testing pre-operatively<xref rid="b0010" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0100"><title>Limitations</title><p id="p0385">The strengths of this review must be taken in context. Firstly, this was a rapid review of the literature. We did not pursue all elements of a formal systematic review given the evolving nature of the COVID-19 pandemic and need for timely evidence. Despite this, a number of formal systematic review methods were utilized, including the use of multiple reviewers and <italic toggle="yes">meta</italic>-analytical techniques. Reviews are inherently limited by the evidence quality available in the literature, and as randomized controlled trials were both few in number and high in risk of bias limitations in conclusions drawn from our findings must be noted <xref rid="b0410" ref-type="bibr">[82]</xref>. However, this study does offer the most comprehensive review of the contemporary literature on the non-surgical management of oral cavity cancer.</p></sec><sec id="s0105"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="p0390">How the COVID-19 pandemic affects treatment decisions and resource availability is likely to change as the pandemic unfolds. While head and neck surgeons should strive to provide standard of care therapies throughout the pandemic, reduced access to the operating room and availability of critical care services for post-operative management may necessitate the use of treatment strategies outside of standards of care, particularly in regions with an inability to manage a surge. This review suggests that primary radiation and chemotherapy are inferior to surgical management for oral cavity cancer. Strategies for oncologically safe surgical delay warranting consideration are sparse but may include select neoadjuvant regimens. Our hope is that this systematic review and <italic toggle="yes">meta</italic>-analysis will shed light on the risks and benefits of contemporary non-surgical options for OSCC within the nuanced COVID-19 pandemic setting. This is particularly important given the expected second wave or surge of COVID-19, which may again put head and neck cancer oncologists in a resource constrained environment. In times of profound uncertainty, the risks and benefits of all strategies must be weighed in the context of patients, healthcare providers, and the healthcare system.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="bi005"><title>References</title><ref id="b0005"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0005"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Emanuel</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Persad</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Upshur</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fair allocation of scarce medical resources in the time of Covid-19</article-title><source>Mass Medical Soc</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMsb2005114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32202722</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0010"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0010"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Noel</surname><given-names>C.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forner</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Enepekides</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Witterick</surname><given-names>I.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Waldron</surname><given-names>J.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Irish</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Considerations for head and neck oncology practices during the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID&#8208;19) pandemic: Wuhan and Toronto experience</article-title><source>Head Neck</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/hed.26205</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7267482</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32338807</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0015"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0015">NCCN. Head and Neck Cancers. NCCN Clinical Practice Guidelines in Oncology Web site. https://oncolife.com.ua/doc/nccn/Head_and_Neck_Cancers.pdf. Updated February 15, 2018. Accessed March 2, 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0020"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0020"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Caudell</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Locher</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonner</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diagnosis-to-treatment interval and control of locoregionally advanced head and neck cancer</article-title><source>Archives of Otolaryngology-Head &amp; Neck Surgery.</source><volume>137</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>282</fpage><lpage>285</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21422314</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/archoto.2011.20</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0025"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0025"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schutte</surname><given-names>H.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heutink</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wellenstein</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of Time to Diagnosis and Treatment in Head and Neck Cancer: A Systematic Review</article-title><source>Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery.</source><volume>162</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>446</fpage><lpage>457</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32093572</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/0194599820906387</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0030"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0030"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>C.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galloway</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Handorf</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Survival impact of increasing time to treatment initiation for patients with head and neck cancer in the United States</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><volume>34</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>169</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26628469</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1200/JCO.2015.61.5906</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4858932</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0035"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0035"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Engelman</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Postoperative care: who should look after patients following surgery?</article-title><source>Anaesthesia.</source><volume>75</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>e5</fpage><lpage>e9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31903574</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/anae.14887</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0040"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0040"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Clinical characteristics and outcomes of patients undergoing surgeries during the incubation period of COVID-19 infection.</source><volume>EClinicalMedicine</volume><year>2020:</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100331</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.eclinm.2020.100331</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7128617</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32292899</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0045"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0045"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical course and risk factors for mortality of adult inpatients with COVID-19 in Wuhan, China: a retrospective cohort study</article-title><source>The Lancet</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30566-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7270627</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32171076</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0050"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0050"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>R.-H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>L.-R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C.-Q.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Predictors of Mortality for Patients with COVID-19 Pneumonia Caused by SARS-CoV-2: A Prospective Cohort Study</article-title><source>Eur Respir J</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1183/13993003.00524-2020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7144257</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32269088</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0055"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0055"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Piccirillo</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Importance of comorbidity in head and neck cancer</article-title><source>The Laryngoscope.</source><volume>110</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2000</year><fpage>593</fpage><lpage>602</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10764003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/00005537-200004000-00011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0060"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0060"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cancer patients in SARS-CoV-2 infection: a nationwide analysis in China</article-title><source>Lancet Oncol</source><volume>21</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>335</fpage><lpage>337</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32066541</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S1470-2045(20)30096-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7159000</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0065"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0065">Canadian Association of Head &amp; Neck Surgical Oncology (CAHNSO) guidelines for management of Head &amp; Neck Cancer during the COVID-19 Pandemic. https://cahnso.com/covid-19-resources/. Published 2020. Accessed April 8, 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0070"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0070">Guidance for ENT surgeons during the COVID-19 pandemic. The Australian Society of Otolaryngology Head and Neck Surgery. http://www.asohns.org.au/about-us/news-and-announcements/latest-news?article=78. Published 2020. Accessed April 8, 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0075"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0075">Topf MC. A Framework for Prioritizing Head and Neck Surgery during the COVID-19 Pandemic. Head &amp; Neck. 2020(In press).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/hed.26184</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7262168</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32298036</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0080"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0080"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaves</surname><given-names>Aline Lauda Freitas</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>Ana Ferreira</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marta</surname><given-names>Gustavo Nader</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Junior</surname><given-names>Gilberto Castro</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferris</surname><given-names>Robert L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giglio</surname><given-names>Ra&#250;l Eduardo</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Golusinski</surname><given-names>Wojciech</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gorphe</surname><given-names>Philippe</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hosal</surname><given-names>Sefik</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leemans</surname><given-names>C. Ren&#233;</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Magn&#233;</surname><given-names>Nicolas</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehanna</surname><given-names>Hisham</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mes&#237;a</surname><given-names>Ricard</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Netto</surname><given-names>Eduardo</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Psyrri</surname><given-names>Amanda</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sacco</surname><given-names>Assuntina G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>Jatin</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>Christian</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vermorken</surname><given-names>Jan B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kowalski</surname><given-names>Luiz Paulo</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Emergency changes in international guidelines on treatment for head and neck cancer patients during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>Oral Oncol</source><volume>107</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>104734</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.oraloncology.2020.104734</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32353793</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7180373</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0085"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0085">Garritty C, Co-Convenor CR. Cochrane Rapid Review (RR) Methods: A Look at Interim Recommendations (Part 2). 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0090"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0090"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Furness</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Glenny</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Worthington</surname><given-names>H.V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interventions for the treatment of oral cavity and oropharyngeal cancer: chemotherapy</article-title><source>Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews.</source><year>2011(4).</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/14651858.CD006386.pub3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21491393</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0095"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0095"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Glenny</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Furness</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Worthington</surname><given-names>H.V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interventions for the treatment of oral cavity and oropharyngeal cancer: radiotherapy</article-title><source>Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews.</source><year>2010(12).</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/14651858.CD006387.pub2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10749265</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21154367</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0100"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0100"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>K.-Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Yang W-f, Su Y-X. Induction chemotherapy for squamous cell carcinomas of the oral cavity: a cumulative meta-analysis</article-title><source>Oral Oncol</source><volume>61</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>104</fpage><lpage>114</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27688112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.oraloncology.2016.08.022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0105"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0105"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marta</surname><given-names>G.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Andrade</surname><given-names>Carvalho H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intensity-modulated radiation therapy for head and neck cancer: systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Radiother Oncol</source><volume>110</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24332675</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.radonc.2013.11.010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0110"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0110"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sayers</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tips and tricks in performing a systematic review</article-title><source>Br J Gen Pract.</source><volume>57</volume><issue>538</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>425</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2047040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17504612</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0115"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0115"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Devisetty</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neoadjuvant versus induction chemotherapy: more than semantics</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><volume>31</volume><issue>23</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>2971</fpage><lpage>2972</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1200/JCO.2013.50.2674</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23733777</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0120"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0120">Sterne JA, Savovi&#263; J, Page MJ, et al. RoB 2: a revised tool for assessing risk of bias in randomised trials. bmj. 2019;366.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmj.l4898</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31462531</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0125"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0125"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stang</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Critical evaluation of the Newcastle-Ottawa scale for the assessment of the quality of nonrandomized studies in meta-analyses</article-title><source>Eur J Epidemiol</source><volume>25</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>603</fpage><lpage>605</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20652370</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10654-010-9491-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0130"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0130"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Landis</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>G.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The measurement of observer agreement for categorical data</article-title><source>Biometrics.</source><volume>33</volume><issue>1</issue><year>1977</year><fpage>159</fpage><lpage>174</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">843571</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0135"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0135"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cochrane handbook for systematic reviews</article-title><source>of interventions.</source><year>2011</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0140"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0140"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cannon</surname><given-names>R.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sowder</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buchmann</surname><given-names>L.O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increasing use of nonsurgical therapy in advanced-stage oral cavity cancer: A population-based study</article-title><source>Head Neck</source><volume>39</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>82</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27641220</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/hed.24542</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0145"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0145"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Crombie</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farah</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tripcony</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dickie</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Batstone</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Primary chemoradiotherapy for oral cavity squamous cell carcinoma</article-title><source>Oral Oncol</source><volume>48</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>1014</fpage><lpage>1018</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22516377</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.oraloncology.2012.03.027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0150"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0150"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Graboyes</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wahlquist</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Primary surgery vs radiotherapy for early stage oral cavity cancer</article-title><source>Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery.</source><volume>158</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>649</fpage><lpage>659</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29256326</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/0194599817746909</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0155"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0155"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujiwara</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burtness</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Husain</surname><given-names>Z.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Treatment guidelines and patterns of care in oral cavity squamous cell carcinoma: primary surgical resection vs. nonsurgical treatment</article-title><source>Oral Oncol</source><volume>71</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>137</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28688680</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.oraloncology.2017.06.013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0160"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0160"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gogarty</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lennon</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deady</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Variation in treatment and outcome in the early stage oral cavity squamous cell carcinoma</article-title><source>Eur Arch Otorhinolaryngol</source><volume>274</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>953</fpage><lpage>960</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27554664</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00405-016-4267-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0165"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0165"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gore</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crombie</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Batstone</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Concurrent chemoradiotherapy compared with surgery and adjuvant radiotherapy for oral cavity squamous cell carcinoma</article-title><source>Head Neck</source><volume>37</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>518</fpage><lpage>523</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24532246</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/hed.23626</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0170"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0170"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hauswald</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zwicker</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rochet</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>A.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Debus</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindel</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Treatment of squamous cell carcinoma of the mobile tongue or tongue margins: An interdisciplinary challenge</article-title><source>Acta Oncol</source><volume>52</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>1017</fpage><lpage>1021</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22978496</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3109/0284186X.2012.722678</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0175"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0175"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iyer</surname><given-names>N.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>V.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Randomized trial comparing surgery and adjuvant radiotherapy versus concurrent chemoradiotherapy in patients with advanced, nonmetastatic squamous cell carcinoma of the head and neck: 10-year update and subset analysis</article-title><source>Cancer</source><volume>121</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>1599</fpage><lpage>1607</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25639864</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/cncr.29251</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0180"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0180"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jenwitheesuk</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Surakunprapha</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chowchuen</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Results of multidisciplinary therapy of squamous cell carcinoma of the buccal mucosa at Srinagarind Hospital, Thailand</article-title><source>Medical journal of the Medical Association of Thailand.</source><volume>93</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>1262</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21114204</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0185"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0185"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kjems</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gothelf</surname><given-names>A.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>H&#229;kansson</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Specht</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kristensen</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Friborg</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Elective nodal irradiation and patterns of failure in head and neck cancer after primary radiation therapy. <italic toggle="yes">International Journal of Radiation Oncology* Biology*</italic></article-title><source>Physics.</source><volume>94</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>775</fpage><lpage>782</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ijrobp.2015.12.380</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26972650</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0190"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0190"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McDowell</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kleid</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rischin</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Corry</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>T4 squamous cell carcinoma of the oral tongue without mandibular involvement: surgery or chemoradiotherapy?</article-title><source>Oral surgery, oral medicine, oral pathology and oral radiology.</source><volume>117</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>169</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.oooo.2013.09.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24275355</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0195"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0195"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pederson</surname><given-names>A.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salama</surname><given-names>J.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Witt</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Concurrent chemotherapy and intensity-modulated radiotherapy for organ preservation of locoregionally advanced oral cavity cancer</article-title><source>Am J Clin Oncol</source><volume>34</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>356</fpage><lpage>361</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21633289</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/COC.0b013e3181e8420b</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0200"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0200"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scher</surname><given-names>E.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Romesser</surname><given-names>P.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Definitive chemoradiation for primary oral cavity carcinoma: a single institution experience</article-title><source>Oral Oncol</source><volume>51</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>709</fpage><lpage>715</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25958830</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.oraloncology.2015.04.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4975927</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0205"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0205"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sowder</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cannon</surname><given-names>R.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buchmann</surname><given-names>L.O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Treatment-related determinants of survival in early-stage (T1&#8211;2N0M0) oral cavity cancer: A population-based study</article-title><source>Head Neck</source><volume>39</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>876</fpage><lpage>880</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28236368</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/hed.24679</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0210"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0210"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spiotto</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jefferson</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wenig</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Markiewicz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weichselbaum</surname><given-names>R.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koshy</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differences in survival with surgery and postoperative radiotherapy compared with definitive chemoradiotherapy for oral cavity cancer: a national cancer database analysis</article-title><source>JAMA Otolaryngology-Head &amp; Neck Surgery.</source><volume>143</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>691</fpage><lpage>699</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28426848</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamaoto.2017.0012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5547927</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0215"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0215"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stenson</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kunnavakkam</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>E.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemoradiation for patients with advanced oral cavity cancer</article-title><source>The Laryngoscope.</source><volume>120</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>99</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19856305</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/lary.20716</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0220"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0220"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Studer</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bredell</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Follow up after IMRT in oral cavity cancer: update</article-title><source>Radiation oncology.</source><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>84</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22686297</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1748-717X-7-84</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3488022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0225"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0225"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>C.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>C.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsou</surname><given-names>Y.-A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tseng</surname><given-names>H.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk factors affect the survival outcome of hard palatal and maxillary alveolus squamous cell carcinoma: 10-year review in a tertiary referral center</article-title><source>Oral Surgery, Oral Medicine, Oral Pathology, Oral Radiology, and Endodontology.</source><volume>110</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.tripleo.2009.11.035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20299251</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0230"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0230"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bossi</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lo Vullo</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guzzo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preoperative chemotherapy in advanced resectable OCSCC: long-term results of a randomized phase III trial</article-title><source>Ann Oncol</source><volume>25</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>462</fpage><lpage>466</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24401930</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/annonc/mdt555</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0235"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0235"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chinn</surname><given-names>S.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spector</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bellile</surname><given-names>E.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficacy of induction selection chemotherapy vs primary surgery for patients with advanced oral cavity carcinoma</article-title><source>JAMA Otolaryngology-Head &amp; Neck Surgery.</source><volume>140</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>134</fpage><lpage>142</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24370563</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamaoto.2013.5892</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4103099</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0240"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0240"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Omura</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomioka</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multicenter phase II trial of preoperative chemoradiotherapy with S-1 for locally advanced oral squamous cell carcinoma</article-title><source>Cancer Chemother Pharmacol</source><volume>71</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>1059</fpage><lpage>1064</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23377375</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00280-013-2101-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3607732</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0245"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0245"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirakawa</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanai</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prognostic importance of pathological response to neoadjuvant chemotherapy followed by definitive surgery in advanced oral squamous cell carcinoma</article-title><source>Jpn J Clin Oncol</source><volume>47</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>1038</fpage><lpage>1046</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28985398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/jjco/hyx097</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0250"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0250"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Inhestern</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmalenberg</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dietz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A two-arm multicenter phase II trial of one cycle chemoselection split-dose docetaxel, cisplatin and 5-fluorouracil (TPF) induction chemotherapy before two cycles of split TPF followed by curative surgery combined with postoperative radiotherapy in patients with locally advanced oral and oropharyngeal squamous cell cancer (TISOC-1)</article-title><source>Ann Oncol</source><volume>28</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>1917</fpage><lpage>1922</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28498880</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/annonc/mdx202</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0255"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0255"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Irjala</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kinnunen</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aitasalo</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mandibular reconstruction using free bone flap after preoperative chemoradiation</article-title><source>Eur Arch Otorhinolaryngol</source><volume>269</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>1513</fpage><lpage>1518</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21990054</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00405-011-1795-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0260"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0260"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kies</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boatright</surname><given-names>D.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phase II trial of induction chemotherapy followed by surgery for squamous cell carcinoma of the oral tongue in young adults</article-title><source>Head Neck</source><volume>34</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>1255</fpage><lpage>1262</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22009800</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/hed.21906</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3893095</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0265"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0265"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kina</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakasone</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kinjo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maruyama</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kawano</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arasaki</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of metronomic neoadjuvant chemotherapy on early tongue cancer</article-title><source>Cancer Chemother Pharmacol</source><volume>78</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>833</fpage><lpage>840</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27577260</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00280-016-3141-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0270"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0270"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirita</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamanaka</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Imai</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preoperative concurrent chemoradiotherapy for stages II&#8211;IV oral squamous cell carcinoma: A retrospective analysis and the future possibility of this treatment strategy</article-title><source>Int J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source><volume>41</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>421</fpage><lpage>428</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22356740</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ijom.2011.12.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0275"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0275"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kreppel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eich</surname><given-names>H.-T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Br&#252;ggenolte</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preoperative vs. postoperative radiochemotherapy in patients with N2 squamous cell carcinoma of the oral cavity</article-title><source>Oral Oncol</source><volume>48</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>1019</fpage><lpage>1024</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22560339</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.oraloncology.2012.04.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0280"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0280"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kreppel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dreiseidler</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rothamel</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of clinical versus histopathological staging in patients with advanced oral squamous cell carcinoma treated with neoadjuvant radiochemotherapy followed by radical surgery</article-title><source>Journal of Cranio-Maxillofacial Surgery.</source><volume>41</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>22</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22727901</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jcms.2012.05.005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0285"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0285"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lyu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sequential Therapy of Advanced Buccal Mucosa Squamous Cell Carcinoma: Three-Year Outcome</article-title><source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source><volume>72</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>606</fpage><lpage>610</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24342583</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.joms.2013.09.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0290"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0290"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>M&#252;cke</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Konen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wagenpfeil</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kesting</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolff</surname><given-names>K.-D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>H&#246;lzle</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Low-dose preoperative chemoradiation therapy compared with surgery alone with or without postoperative radiotherapy in patients with head and neck carcinoma</article-title><source>Ann Surg Oncol</source><volume>18</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>2739</fpage><lpage>2747</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21424882</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1245/s10434-011-1643-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0295"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0295"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>L.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sumer</surname><given-names>B.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Truelson</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of treatment sequence of multimodal therapy for advanced oral cavity cancer with mandible invasion</article-title><source>Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery.</source><volume>145</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>961</fpage><lpage>966</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21810773</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/0194599811417550</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0300"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0300"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sadighi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keyhani</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harirchi</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neoadjuvant Chemotherapy for Locally Advanced Squamous Carcinoma of Oral Cavity: a Pilot Study</article-title><source>Acta Medica Iranica.</source><volume>380&#8211;386</volume><year>2015</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26069178</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0305"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0305"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>L-p</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C-p</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>G-x</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Randomized phase III trial of induction chemotherapy with docetaxel, cisplatin, and fluorouracil followed by surgery versus up-front surgery in locally advanced resectable oral squamous cell carcinoma</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><volume>31</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>744</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23129742</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1200/JCO.2012.43.8820</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5569675</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0310"><label>62</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0310"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>L-p</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C-p</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>G-x</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long-term results of a randomized phase III trial of TPF induction chemotherapy followed by surgery and radiation in locally advanced oral squamous cell carcinoma</article-title><source>Oncotarget.</source><volume>6</volume><issue>21</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>18707</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26124084</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.18632/oncotarget.4531</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4621922</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0315"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0315">Uppaluri. Neoadjuvant and Adjuvant Pembrolizumab in Resectable Locally Advanced, Human Papillomavirus-Unrelated Head and Neck Cancer: A Multicenter, Phase 2 Trial In. medRxiv2020.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-20-1695</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7547532</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32665297</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0320"><label>64</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0320"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trama</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Botta</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foschi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Indicators for measuring integrated quality of care for head and neck cancers: the experience of the European project RARECAREnet</article-title><source>Front Oncol</source><volume>9</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>837</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31555591</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fonc.2019.00837</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6722861</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0325"><label>65</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0325"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soutar</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Early closure of a randomized trial: surgery and postoperative radiotherapy versus radiotherapy in the management of intra-oral tumours</article-title><source>Clinical Oncology.</source><volume>10</volume><issue>3</issue><year>1998</year><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9704176</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0936-6555(98)80055-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0330"><label>66</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0330"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oral cancer: Current role of radiotherapy and chemotherapy</article-title><source>Medicina oral, patologia oral y cirugia bucal.</source><volume>18</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2013</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e233</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4317/medoral.18772</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3613874</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23385513</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0335"><label>67</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0335"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Caparrotti</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Osteoradionecrosis of the mandible in patients with oropharyngeal carcinoma treated with intensity-modulated radiotherapy</article-title><source>Cancer</source><volume>123</volume><issue>19</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>3691</fpage><lpage>3700</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28608925</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/cncr.30803</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0340"><label>68</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0340"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Day</surname><given-names>A.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sher</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Head and neck oncology during the COVID-19 pandemic: Reconsidering traditional treatment paradigms in light of new surgical and other multilevel risks</article-title><source>Oral Oncol</source><volume>104684</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.oraloncology.2020.104684</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7136871</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32330858</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0345"><label>69</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0345"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk of COVID-19 for cancer patients</article-title><source>Lancet Oncol</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S1470-2045(20)30150-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7130057</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32142622</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0350"><label>70</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0350"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fesinmeyer</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blough</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tock</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramsey</surname><given-names>S.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of radiotherapy interruptions on survival in medicare enrollees with local and regional head-and-neck cancer. <italic toggle="yes">International Journal of Radiation Oncology* Biology*</italic></article-title><source>Physics.</source><volume>78</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>675</fpage><lpage>681</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ijrobp.2009.08.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20133084</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0355"><label>71</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0355"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Domenge</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lefebvre</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Randomized trial of neoadjuvant chemotherapy in oropharyngeal carcinoma</article-title><source>Br J Cancer</source><volume>83</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2000</year><fpage>1594</fpage><lpage>1598</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11189100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1054/bjoc.2000.1512</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2363468</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0360"><label>72</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0360"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paccagnella</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mastromauro</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>D'Amanzo</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghi</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Induction chemotherapy before chemoradiotherapy in locally advanced head and neck cancer: the future?</article-title><source>Oncologist.</source><volume>15</volume><year>2010</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1634/theoncologist.2010-S3-08</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21036883</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0365"><label>73</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0365"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Licitra</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grandi</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guzzo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Primary chemotherapy in resectable oral cavity squamous cell cancer: a randomized controlled trial</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><volume>21</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2003</year><fpage>327</fpage><lpage>333</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12525526</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1200/JCO.2003.06.146</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0370"><label>74</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0370"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Couzin-Frankel</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cancer Immunotherapy</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>342</volume><issue>6165</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>1432</fpage><lpage>1433</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science:342.6165.1432</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24357284</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0375"><label>75</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0375"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>E.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Souli&#232;res</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Le Tourneau</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pembrolizumab versus methotrexate, docetaxel, or cetuximab for recurrent or metastatic head-and-neck squamous cell carcinoma (KEYNOTE-040): a randomised, open-label, phase 3 study</article-title><source>The Lancet.</source><volume>393</volume><issue>10167</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>156</fpage><lpage>167</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(18)31999-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30509740</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0380"><label>76</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0380"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferris</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blumenschein</surname><given-names>G.</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fayette</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nivolumab for recurrent squamous-cell carcinoma of the head and neck</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><volume>375</volume><issue>19</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>1856</fpage><lpage>1867</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27718784</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMoa1602252</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5564292</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0385"><label>77</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0385"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sa&#226;da-Bouzid</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Defaucheux</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karabajakian</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hyperprogression during anti-PD-1/PD-L1 therapy in patients with recurrent and/or metastatic head and neck squamous cell carcinoma</article-title><source>Ann Oncol</source><volume>28</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>1605</fpage><lpage>1611</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28419181</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/annonc/mdx178</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0390"><label>78</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0390"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernal</surname><given-names>M.O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chepeha</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prawira</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Abstract CT124: Sitravatinib and nivolumab in oral cavity cancer window of opportunity study (SNOW)</article-title><source>AACR</source><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/jitc-2021-003476</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8488751</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34599023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0395"><label>79</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0395"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Judson</surname><given-names>S.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Munster</surname><given-names>V.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nosocomial Transmission of Emerging Viruses via Aerosol-Generating Medical Procedures</article-title><source>Viruses.</source><volume>11</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>940</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/v11100940</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6832307</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31614743</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0400"><label>80</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0400"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The transmission and diagnosis of 2019 novel coronavirus infection disease (COVID-19): A Chinese perspective</article-title><source>J Med Virol</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/jmv.25749</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7228390</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32141619</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0405"><label>81</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0405"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Misra</surname><given-names>Anoop</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Doctors and healthcare workers at frontline of COVID 19 epidemic: Admiration, a pat on the back, and need for extreme caution</article-title><source>Diabetes &amp; Metabolic Syndrome: Clinical Research &amp; Reviews</source><volume>14</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>255</fpage><lpage>256</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.dsx.2020.03.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7102612</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32248083</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0410"><label>82</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0410"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Noel</surname><given-names>C.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McMullen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The fragility of statistically significant findings from randomized trials in head and neck surgery</article-title><source>The Laryngoscope.</source><volume>128</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>2094</fpage><lpage>2100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29683494</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/lary.27183</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="s0115" sec-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><title>Supplementary data</title><p id="p0400">The following are the Supplementary data to this article:<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="m0005" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Supplementary data 1</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc1.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material>
</p></sec><fn-group><fn id="s0110" fn-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><p id="p0395">Supplementary data to this article can be found online at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.oraloncology.2020.104849" id="ir005">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.oraloncology.2020.104849</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article></pmc-articleset>