<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Inflamm Bowel Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Inflamm. Bowel Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3518</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">ibdjournal</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ibd</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Inflammatory Bowel Diseases</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1078-0998</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1536-4844</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7301406</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC7301406.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">7301406</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">7301406</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31559415</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ibd/izz210</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">izz210</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Clinical Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection"><subject>AcademicSubjects/MED00260</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Laryngeal Carcinoma in Patients With Inflammatory Bowel Disease: Clinical Outcomes and Risk Factors</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9793-0957</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>van de Ven</surname><given-names initials="SEM">Steffi E M</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Derikx</surname><given-names initials="LAAP">Lauranne A A P</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0887-4127</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagtegaal</surname><given-names initials="ID">Iris D</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0003">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Herpen</surname><given-names initials="CM">Carla M</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0004">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Takes</surname><given-names initials="RP">Robert P</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0005">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Melchers</surname><given-names initials="WJG">Willem J G</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0006">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pierik</surname><given-names initials="M">Marieke</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0007">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van den Heuvel</surname><given-names initials="T">Tim</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0007">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Verhoeven</surname><given-names initials="RHA">Rob H A</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0008">8</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoentjen</surname><given-names initials="F">Frank</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nissen</surname><given-names initials="LHC">L H C</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0009">9</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1"/></contrib><on-behalf-of>on Behalf of the Dutch Initiative on Crohn and Colitis (ICC), Dutch Head and Neck Society, PALGA Group, and IBD/HNC Group</on-behalf-of></contrib-group><aff id="AF0001"><label>1</label>
<institution>Department of Gastroenterology and Hepatology, Erasmus MC, University Medical Center</institution>, Rotterdam, <country country="NL">the Netherlands</country></aff><aff id="AF0002"><label>2</label>
<institution>Department of Gastroenterology and Hepatology, Radboud University Medical Center</institution>, Nijmegen, <country country="NL">the Netherlands</country></aff><aff id="AF0003"><label>3</label>
<institution>Department of Pathology, Radboud University Medical Center</institution>, Nijmegen, <country country="NL">the Netherlands</country></aff><aff id="AF0004"><label>4</label>
<institution>Department of Medical Oncology, Radboud University Medical Centre</institution>, Nijmegen, <country country="NL">the Netherlands</country></aff><aff id="AF0005"><label>5</label>
<institution>Department of Otolaryngology and Head and Neck Surgery, Radboud University Medical Center</institution>, Nijmegen, <country country="NL">the Netherlands</country></aff><aff id="AF0006"><label>6</label>
<institution>Department of Medical Microbiology, Radboud University Medical Center</institution>, Nijmegen, <country country="NL">the Netherlands</country></aff><aff id="AF0007"><label>7</label>
<institution>Department of Gastroenterology and Hepatology, Maastricht University Medical Centre</institution>, Maastricht, <country country="NL">the Netherlands</country></aff><aff id="AF0008"><label>8</label>
<institution>Department of Research &amp; Development, Netherlands Comprehensive Cancer Organization</institution>, Utrecht, <country country="NL">the Netherlands</country></aff><aff id="AF0009"><label>9</label>
<institution>Department of Gastroenterology and Hepatology, Jeroen Bosch Hospital</institution>, &#8216;s-Hertogenbosch, <country country="NL">the Netherlands</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1">Address correspondence to: Loes H. C. Nissen, PhD, Department of Gastroenterology and Hepatology, Jeroen Bosch Hospital, Henri Dunantstraat 1, Postbox 90153, 5200 ME &#8216;s-Hertogenbosch, the Netherlands (<email>lo.nissen@jbz.nl</email>).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>7</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2019-09-27"><day>27</day><month>9</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>26</volume><issue>7</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">359807</issue-id><fpage>1060</fpage><lpage>1067</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>7</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="editorial-decision"><day>14</day><month>8</month><year>2019</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>27</day><month>09</month><year>2019</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>23</day><month>06</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2020-06-24 00:37:59.600"><day>24</day><month>06</month><year>2020</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2019 Crohn&#8217;s &amp; Colitis Foundation. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Crohn&#8217;s &amp; Colitis Foundation.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="cc-by-nc" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="izz210.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="izz210.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><sec id="s0100"><title>Background</title><p>Inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) patients are at increased risk for developing extra-intestinal malignancies, mainly due to immunosuppressive medication. The risk of developing head and neck cancer in immunosuppressed transplant patients is increased. The relation between IBD patients and laryngeal cancer (LC) remains unclear. We aimed (1) to identify risk factors in IBD patients for LC development and (2) to compare clinical characteristics, outcome, and survival of LC in IBD patients with the general population.</p></sec><sec id="s0101"><title>Methods</title><p>All IBD patients with LC (1993&#8211;2011) were retrospectively identified using the Dutch Pathology Database. We performed 2 case&#8211;control studies: (1) to identify risk factors, we compared patients with IBD and LC (cases) with the general IBD population; (2) to analyze LC survival, we compared cases with controls from the general LC population.</p></sec><sec id="s0102"><title>Results</title><p>We included 55 cases, 1800 IBD controls, and 2018 LC controls. Cases were more frequently male compared with IBD controls (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001). For ulcerative colitis (UC), cases were older at IBD diagnosis (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001). Crohn&#8217;s disease (CD) cases were more frequently tobacco users (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001) and more often had stricturing (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.006) and penetrating (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.008) disease. We found no survival difference. Immunosuppressive medication had no impact on survival.</p></sec><sec id="s0103"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Male sex was a risk factor for LC in IBD patients. Older age at IBD diagnosis was a risk factor for UC to develop LC. Tobacco use and stricturing and penetrating disease were risk factors for LC development in CD patients. Inflammatory bowel disease was not associated with impaired survival of LC. Immunosuppressive medication had no influence on survival.</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>Risk factors for laryngeal cancer development in inflammatory bowel disease patients are male sex, older age at ulcerative colitis diagnosis, stricturing and penetrating disease, and tobacco use in Crohn&#8217;s disease patients. Inflammatory bowel disease was not associated with impaired survival of laryngeal cancer.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>inflammatory bowel diseases</kwd><kwd>head and neck cancer</kwd><kwd>laryngeal carcinoma</kwd><kwd>immunosuppressive therapy</kwd></kwd-group><counts><page-count count="8"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) patients are at increased risk for developing colorectal cancer (CRC) due to prolonged chronic inflammation.<sup><xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> In IBD patients, there is also an increased risk of developing extra-intestinal malignancies (EIMs), in part due to the use of immunosuppressive medication.<sup><xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3&#8211;6</xref></sup> This can be the result of DNA damage and decreased immune surveillance.<sup><xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> Due to the potential cancer risk, there is rising concern about the use of immunosuppressive medication in IBD patients.<sup><xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> Moreover, the use of immunosuppressive medication in IBD patients is associated with an increased risk of developing skin cancer and lymphoma.<sup><xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup></p><p>In other patient cohorts with immunosuppressive medication, such as in transplant patients or in patients with rheumatoid arthritis, the increased cancer risk is well established.<sup><xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> Both tumor growth and metastasis development can accelerate as a consequence of immunosuppressive medication, resulting in reduced survival rates.<sup><xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> For example, 1 study reported that the incidence of head and neck cancer (HNC) in transplant patients was doubled compared with the general population, with worse survival.<sup><xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> Although human papillomavirus (HPV) is associated with the development of cancer in the (oro)pharynx, HPV infection is not a major cause of laryngeal cancer (LC).<sup><xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup></p><p>The prevalence of LC is up to 3.0% in transplant patients on immunosuppressive medication.<sup><xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14&#8211;19</xref></sup> No specific risk factors for LC development have been identified in transplant patients, probably due to the small number of cases. Only a few articles have been published about the HNC prevalence in IBD patients on immunosuppressive medication.<sup><xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">20&#8211;23</xref></sup> Although the risk of developing oral cavity carcinoma (OCC) and oropharyngeal carcinoma (PC) in IBD patients has previously been reported, the occurrence of LC in IBD patients has scarcely been reported in literature.<sup><xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> In a series of 404 patients with Crohn&#8217;s disease (CD) treated with infliximab, only 1 patient developed LC.<sup><xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup></p><p>In this study, we aimed to (1) identify risk factors in IBD patients for the development of LC, (2) compare the clinical characteristics, outcome, and survival of IBD patients with LC with those of the general population, and (3) assess whether immunosuppressive medication had an influence on the survival. Given impaired survival in IBD patients with OCC,<sup><xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> we hypothesized a worse outcome in IBD patients with LC (cases) compared with the general LC population. In addition, we hypothesized worse survival in cases treated with immunosuppressive medication compared with cases who did not use immunosuppressive medication. We performed 2 population-based case&#8211;control studies with cases and IBD controls, and with cases and LC controls.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials" id="s2"><title>METHODS</title><sec id="s3"><title>Study Design</title><p>Two retrospective population-based case&#8211;control studies were performed:</p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>To identify risk factors for the development of LC in IBD patients, IBD patients with LC (cases) were compared with the general IBD population (controls).</p></list-item><list-item><p>To compare clinical characteristics, outcome, and survival of the LC population between those with IBD and the general LC population, IBD patients with LC (cases) were compared with the general LC population (controls).</p></list-item></list></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Case Selection</title><p>To identify all Dutch IBD patients with LC (cases), a search was performed using the national pathology database PALGA. PALGA is the Dutch nationwide network and registry of histo- and cytopathology.<sup><xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> The search was performed between January 1, 1993, and December 31, 2012. Search terms for IBD (&#8220;ulcerative colitis&#8221; or &#8220;Crohn&#8217;s disease&#8221; or &#8220;indeterminate colitis&#8221; or &#8220;chronic idiopathic inflammatory bowel disease&#8221;) were combined with search terms for LC (&#8220;laryngeal neoplasms&#8221; or &#8220;cancer of larynx&#8221; or &#8220;laryngeal cancer&#8221;). First, pathology reports were reviewed to make an initial selection of cases. Subsequently, the medical charts of these cases were reviewed.</p><p>Patients were included if a diagnosis of both LC and IBD (CD, ulcerative colitis [UC], or IBD-unclassified) was established according to previously published criteria.<sup><xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> Exclusion criteria were LC in situ, diagnosis of IBD &gt;3 months after LC diagnosis, no confirmed diagnosis of IBD or LC, diagnosis before 1993 or after 2012, and laryngeal lymphoma. The following data were collected from the medical charts: sex, date of birth, history of smoking and alcohol, medical history, length, and weight. Furthermore, IBD-specific data were collected, including IBD type based on histopathological evaluation, IBD phenotype, date of IBD diagnosis, use of IBD medication (corticosteroids, 5-aminosalicylates, thiopurines, calcineurin inhibitors, methotrexate, and anti-TNF therapy) and period of medication use, presence of primary sclerosing cholangitis, and type of surgery required for IBD. Characteristics of LC included date of LC diagnosis, tumor stage according to TNM classification (7th edition), history of LC, primary treatment of LC, differentiation grade, recurrence, and survival.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Control Selection</title><p>Inflammatory bowel disease controls (case&#8211;control study I) were derived from the IBD South Limburg (IBDSL) cohort. The IBDSL cohort consists of adult patients with IBD in South Limburg (the Netherlands) who were diagnosed between 1991 and 2011.<sup><xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> Currently, 93% of IBD patients in South Limburg are registered in this cohort. A random selection of 1800 patients was made, as described in detail in a previous publication.<sup><xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> Similar data were extracted from both cases and IBD controls, although duration of immunosuppressive medication and smoking and alcohol history were not available for all IBD controls.</p><p>LC controls (case&#8211;control study II) were derived from the Netherlands Cancer Registry (NCR). The NCR cohort consists of all newly diagnosed patients with cancer in the Southeast of the Netherlands (province of North Brabant and the Northern part of the province of Limburg) since 1989. This cohort is managed by the Netherlands Comprehensive Cancer Organization; &gt;95% of all cancers in this region are registered in this cohort. All LC patients between 1993 and 2012 with LC were selected.<sup><xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup></p><p>Similar data were extracted from both cases and controls, although the duration of immunosuppressive medication and smoking and alcohol history were not available for all IBD controls.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Statistics</title><p>Univariable analysis was used for both case&#8211;control studies to compare potential risk factors, LC characteristics, and outcomes between cases and controls. Continuous data were compared with the unpaired 2-sample <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test or Mann-Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic> test. The Pearson chi-square test or Fisher exact test was used to analyze categorical data. Variables with a <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value of &lt;0.1 in univariable analyses were included in a multivariable model (model further described per case&#8211;control study). A <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value of &lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant. All statistical analyses were performed with IBM SPSS statistics, version 24.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Case&#8211;Control Study I</title><p>A multivariable logistic regression model with backward sampling was used for case&#8211;control study I. This model was made separately for UC and CD patients to identify independent risk factors for LC development. This model was adjusted for the duration of follow-up (fixed variable). Follow-up was defined as the time since IBD onset until the date of LC diagnosis, the end of follow-up, or death. Medication use was not included in multivariable analyses because the use of medication, especially in the distant past, might not be reliable and may be different from current regimes. Therefore, another multivariable logistic regression analysis was performed (sensitivity analysis) including patients with IBD in both the case and control groups. Medication use was included in this logistic regression model.</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Case&#8211;Control Study II</title><p>Kaplan-Meier survival curves with log-rank analysis were performed to compare the clinical outcome and survival of IBD patients with LC with those of the general LC population. A separate survival analysis was performed to compare the effect of immunosuppressive medication on the clinical outcome and survival of IBD patients with LC (immunosuppressive medication vs no immunosuppressive medication). Confounder correction was performed with a Cox regression model with forward sampling. A covariate was considered as a confounder when the beta coefficient of the variable of interest changed by 10% or more.</p></sec><sec id="s9"><title>Ethical Considerations</title><p>This study was approved by the Privacy Commission and Scientific Council of PALGA and by the Medical Ethics Review Committee of the Radboud UMC, Nijmegen, the Netherlands (registration number 2013/211).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s10"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="s11"><title>Case Selection</title><p>The initial PALGA search yielded 760 potential cases (patients with IBD and head and neck cancer). We excluded 391 patients without LC based on histology reports (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). The medical charts of the remaining 369 patients were reviewed. After chart review, 310 patients were excluded, resulting in 55 cases with IBD and LC.</p><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIGURE 1.</label><caption><p>Flowchart of case inclusion. Abbreviations: CIS, carcinoma in situ; SCC, squamous cell cancer.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="izz210f0001.jpg"/></fig><sec id="s12"><title>Control selection of the general IBD population, risk factors</title><p>In total, 1800 IBD patients from the IBDSL cohort were randomly selected for the identification of risk factors. Univariable comparison between IBD patients with LC (cases) and IBDSL controls (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) showed that cases were older at IBD diagnosis (median, 53.0 vs 39.0 years; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001), were more frequently male (83.6% vs 46.5%; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001), and were more frequently (previous or current) tobacco users (100% vs 62.5%; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001). Crohn&#8217;s disease cases more often had stricturing (66.7% vs 14.6%; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.006) and penetrating (53.3% vs 10.4%; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.008) disease.</p><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>TABLE 1.</label><caption><p>Univariable Comparison of Potential Risk Factors Between IBD Patients With LC (Cases) and IBDSL Controls</p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">IBDSL</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Larynx</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 1800</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 55</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Missing, No.</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age at diagnosis, median, y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male sex, No. (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">817 (46.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (83.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking (no; only CD patients), No. (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Nonsmoker</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">253 (37.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/122</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Smoker</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">345 (51.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (61.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Ex-smoker</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76 (11.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (38.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary sclerosering cholangitis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (0.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.307</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IBD type, No. (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Ulcerative colitis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1004 (55.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (66.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.138</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Crohn&#8217;s disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">796 (44.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (34.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Indeterminate colitis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ulcerative colitis,<sup>a</sup> No. (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Proctitis (E1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">243 (24.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (14.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.206</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Left-sided colitis (E2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">472 (47.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (45.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Pancolitis (E3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">279 (28.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (40.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crohn&#8217;s disease,<sup>a</sup> No. (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Ileum (L1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">223 (12.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (25.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Colon (L2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">183 (10.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (37.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Ileocolonic (L3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">389 (21.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (37.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Upper digestive (L4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65 (3.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.624</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Stricturing (B2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">263 (14.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (66.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Penetrating (B3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">188 (10.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (53.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medication, No. (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;5-aminosalicylates</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1605 (89.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 (84.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9/13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.268</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Steroids</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1113 (61.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (68.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11/13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.458</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Thiopurines</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">717 (39.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (36.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11/17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.607</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Methotrexate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95 (5.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.729</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Cyclosporin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (1.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.491</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Biologicals</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">350 (19.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (13.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.286</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IBD-related surgery, No. (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1284 (71.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (61.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.112</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of follow-up since IBD, y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.759</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fn-0100"><p>
<sup>a</sup>According to the Montreal classification, smoking data of IBDSL were only available for CD patients.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The multivariable logistic regression model (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>) for UC included the following variables: age at IBD diagnosis and sex. For CD, we included the following variables: age at diagnosis, sex, smoking (data absent for UC patients), and stricturing and penetrating disease behavior. Independent risk factors in UC patients for the development of LC were male sex (odds ratio [OR], 9.4; 95% confidence interval [CI], 2.8&#8211;31.4; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01) and older age at IBD diagnosis (OR, 1.1; 95% CI, 1.0&#8211;1.1; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01). In CD patients, male sex (OR, 3.7; 95% CI, 1.1&#8211;12.2; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.03), past or current tobacco use (OR, 4.6; 95% CI, 1.8&#8211;11.3; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01), and stricturing disease (OR, 3.8; 95% CI, 1.2&#8211;12.2; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.03) were independent risk factors for the development of LC.</p><table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>TABLE 2.</label><caption><p>Multivariable Regression Model After Adjustment for Follow-up: Independent Risk Factors for LC Development</p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coefficient &#946;</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Odds Ratio (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Larynx</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ulcerative colitis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male sex</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.244</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.428 (2.831&#8211;31.394)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All cases (n = 35)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age at IBD diagnosis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.058</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.060 (1.034&#8211;1.086)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ulcerative colitis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male sex</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.255</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.532 (2.039&#8211;44.571)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sensitivity analysis (n = 29)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age at IBD diagnosis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.069</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.072 (1.036&#8211;1.109)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5-aminosalicylates</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;3.321</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.036 (0.010&#8211;0.131)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crohn&#8217;s disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male sex</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.297</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.658 (1.101&#8211;12.154)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.034</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All cases (n = 18)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.521</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.578 (1.840&#8211;11.345)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stricturing disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.327</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.770 (1.168&#8211;12.165)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.026</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crohn&#8217;s disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.544</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.686 (1.681&#8211;13.063)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sensitivity analysis (n = 15)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Penetrating disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.605</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.979 (1.238&#8211;20.021)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fn-0101"><p>Similar inclusion periods of IBD diagnosis (since 1991) for cases and controls were used in the sensitivity analysis. Eliminated nonsignificant variables are not shown; only the final model is shown.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>A sensitivity analysis (including only patients with an IBD diagnosis since 1991 to reliably evaluate the impact of medication use on LC risk) showed that the use of 5-aminisalicylates (5-ASA; OR, 0.04; 95% CI, 0.01&#8211;0.13; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01) is associated with a lower risk of LC for UC patients. Penetrating disease (OR, 5.0; 95% CI, 1.2&#8211;20.0; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.02) is a risk factor for LC development in CD patients (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s13"><title>Control selection of the general LC population: clinical characteristics and outcome</title><p>In total, 2018 LC patients from the NCR were selected as controls for the identification of risk factors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). Characteristics of patients with LC (both cases and controls) are shown in <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. The median age of patients with LC (controls) was 65 years, and most patients were male (82.8%). TNM stage was in most cases I or II (62.5%), and patients were most often treated with radiotherapy (84.2%). The overall 5-year survival of patients with LC (controls) was 60% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>). No differences in survival between cases and controls (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.942) were found, also after adjusting for TNM stage (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.634) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A, B</xref>).</p><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIGURE 2.</label><caption><p>Flowchart of inclusion of NCR controls (general population).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="izz210f0002.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIGURE 3.</label><caption><p>A, Laryngeal carcinoma survival curves. B, Laryngeal carcinoma survival curves after adjusting for TNM stage. <sup>a</sup>Confounder correction, including TNM stage.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="izz210f0003.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap id="T3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>TABLE 3.</label><caption><p>Univariable Comparison of Larynx Carcinoma Characteristics Between Cases and Controls</p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">LC patients</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">NCR patients</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Missing, No.</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">N = 55</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">N = 2018</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">IBD/NCR</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age at diagnosis, median, y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.920</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female sex, No. (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (16.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">347 (17.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.872</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tumor location, No. (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Supraglottis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (21.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">697 (35.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.122</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Glottis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (76.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1253 (63.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Subglottis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (1.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Histology, No. (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;SCC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53 (96.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1979 (98.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.297</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Differentiation, No. (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Good</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (15.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">222 (14.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23/473</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.509</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Moderate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (71.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1000 (64.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Poor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (12.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">323 (20.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical tumor stage, No. (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;T stage<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;T1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (47.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">793 (40.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.259</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;T2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (34.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">598 (30.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;T3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (7.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">329 (16.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;T4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (10.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">254 (12.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;N stage<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;N0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (88.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1550 (81.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/104</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.114</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;N1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">120 (6.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;N2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (9.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">219 (11.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;N3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (1.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;M stage (yes)<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (1.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.153</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.673</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;TNM&#8212;stadium<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Stadium I</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (44.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">635 (36.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/254</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.210</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Stadium II</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (32.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">467 (26.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Stadium III</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (6.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">264 (15.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Stadium IV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (18.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">398 (22.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment, No. (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Surgery (yes)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (29.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">467 (23.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.303</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Chemotherapy (yes)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (2.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.838</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Radiotherapy (yes)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (83.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1699 (84.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.911</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Previous malignancy (yes), No. (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (22.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">299 (14.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.120</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fn-0102"><p>Cases: IBD patients with larynx carcinoma; controls: patients in the general population with larynx carcinoma derived from the NCR.</p></fn><fn id="fn-0103"><p>Abbreviation: SCC, squamous cell carcinoma.</p></fn><fn id="fn-0104"><p>
<sup>a</sup>According to the 7th TNM edition.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="s14"><title>Survival in IBD Patients With Immunosuppressive Therapy Before LC Diagnosis</title><p>Of the 55 patients with IBD and LC, 29 patients had a history of immunosuppressive medication use before diagnosis of LC, whereas 26 patients did not use immunosuppressive medication before LC diagnosis. There was no significant difference in overall survival between these 2 groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.926).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s15"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>In this nationwide cohort study, we found male sex to be an independent risk factor for LC development in IBD patients, both for CD and UC. For UC specifically, older age at IBD diagnosis was a risk factor, and the use of 5-ASA was associated with a lower risk for LC. In CD, past or current tobacco use and stricturing or penetrating disease were independent risk factors for developing LC. We found no impact of immunosuppressive medication on survival after LC diagnosis.</p><p>Data regarding the impact of immunosuppressive medication in IBD patients on cancer survival are limited and conflicting. There was no difference in survival for IBD patients with melanoma compared with the general population, whereas IBD patients with gastric cancer, CRC, or OCC showed impaired survival.<sup><xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">27&#8211;29</xref></sup> However, most studies are limited by a retrospective design and carry a risk of bias.<sup><xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">27&#8211;29</xref></sup> Data from transplant patients show that the largest effect on the survival of cancer is observed within the first 2 years after the start of immunosuppressive medication.<sup><xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> As the type of immunosuppression, dose, and treatment duration in IBD patients are different, it is uncertain whether these results can be extrapolated to the IBD population. In addition, although transplant patients will use immunosuppressive medication throughout their lives, most IBD patients will switch or discontinue immunosuppressive medication due to side effects or loss of response.<sup><xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup></p><p>Our results suggest that immunosuppressive medication can be safely used in IBD patients with LC and are therefore reassuring for clinical daily practice. However, they have to be interpreted with caution for several reasons. First, confounding by indication might be present, as most clinicians are reluctant to prescribe immunosuppressive medication to patients at risk for cancer given the possible negative effects. This probably results in mostly low-risk patients receiving immunosuppressive medication. Second, the time relation between tumor development and the start of immunosuppressive medication was unclear due to the retrospective design of this study. Third, because of the limited number of enrolled cases, data could be underpowered to show a significant difference in survival. In the ECCO guidelines, data were limited regarding the effect of immunosuppressive medication on the survival in IBD patients with cancer.<sup><xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup> No firm conclusions can be drawn about the safety of immunosuppressive medication in IBD patients with LC.</p><p>We found older age at IBD diagnosis to be an independent risk factor for the development of LC, particularly in patients with UC. Our results are in line with previous studies of our group and others.<sup><xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">33&#8211;37</xref></sup> One study comparing IBD patients over the age of 60 years with IBD patients aged 18 to 40 years observed a higher rate of cancer in the elderly-onset IBD patients (14% vs 0.5%; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01).<sup><xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup> It could be speculated that the phenotype of elderly-onset IBD is associated with a higher risk of cancer.<sup><xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup> On the other hand, the high prevalence of tobacco use in LC patients may result in late UC onset and confound our findings. Indeed, we found tobacco use to be an independent risk factor for LC development, especially in CD patients (data lacking for UC). This is consistent with the current literature about risk factors for LC.<sup><xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup> Although stricturing disease and penetrating disease in CD patients were independent risk factors for LC development regardless of tobacco use, tobacco use may contribute to ongoing inflammation and result in stricturing and penetrating disease.</p><p>To our knowledge, this is the largest systematically collected series of data from LC patients with IBD, which is the major strength of this study. Nonetheless, there are some limitations of our study that need to be addressed. First, the retrospective design resulted in missing data. For example, data regarding the exact time period of immunosuppressive medication use were lacking, impeding analysis of the impact of immunosuppressive medication on LC development. Moreover, the date of IBD diagnosis may be not completely reliable, as this was extracted from the PALGA database. Second, we used 3 different databases to collect all data, as there was not 1 database that contained all required data. Data from the IBDSL and NCR were collected prospectively, whereas data from our cases were collected retrospectively. Finally, the use of preconceived databases may result in missing parameters. As such, data on alcohol use are lacking.</p><p>In conclusion, we found no difference in survival between IBD patients with LC and the general LC population. Moreover, immunosuppressive medication did not impact survival. Male sex was an independent risk factor for LC development in IBD patients. Elderly-onset IBD emerged as a risk factor for LC development, particularly in UC patients. Smoking and stricturing or penetrating disease were independent risk factors in CD patients for the development of LC. Based on our results, routine screening for LC is discouraged in IBD patients, as the LC incidence is low.</p></sec></body><back><notes id="n1"><p>Supported by: This research did not receive any specific grant from funding agencies in the public, commercial, or nonprofit sectors.</p><p>Conflicts of interest: None declared.</p></notes><ref-list id="r1"><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="CIT0001"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eaden</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abrams</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mayberry</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The risk of colorectal cancer in ulcerative colitis: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Gut.</source><year>2001</year>;<volume>48</volume>:<fpage>526</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>535</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11247898</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/gut.48.4.526</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1728259</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rutter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Severity of inflammation is a risk factor for colorectal neoplasia in ulcerative colitis</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology.</source><year>2004</year>;<volume>126</volume>:<fpage>451</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>459</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14762782</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1053/j.gastro.2003.11.010</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Biancone</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Onali</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Petruzziello</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Cancer and immunomodulators in inflammatory bowel diseases</article-title>. <source>Inflamm Bowel Dis.</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>674</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>698</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25545375</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/MIB.0000000000000243</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beaugerie</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inflammatory bowel disease therapies and cancer risk: where are we and where are we going?</article-title><source>Gut.</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>61</volume>:<fpage>476</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>483</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22157331</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/gutjnl-2011-301133</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duricova</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Elkjaer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Risk of extra-intestinal cancer in inflammatory bowel disease: meta-analysis of population-based cohort studies</article-title>. <source>Am J Gastroenterol.</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>105</volume>:<fpage>1480</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1487</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20332773</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/ajg.2009.760</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beaugerie</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sokol</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seksik</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Noncolorectal malignancies in inflammatory bowel disease: more than meets the eye</article-title>. <source>Dig Dis.</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>375</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>381</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19786768</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1159/000228577</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Giagkou</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saridi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Albani</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Dermal lesions and skin cancer in patients with inflammatory bowel disease receiving immunosuppressive therapy</article-title>. <source>Asian Pac J Cancer Prev.</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>2845</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2851</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30362311</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.22034/APJCP.2018.19.10.2845</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6291021</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lemaitre</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kirchgesner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rudnichi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Association between use of thiopurines or tumor necrosis factor antagonists alone or in combination and risk of lymphoma in patients with inflammatory bowel disease</article-title>. <source>JAMA.</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>318</volume>:<fpage>1679</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1686</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29114832</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.2017.16071</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5818785</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kinlen</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Incidence of cancer in rheumatoid arthritis and other disorders after immunosuppressive treatment</article-title>. <source>Am J Med.</source><year>1985</year>;<volume>78</volume>:<fpage>44</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>49</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0002-9343(85)90245-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3970040</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gutierrez-Dalmau</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Campistol</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immunosuppressive therapy and malignancy in organ transplant recipients: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Drugs.</source><year>2007</year>;<volume>67</volume>:<fpage>1167</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1198</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17521218</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2165/00003495-200767080-00006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Preciado</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Squamous cell carcinoma of the head and neck in solid organ transplant recipients</article-title>. <source>Head Neck.</source><year>2002</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>319</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>325</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11933172</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/hed.10055</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalianis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human papillomavirus and oropharyngeal cancer, the epidemics, and significance of additional clinical biomarkers for prediction of response to therapy</article-title>. <source>Int J Oncol.</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>44</volume>:<fpage>1799</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1805</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24676623</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3892/ijo.2014.2355</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4063535</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Onerci Celebi</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sener</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hosal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Human papillomavirus infection in patients with laryngeal carcinoma</article-title>. <source>BMC Cancer.</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>1005</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30342481</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12885-018-4890-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6195980</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>ZN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name></person-group>; <person-group><collab>Liver Surgery Group</collab></person-group><article-title>De novo malignancies after liver transplantation with 14 cases at a single center</article-title>. <source>Transplant Proc.</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>2483</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2487</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26518956</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.transproceed.2015.08.008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nure</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frongillo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lirosi</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Incidence of upper aerodigestive tract cancer after liver transplantation for alcoholic cirrhosis: a 10-year experience in an Italian center</article-title>. <source>Transplant Proc.</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>2733</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2735</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24034035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.transproceed.2013.08.011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marqu&#233;s Medina</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jim&#233;nez Romero</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>G&#243;mez de la C&#225;mara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Malignancy after liver transplantation: cumulative risk for development</article-title>. <source>Transplant Proc.</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>2447</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2449</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19715947</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.transproceed.2009.06.153</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adami</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>G&#228;bel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lindel&#246;f</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Cancer risk following organ transplantation: a nationwide cohort study in Sweden</article-title>. <source>Br J Cancer.</source><year>2003</year>;<volume>89</volume>:<fpage>1221</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1227</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14520450</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.bjc.6601219</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2394311</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonetta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bandera</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roviello</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Neoadjuvant chemotherapy and radical radiotherapy associated with cetuximab for laryngeal cancer in a pancreas and renal recipient</article-title>. <source>Anticancer Drugs.</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>470</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>473</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26908347</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/CAD.0000000000000352</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shinohara</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maity</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jha</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Sirolimus as a potential radiosensitizer in squamous cell cancer of the head and neck</article-title>. <source>Head Neck.</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>406</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>411</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18704962</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/hed.20898</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2737255</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vilas-Boas</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Magro</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Balhau</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Oral squamous cell carcinoma in a Crohn&#8217;s disease patient taking azathioprine: case report and review of the literature</article-title>. <source>J Crohns Colitis.</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>792</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>795</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22464812</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.crohns.2012.03.004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Warnakulasuriya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neoplasia of the tongue in a patient with Crohn&#8217;s disease treated with azathioprine: case report</article-title>. <source>Eur J Gastroenterol Hepatol.</source><year>2003</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>185</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>187</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12560764</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/00042737-200302000-00013</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0022"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Giagkou</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Christodoulou</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Katsanos</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mouth cancer in inflammatory bowel diseases</article-title>. <source>Oral Dis.</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>260</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>264</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26671147</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/odi.12420</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0023"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nissen</surname><given-names>LHC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Derikx</surname><given-names>LAAP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>AME</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>; <person-group><collab>Dutch Initiative on Crohn and Colitis (ICC); Dutch Head and Neck Society, PALGA Group; IBD/HNC Group</collab></person-group><article-title>Risk factors and clinical outcomes of head and neck cancer in inflammatory bowel disease: a nationwide cohort study</article-title>. <source>Inflamm Bowel Dis.</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>2015</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2026</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30759216</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/ibd/izy096</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0024"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Biancone</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Orlando</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kohn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Infliximab and newly diagnosed neoplasia in Crohn&#8217;s disease: a multicentre matched pair study</article-title>. <source>Gut.</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>55</volume>:<fpage>228</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>233</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16120759</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/gut.2005.075937</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1856527</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0025"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Casparie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tiebosch</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Pathology databanking and biobanking in the Netherlands, a central role for PALGA, the nationwide histopathology and cytopathology data network and archive</article-title>. <source>Cell Oncol.</source><year>2007</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>19</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>24</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17429138</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1155/2007/971816</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4618410</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0026"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van den Heuvel</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jonkers</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jeuring</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Cohort profile: the Inflammatory Bowel Disease South Limburg Cohort (IBDSL)</article-title>. <source>Int J Epidemiol.</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>e7</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26045509</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/ije/dyv088</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0027"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nissen</surname><given-names>LHC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pierik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Derikx</surname><given-names>LAAP</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Risk factors and clinical outcomes in patients with IBD with melanoma</article-title>. <source>Inflamm Bowel Dis.</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>2018</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2026</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28837522</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/MIB.0000000000001191</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0028"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nissen</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Assendorp</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Post</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Impaired gastric cancer survival in patients with inflammatory bowel disease</article-title>. <source>J Gastrointestin Liver Dis.</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>431</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>440</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27981298</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.15403/jgld.2014.1121.254.nis</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0029"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Konishi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kishimoto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>; <person-group><collab>Japanese Society for Cancer of the Colon and Rectum</collab></person-group><article-title>Ulcerative colitis-associated colorectal cancer shows a poorer survival than sporadic colorectal cancer: a nationwide Japanese study</article-title>. <source>Inflamm Bowel Dis.</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>802</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>808</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20848547</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/ibd.21365</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0030"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Penn</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Post-transplant malignancy: the role of immunosuppression</article-title>. <source>Drug Saf.</source><year>2000</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>101</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>113</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10945373</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2165/00002018-200023020-00002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0031"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jharap</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seinen</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Boer</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Thiopurine therapy in inflammatory bowel disease patients: analyses of two 8-year intercept cohorts</article-title>. <source>Inflamm Bowel Dis.</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>1541</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1549</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20155846</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/ibd.21221</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0032"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Annese</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beaugerie</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Egan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>; <person-group><collab>ECCO</collab></person-group><article-title>European evidence-based consensus: inflammatory bowel disease and malignancies</article-title>. <source>J Crohns Colitis.</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>945</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>965</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26294789</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/ecco-jcc/jjv141</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0033"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baars</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuipers</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Haastert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Age at diagnosis of inflammatory bowel disease influences early development of colorectal cancer in inflammatory bowel disease patients: a nationwide, long-term survey</article-title>. <source>J Gastroenterol.</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>1308</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1322</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22627504</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00535-012-0603-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3523115</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0034"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brackmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aamodt</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Two distinct groups of colorectal cancer in inflammatory bowel disease</article-title>. <source>Inflamm Bowel Dis.</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>9</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>16</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18618636</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/ibd.20542</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0035"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Derikx</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nissen</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Drenth</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>; <person-group><collab>Dutch Initiative on Crohn and Colitis; PALGA Group; IBD/RCC Group</collab></person-group><article-title>Better survival of renal cell carcinoma in patients with inflammatory bowel disease</article-title>. <source>Oncotarget.</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>38336</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>38347</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26447542</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.18632/oncotarget.5186</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4742003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0036"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kishikawa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kazama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Results of a 36-year surveillance program for ulcerative colitis-associated neoplasia in the Japanese population</article-title>. <source>Dig Endosc.</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>236</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>244</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28836702</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/den.12955</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0037"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Butter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weiler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Biedermann</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Clinical manifestations, pathophysiology, treatment and outcome of inflammatory bowel diseases in older people</article-title>. <source>Maturitas.</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>110</volume>:<fpage>71</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>78</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29563038</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.maturitas.2018.01.015</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0038"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma&#241;osa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Calafat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Francisco</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>; <person-group><collab>GETECCU</collab></person-group><article-title>Phenotype and natural history of elderly onset inflammatory bowel disease: a multicentre, case-control study</article-title>. <source>Aliment Pharmacol Ther.</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>605</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>614</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29369387</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/apt.14494</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0039"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Charpentier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Salleron</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Savoye</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Natural history of elderly-onset inflammatory bowel disease: a population-based cohort study</article-title>. <source>Gut.</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>63</volume>:<fpage>423</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>432</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23408350</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/gutjnl-2012-303864</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0040"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hashibe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chuang</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Interaction between tobacco and alcohol use and the risk of head and neck cancer: pooled analysis in the International Head and Neck Cancer Epidemiology Consortium</article-title>. <source>Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev.</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>541</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>550</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19190158</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/1055-9965.EPI-08-0347</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3051410</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>