<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Tob Induc Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Tob Induc Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">701</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">tobinducdis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TID</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Tobacco Induced Diseases</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2070-7266</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1617-9625</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The International Society for the Prevention of Tobacco Induced Diseases</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8349177</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC8349177.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">8349177</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">8349177</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34429727</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18332/tid/140091</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">65</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Provider and clinical setting characteristics associated with tobacco pharmacotherapy dispensed in the Veterans Health Administration</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blok</surname><given-names initials="AC">Amanda C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ignacio</surname><given-names initials="RV">Rosalinda V.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0003">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Geraci</surname><given-names initials="MC">Mark C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0004">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names initials="HM">Hyungjin Myra</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0005">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names initials="PG">Paul G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0006">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duffy</surname><given-names initials="SA">Sonia A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0007">7</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0008">8</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label>VA Center for Clinical Management Research, VA Ann Arbor Healthcare System, Ann Arbor, United States</aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label>Department of Systems, Populations and Leadership, School of Nursing, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, United States</aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label>Department of Biostatistics, School of Public Health, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, United States</aff><aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label>Department of Veterans Affairs Pharmacy Benefits Management Services, United States Department of Veterans Affairs, Hines, United States</aff><aff id="aff0005"><label>5</label>Center for Statistical Consultation and Research, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, United States</aff><aff id="aff0006"><label>6</label>Health Economics Resource Center, United States Department of Veterans Affairs, Menlo Park, United States</aff><aff id="aff0007"><label>7</label>College of Nursing, The Ohio State University, Columbus, United States</aff><aff id="aff0008"><label>8</label>Department of Psychiatry, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, United States</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>CORRESPONDENCE TO</bold> Sonia A. Duffy. College of Nursing, The Ohio State University, 1585 Neil Ave, Columbus, OH 43210, United States. E-mail: <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="duffy.278@osu.edu">duffy.278@osu.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>06</day><month>8</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>19</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">372467</issue-id><elocation-id>65</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>3</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>04</day><month>6</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>08</day><month>7</month><year>2021</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>06</day><month>08</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>23</day><month>08</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-04-03 02:25:40.640"><day>03</day><month>04</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2021 Blok A.C. et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="TID-19-65.pdf"/><abstract><sec id="s1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>While initiation rates of tobacco cessation pharmacotherapy have improved both inside and outside the Department of Veteran Affairs (VA), prescribing rates remain low. The objective of this study was to examine correlation of the characteristics of providers, clinics, and facilities with initiation of tobacco cessation pharmacotherapy.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>METHODS</title><p>This retrospective, observational study used VA outpatient electronic medical record data from federal fiscal year 2011. Logistic regression models estimated the adjusted odds ratio associated with provider characteristics for pharmacotherapy initiation.</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>RESULTS</title><p>For the 639507 veterans who used tobacco, there were 30388 providers caring for them. Younger (p&lt;0.001) and female (p&lt;0.001) providers were more likely to initiate tobacco cessation pharmacotherapy. Compared to physicians, pharmacists were 74% more likely to initiate pharmacotherapy, while all groups of nurses were 5&#8211;8% and physicians&#8217; assistants were 12% less likely (p&lt;0.001). Compared to those seen in primary care clinics, patients assessed in substance use treatment clinics were 16% more likely to have pharmacotherapy initiated (p&lt;0.001), while those in psychiatry were 10% less likely (p&lt;0.001), and those in outpatient surgery were 39% less likely to initiate pharmacotherapy (p&lt;0.001). Compared to almost all other classes of VA facilities, patients seen in primary care community-based outpatient clinics (CBOCs) were 7&#8211;28% more likely to initiate pharmacotherapy (p&lt;0.0001).</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>CONCLUSIONS</title><p>While the VA is at the leading edge of providing tobacco cessation pharmacotherapy, targeting quality improvement efforts towards providers, clinics, and facilities with low prescribing rates will be essential to continue the declining rates of tobacco use among VA patients.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>smoking cessation agents</kwd><kwd>tobacco use cessation</kwd><kwd>drug prescriptions</kwd><kwd>health personnel</kwd><kwd>health services</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Pharmacological treatment for tobacco dependence has been shown to be clinically effective and cost effective<sup><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup>. Thus, clinical practice guidelines have recommended pharmacotherapy for the treatment of tobacco use since 2000<sup><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>. In response, the Veterans Administration (VA) implemented the National Smoking and Tobacco Use Cessation Program in 2004, mandating the availability of tobacco cessation pharmacotherapy to veterans who are interested in quitting, regardless of their interest in tobacco treatment programs<sup><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup>. This initiative included the implementation of tobacco treatment policy, increased provider training, increased availability of tobacco treatment pharmacotherapy and counseling, and increased the rate and quality of tobacco cessation interventions using clinical reminders in the electronic medical record system.</p><p>A prior study by our team showed that tobacco cessation pharmacotherapy for patients in the outpatient setting increased from 13.8% in 2004 to 26.8% after a VA Directive was initiated in 2008, then plateaued to 25.8% in 2011<sup><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup>. While there was substantial initial improvement, determining practices and providers that remain low-prescribers of pharmacotherapy is needed to break through the plateau effect on prescribing behavior change. This is crucial for tobacco cessation in veterans, as three quarters of those who use tobacco remain untreated. Similarly, studies outside the VA have shown a third or less of tobacco quit attempts are aided by the use of FDA-approved medications<sup><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>. This is unfortunate, as the use of FDA-approved medications increases the quit rate by 50&#8211;60%, regardless of setting<sup><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup>.</p><p>There are many clinical provider-level and clinical setting-level influences that contribute to the low rate of initiating pharmacotherapy for treating tobacco dependence. Clinical providers experience barriers to prescribing pharmacotherapy, which can include a lack of confidence in their ability to provide effective tobacco cessation interventions, false perceptions of a lack of interest by patients, and misconceptions that pharmacotherapy is not effective<sup><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>. In general, providers are far more likely to &#8216;ask&#8217; patients about their tobacco status and stop there, rather than continue on to introduce cessation interventions, particularly pharmacotherapy<sup><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup>. Clinical setting-level barriers for prescription initiation can include a lack of time along with competing task pressures for providers, a lack of support for providing tobacco treatment services, a high cost for treatment, or problems with electronic documentation systems<sup><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup>.</p><p>There is a lack of research describing differences in pharmacotherapy initiation between different types of providers and clinical settings, as well as exploring the influence of these characteristics on pharmacotherapy initiation. Understanding multi-level factors associated with initiating tobacco pharmacotherapy is critical to improve tobacco treatment quality of care, yet requires a large amount of data to do so. This analysis leverages the availability of data from the Veterans Health Administration (VHA), the largest integrated healthcare system in the US, providing care at 170 medical centers and 1074 outpatient sites of care, and serving nine million veterans each year<sup><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>. To target tobacco treatment educational efforts, specific information is needed about the characteristics of providers, clinics and facilities that do and do not initiate tobacco cessation pharmacotherapy. Not only is it important to describe who is currently receiving cessation pharmacotherapy, which our team has explored in the VA<sup><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup>, but also to describe the clinical and organizational attributes that contribute to prescribing pharmacotherapy for tobacco users. Hence, the objective of this study was to determine the characteristics of providers, clinics and facilities that initiated or did not initiate tobacco cessation.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="sec2"><title>METHODS</title><sec id="sec2.1"><title>Design</title><p>This was a retrospective, observational study of VA outpatients who used tobacco in federal fiscal year 2011 (FY 2011). Provider, clinic and facility characteristics, as well as patient demographic and clinical data, were abstracted from the VA Corporate Data Warehouse (CDW), the national repository of VA electronic medical records (EMR). Tobacco use status data were obtained from the Health Factor (HF) dataset, containing provider responses to clinical reminders. Full details of the method for determining tobacco use status are available elsewhere<sup><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup>. Tobacco cessation pharmacotherapy prescription data were abstracted from the outpatient VA Pharmacy Benefits Management (PBM) system.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><title>Sample</title><sec id="s2b1"><title>Patient sample</title><p>The initial cohort of veterans who were patients that used tobacco included 838309 VA outpatients with current tobacco use status in FY 2011 who had at least one hospital or clinic visit in the prior 12 months. Only 13.2% (765865) of the 5.80 million VA patients in FY 2011 did not have HF data, and therefore tobacco use data, available. To focus on initiation of cessation pharmacotherapy, the study included only those who had not received pharmacotherapy in the prior 12 months<sup><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup>. Excluded from the analysis were 23.7% (198802/838309) of observations that lacked one or more data elements. Reasons for exclusion included inability to identify a single responsible provider at the time of initial screening (14%), patient in residential setting at time of screening (2%), patient record missing data on race (9.2%), or patient record missing data on ethnicity (6.3%). The total of these exceeds 23.7% because of observations that were missing more than one item. A companion paper indicated that those excluded were significantly less likely to have initiated pharmacotherapy and more likely to be younger, male, non-White, Hispanic, have less psychiatric and medical comorbidities, have died during the follow-up period (all p&lt;0.05)<sup><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup>. The final cohort for analysis included 76.3% 639507/838309) of Veterans who screened positive for tobacco use and who did not use pharmacotherapy in the prior year.</p></sec><sec id="s2b2"><title>Provider sample</title><p>Provider initiation (or non-initiation) of tobacco cessation pharmacotherapy was assigned to the provider who conducted the index HF assessment. If multiple providers were involved, the first provider recorded in the HF assessment was assigned as the responsible provider. While in real-world practice multiple providers may be involved in patients&#8217; care, clinician feedback has indicated that the person most likely to initiate tobacco cessation treatment is the person that actually conducts the tobacco cessation assessment. Thus, the person conducting the tobacco assessment was assigned to be the responsible provider. While registered nurses and licensed practical nurses do not have prescription authority, they are able to initiate pharmacotherapy by alerting a prescribing provider and/or adding a prescription to be signed by a prescribing provider. If a responsible provider was not identified in the HF data, responsibility was assigned to the provider of record in the outpatients associated with the index HF assessment.</p><p>To align our analyses with the responsible provider, we examined the clinics and facilities where the HF assessment took place to determine the prevalence of tobacco cessation care. Clinic stop codes, standardized codes used to characterize VA clinical settings, were categorized based on the Health Economics and Resource Center&#8217;s (HERC&#8217;s) category of care assignments. These codes identify the work group primarily responsible for providing a clinical service and are used for purposes of workload credit, managerial accounting and program evaluation. Details on the linkage is found on the HERC website<sup><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup>. Outpatient clinic categories of care with less than 1% of study patients were combined (dialysis, ancillary services, rehabilitation, diagnostics services, prosthetics, outpatient dental, adult daycare, home care, unassigned). Facility classification, complexity, and rurality, were based on data from the Planning System Support Group (PSSG)<sup><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr"/>14</sup>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><title>Procedures</title><p>This study was approved by the Institutional Review Boards (IRBs) at both the VA Ann Arbor Healthcare System and the VA Palo Alto Health Care System. The IRB approved only retrospective use of data from the time of initial IRB approval in 2013. Hence, this study used veterans who were assessed in FY 2011 and followed for 18 months to find the effectiveness of cessation pharmacotherapy<sup><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup>.</p><p>Pharmacotherapy prescriptions were abstracted from pharmacy data for the 6 months following the index assessment. The provider was deemed to have initiated pharmacotherapy if the patient screened for tobacco use ultimately received a VA prescription for pharmacotherapy within this 6-month period. Predictors of the use of tobacco pharmacotherapy relating to providers, clinics, and facilities, were studied in patients identified as currently using tobacco at the time of their last assessment in 2011. Comorbidities were determined from utilization data in the 12-month period prior to the tobacco assessment in 2011.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><title>Measures</title><sec id="s2d1"><title>Outcome variable</title><p>The dependent variable was initiation of tobacco cessation pharmacotherapy, including nicotine replacement therapy (NRT), varenicline, and prescriptions for bupropion SR 150 mg taken twice per day, the dose approved by the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) for tobacco cessation. Lower dosages of bupropion, typically used for depression, were not considered cessation pharmacotherapy.</p></sec><sec id="s2d2"><title>Patient characteristics</title><p>Included as covariates were patient characteristics (age, sex, race, ethnicity, as well as medical, psychiatric, and substance use disorder comorbidities) known to influence patient receptivity and subsequent initiation of tobacco cessation therapy. Standard sets of International Classification of Diseases (ICD-9) diagnostic codes were used to identify medical conditions (yes/no)<sup><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> and psychiatric and substance use disorder comorbidities (yes/no)<sup><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="s2d3"><title>Provider and facility characteristics</title><p>Provider characteristics, included as predictors of patient receipt of cessation pharmacotherapy, included age, sex, provider type (based on position title and degree), clinic (based on the clinic stop), and facility characteristics. Clinics were categorized based on Health Economics Resource Center (HERC) Category of Care Assignments (outpatient primary care, specialty care, psychiatry, substance use disorder treatment, surgery, and other). Facility classification (e.g. VAMC, multi-specialty or primary care community-based outpatient center), complexity, and rurality characteristics were based on VA Site Tracking system (VAST) data from the Planning System Support Group<sup><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup>. The Clinical Complexity Index rating for each VAMC complexity relates to the level of patient risk, patient volume and teaching or research done at the facility. The VA Facility Complexity Model classifies VA medical facilities at levels 1a, 1b, 1c, 2, or 3, with level-1a facilities being the most complex and level 3 facilities the least complex. To control for the unmeasured facility-level differences in the use of pharmacotherapy and location-specific differences affecting tobacco use, such as tobacco tax rates and tobacco use regulations, a set of indicator variables were created for the 130 facilities where the index tobacco use assessment took place.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The proportion of providers prescribing tobacco cessation pharmacotherapies were calculated overall and by each provider characteristic, clinic classification, and facility characteristic. Logistic regression models were used to estimate the adjusted odds ratio (AOR) for each potential provider characteristic for pharmacotherapy initiation. First, multivariable logistic regression models were done separately for each provider characteristic controlling for patient characteristics (demographic, psychiatric/ substance use diagnosis, medical comorbidities) and facilities, with Generalized Estimating Equation (GEE) controlling for the correlation of patients within providers. Second, multivariable logistic regression model for all provider characteristics controlling for patient characteristics (demographic, psychiatric/ substance use diagnosis, medical comorbidities) and facilities with GEE controlling for the correlation of patients within providers. AORs represent the independent association between a given provider characteristic and pharmacotherapy initiation, i.e. odds of initiation in those with the characteristic relative to those without the characteristic. Provider characteristics of age and sex were missing for 182474 patient-level observations (28.5%). Due to the problem of using an indicator variable, we performed a multivariable logistic model excluding patients seen by providers with missing age or sex as a sensitivity analysis (n=182474; 28.5%).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec3"><title>RESULTS</title><p>The index HF assessment of the 639507 veterans who were patients that screened positive for tobacco use and who did not use pharmacotherapy in the prior year were made by 30388 unique providers in FY 2011 (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Among providers who made the index HF assessment, 53% were age &lt;55 years and 52% were female. Provider types included 47% physicians, 3% physician assistants, 10% nurse practitioners, 17% registered nurses, 9% licensed practical/vocational nurses, 1% pharmacists, and 13% other providers or missing type data. The majority (80%) of the patients were assessed in outpatient primary care clinics, 10% in outpatient psychiatry clinics, 6% in outpatient specialty clinics, and the remainder in outpatient substance use disorder treatment, outpatient surgery and other outpatient settings (4%).</p><table-wrap id="t0001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Characteristics of providers caring for veterans who use tobacco</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col charoff="40%" span="1"/><col charoff="20%" span="1"/><col charoff="20%" span="1"/><col charoff="20%" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th valign="top" rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Provider&#160;characteristics</italic></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Providers</italic></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Providers&#160;initiating&#160;tobacco&#160;cessation&#160;pharmacotherapy&#160;<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf1-1"><sup>a</sup></xref></italic></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Veterans&#160;currently&#160;using&#160;tobacco</italic></th></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n&#160;(%)</italic></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">%</italic></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n&#160;(%)</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>All</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30388 (100)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">639507 (100)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Age</bold> (years)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18&#8211;44</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9249 (30.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">136037 (21.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45&#8211;54</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6931 (22.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">164835 (25.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55&#8211;64</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6862 (22.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">165609 (25.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;65</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1403 (4.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33032 (5.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;18 or missing</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6786 (22.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">139994 (21.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sex</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15907 (52.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">307112 (48.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9472 (31.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">236197 (36.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Missing</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5009 (16.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96198 (15.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Provider type</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physician</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14159 (46.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">382277 (59.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physician assistant</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">907 (3.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39399 (6.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nurse practitioner</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2959 (9.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96511 (15.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Registered nurse</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5148 (16.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43874 (6.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Licensed practical/vocational nurse</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2802 (9.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48580 (7.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pharmacist</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">398 (1.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1910 (0.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3755 (12.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24900 (3.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Missing</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">260 (0.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2056 (0.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Clinic category</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient medicine-primary care</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16549 (54.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">510765 (79.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient medicine-specialty care</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6992 (23.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37879 (5.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient psychiatry</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6067 (20.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65946 (10.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient substance use treatment</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">964 (3.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6758 (1.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient surgery</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1182 (3.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7099 (1.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient other</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2550 (8.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11060 (1.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Facility classification</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthcare center</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">810 (2.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16915 (2.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multi-specialty CBOC</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4099 (13.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">124009 (19.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other outpatient services</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">381 (1.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6456 (1.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary care CBOC</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4783 (15.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">143589 (22.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VAMC 1a-high complexity</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">579 (1.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15446 (2.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VAMC 1b-high complexity</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10188 (33.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">132777 (20.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VAMC 1c-high complexity</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3813 (12.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59989 (9.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VAMC 2-medium complexity</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2965 (9.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55585 (8.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VAMC 3-low complexity</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2440 (8.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49640 (7.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unclassified</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1765 (5.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35101 (5.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Facility rurality</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urban</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26822 (88.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">531978 (83.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rural/highly rural/insular</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4163 (13.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">107529 (16.8)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf1-1"><label>a</label><p>For one or more veterans currently using tobacco. CBOC: community-based outpatient clinic. VAMC: Veterans Affairs Medical Center.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>About 49% of the patients received their tobacco use assessment in VA medical centers (VAMCs) and the majority (83%) in VA facilities located in urban areas. Overall, 52% of providers who made the index HF assessment had one or more patients who initiated tobacco cessation pharmacotherapy.</p><p><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> presents the results of the logistic regression analysis for pharmacotherapy initiation with provider, clinic, and facility characteristics, as predictors controlling for patient characteristics (demographics, psychiatric conditions, medical comorbidities) and facilities. Results of the multivariable logistic regression analysis show that providers who were older (AOR=0.96, p&lt;0.05; AOR=0.91; AOR=0.87; for age groups 45&#8211;54 years, 55&#8211;64 years, &#8805;65 years respectively, compared to age group 18&#8211;44 years) and male providers (AOR=0.93, p&lt;0.001 for males, compared to females) were less likely to initiate tobacco pharmacotherapy. Moreover, in terms of provider type, compared to physicians, pharmacists were 74% more likely to initiate pharmacotherapy (AOR=1.74, p&lt;0.001), while selected nurse categories were 5&#8211;8% less likely to initiate treatment (AOR=0.92, p&lt;0.001 to AOR=0.95, p&lt;0.001 for nurse categories, compared to physicians), and physician assistants were the least likely to initiate pharmacotherapy (AOR=0.88, p&lt;0.001 for physician assistants, compared to physicians).</p><table-wrap id="t0002" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Logistic regression model of treating (or not treating) veterans with tobacco cessation pharmacotherapy (N=639507); adjusted odds ratios are for odds of pharmacotherapy associated with provider characteristics</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col charoff="40%" span="1"/><col charoff="30%" span="1"/><col charoff="30%" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th valign="top" rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Characteristics</italic></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Simple&#160;model</italic></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Multivariable&#160;model</italic></th></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">AOR&#160;(95%&#160;CI)&#160;<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-1"><sup>a</sup></xref></italic></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">AOR&#160;(95%&#160;CI)&#160;<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-2"><sup>b</sup></xref></italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Provider characteristics</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Age</bold> (years)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18&#8211;44</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45&#8211;54</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96 (0.93&#8211;0.99)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">**</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96 (0.93&#8211;0.99)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-3">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55&#8211;64</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 (0.87&#8211;0.94)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">**</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91 (0.88&#8211;0.95)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">**</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;65</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85 (0.80&#8211;0.90)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">**</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 (0.82&#8211;0.93)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">**</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;18 or missing</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99 (0.95&#8211;1.04)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96 (0.92&#8211;1.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sex</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94 (0.92&#8211;0.97)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">**</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93 (0.91&#8211;0.96)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">**</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Missing</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06 (1.02&#8211;1.10)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">**</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01 (0.97&#8211;1.06)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Provider type</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physician</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physician assistant</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89 (0.84&#8211;0.94)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">**</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88 (0.83&#8211;0.94)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">**</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nurse practitioner</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97 (0.94&#8211;1.01)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95 (0.91&#8211;0.99)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">**</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Registered nurse</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96 (0.92&#8211;1.00)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95 (0.91&#8211;0.99)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-3">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Licensed practical/vocational nurse</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97 (0.92&#8211;1.02)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 (0.88&#8211;0.97)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">**</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pharmacist</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.70 (1.47&#8211;1.97)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">**</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.74 (1.50&#8211;2.02)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">**</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85 (0.81&#8211;0.89)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">**</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86 (0.81&#8211;0.91)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">**</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Missing</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 (0.88&#8211;1.26)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97 (0.81&#8211;1.16)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Clinic category</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient medicine-primary care</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient medicine-specialty care</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 (0.86&#8211;0.94)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">**</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94 (0.90&#8211;0.98)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">**</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient psychiatry</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86 (0.83&#8211;0.90)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">**</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 (0.87&#8211;0.94)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">**</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient substance use treatment</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06 (0.97&#8211;1.15)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16 (1.07&#8211;1.27)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">**</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient surgery</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57 (0.51&#8211;0.64)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">**</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61 (0.55&#8211;0.69)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">**</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient other</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91 (0.85&#8211;0.98)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-3">*</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 (0.83&#8211;0.97)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">**</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Facility classification</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthcare center</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95 (0.86&#8211;1.04)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93 (0.84&#8211;1.03)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multi-specialty CBOC</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89 (0.85&#8211;0.93)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">**</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89 (0.85&#8211;0.92)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">**</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other outpatient services</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98 (0.87&#8211;1.10)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 (0.88&#8211;1.12)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary care CBOC</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VAMC 1a-high complexity</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81 (0.77&#8211;0.85)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">**</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82 (0.78&#8211;0.86)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">**</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VAMC 1b-high complexity</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77 (0.72&#8211;0.82)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">**</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77 (0.72&#8211;0.82)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">**</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VAMC 1c-high complexity</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 (0.84&#8211;0.97)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">**</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91 (0.85&#8211;0.97)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">**</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VAMC 2-medium complexity</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79 (0.74&#8211;0.85)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">**</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81 (0.75&#8211;0.86)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">**</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VAMC 3-low complexity</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71 (0.66&#8211;0.77)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">**</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72 (0.67&#8211;0.78)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">**</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unclassified</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83 (0.76&#8211;0.91)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">**</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83 (0.76&#8211;0.91)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">**</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Facility rurality</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urban</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rural/highly rural/insular</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 (1.01&#8211;1.10)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">**</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97 (0.93&#8211;1.01)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf2-1"><p>a Multivariable logistic regression model done separately for each provider characteristic controlling for patient characteristics (demographic, psychiatric/substance use diagnosis, medical comorbidities) and facilities, with Generalized Estimating Equation (GEE) controlling for the correlation of patients within providers.</p></fn><fn id="tf2-2"><label>b</label><p>Multivariable logistic regression model for all provider characteristics controlling for patient characteristics (demographic, psychiatric/substance use diagnosis, medical comorbidities) and facilities with GEE controlling for the correlation of patients within providers. All analyses controlled for 130 facilities using dummy variables for parent facilities. CBOC: communitybased outpatient clinic. VAMC: Veterans Affairs Medical Center.</p></fn><fn id="tf2-3"><label>*</label><p>p&lt;0.05,</p></fn><fn id="tf2-4"><label>**</label><p>p&lt;0.001.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Patients assessed as currently using tobacco in outpatient substance use disorder treatment clinics (about 10% of sample) were more likely to have cessation pharmacotherapy initiated compared to those seen in outpatient primary care clinics (AOR=1.16, p&lt;0.001). Those in other clinic categories were slightly less likely to have pharmacotherapy initiated (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>) with outpatient surgery over a third less likely to receive pharmacotherapy (AOR=0.61, p&lt;0.001). Those seen in primary care CBOCs were more likely to initiate pharmacotherapy than other classes of VA facilities such as healthcare centers, multi-specialty CBOCs, and VAMCs, (p&lt;0.001). The sensitivity analysis excluding 182474 (28.5%) patients seen by providers with missing age or sex yielded similar results as the main analysis.</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec4"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>After adjusting for patient demographic and clinical characteristics and facilities, this study showed that several provider demographic characteristics were associated with providing tobacco cessation pharmacotherapy. Younger providers were more likely to prescribe tobacco cessation pharmacotherapy, perhaps because tobacco treatment is being increasingly emphasized in educational curricula<sup><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup>. Female providers were more likely than males to provide pharmacotherapy. Similarly, the literature has shown that female physicians are more likely to adhere to clinical guidelines<sup><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup>, as well as provide general and cancer-specific preventive care, including psychosocial and substance use disorder counseling<sup><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup>.</p><p>While physician-delivered interventions have been found to increase cessation efforts<sup><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup>, nurse-led and pharmacist-led interventions in various clinical settings have shown an increase in patients being offered pharmacotherapy and an improvement in patient acceptance of pharmacotherapy<sup><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup>. In this study, pharmacists were more likely than the physician reference group to prescribe tobacco pharmacotherapy. This is most likely due to the pharmacists&#8217; role in the VA, as pharmacists are often assigned the responsibility of providing tobacco cessation services. VA pharmacists have generally initiated evidence-based quality improvement efforts, such as obtaining an accurate tobacco-use assessment, initiating tobacco cessation pharmacotherapy, and continued follow-up care. Pharmacists are an ideal provider type to initiate pharmacotherapy support for tobacco cessation, with evidence-based outreach programs having the potential to increase the impact of their work on patient cessation. A trial testing the impact of a pharmacist-led telephone counseling program in primary care significantly increased prescription tobacco cessation medication adherence by 4.1% compared with usual care, and had a higher number of abstinent smokers at 12 weeks<sup><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup>.</p><p>Under-prescribing clinical provider groups include physician assistants, advanced practice nurses, registered nurses, and licensed nurses. These groups may have a lack of training on providing tobacco cessation in their educational curricula and on the job<sup><xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup>. An alternative explanation for the lower rates of treatment by physician assistants may reflect their practice setting (e.g. surgical or specialty care) which may defer tobacco treatment to other specialties such as primary care or pharmacy. VA physician assistants and nurse practitioners in primary care have been shown to provide more cost-efficient care than VA physicians<sup><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup>, and potentially have more opportunity for initiation as well, due to their smaller panel size. While physician assistants were the lowest prescribing group and are the smallest of the provider groups, addressing barriers of education<sup><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> and recognition of the importance of the pharmacotherapy prescription guidelines would likely enhance prescription rates by this group. While advance practice nurses and registered nurses initiated tobacco cessation pharmacotherapy only slightly less than physicians, nurse-initiated interventions could potentially be ramped up, as nurses are the largest group of frontline providers and nurse-delivered cessation interventions have been found to be efficacious<sup><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup>. Staff training and integration into nurse workflow is needed for nurse initiation at the VA, with programs to assist with follow-up on prescription initiation when patients transition from the inpatient to the outpatient setting<sup><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup>.</p><p>Tobacco use is highly comorbid with substance use disorder, and our study found patients seen in substance use treatment clinics were more likely to initiate pharmacotherapy compared to those seen in outpatient primary care clinics. Patients with substance use disorder (SUD) are twice as likely to smoke than the general population, with a study reporting 59% of veterans enrolled in a SUD clinic used tobacco and 86.5% of these patients were offered treatment for tobacco use on intake<sup><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup>. While only 41% attempted cessation when enrolled in the SUD clinic, evidence shows that while the timing of the quit attempt is crucial, quitting tobacco can increase the odds of continued abstinence from all substances<sup><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup>. While tobacco use is also highly comorbid with psychiatric disorders, it was unfortunate to find low prescribing rates in outpatient psychiatric clinics. As might be expected and similar to other studies<sup><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>, prescribing rates were particularly low in outpatient surgery where patients may not be fully conscious, but within the broader context of outpatient surgical care, it might also be a missed opportunity to provide pre-operative teaching regarding tobacco cessation.</p><p>Similar to other studies<sup><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup>, patients seen in primary care CBOCs were fairly likely to initiate tobacco cessation pharmacotherapy (63% of their providers), perhaps because cessation counselling has become &#8216;standard of care&#8217; in primary care<sup><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>. Higher complexity facilities (1a, 1b, and 1c) were less likely to initiate tobacco cessation pharmacotherapy (44, 47, and 50%, respectively) perhaps because of multiple competing priorities. An explanation for lower prescriptions in other outpatient clinical settings may be clinical practice norms that defer tobacco cessation pharmacotherapy to primary care. This is a large missed opportunity for effectively addressing tobacco use, as every clinical encounter that assesses tobacco use should be followed with the evidence-based action of pharmacotherapy if not already initiated. Clinical practice norms and attitudes are modifiable and can be addressed in practice improvement efforts.</p><sec id="sec4.1"><title>Policy implications</title><p>VA data show that tobacco use rates have declined from 33% of VA patients in 1999 to 14.6% in 2018<sup><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup>. Contrary to other real-world studies published outside of the VA<sup><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup>, a recently published study on this cohort conducted by our team showed that pharmacotherapy was effective in the real-world VA setting<sup><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup>. A second study found that the delivery of cessation pharmacotherapy was cost effective. Compared to the general public, tobacco use is more prevalent in the military<sup><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup> and, as active duty military members transition to the VA setting, many will be in need of tobacco treatment delivered by providers who are optimally prepared. Targeting tobacco cessation education toward provider subgroups and changing culture in clinics and facilities that are least likely to initiate tobacco cessation pharmacotherapy will be essential to quality improvement efforts in the VA. Additionally, health system changes to leverage technology and workflow to support pharmacotherapy is increasingly needed. These efforts are particularly important due to the VA issuing a directive to ban all tobacco use on all VA medical campuses in late 2019<sup><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.2"><title>Strengths and limitations</title><p>The study included a large national sample of over 30000 providers that treated almost 640000 veterans that used tobacco. While the results are only generalizable to the VA setting, there are implications for non-VA settings. The study was able to control for a large number of individual and organizational covariates. However, several potential provider factors were not available, including provider race, tobacco use, and attitudes around prescribing. The EMR may not have captured all tobacco treatment interventions provided (including undocumented pharmacotherapy recommendations) or facility differences that designate a particular type of provider to conduct tobacco cessation such that a lower rate of prescription would be expected by other provider types. Studies are in progress to trigger providers to better document tobacco treatment<sup><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup>. While the rationale for including prescriptions up to 6 months after the index visit was chosen to increase the likelihood that prescribing rates will not be underestimated (a more &#8216;conservative&#8217; approach), it also increases the likelihood that the clinician conducting the index assessment and the clinical setting in which it occurred are not tied directly to the actual prescription of tobacco cessation pharmacotherapy. However, a companion paper reported that, of those who initiated pharmacotherapy, the average time from the clinical reminder assessment to pharmacology treatment was 1.3 months<sup><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup>. Additionally, the amount tobacco used per day, type of tobacco use, and the type of pharmacotherapy treatment prescribed, were not present in the data, limiting sub-analyses to inform further tailoring of recommendations. While the VA medical record does not allow for identification of type of tobacco (unless written in notes) at the time, the overwhelming majority of veterans who used tobacco smoked cigarettes<sup><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup>.</p><p>Although evidence supports that the Health Factors data are reasonably reliable and valid for purposes of identifying tobacco use, similar to other settings, there are inconsistencies among providers in how and when tobacco use is assessed. Even though bupropion doses for depression versus tobacco cessation were distinguished in the same way that has been in other studies<sup><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup>, there is a possibility that bupropion prescriptions were misclassified. Given that the nicotine patch, gum and lozenge are available over the counter, and that many veterans receive care both inside and outside of VA, it is possible that some participants may have been receiving tobacco cessation medications from other sources. Lastly, the age of the data (FY 2011) may not represent the latest pharmacotherapy prescribing behavior of clinicians, as provider-level and clinical-setting level characteristics, tobacco treatment policies and medication contraindications may have changed<sup><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup>.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec5"><title>CONCLUSIONS</title><p>While the VA is at the leading edge of providing tobacco treatment, as in all systems, there are underperforming subgroups of providers and care settings. This study showed that male, older, and non-pharmacist providers, specialty and outpatient surgery clinics, as well as hospital settings, were less likely to provide tobacco cessation pharmacotherapy. As active-duty military members who use tobacco transition to the VA setting, targeting quality improvement efforts towards providers, clinics and facilities with low cessation pharmacotherapy initiation rates will be essential to continuing the declining rates of tobacco use in the VA.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p>The project was supported by Merit Review Award (Number I01 HX001764) from the United States Department of Veterans Affairs Health Services Research &amp; Development Service of the VA Office of Research and Development. The views expressed in this article are those of the authors and do not necessarily represent the views of the Department of Veterans Affairs. We gratefully acknowledge the contribution of Adam Chow of the VA Health Economics Resource Center, Menlo Park, CA for his help in identifying tobacco use status.</p></ack><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>CONFLICTS OF INTEREST</title><p>The authors have each completed and submitted an ICMJE form for disclosure of potential conflicts of interest. The authors declare that they have no competing interests, financial or otherwise, related to the current work. P.G. Barnett reports that his institution received payment from Merit Review Award I01 <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="HX001764">HX001764</ext-link> from the U.S. Department of Veterans Affairs Health Services Research &amp; Development Service.</p></sec><sec><title>FUNDING</title><p>This work was supported by the Health Services Research and Development Service of the U.S. Department of Veterans Affairs (Proposal number IIR 14-301) awarded to SD. This funding was in the form of an unrestricted allocation. The sponsor did not directly shape the design or conduct of the study, the collection, management, analysis, and interpretation of the data, or the preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript.</p></sec><sec><title>ETHICAL APPROVAL AND INFORMED CONSENT</title><p>Ethical approval and informed consent were not required as all data used were from existing databases.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>DATA AVAILABILITY</title><p>The data supporting this research cannot be made available for privacy reasons.</p></sec><sec><title>AUTHORS&#8217; CONTRIBUTIONS</title><p>ACB, SAD, MCG, RVI, HMK and PGB made substantial contributions to the conception, interpretation of analysis and findings, and critical revision for intellectual content. RVI made substantial contributions to analysis and interpretation of data. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec><title>PROVENANCE AND PEER REVIEW</title><p>Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed.</p></sec><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="cit0001"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>U.S. Department of Health and Human Services</collab></person-group><article-title>Smoking Cessation</article-title><source>A Report of the Surgeon General</source><year>2020</year><publisher-name>U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, National Center for Chronic Disease Prevention and Health Promotion, Office on Smoking and Health</publisher-name><comment>Accessed March 30, 2021. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.hhs.gov/sites/default/files/2020-cessation-sgr-full-report.pdf">https://www.hhs.gov/sites/default/files/2020-cessation-sgr-full-report.pdf</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0002"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Tobacco Use and Dependence Guideline Panel</collab></person-group><source>Treating Tobacco Use and Dependence: 2008 Update</source><year>2008</year><publisher-name>U.S. Department of Health and Human Services</publisher-name><comment>Accessed March 30, 2021. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK63952/#!po=5.00000">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK63952/#!po=5.00000</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0003"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Department of Veteran Affairs</collab></person-group><article-title>National Smoking and Tobacco Use Cessation Program</article-title><source>VHA DIRECTIVE 1056</source><year>2014</year><publisher-name>VHA Publications</publisher-name><comment>Accessed March 30, 2021. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.oklahoma.va.gov/1056_D_2014-02-10.pdf">https://www.oklahoma.va.gov/1056_D_2014-02-10.pdf</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0004"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ignacio</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Trends and Patient Characteristics Associated with Tobacco Pharmacotherapy Dispensed in the Veterans Health Administration</article-title><source>Nicotine Tob Res</source><year>2018</year><volume>20</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1173</fpage><lpage>1181</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ntr/ntx229</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30184237</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0005"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramsey</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McIntosh</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tobacco Use Prevalence and Smoking Cessation Pharmacotherapy Prescription Patterns Among Hospitalized Patients by Medical Specialty</article-title><source>Nicotine Tob Res</source><year>2019</year><volume>21</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>631</fpage><lpage>637</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ntr/nty031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29481616</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6468129</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0006"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartmann-Boyce</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chepkin</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bullen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lancaster</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nicotine replacement therapy versus control for smoking cessation</article-title><source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source><year>2018</year><volume>5</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>CD000146</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD000146.pub5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29852054</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6353172</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0007"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dube</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Babb</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McAfee</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Patient-reported recall of smoking cessation interventions from a health professional</article-title><source>Prev Med</source><year>2013</year><volume>57</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>715</fpage><lpage>717</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ypmed.2013.07.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23872172</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4572889</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0008"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duffy</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reeves</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hermann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karvonen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In-hospital smoking cessation programs: what do VA patients and staff want and need?</article-title><source>Appl Nurs Res</source><year>2008</year><volume>21</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>206</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apnr.2006.11.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18995161</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0009"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>US Department of Veterans Affairs</collab></person-group><source>Veterans Health Administration</source><year>2020</year><month>8</month><day>10</day><comment>Accessed March 30, 2021. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.va.gov/health/">https://www.va.gov/health/</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0010"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ignacio Rosalinda</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cost-Effectiveness of Real World Administration of Tobacco Pharmacotherapy in the Veterans Health Administration</article-title><source>Addiction</source><year>2019</year><volume>114</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1436</fpage><lpage>1445</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/add.14621</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30924195</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0011"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hur</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A comparison of neuropsychiatric adverse events during early treatment with varenicline or a nicotine patch</article-title><source>Addiction</source><year>2016</year><volume>111</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1283</fpage><lpage>1892</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/add.13329</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26826702</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0012"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duffy</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ignacio</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effectiveness of tobacco cessation pharmacotherapy in the Veterans Health Administration</article-title><source>Tob Control</source><year>2018</year><volume>28</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>540</fpage><lpage>547</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/tobaccocontrol-2018-054473</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30181383</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0013"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>U.S. Department of Veteran Affairs</collab></person-group><source>HERC: Average Cost</source><year>2019</year><comment>Accessed March 30,2021. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.herc.research.va.gov/include/page.asp?id=average-cost">https://www.herc.research.va.gov/include/page.asp?id=average-cost</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0014"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>U.S. Department of Veteran Affairs</collab></person-group><source>HERC: Other data</source><year>2019</year><comment>Accessed March 30, 2021. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.herc.research.va.gov/include/page.asp?id=other">https://www.herc.research.va.gov/include/page.asp?id=other</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0015"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elixhauser</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steiner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coffey</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comorbidity measures for use with administrative data</article-title><source>Medical care</source><volume>1998</volume><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00005650-199801000-00004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9431328</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0016"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Quan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sundararajan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Halfon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Coding algorithms for defining comorbidities in ICD-9-CM and ICD-10 administrative data</article-title><source>Medical Care</source><year>2005</year><volume>43</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1130</fpage><lpage>1139</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.mlr.0000182534.19832.83</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16224307</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0017"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Herold</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schiekirka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Structured smoking cessation training for medical students: a prospective study</article-title><source>Nicotine Tob Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>18</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>2209</fpage><lpage>2215</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ntr/ntw191</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27613926</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5103940</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0018"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baumh&#228;kel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>M&#252;ller</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>B&#246;hm</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of gender of physicians and patients on guideline-recommended treatment of chronic heart failure in a cross-sectional study</article-title><source>Eur J Heart Fail</source><year>2009</year><volume>11</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>299</fpage><lpage>303</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurjhf/hfn041</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19158153</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2645055</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0019"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dresner</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vinker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The association between physicians&#8217; and patients&#8217; preventive health practices</article-title><source>CMAJ</source><year>2013</year><volume>185</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>649</fpage><lpage>653</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1503/cmaj.121028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23569163</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3652935</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0020"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stead</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bergson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lancaster</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physician advice for smoking cessation</article-title><source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source><year>2008</year><issue>2</issue><fpage>CD000165</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD000165.pub3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18425860</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0021"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>VH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heath</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Livingstone-Banks</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartmann-Boyce</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nursing interventions for smoking cessation</article-title><source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source><year>2017</year><volume>12</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>CD001188</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD001188.pub5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29243221</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6486227</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0022"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sui</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ming</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pharmacist-led Smoking Cessation Services: Current and Future Perspectives, in Neuroscience of Nicotine</article-title><source>Elsevier</source><volume>2019</volume><fpage>441</fpage><lpage>449</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0023"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A pragmatic randomized trial comparing telephone-based enhanced pharmacy care and usual care to support smoking cessation</article-title><source>J Manag Care Spec Pharm</source><year>2016</year><volume>22</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1417</fpage><lpage>1425</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18553/jmcp.2016.22.12.1417</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27882838</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10397624</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0024"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Binnal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gururaghavendran</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Denny</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tallada</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tobacco Cessation Scenarios Among Healthcare Profession Students: A Multidisciplinary Study</article-title><source>Asian Pac J Cancer Prev</source><year>2018</year><volume>19</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1081</fpage><lpage>1088</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.22034/APJCP.2018.19.4.1081</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29699368</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6031790</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0025"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berkowitz</surname><given-names>TSZ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impact of physicians, nurse practitioners, and physician assistants on utilization and costs for complex patients</article-title><source>Health Affairs</source><year>2019</year><volume>38</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1028</fpage><lpage>1036</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1377/hlthaff.2019.00014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31158006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0026"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>DiCocco</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessing the current status of tobacco dependence education curricula in US physician assistant programs</article-title><source>Journal of Physician Assistant Education</source><year>2011</year><volume>22</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>4</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01367895-201122030-00001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22070058</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0027"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>&#8216;Let Me Get You a Nicotine Patch&#8217;: Nurses' Perceptions of Implementing Smoking Cessation Guidelines for Hospitalized Veterans</article-title><source>Mil Med</source><year>2016</year><volume>181</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>382</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7205/MILMED-D-15-00101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27046185</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7540252</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0028"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gass</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Winters</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>VanderVeen</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chermack</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characteristics and clinical treatment of tobacco smokers enrolled in a VA substance use disorders clinic</article-title><source>J Subst Abuse Treat</source><year>2018</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsat.2017.10.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29195588</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0029"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration</collab></person-group><article-title>Implementing Tobacco Cessation Programs in Substance Use Disorder Treatment Settings: A Quick Guide for Program Directors and Clinicians</article-title><source>HHS Publication No. SMA18-5069QG</source><year>2018</year><publisher-name>U.S. Department of Health and Human Services</publisher-name><comment>Accessed March 30, 2021. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://store.samhsa.gov/sites/default/files/d7/priv/sma18-5069qg.pdf">https://store.samhsa.gov/sites/default/files/d7/priv/sma18-5069qg.pdf</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0030"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferketich</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wewers</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Are physicians asking about tobacco use and assisting with cessation? Results from the 2001&#8211;2004 national ambulatory medical care survey (NAMCS)</article-title><source>Prev Med</source><year>2006</year><volume>43</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>472</fpage><lpage>476</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ypmed.2006.07.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16920185</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0031"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dhanireddy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prince</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schimpf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pearman</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>2019 Survey of Veteran Enrollees&#8217; Health and Use of Health Care</article-title><source>Contract No: VA245-17-C-0178</source><year>2020</year><publisher-name>U.S. Department of Veterans Affairs</publisher-name><comment>Accessed March 30, 2021. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.va.gov/HEALTHPOLICYPLANNING/SOE2019/2019_Enrollee_Data_Findings_Report-March_2020_508_Compliant.pdf">https://www.va.gov/HEALTHPOLICYPLANNING/SOE2019/2019_Enrollee_Data_Findings_Report-March_2020_508_Compliant.pdf</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0032"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alpert</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Connolly</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Biener</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A prospective cohort study challenging the effectiveness of population-based medical intervention for smoking cessation</article-title><source>Tob Control</source><year>2013</year><volume>22</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>32</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/tobaccocontrol-2011-050129</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22234781</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0033"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bondurant</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wedge</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><source>Institute of Medicine (US) Committee on Smoking Cessation in Military and Veteran Populations</source><year>2009</year><publisher-name>National Academies Press</publisher-name><comment>Accessed March 30, 2021. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK215333/toc/?report=reader">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK215333/toc/?report=reader</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25009944</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0034"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Veterans Health Administration</collab></person-group><source>Smoke-Free VA Healthcare Facilities</source><year>2019</year><publisher-name>U. S. Department of Veterans Affairs</publisher-name><comment>Accessed March 30, 2021. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.va.gov/health/smokefree/#top">https://www.va.gov/health/smokefree/#top</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0035"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kharrazi</surname><given-names>HHK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huerta</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Electronic medical record reminders and smoking cessation activities in primary care</article-title><source>Addict Behav</source><year>2018</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>209</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.addbeh.2017.10.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29065376</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0036"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Odani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Agaku</surname><given-names>IT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Graffunder</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tynan</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Armour</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tobacco product use among military veterans&#8212;United States, 2010&#8211;2015</article-title><source>Morbidity and Mortality Weekly Report</source><year>2018</year><volume>67</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm6701a2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29324732</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5769800</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0037"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Siroka</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamlett-Berry</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Using policy to increase prescribing of smoking cessation medications in the VA healthcare system</article-title><source>Tob Control</source><year>2010</year><volume>19</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>507</fpage><lpage>511</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/tc.2009.035147</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20870742</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0038"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sambamoorthi</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trends in utilization of smoking cessation agents before and after the passage of FDA boxed warning in the United States</article-title><source>Drug Alcohol Depend</source><year>2017</year><volume>177</volume><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>193</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2017.03.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28605678</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5568118</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>