<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Arthroplasty</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Arthroplasty</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">4152</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">arthroplasty</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Arthroplasty</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2524-7948</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9969675</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC9969675.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">9969675</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">9969675</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36843080</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s42836-023-00164-9</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">164</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Cannabis use disorder is associated with shorter length of stay and increased home discharge after primary total joint arthroplasty: a propensity-weighted analysis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahmon</surname><given-names initials="D">Dalia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6577-5224</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Zalikha</surname><given-names initials="AK">Abdul Kareem</given-names></name><address><email>akzalikha@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mazur</surname><given-names initials="M">Matthew</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hajj Hussein</surname><given-names initials="I">Inaya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Othmani</surname><given-names initials="MM">Mouhanad M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.261277.7</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2219 916X</institution-id><institution>Department of Foundational Medical Studies, </institution><institution>Oakland University William Beaumont School of Medicine, </institution></institution-wrap>Rochester, MI 48309 USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.413184.b</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0088 6903</institution-id><institution>Department of Orthopaedic Surgery and Sports Medicine, Detroit Medical Center, </institution></institution-wrap>Detroit, MI 48201 USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.239585.0</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2285 2675</institution-id><institution>Department of Orthopaedic Surgery, </institution><institution>Columbia University Medical Center, </institution></institution-wrap>New York, NY USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>2</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">425092</issue-id><elocation-id>9</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>8</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>1</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>27</day><month>02</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>28</day><month>02</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-03-01 05:10:12.137"><day>01</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2023</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="42836_2023_Article_164.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par1">Increased legalization of cannabis use across the United States has been correlated with increased cannabis use in the clinical setting. However, little is known regarding the characteristics and postoperative outcomes after primary joint arthroplasty (TJA) for patients with cannabis use disorder (CUD).</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">This retrospective cohort study used data from the National Inpatient Sample of patients undergoing primary TJA between 2006 to 2015. Patients were grouped based on presence of concomitant CUD. Patient demographic characteristics and outcome data between groups were analyzed. Propensity score methodology was used to compare immediate in-hospital complications and economic outcomes.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">A total of 8,740,798 TJAs were included. The prevalence of CUD increased nearly five-fold from 0.05% to 0.26% during this time (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.0001). CUD patients were significantly younger, more likely to be male, most frequently of non-Hispanic Black race, and had higher rates of Medicaid insurance. Patients with CUD had a significantly shorter length of hospital stay (3.04 <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 3.24 days, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0297), while incurring significantly higher daily ($22,614 <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> $17,955, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.0001) and total charges during admission ($58,507 <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> $50,924, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.0001), compared to patients without CUD. When compared with the control group, CUD was associated with significantly greater odds of home discharge (odds ratio (OR): 1.45, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0007), and significantly lower odds of rehab discharge (OR: 0.70, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0013). There were no differences in overall complication profile or in the vast majority of individual in-hospital complications between groups.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">While CUD is correlated to shorter length of stay and increased home discharge after TJA, it does not show a strong effect on complications in an inpatient postoperative setting. It is important for clinicians to appreciate the demographic profile and expected clinical and economic outcomes for patients with CUD undergoing TJA, particularly in the context of evolving laws surrounding cannabis use.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Cannabis use disorder</kwd><kwd>Total joint arthroplasty</kwd><kwd>Total hip arthroplasty</kwd><kwd>Total knee arthroplasty</kwd><kwd>Epidemiology</kwd><kwd>Demographics</kwd><kwd>Complications</kwd><kwd>Outcomes</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#169; The Author(s) 2023</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par11">Widespread legalization and decriminalization of cannabis across the United States has been associated with a considerable rise in self-reported cannabis use amongst surgical patients, including those undergoing total joint arthroplasty [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. While cannabis is primarily used for recreational purposes, cannabinoid metabolites have shown analgesic and anti-inflammatory properties and have thus been proposed as an alternative to opioids in the management of acute and chronic pain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. While cannabis use may conceivably be beneficial in the postoperative setting, cannabis use disorder (CUD), defined in part as a problematic pattern of cannabis use leading to clinically significant impairment or distress, has been correlated with increased postoperative pain and opioid use following orthopedic surgical procedures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. It remains unclear what potential utilization and implication the cannabis use has on postoperative clinical and economic outcomes of patients undergoing major elective surgery, such as total joint arthroplasty (TJA) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. The relevant literature on this topic has yielded conflicting results, while being complicated by a patient population that is constantly evolving in the context of social and legal changes leading to increased cannabis use [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>].</p><p id="Par12">Total hip arthroplasty (THA) and total knee arthroplasty (TKA), collectively referred to as total joint arthroplasty (TJA), are among the most frequently performed surgeries in the United States [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Literature evaluating demographic and outcome trends for CUD patients undergoing TJA is altogether lacking. The rise in self-reported cannabis use paralleling continuously increasing rates of TJA has made it extremely relevant and worthwhile for healthcare professionals to better understand this population. Furthermore, given increased pressures in national healthcare systems aimed at improving quality and minimizing variability in outcomes, it is crucial to identify potential implications of CUD on in-hospital postoperative outcomes after TJA. Investigating these topics will help address current gaps in the literature while providing insight into the most appropriate clinical care and perioperative interventions for this patient population.</p><p id="Par13">The main objectives of this study were to highlight trends in cannabis use disorder among TJA patients, evaluate epidemiological and demographic characteristics of TJA patients with and without CUD, and compare inpatient postoperative clinical and economic outcomes among patients with and without CUD.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><p id="Par14">Discharge data from 2006 to 2015 were collected from the National Inpatient Sample (NIS) database and retrospectively analyzed in this study. The NIS was developed for the Healthcare Cost and Utilization Project (HCUP) and is the largest publicly available all-payer inpatient hospital database in the United States. The NIS contains data from over seven million hospital stays, representing a 20% stratified sample of discharges from community hospitals across the US. The <italic toggle="yes">International Classification of Disease, the Ninth Revision, Clinical Modification (ICD-9-CM)</italic> coding system was used during this study period. Institutional review board exemption was approved for this study.</p><p id="Par15">TJA patients were considered to be those undergoing either a primary THA or TKA. Patients older than 40 years who underwent a primary THA (<italic toggle="yes">ICD-9-CM</italic>, code 81.51) or primary TKA (81.54) were included in this study. The TJA population was then divided into two groups: (1) patients with cannabis use disorder (CUD), and (2) patients without CUD (referred to as the control group). Cannabis use disorder (CUD) was identified using <italic toggle="yes">ICD-9-CM</italic> codes 304.30, 304.31, 304.32, and 305.2. Exclusion criteria involved patients below the age of 40 years old, those undergoing revision procedures, and patient codes containing the specifier "in remission". The term &#8220;any complication&#8221; was used to refer to any postoperative cardiac, gastrointestinal (GI), genitourinary (GU), hematoma/seroma, wound dehiscence, infection, deep vein thrombosis (DVT), pulmonary embolism (PE), or anemia complications. Patient epidemiological and demographic characteristics, comorbidities, hospital length of stay, discharge disposition, immediate in-hospital complications, and economic outcomes of cohorts with and without CUD were then comparatively analyzed.</p><p id="Par16">Appropriate NIS trend weights were employed for analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Discharge characteristics were documented, and analysis was performed according to recommendations from the Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality (AHRQ) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Differences in patient characteristics, such as age, gender, and comorbidities, were analyzed using <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-tests and univariate logistic regressions, and further elucidated using propensity score matching through a combination of the Elixhauser Comorbidity Index and Inverse Probability of Treatment Weights (IPTW) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Statistical significance was defined at <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05. All data analyses were performed using SAS 9.4 (SAS Institute Inc., Cary, NC, USA) and Stata 13 (StataCorp, LLC, College Station, TX, USA).</p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec4"><title>Trends in CUD by year</title><p id="Par17">An estimated total of 8,740,798 TJAs were examined from 2006 to the third quarter of 2015. This total consisted of 2,838,741 THA and 5,902,057 TKA procedures. There was an approximately five-fold increase in the prevalence of CUD during this period, from 0.05% in 2006 to 0.26% in 2015 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.0001) (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Trend in cannabis use disorder rate by year in patients undergoing total joint arthroplasty</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Year</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rate (95% CI)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></bold>-Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2006</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.05% (0.03%, 0.07%)</td><td rowspan="10" colspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2007</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.04% (0.03%, 0.05%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2008</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.07% (0.05%, 0.08%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2009</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.07% (0.05%, 0.09%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2010</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.07% (0.06%, 0.09%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2011</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.13% (0.10%, 0.17%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2012</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.13% (0.11%, 0.14%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2013</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.14% (0.12%, 0.16%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2014</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.20% (0.18%, 0.23%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2015</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.26% (0.23%, 0.29%)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Demographic and hospital factors</title><p id="Par18">Significant differences in several demographic and hospital factors between CUD and non-CUD patients undergoing TJA were identified (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). These differences were observed for all variables besides &#8220;Elective Admission&#8221; and &#8220;Bedsize of Hospital&#8221;. Specifically, patients with CUD were significantly younger, more often of male gender, more frequently had Medicaid insurance with lower rates of Medicare insurance, were more likely to be non-Hispanic Black, and were less likely to be non-Hispanic White when compared to the non-CUD cohort. Patients with CUD were seen most frequently in urban teaching hospitals and in Western regions of the United States.<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Demographic and hospital factors, stratified by CUD <italic toggle="yes">vs</italic>. no CUD</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">CUD (<bold><italic toggle="yes">n</italic></bold> = 10,450)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">No CUD (<bold><italic toggle="yes">n</italic></bold> = 8,728,240)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></bold>-Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Age (Years)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Mean (Standard Error)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">55.35 (0.18)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">66.21 (0.04)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Biological Sex of Patient</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Male</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6,778 (64.86%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,429,533 (39.29%)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Female</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,672 (35.14%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5,298,707 (60.71%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Expected Primary Payor</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Medicare</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,182 (30.45%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,780,850 (54.77%)</td><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Medicaid</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,363 (22.62%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">268,762 (3.08%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Private</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,033 (38.60%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,346,741 (38.34%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Other</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">872 (8.34%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">331,885 (3.81%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Race of Patient</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Non-Hispanic White</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6,430 (61.54%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6,320,578 (72.42%)</td><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Non-Hispanic Black</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,320 (22.20%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">547,050 (6.27%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Hispanic</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">350 (3.35%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">349,886 (4.01%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Other Races</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,350 (12.92%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,510,725 (17.31%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Bedsize of Hospital</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Small</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,848 (17.68%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,708,714 (19.58%)</td><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">0.0733</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Medium</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,065 (29.33%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,298,152 (26.33%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Large</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5,527 (52.89%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,691,766 (53.75%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Unknown</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 10 cases</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 10 cases</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Location/Teaching Status of Hospital</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Rural</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">863 (8.25%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">972,637 (11.14%)</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Urban Nonteaching</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,112 (29.78%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,727,312 (42.70%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Urban Teaching</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6,465 (61.87%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,998,683 (45.81%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Region of Hospital</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Northeast</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,785 (17.08%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,553,107 (17.79%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Midwest</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,803 (26.82%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,360,652 (27.05%)</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;South</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,655 (25.41%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,092,824 (35.43%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;West</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,206 (30.68%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,721,657 (19.73%)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">CUD</italic> Cannabis Use Disorder</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Elixhauser comorbidities stratified by CUD</title><p id="Par19">Significant positive associations were found between groups on Elixhauser analysis of comorbidities (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Patients with CUD were more likely to have comorbid acquired immune deficiency syndrome (AIDS) (0.80% <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 0.05%, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.0001), alcohol abuse (20.09% <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 1.09%, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.0001), chronic pulmonary disease (23.77% <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 14.64%, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.0001), coagulopathy (2.70% <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 2.00%, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0246), depression (19.78% <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 12.17%, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.0001), liver disease (5.31% <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 0.94%, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.0001), neurological disorders (5.37% <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 3.81%, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0002), obesity (24.65% <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 19.57%, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.0001), and psychoses (9.53% <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 1.99%, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.0001).<table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Elixhauser comorbidities stratified by CUD <italic toggle="yes">v</italic><italic toggle="yes">s</italic>. no CUD</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">CUD (<bold><italic toggle="yes">n</italic></bold> = 10,450)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">No CUD (<bold><italic toggle="yes">n</italic></bold> = 8,728,240)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></bold>-Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome (AIDS)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">83 (0.80%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,646 (0.05%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Alcohol Abuse</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,100 (20.09%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">95,468 (1.09%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Deficiency Anemias</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,091 (10.44%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,127,581 (12.92%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0017</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rheumatoid Arthritis/Collagen Vascular Disease</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">447 (4.28%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">335,856 (3.85%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3131</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chronic Blood Loss Anemia</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">134 (1.28%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">142,540 (16.33%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1989</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Congestive Heart Failure</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">228 (2.18%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">226,512 (2.60%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2620</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chronic Pulmonary Disease</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,484 (23.77%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,278,145 (14.64%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Coagulopathy</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">282 (2.70%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">174,526 (2.00%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0246</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Depression</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,067 (19.78%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,062,505 (12.17%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Diabetes (Uncomplicated)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,349 (12.91%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,556,934 (17.84%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Diabetes (Complicated)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 10 cases</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">137,858 (1.58%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0191</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hypertension</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6,025 (57.66%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5,706,745 (65.38%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hypothyroidism</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">696 (6.66%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,306,443 (14.97%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Liver Disease</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">555 (5.31%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">82,328 (0.94%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lymphoma</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 10 cases</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24,127 (0.28%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9284</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fluid and Electrolyte Disorder</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">921 (8.81%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">740,054 (8.48%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6006</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Metastatic Cancer</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 10 cases</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12,175 (0.14%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5252</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Other Neurological Disorders</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">561 (5.37%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">332,666 (3.81%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0002</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Obesity</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,576 (24.65%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,708,050 (19.57%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Paralysis</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">67 (0.64%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">25,084 (0.29%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0022</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Peripheral Vascular Disorders</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">198 (1.89%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">186,509 (2.14%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4478</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Psychoses</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">996 (9.53%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">173,906 (1.99%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pulmonary Circulation Disorders</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">88 (0.84%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">81,867 (0.94%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6627</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Renal Failure</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">288 (2.75%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">353,326 (4.05%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0023</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Solid Tumor without Metastasis</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 10 cases</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">40,426 (0.46%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6600</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Peptic Ulcer Disease Excluding Bleeding</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 10 cases</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,692 (0.02%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6331</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Valvular Heart Disease</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">188 (1.80%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">323,668 (3.71%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Weight Loss</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">60 (0.57%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">29,898 (0.34%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0740</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">CUD</italic> Cannabis Use Disorder</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par20">Significant negative associations between groups were also observed (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Patients with CUD were significantly less likely to have comorbid deficiency anemia (10.44% <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 12.92%, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0017), uncomplicated diabetes (12.91% <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 17.84%, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.0001), hypertension (57.66% <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 65.38%, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.0001), hypothyroidism (6.66% <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 14.97%, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.0001), renal failure (2.75% <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 4.05%, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0023), and valvular heart disease (1.80% <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 3.71%, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.0001). Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref> provides a complete description of Elixhauser's comorbidities between the two groups.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>IPTW outcomes, stratified by CUD</title><p id="Par21">No statistically significant differences were found in the composite "any complication" variable between CUD and non-CUD patients (23.45% <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 23.87%, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.8149) upon IPTW analysis. Ultimately, 8 of the 9 individual in-hospital complications were not significantly different between groups, with a 79% decrease in odds of developing PE in the CUD cohort as the only significant divergence (OR: 0.21; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0030). CUD was not significantly associated with cardiac complications, GI complications, GU complications, hematoma/seroma, wound dehiscence, postoperative infection, DVT, or postoperative anemia.</p><p id="Par22">There were statistically significant differences in economic and discharge outcomes between cohorts. CUD was associated with a shorter average length of hospital stay (3.04 <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 3.24 days, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0297). Patients with CUD had both significantly higher total ($58,507 <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> $50,924, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.0001) and daily charges ($22,614 <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> $17,955, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.0001), compared to patients without CUD. Furthermore, CUD was associated with 45% greater odds of home discharge (OR: 1.45; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0007), and 30% lower odds of rehab discharge (OR: 0.70; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0013). Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref> provides a complete description of ITPW complications and economic outcomes.<table-wrap id="Tab4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Complication, economic, and disposition outcomes, stratified by CUD versus no CUD</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">CUD</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">No CUD</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">OR<sub><bold>IPTW</bold></sub> (95% CI)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></bold>-Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Any Complications</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.45%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.87%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.98 (0.81, 1.19)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8149</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cardiac Complication</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.63%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.64%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.99 (0.55, 1.78)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9813</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gastrointestinal (GI) Complication</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.05%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.27%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.17 (0.03, 1.16)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0706</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Genitourinary (GU) Complication</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.11%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.52%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.17 (0.66, 7.11)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2002</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hematoma/Seroma</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.37%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.64%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.58 (0.24, 1.39)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2202</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Wound Dehiscence</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.21%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.09%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.45 (0.80, 7.46)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1154</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Postoperative Infection</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.12%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.13%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.92 (0.23, 3.65)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9104</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Deep Vein Thrombosis</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.14%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.43 (0.12, 1.53)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1923</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pulmonary Embolism</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.07%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.34%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.21 (0.08, 0.59)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0030</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Postoperative Anemia</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.63%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.08%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.97 (0.80, 1.19)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7926</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Home Discharge</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">73.90%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">66.14%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.45 (1.17, 1.80)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0007</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rehab Discharge</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.50%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.90%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.70 (0.56, 0.87)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0013</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Length of Stay (days)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.04</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.24</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">--- (---, ---)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0297</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total Charges ($)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$58,507</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$50,924</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">--- (---, ---)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">CUD</italic> Cannabis Use Disorder</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par23">As the number of TJA procedures perpetually increases, so does the relative proportion of patients with CUD. This study noted a greater than 5-fold increase in the prevalence of CUD amongst TJA patients over nearly a decade. This trend is similar to the 3-fold increase in CUD for elective surgical admissions that was previously reported between 2006&#8211;2015 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Increased CUD prevalence has been attributed to increasing social acceptance and the progressive legalization of cannabis, with the subsequent rise in self-reported cannabis use [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. This study aimed to characterize this emerging population of TJA patients with CUD by investigating demographic profiles and relevant clinical inpatient postoperative outcomes.</p><p id="Par24">TJA patients with CUD were younger, more often male and non-Hispanic Black, and less likely to be non-Hispanic White. These demographic characteristics mirror cannabis use trends amongst various racial and ethnic groups [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Several factors may contribute to CUD within certain demographic groups, including environmental circumstances, community norms, increased blunt usage, and socioeconomic barriers to healthcare [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Additionally, while overall CUD prevalence is higher among men, women with CUD face unique challenges, including higher rates of comorbid depression, anxiety, and more severe withdrawal symptoms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. It is important for clinicians to consider these factors in the immediate postoperative in-hospital setting, where limited access to cannabis may incite withdrawal symptoms. When addressing substance use in the perioperative setting, careful attention should be directed to the unique barriers, challenges, and characteristics faced by these patients.</p><p id="Par25">Patients with CUD had a mean age of 55.35 years, against 66.21 years in the control group. This finding helps explain the significant differences in expected primary payor, as patients with CUD had higher rates of Medicaid (coverage for low-income individuals of all ages) and lower rates of Medicare (coverage for adults &#8805; 65 years and those with disabilities) insurance compared to the control group. It has been previously shown that most adults with CUD have a relatively lower income, and therefore may qualify for Medicaid benefits [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Thus, as the majority of funding for substance use treatment comes from public sources, it is critical for public health initiatives to expand coverage and resources available for lower-income individuals and improving the infrastructure for screening, intervention, and treatment for substance use disorders [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>].</p><p id="Par26">Several significant comorbidity associations were found in the CUD cohort in this study. CUD patients had significantly higher rates of comorbidities that are associated with risky behaviors and disinhibition, such as acquired immune deficiency syndrome (AIDS), alcohol abuse, and liver pathology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. This supports previous literature, showing marijuana use and other substance abuse disorders are associated with inhibitory control impairment and subsequent risky behaviors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Patients with CUD also had significantly higher rates of comorbid mental illness. The high degree of comorbid depression and psychoses in cannabis users has already been well documented [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Although these studies have not established causality between CUD and psychiatric disorders, there is sufficient evidence to justify interventions for harm reduction and prevention among at-risk populations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. This association is especially important in the arthroplasty perioperative setting, as mental illness is highly associated with increased morbidity following total joint arthroplasty [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. As legislation has evolved over recent years, attitudes have shifted towards increased acceptability and views that cannabis is a harmless substance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. However, the associated comorbidities noted in CUD patients are independent risk factors that may predispose patients to poor health outcomes following TJA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. With the rise in the prevalence of cannabis use and dependence, it is increasingly important for clinicians to account for these comorbidities in the perioperative setting.</p><p id="Par27">This study found no significant differences in the overall complication rates between groups. The only significant difference upon scrutinizing individual complications involved a lower rate of PE in CUD patients. Interestingly, there was no difference in DVT rate between groups. This contradicted previous literature correlating CUD with higher rates of thromboembolic complications caused by changes in hematological parameters and platelet morphology with cannabis use [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. While statistical methodological differences may play a role in this observation, this paradoxical finding may also potentially be explained by aggressive perioperative management and monitoring of patients with CUD for PE, ultimately leading to increased prevention. Regardless, more investigation into this relationship is warranted. For all other immediate postoperative complications, isolating CUD through propensity-weighted analysis showed no significant difference between cohorts. This is an encouraging supplement to recent literature showing no differences in perioperative clinical outcomes between similar cohorts undergoing major elective surgeries and arthroplasty [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>].</p><p id="Par28">Analysis of economic outcomes revealed that CUD patients had significantly shorter length of stay (LOS) and higher rates of home discharge following primary TJA compared to the control group. This contrasted with previous reports of increased LOS for patients with CUD following primary TJA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. Differences in statistical methodology likely account for these differences, as this study's propensity weighting methodology allowed for controlling a large number of potentially confounding factors for LOS and discharge disposition. It is intuitive that patients with CUD, who are, by definition, dependent on cannabis or have a problematic pattern of cannabis use, would be incentivized to leave the hospital as soon as possible and return home to continue use of cannabis and potentially other substances. Because such use may be associated with problematic behavioral changes and abandonment of social, occupational, or recreational activities, these patients may be at risk for worse postoperative and overall health outcomes in the postoperative, post-discharge period. In contrast, the preoperative and in-hospital period, during which a multidisciplinary team has full access to care for these patients, can thus serve as an opportune time for comprehensive social and medical intervention. As such, orthopedic surgeons and the multidisciplinary medical and social service team should remain aware of the risks these patients face, and perioperative interventions should be considered to optimize both long-term outcomes and general health improvement in these patients.</p><p id="Par29">This study is limited for several reasons. A majority of these limitations are inherently related to study design. A large national registry database such as the NIS provides a rich source of data to analyze, however, input of these data is often inconsistent and/or incomplete [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Additional drawbacks stemmed from inherent limitations in the NIS database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. The database only reports on current hospital admissions without data on longer-term follow-up. Therefore, postoperative outcome measures only related to the immediate in-hospital setting for this study. For example, this database allows for analysis of length of stay and discharge disposition, but excludes specific data on timing for return to work or rehabilitation requirements. Literature would benefit from future studies focusing on long-term outcomes of CUD and TJA building on the epidemiological and demographic characteristics of patients with CUD at the time of primary TJA presented here. The NIS database is also limited as it reports data in aggregate, and individual patient granularity is not profiled. Findings in this study showed significant differences in "total charges" of admission between CUD and non-CUD study groups. While the NIS database keeps a record of "total charges" accrued during a patient's hospital admission, these are not itemized into individual charges and thus prevents any closer analysis of variations in hospital charges between patients. Similarly, specific postoperative pain medication requirements for individual patients are not recorded in the NIS database. Further studies on this topic would benefit from including a more thorough analysis of the patients' postoperative course in regard to pain medication requirements. Lastly, this study only included patients with CUD, a subset which represents only about 10% of the 193 million worldwide cannabis users [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. Future studies may evaluate how the characteristics and postoperative outcomes of TJA patients with classified CUD compare to those self-reporting recreational cannabis use. Unfortunately, this distinction cannot be made within the current NIS database.</p><p id="Par30">This study has numerous strengths despite the unavoidable limitations. This study, to the authors' knowledge, constituted the largest investigation of epidemiological and demographic characteristics of patients with CUD undergoing primary TJA. The length and size of this study allowed for a robust understanding of demographic profiles for the growing population of patients with CUD undergoing primary TJA. Additionally, information on clinical and economic postoperative outcomes for these patients provides a better understanding of the implications of cannabis use in the immediate postoperative setting. While cannabis use is becoming increasingly legalized throughout the United States, CUD is also a relevant problem in other countries around the world. While high-income countries maintain the highest prevalence of cannabis use, there is a growing prevalence of cannabis use in low-income and middle-income countries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. Specifically, there is a higher estimated use in North Africa (12.4%), West and Central Africa (12.4%) and Oceania (10.3%) compared to Asia (1.8%), North Africa (4.3%) and Eastern and Southern Europe (2.4%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. This study's findings can provide physicians worldwide with a better understanding of CUD and serve this growing patient population.</p><p id="Par31">In conclusion, this study found a significant and greater-than-five-fold increase in the prevalence of CUD among patients undergoing primary TJA from 2006&#8211;2015. Progressive legalization of cannabis use makes it increasingly important for clinicians to understand the characteristics of this evolving patient population. As this growing population continues to evolve, understanding their comorbidities, behavioral characteristics, and postoperative clinical and economic outcomes allow orthopedic surgeons and the multidisciplinary healthcare teams to better tailor their care and management of these patients. Further research should aim to more closely and comparatively assess the demographic profile of patients with both recreational use and substance use disorder, along with potential barriers in their access to medical care. This understanding should be associated with the expansion and improvement of public health initiatives and the development of frameworks to better deliver substance use screenings and interventions to this patient population. Such initiatives, combined with the development of standardized perioperative protocols, have the potential to optimize postsurgical and overall health outcomes in this at-risk patient population.</p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>THA</term><def><p id="Par5">Total hip arthroplasty</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TKA</term><def><p id="Par6">Total knee arthroplasty</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TJA</term><def><p id="Par7">Total joint arthroplasty</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CUD</term><def><p id="Par8">Cannabis use disorder</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LOS</term><def><p id="Par9">Length of stay</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NIS</term><def><p id="Par10">National Inpatient Sample</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#8217;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors acknowledge Patrick Karabon&#160;for his contribution to data analysis.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#8217; contributions</title><p>The authors confirm their contribution to the paper as follows: Study conception and design: A.K.Z., M.M.E., I.H.H.. Data collection: D.R., M.M., A.K.Z., M.M.E., I. H.H.. Analysis and interpretation of results: D.R., M.M., A.K.Z., I.H.H,&#160;M.M.E.. Draft manuscript preparation: D.R., M.M., A.K.Z, I.H.H.,&#160;M.M.E. All authors have reviewed the results and approved the final version of the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Not applicable, this investigation has no funding sources to disclose.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>The data that support the findings of this study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par32">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par33">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par34">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jennings</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eschen</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Has self-reported marijuana use changed in patients undergoing total joint arthroplasty after the legalization of marijuana?</article-title><source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source><year>2019</year><volume>477</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/CORR.0000000000000339</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30794232</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6345315</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McGuinness</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jivraj</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wijeysundera</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mittleman</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bateman</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cannabis use disorder and perioperative outcomes in major elective surgeries: a retrospective cohort analysis</article-title><source>Anesthesiology</source><year>2020</year><volume>132</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>625</fpage><lpage>635</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/aln.0000000000003067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31789638</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jennings</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Angerame</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eschen</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Phocas</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cannabis use does not affect outcomes after total knee arthroplasty</article-title><source>J Arthroplast</source><year>2019</year><volume>34</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1667</fpage><lpage>1669</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arth.2019.04.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31072746</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bicket</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McGinty</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cannabis use disorder and surgery: a budding problem?</article-title><source>Anesthesiology</source><year>2020</year><volume>132</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>612</fpage><lpage>613</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/aln.0000000000003135</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32053558</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7071976</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pot and pain</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2016</year><volume>354</volume><issue>6312</issue><fpage>566</fpage><lpage>568</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.354.6312.566</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27811265</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhatia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buzon-Tan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ilangomaran</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kara</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Weeding out the problem: the impact of preoperative cannabinoid use on pain in the perioperative period</article-title><source>Anesth Analg</source><year>2019</year><volume>129</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>874</fpage><lpage>881</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1213/ANE.0000000000003963</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31425232</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Agarwalla</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gowd</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amin</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Werner</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential use of narcotics in total hip arthroplasty: a comparative matched analysis between osteoarthritis and femoral neck fracture</article-title><source>J Arthroplast</source><year>2020</year><volume>35</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>471</fpage><lpage>476</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arth.2019.09.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31564525</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kim P, Yamashita T, Shen JJ, Park SM, Chun SY, Kim SJ, et al. Dissociation between the growing opioid demands and drug policy directions among the U.S. older adults with degenerative joint diseases. Med (United States). 2019;98(28). 10.1097/MD.0000000000016169.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/MD.0000000000016169</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6641693</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31305399</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anciano Granadillo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cancienne</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gwathmey</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Werner</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Perioperative opioid analgesics and hip arthroscopy: trends, risk factors for prolonged use, and complications</article-title><source>Arthrosc - J Arthrosc Relat Surg</source><year>2018</year><volume>34</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>2359</fpage><lpage>2367</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arthro.2018.03.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29730217</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Law</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurowicki</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sabeh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Summers</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hubbard</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cannabis use increases risk for revision after total knee arthroplasty</article-title><source>J Long-Term Eff Med Implants</source><year>2018</year><volume>28</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1615/JLongTermEffMedImplants.2018027401</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30317962</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6396273</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Best</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buller</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klika</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barsoum</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Outcomes following primary total hip or knee arthroplasty in substance misusers</article-title><source>J Arthroplast</source><year>2015</year><volume>30</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1137</fpage><lpage>1141</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arth.2015.01.052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25765129</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roche</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Law</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sodhi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurowicki</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Disla</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Incidence of drug abuse in revision total knee arthroplasty population</article-title><source>J Knee Surg</source><year>2018</year><volume>31</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>928</fpage><lpage>933</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0038-1669915</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30193389</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6427918</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vakharia</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mannino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salem</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roche</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>CHJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mont</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The association between cannabis use disorder and the outcome following primary total hip arthroplasty: analysis of a nationwide administrative claims database</article-title><source>Bone Jt J</source><year>2021</year><volume>103-B</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>115</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1302/0301-620X.103B7.BJJ-2020-2424.R1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34192906</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cerd&#225;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mauro</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association between recreational marijuana legalization in the United States and changes in marijuana use and cannabis use disorder from 2008 to 2016</article-title><source>JAMA Psychiatry</source><year>2020</year><volume>77</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>171</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2019.3254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31722000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6865220</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurtz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ong</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mowat</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Halpern</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Projections of primary and revision hip and knee Arthroplasty in the United States from 2005 to 2030</article-title><source>J Bone Jt Surg</source><year>2007</year><volume>89</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>780</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2106/JBJS.F.00222</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17403800</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Trend Weights for HCUP NIS Data. Rockville: Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality;&#160;<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.hcup-us.ahrq.gov/db/nation/nis/trendwghts.jsp">https://www.hcup-us.ahrq.gov/db/nation/nis/trendwghts.jsp</ext-link>.&#160;Accessed 17 Nov 2022.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Houchens R, Elixhauser A. (2012) Final Report on Calculating Nationwide Inpatient Sample (NIS) Variances for Data Years 2011 and Earlier. U.S. Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Houchens R, Ross D, Elixhauser A. (2015) Final Report on Calculating National Inpatient Sample (NIS) Variances for Data Years 2012 and Later. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hcup-us.ahrq.gov/reports/methods/methods.jsp">http://www.hcup-us.ahrq.gov/reports/methods/methods.jsp</ext-link>. HCUPNIS.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dugoff</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schuler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stuart</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Generalizing observational study results: applying propensity score methods to complex surveys</article-title><source>Health Serv Res</source><year>2014</year><volume>49</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>284</fpage><lpage>303</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1475-6773.12090</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23855598</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3894255</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stuart</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Matching methods for causal inference: a review and a look forward</article-title><source>Stat Sci</source><year>2010</year><volume>25</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1214/09-STS313</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20871802</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2943670</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ondeck</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bohl</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bovonratwet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McLynn</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grauer</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Discriminative ability of Elixhauser&#8217;s comorbidity measure is superior to other comorbidity scores for inpatient adverse outcomes after total hip arthroplasty</article-title><source>J Arthroplast</source><year>2018</year><volume>33</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>250</fpage><lpage>257</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arth.2017.08.032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28927567</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Swartz</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trends in cannabis use disorders among racial/ethnic population groups in the United States</article-title><source>Drug Alcohol Depend</source><year>2016</year><volume>165</volume><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>190</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2016.06.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27317045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4939114</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Compton</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Colliver</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Glantz</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stinson</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of marijuana use disorders in the United States: 1991-1992 and 2001-2002</article-title><source>J Am Med Assoc</source><year>2004</year><volume>291</volume><issue>17</issue><fpage>2114</fpage><lpage>2121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.291.17.2114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15126440</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Herrmann</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weerts</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vandrey</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sex differences in cannabis withdrawal symptoms among treatment-seeking cannabis users</article-title><source>Exp Clin Psychopharmacol</source><year>2015</year><volume>23</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>415</fpage><lpage>421</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/pha0000053</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26461168</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4747417</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Secades-Villa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Okuda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gender differences in cannabis use disorders: results from the National Epidemiologic Survey of alcohol and related conditions</article-title><source>Drug Alcohol Depend</source><year>2013</year><volume>130</volume><issue>1-3</issue><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2012.10.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23182839</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3586748</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mannelli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Swartz</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and correlates of treatment utilization among adults with cannabis use disorder in the United States</article-title><source>Drug Alcohol Depend</source><year>2017</year><volume>177</volume><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2017.03.037.Prevalence</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28599214</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5538354</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mark</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levit</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vandivort-Warren</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buck</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coffey</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in US spending on mental health and substance abuse treatment, 1986-2005, and implications for policy</article-title><source>Health Aff</source><year>2011</year><volume>30</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>284</fpage><lpage>292</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1377/hlthaff.2010.0765</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21289350</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crook</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitener</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Albright</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Greenawalt</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zurlo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>HIV transmission risk behaviors among people living with HIV/ AIDS: the need to integrate HIV prevention interventions and public health strategies into HIV care ping</article-title><source>J Public Health Manag Pract</source><year>2015</year><volume>21</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/PHH.0000000000000038</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24335609</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4051857</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mattick</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jamadar</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iredale</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Deficits in behavioural inhibition in substance abuse and addiction: a meta-analysis</article-title><source>Drug Alcohol Depend</source><year>2014</year><volume>145</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2014.08.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25195081</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Andrade</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petry</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Marijuana use is associated with risky sexual behaviors in treatment-seeking polysubstance abusers</article-title><source>Am J Drug Alcohol Abuse</source><year>2013</year><volume>39</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>266</fpage><lpage>271</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/00952990.2013.803112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23841867</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3793248</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Alarc&#243;-Rosales R, S&#225;nchez-SanSegundo M, Ferrer-Cascales R, Albaladejo-Bl&#225;zquez N, Ruiz-Robledillo N, Delvecchio E, et al. Relationships between problematic cannabis use and risky behaviors in Spanish adolescents. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2019;16(17). 10.3390/ijerph16173029.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijerph16173029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6747259</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31438581</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lev-Ran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roerecke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Le Foll</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>George</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McKenzie</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rehm</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The association between cannabis use and depression: a systematic review and meta-analysis of longitudinal studies</article-title><source>Psychol Med</source><year>2014</year><volume>44</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>797</fpage><lpage>810</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0033291713001438</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23795762</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marconi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Forti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vassos</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Meta-analysis of the association between the level of cannabis use and risk of psychosis</article-title><source>Schizophr Bull</source><year>2016</year><volume>42</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1262</fpage><lpage>1269</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/schbul/sbw003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26884547</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4988731</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Onaemo</surname><given-names>VN</given-names></name><collab>Fawehinmi TO</collab><name name-style="western"><surname>D&#8217;Arcy</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comorbid cannabis use disorder with major depression and generalized anxiety disorder: a systematic review with meta-analysis of nationally representative epidemiological surveys</article-title><source>J Affect Disord</source><year>2021</year><volume>281</volume><fpage>467</fpage><lpage>475</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2020.12.043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33360749</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zalikha</surname><given-names>AKM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karabon PMs, Hajj Hussein IP, El-Othmani MMM.</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Anxiety and depression impact on Inhospital complications and outcomes after total knee and hip arthroplasty: a propensity score-weighted retrospective analysis</article-title><source>J Am Acad Orthop Surg</source><year>2021</year><volume>29</volume><issue>20</issue><fpage>873</fpage><lpage>884</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5435/JAAOS-D-20-00721</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34525481</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kamalapathy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurker</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Althoff</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Browne</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Werner</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of mental illness on postoperative adverse outcomes after outpatient joint surgery</article-title><source>J Arthroplast</source><year>2021</year><volume>36</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>2734</fpage><lpage>2741</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arth.2021.04.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33896669</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasin</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>US epidemiology of cannabis use and associated problems</article-title><source>Neuropsychopharmacology</source><year>2018</year><volume>43</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/npp.2017.198</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28853439</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5719106</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Neill</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Queally</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hickey</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mulhall</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Outcome of total hip and knee arthroplasty in HIV-infected patients: a systematic review</article-title><source>Orthop Rev (Pavia)</source><year>2019</year><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4081/or.2019.8020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6452098</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30996842</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Best</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buller</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gosthe</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klika</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barsoum</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alcohol misuse is an independent risk factor for poorer postoperative outcomes following primary total hip and total knee arthroplasty</article-title><source>J Arthroplast</source><year>2015</year><volume>30</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1293</fpage><lpage>1298</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arth.2015.02.028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25769745</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garbarino</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anis</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The cumulative effect of substance abuse disorders and depression on postoperative complications after primary total knee arthroplasty</article-title><source>J Arthroplast</source><year>2020</year><volume>35</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>157</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arth.2020.01.027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32061474</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vakharia</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sodhi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anis</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ehiorobo</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mont</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roche</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Patients who have cannabis use disorder have higher rates of venous Thromboemboli, readmission rates, and costs following primary Total knee Arthroplasty</article-title><source>J Arthroplast</source><year>2020</year><volume>35</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>997</fpage><lpage>1002</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arth.2019.11.035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31973970</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guzel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yazici</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yazici</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erol</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alterations of the hematologic cells in synthetic cannabinoid users</article-title><source>J Clin Lab Anal</source><year>2017</year><volume>31</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcla.22131</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6817267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28169460</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deusch</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kress</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kraft</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kozek-Langenecker</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The procoagulatory effects of delta-9-tetrahydrocannabinol in human platelets</article-title><source>Anesth Analg</source><year>2004</year><volume>99</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1127</fpage><lpage>1130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1213/01.ANE.0000131505.03006.74</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15385362</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baldassarri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bertoni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bagarotti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarasso</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zanfa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Catani</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The endocannabinoid 2-arachidonoylglycerol activates human platelets through non-CB1/CB2 receptors</article-title><source>J Thromb Haemost</source><year>2008</year><volume>6</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1772</fpage><lpage>1779</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1538-7836.2008.03093.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18647220</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Runner RP, Luu AN, Nassif NA, Scudday TA, Patel JJ, Barnett SL, et al. Use of Tetrahydrocannabinol and Cannabidiol products in the perioperative period around primary unilateral total hip and knee arthroplasty. J Arthroplast. 2020. 10.1016/j.arth.2020.01.077.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.arth.2020.01.077</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32173619</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pass</surname><given-names>HI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medical registries: continued attempts for robust quality data</article-title><source>J Thorac Oncol</source><year>2010</year><volume>5</volume><issue>6 SUPPL. 2</issue><fpage>198</fpage><lpage>199</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/JTO.0b013e3181dcf957</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20502263</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bozic</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bashyal</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anthony</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shulman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rubash</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Is administratively coded comorbidity and complication data in total joint arthroplasty valid?</article-title><source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>471</volume><fpage>201</fpage><lpage>205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11999-012-2352-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22528384</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3528892</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Connor J, Stjepanovi&#263; D, Le Foll B, Hoch E, Budney A, Hall W. Cannabis use and cannabis use disorder. Nat Rev Dis Prim. 2021;7(1). 10.1038/s41572-021-00247-4.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41572-021-00247-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8655458</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33627670</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>